John

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21

THE GOSPEL ACCORDING TO ST. JOHN

1

1  In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. 2 [*] The same was in the beginning with God. 3 [*] All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made that was made. 4  In him was life; and the life was the light of men. 5  And the light shineth in darkness; and the darkness comprehended it not.

6 ¶ [*]There was a man sent from God, whose name was John. 7  The same came for a witness, to bear witness of the Light, that all men through him might believe. 8  He was not that Light, but was sent to bear witness of that Light. 9  That was the true Light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world. 10  He was in the world, and [*]the world was made by him, and the world knew him not. 11  He came unto his own, and his own received him not. 12  But as many as received him, to them gave he [∥]power to become the sons of God, even to them that believe on his name: 13  Which were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God. 14 [*] And the Word was made flesh, and dwelt among us, (and we beheld his glory, the glory as of the only begotten of the Father,) full of grace and truth.

15 ¶ John bare witness of him, and cried, saying, This was he of whom I spake, He that cometh after me is preferred before me: for he was before me. 16  And of his [*]fulness have all we received, and grace for grace. 17  For the law was given by Moses, but grace and truth came by Jesus Christ. 18 [*] No man hath seen God at any time; the only begotten Son, which is in the bosom of the Father, he hath declared him.

19 ¶ And this is the record of John, when the Jews sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem to ask him, Who art thou? 20  And he confessed, and denied not; but confessed, I am not the Christ. 21  And they asked him, What then? Art thou Elias? And he saith, I am not. Art thou [∥]that prophet? And he answered, No. 22  Then said they unto him, Who art thou? that we may give an answer to them that sent us. What sayest thou of thyself? 23 [*] He said, I am the voice of one crying in the wilderness, Make straight the way of the Lord, as said the prophet Esaias. 24  And they which were sent were of the Pharisees. 25  And they asked him, and said unto him, Why baptizest thou then, if thou be not that Christ, nor Elias, neither that prophet? 26  John answered them, saying, I baptize with water: but there standeth one among you, whom ye know not; 27 [*] He it is, who coming after me is preferred before me, whose shoe’s latchet I am not worthy to unloose. 28  These things were done in Bethabara beyond Jordan, where John was baptizing.

29 ¶ The next day John seeth Jesus coming unto him, and saith, Behold the Lamb of God, which [∥]taketh away the sin of the world. 30  This is he of whom I said, After me cometh a man which is preferred before me: for he was before me. 31  And I knew him not: but that he should be made manifest to Israel, therefore am I come baptizing with water. 32 [*] And John bare record, saying, I saw the Spirit descending from heaven like a dove, and it abode upon him. 33  And I knew him not: but he that sent me to baptize with water, the same said unto me, Upon whom thou shalt see the Spirit descending, and remaining on him, the same is he which baptizeth with the Holy Ghost. 34  And I saw, and bare record that this is the Son of God.

35 ¶ Again the next day after John stood, and two of his disciples; 36  And looking upon Jesus as he walked, he saith, Behold the Lamb of God! 37  And the two disciples heard him speak, and they followed Jesus. 38  Then Jesus turned, and saw them following, and saith unto them, What seek ye? They said unto him, Rabbi, (which is to say, being interpreted, Master,) where [∥]dwellest thou? 39  He saith unto them, Come and see. They came and saw where he dwelt, and abode with him that day: for it was [∥]about the tenth hour. 40  One of the two which heard John speak, and followed him, was Andrew, Simon Peter’s brother. 41  He first findeth his own brother Simon, and saith unto him, We have found the Messias, which is, being interpreted, [∥]the Christ. 42  And he brought him to Jesus. And when Jesus beheld him, he said, Thou art Simon the son of Jona: thou shalt be called Cephas, which is by interpretation, [∥]A stone.

43 ¶ The day following Jesus would go forth into Galilee, and findeth Philip, and saith unto him, Follow me. 44  Now Philip was of Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter. 45  Philip findeth Nathanael, and saith unto him, We have found him, of whom [*]Moses in the law, and the [*]prophets, did write, Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph. 46  And Nathanael said unto him, Can there any good thing come out of Nazareth? Philip saith unto him, Come and see. 47  Jesus saw Nathanael coming to him, and saith of him, Behold an Israelite indeed, in whom is no guile! 48  Nathanael saith unto him, Whence knowest thou me? Jesus answered and said unto him, Before that Philip called thee, when thou wast under the fig tree, I saw thee. 49  Nathanael answered and saith unto him, Rabbi, thou art the Son of God; thou art the King of Israel. 50  Jesus answered and said unto him, Because I said unto thee, I saw thee under the fig tree, believest thou? thou shalt see greater things than these. 51  And he saith unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Hereafter ye shall see heaven open, and the angels of God ascending and descending upon the Son of man.

2

1  And the third day there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee; and the mother of Jesus was there: 2  And both Jesus was called, and his disciples, to the marriage. 3  And when they wanted wine, the mother of Jesus saith unto him, They have no wine. 4  Jesus saith unto her, Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come. 5  His mother saith unto the servants, Whatsoever he saith unto you, do it. 6  And there were set there six waterpots of stone, after the manner of the purifying of the Jews, containing two or three firkins apiece. 7  Jesus saith unto them, Fill the waterpots with water. And they filled them up to the brim. 8  And he saith unto them, Draw out now, and bear unto the governor of the feast. And they bare it. 9  When the ruler of the feast had tasted the water that was made wine, and knew not whence it was: (but the servants which drew the water knew;) the governor of the feast called the bridegroom, 10  And saith unto him, Every man at the beginning doth set forth good wine; and when men have well drunk, then that which is worse: but thou hast kept the good wine until now. 11  This beginning of miracles did Jesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested forth his glory; and his disciples believed on him.

12 ¶ After this he went down to Capernaum, he, and his mother, and his brethren, and his disciples: and they continued there not many days.

13 ¶ And the Jews’ passover was at hand, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem, 14  And found in the temple those that sold oxen and sheep and doves, and the changers of money sitting: 15  And when he had made a scourge of small cords, he drove them all out of the temple, and the sheep, and the oxen; and poured out the changers’ money, and overthrew the tables; 16  And said unto them that sold doves, Take these things hence; make not my Father’s house an house of merchandise. 17  And his disciples remembered that it was written, [*]The zeal of thine house hath eaten me up.

18 ¶ Then answered the Jews and said unto him, What sign shewest thou unto us, seeing that thou doest these things? 19  Jesus answered and said unto them, [*]Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up. 20  Then said the Jews, Forty and six years was this temple in building, and wilt thou rear it up in three days? 21  But he spake of the temple of his body. 22  When therefore he was risen from the dead, his disciples remembered that he had said this unto them; and they believed the scripture, and the word which Jesus had said.

23 ¶ Now when he was in Jerusalem at the passover, in the feast day, many believed in his name, when they saw the miracles which he did. 24  But Jesus did not commit himself unto them, because he knew all men, 25  And needed not that any should testify of man: for he knew what was in man.

3

1  There was a man of the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews: 2  The same came to Jesus by night, and said unto him, Rabbi, we know that thou art a teacher come from God: for no man can do these miracles that thou doest, except God be with him. 3  Jesus answered and said unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born [∥]again, he cannot see the kingdom of God. 4  Nicodemus saith unto him, How can a man be born when he is old? can he enter the second time into his mother’s womb, and be born? 5  Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God. 6  That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit. 7  Marvel not that I said unto thee, Ye must be born [∥]again. 8  The wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, but canst not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit. 9  Nicodemus answered and said unto him, How can these things be? 10  Jesus answered and said unto him, Art thou a master of Israel, and knowest not these things? 11  Verily, verily, I say unto thee, We speak that we do know, and testify that we have seen; and ye receive not our witness. 12  If I have told you earthly things, and ye believe not, how shall ye believe, if I tell you of heavenly things? 13  And no man hath ascended up to heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven.

14 ¶ [*]And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, even so must the Son of man be lifted up: 15  That whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have eternal life.

16 ¶ [*]For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life. 17 [*] For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world; but that the world through him might be saved.

18 ¶ He that believeth on him is not condemned: but he that believeth not is condemned already, because he hath not believed in the name of the only begotten Son of God. 19  And this is the condemnation, [*]that light is come into the world, and men loved darkness rather than light, because their deeds were evil. 20  For every one that doeth evil hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, lest his deeds should be [∥]reproved. 21  But he that doeth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifest, that they are wrought in God.

22 ¶ After these things came Jesus and his disciples into the land of Judæa; and there he tarried with them, [*]and baptized.

23 ¶ And John also was baptizing in Ænon near to Salim, because there was much water there: and they came, and were baptized. 24  For John was not yet cast into prison.

25 ¶ Then there arose a question between some of John’s disciples and the Jews about purifying. 26  And they came unto John, and said unto him, Rabbi, he that was with thee beyond Jordan, [*]to whom thou barest witness, behold, the same baptizeth, and all men come to him. 27  John answered and said, [*]A man can [∥]receive nothing, except it be given him from heaven. 28  Ye yourselves bear me witness, that I said, [*]I am not the Christ, but that I am sent before him. 29  He that hath the bride is the bridegroom: but the friend of the bridegroom, which standeth and heareth him, rejoiceth greatly because of the bridegroom’s voice: this my joy therefore is fulfilled. 30  He must increase, but I must decrease. 31  He that cometh from above is above all: he that is of the earth is earthly, and speaketh of the earth: he that cometh from heaven is above all. 32  And what he hath seen and heard, that he testifieth; and no man receiveth his testimony. 33  He that hath received his testimony [*]hath set to his seal that God is true. 34  For he whom God hath sent speaketh the words of God: for God giveth not the Spirit by measure unto him. 35 [*] The Father loveth the Son, and hath given all things into his hand. 36 [*] He that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life: and he that believeth not the Son shall not see life; but the wrath of God abideth on him.

4

1  When therefore the Lord knew how the Pharisees had heard that Jesus made and baptized more disciples than John, 2 (Though Jesus himself baptized not, but his disciples,) 3  He left Judæa, and departed again into Galilee. 4  And he must needs go through Samaria. 5  Then cometh he to a city of Samaria, which is called Sychar, near to the parcel of ground [*]that Jacob gave to his son Joseph. 6  Now Jacob’s well was there. Jesus therefore, being wearied with his journey, sat thus on the well: and it was about the sixth hour. 7  There cometh a woman of Samaria to draw water: Jesus saith unto her, Give me to drink. 8 (For his disciples were gone away unto the city to buy meat.) 9  Then saith the woman of Samaria unto him, How is it that thou, being a Jew, askest drink of me, which am a woman of Samaria? for the Jews have no dealings with the Samaritans. 10  Jesus answered and said unto her, If thou knewest the gift of God, and who it is that saith to thee, Give me to drink; thou wouldest have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water. 11  The woman saith unto him, Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the well is deep: from whence then hast thou that living water? 12  Art thou greater than our father Jacob, which gave us the well, and drank thereof himself, and his children, and his cattle? 13  Jesus answered and said unto her, Whosoever drinketh of this water shall thirst again: 14  But whosoever drinketh of the water that I shall give him shall never thirst; but the water that I shall give him shall be in him a well of water springing up into everlasting life. 15  The woman saith unto him, Sir, give me this water, that I thirst not, neither come hither to draw. 16  Jesus saith unto her, Go, call thy husband, and come hither. 17  The woman answered and said, I have no husband. Jesus said unto her, Thou hast well said, I have no husband: 18  For thou hast had five husbands; and he whom thou now hast is not thy husband: in that saidst thou truly. 19  The woman saith unto him, Sir, I perceive that thou art a prophet. 20  Our fathers worshipped in this mountain; and ye say, that [*]in Jerusalem is the place where men ought to worship. 21  Jesus saith unto her, Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when ye shall neither in this mountain, nor yet at Jerusalem, worship the Father. 22  Ye worship ye know not what: we know what we worship: for salvation is of the Jews. 23  But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and in truth: for the Father seeketh such to worship him. 24 [*] God is a Spirit: and they that worship him must worship him in spirit and in truth. 25  The woman saith unto him, I know that Messias cometh, which is called Christ: when he is come, he will tell us all things. 26  Jesus saith unto her, I that speak unto thee am he.

27 ¶ And upon this came his disciples, and marvelled that he talked with the woman: yet no man said, What seekest thou? or, Why talkest thou with her? 28  The woman then left her waterpot, and went her way into the city, and saith to the men, 29  Come, see a man, which told me all things that ever I did: is not this the Christ? 30  Then they went out of the city, and came unto him.

31 ¶ In the mean while his disciples prayed him, saying, Master, eat. 32  But he said unto them, I have meat to eat that ye know not of. 33  Therefore said the disciples one to another, Hath any man brought him ought to eat? 34  Jesus saith unto them, My meat is to do the will of him that sent me, and to finish his work. 35  Say not ye, There are yet four months, and then cometh harvest? behold, I say unto you, Lift up your eyes, and look on the fields; [*]for they are white already to harvest. 36  And he that reapeth receiveth wages, and gathereth fruit unto life eternal: that both he that soweth and he that reapeth may rejoice together. 37  And herein is that saying true, One soweth, and another reapeth. 38  I sent you to reap that whereon ye bestowed no labour: other men laboured, and ye are entered into their labours.

39 ¶ And many of the Samaritans of that city believed on him for the saying of the woman, which testified, He told me all that ever I did. 40  So when the Samaritans were come unto him, they besought him that he would tarry with them: and he abode there two days. 41  And many more believed because of his own word; 42  And said unto the woman, Now we believe, not because of thy saying: for we have heard him ourselves, and know that this is indeed the Christ, the Saviour of the world.

43 ¶ Now after two days he departed thence, and went into Galilee. 44  For [*]Jesus himself testified, that a prophet hath no honour in his own country. 45  Then when he was come into Galilee, the Galilæans received him, having seen all the things that he did at Jerusalem at the feast: for they also went unto the feast. 46  So Jesus came again into Cana of Galilee, [*]where he made the water wine. And there was a certain [∥]nobleman, whose son was sick at Capernaum. 47  When he heard that Jesus was come out of Judæa into Galilee, he went unto him, and besought him that he would come down, and heal his son: for he was at the point of death. 48  Then said Jesus unto him, Except ye see signs and wonders, ye will not believe. 49  The nobleman saith unto him, Sir, come down ere my child die. 50  Jesus saith unto him, Go thy way; thy son liveth. And the man believed the word that Jesus had spoken unto him, and he went his way. 51  And as he was now going down, his servants met him, and told him, saying, Thy son liveth. 52  Then enquired he of them the hour when he began to amend. And they said unto him, Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him. 53  So the father knew that it was at the same hour, in the which Jesus said unto him, Thy son liveth: and himself believed, and his whole house. 54  This is again the second miracle that Jesus did, when he was come out of Judæa into Galilee.

5

1  After [*]this there was a feast of the Jews; and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. 2  Now there is at Jerusalem by the sheep [∥]market a pool, which is called in the Hebrew tongue Bethesda, having five porches. 3  In these lay a great multitude of impotent folk, of blind, halt, withered, waiting for the moving of the water. 4  For an angel went down at a certain season into the pool, and troubled the water: whosoever then first after the troubling of the water stepped in was made whole of whatsoever disease he had. 5  And a certain man was there, which had an infirmity thirty and eight years. 6  When Jesus saw him lie, and knew that he had been now a long time in that case, he saith unto him, Wilt thou be made whole? 7  The impotent man answered him, Sir, I have no man, when the water is troubled, to put me into the pool: but while I am coming, another steppeth down before me. 8  Jesus saith unto him, Rise, take up thy bed, and walk. 9  And immediately the man was made whole, and took up his bed, and walked: and on the same day was the sabbath.

10 ¶ The Jews therefore said unto him that was cured, It is the sabbath day: [*]it is not lawful for thee to carry thy bed. 11  He answered them, He that made me whole, the same said unto me, Take up thy bed, and walk. 12  Then asked they him, What man is that which said unto thee, Take up thy bed, and walk? 13  And he that was healed wist not who it was: for Jesus had conveyed himself away, [∥]a multitude being in that place. 14  Afterward Jesus findeth him in the temple, and said unto him, Behold, thou art made whole: sin no more, lest a worse thing come unto thee. 15  The man departed, and told the Jews that it was Jesus, which had made him whole. 16  And therefore did the Jews persecute Jesus, and sought to slay him, because he had done these things on the sabbath day.

17 ¶ But Jesus answered them, My Father worketh hitherto, and I work. 18  Therefore the Jews sought the more to kill him, [‡]because he not only had broken the sabbath, but said also that God was his Father, making himself equal with God. 19  Then answered Jesus and said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, The Son can do nothing of himself, but what he seeth the Father do: for what things soever he doeth, these also doeth the Son likewise. 20  For the Father loveth the Son, and sheweth him all things that himself doeth: and he will shew him greater works than these, that ye may marvel. 21  For as the Father raiseth up the dead, and quickeneth them; even so the Son quickeneth whom he will. 22  For the Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all judgment unto the Son: 23  That all men should honour the Son, even as they honour the Father. He that honoureth not the Son honoureth not the Father which hath sent him. 24  Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that heareth my word, and believeth on him that sent me, hath everlasting life, and shall not come into condemnation; but is passed from death unto life. 25  Verily, verily, I say unto you, The hour is coming, and now is, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God: and they that hear shall live. 26  For as the Father hath life in himself; so hath he given to the Son to have life in himself; 27  And hath given him authority to execute judgment also, because he is the Son of man. 28  Marvel not at this: for the hour is coming, in the which all that are in the graves shall hear his voice, 29  And shall come forth; [*]they that have done good, unto the resurrection of life; and they that have done evil, unto the resurrection of damnation. 30  I can of mine own self do nothing: as I hear, I judge: and my judgment is just; because I seek not mine own will, but the will of the Father which hath sent me. 31 [*] If I bear witness of myself, my witness is not true.

32 ¶ [*]There is another that beareth witness of me; and I know that the witness which he witnesseth of me is true. 33  Ye sent unto John, [*]and he bare witness unto the truth. 34  But I receive not testimony from man: but these things I say, that ye might be saved. 35  He was a burning and a shining light: and ye were willing for a season to rejoice in his light.

36 ¶ But I have greater witness than that of John: for the works which the Father hath given me to finish, the same works that I do, bear witness of me, that the Father hath sent me. 37  And the Father himself, which hath sent me, [*]hath borne witness of me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, [*]nor seen his shape. 38  And ye have not his word abiding in you: for whom he hath sent, him ye believe not.

39 ¶ Search the scriptures; for in them ye think ye have eternal life: and they are they which testify of me. 40  And ye will not come to me, that ye might have life. 41  I receive not honour from men. 42  But I know you, that ye have not the love of God in you. 43  I am come in my Father’s name, and ye receive me not: if another shall come in his own name, him ye will receive. 44 [*] How can ye believe, which receive honour one of another, and seek not the honour that cometh from God only? 45  Do not think that I will accuse you to the Father: there is one that accuseth you, even Moses, in whom ye trust. 46  For had ye believed Moses, ye would have believed me: [*]for he wrote of me. 47  But if ye believe not his writings, how shall ye believe my words?

6

1  After these things Jesus went over the sea of Galilee, which is the sea of Tiberias. 2  And a great multitude followed him, because they saw his miracles which he did on them that were diseased. 3  And Jesus went up into a mountain, and there he sat with his disciples. 4 [*] And the passover, a feast of the Jews, was nigh.

5 ¶ [*]When Jesus then lifted up his eyes, and saw a great company come unto him, he saith unto Philip, Whence shall we buy bread, that these may eat? 6  And this he said to prove him: for he himself knew what he would do. 7  Philip answered him, Two hundred pennyworth of bread is not sufficient for them, that every one of them may take a little. 8  One of his disciples, Andrew, Simon Peter’s brother, saith unto him, 9  There is a lad here, which hath five barley loaves, and two small fishes: but what are they among so many? 10  And Jesus said, Make the men sit down. Now there was much grass in the place. So the men sat down, in number about five thousand. 11  And Jesus took the loaves; and when he had given thanks, he distributed to the disciples, and the disciples to them that were set down; and likewise of the fishes as much as they would. 12  When they were filled, he said unto his disciples, Gather up the fragments that remain, that nothing be lost. 13  Therefore they gathered them together, and filled twelve baskets with the fragments of the five barley loaves, which remained over and above unto them that had eaten. 14  Then those men, when they had seen the miracle that Jesus did, said, This is of a truth that prophet that should come into the world.

15 ¶ When Jesus therefore perceived that they would come and take him by force, to make him a king, he departed again into a mountain himself alone. 16 [*] And when even was now come, his disciples went down unto the sea, 17  And entered into a ship, and went over the sea toward Capernaum. And it was now dark, and Jesus was not come to them. 18  And the sea arose by reason of a great wind that blew. 19  So when they had rowed about five and twenty or thirty furlongs, they see Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing nigh unto the ship: and they were afraid. 20  But he saith unto them, It is I; be not afraid. 21  Then they willingly received him into the ship: and immediately the ship was at the land whither they went.

22 ¶ The day following, when the people which stood on the other side of the sea saw that there was none other boat there, save that one whereinto his disciples were entered, and that Jesus went not with his disciples into the boat, but that his disciples were gone away alone; 23 (Howbeit there came other boats from Tiberias nigh unto the place where they did eat bread, after that the Lord had given thanks:) 24  When the people therefore saw that Jesus was not there, neither his disciples, they also took shipping, and came to Capernaum, seeking for Jesus. 25  And when they had found him on the other side of the sea, they said unto him, Rabbi, when camest thou hither? 26  Jesus answered them and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Ye seek me, not because ye saw the miracles, but because ye did eat of the loaves, and were filled. 27 [∥] Labour not for the meat which perisheth, but for that meat which endureth unto everlasting life, which the Son of man shall give unto you: [*]for him hath God the Father sealed. 28  Then said they unto him, What shall we do, that we might work the works of God? 29  Jesus answered and said unto them, [*]This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath sent. 30  They said therefore unto him, What sign shewest thou then, that we may see, and believe thee? what dost thou work? 31 [*] Our fathers did eat manna in the desert; as it is written, [*]He gave them bread from heaven to eat. 32  Then Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Moses gave you not that bread from heaven; but my Father giveth you the true bread from heaven. 33  For the bread of God is he which cometh down from heaven, and giveth life unto the world. 34  Then said they unto him, Lord, evermore give us this bread. 35  And Jesus said unto them, I am the bread of life: he that cometh to me shall never hunger; and he that believeth on me shall never thirst. 36  But I said unto you, That ye also have seen me, and believe not. 37  All that the Father giveth me shall come to me; and him that cometh to me I will in no wise cast out. 38  For I came down from heaven, not to do mine own will, but the will of him that sent me. 39  And this is the Father’s will which hath sent me, that of all which he hath given me I should lose nothing, but should raise it up again at the last day. 40  And this is the will of him that sent me, that every one which seeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlasting life: and I will raise him up at the last day. 41  The Jews then murmured at him, because he said, I am the bread which came down from heaven. 42  And they said, [*]Is not this Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? how is it then that he saith, I came down from heaven? 43  Jesus therefore answered and said unto them, Murmur not among yourselves. 44  No man can come to me, except the Father which hath sent me draw him: and I will raise him up at the last day. 45 [*] It is written in the prophets, And they shall be all taught of God. Every man therefore that hath heard, and hath learned of the Father, cometh unto me. 46  Not that any man hath seen the Father, [*]save he which is of God, he hath seen the Father. 47  Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth on me hath everlasting life. 48  I am that bread of life. 49  Your fathers did eat manna in the wilderness, and are dead. 50  This is the bread which cometh down from heaven, that a man may eat thereof, and not die. 51  I am the living bread which came down from heaven: if any man eat of this bread, he shall live for ever: and the bread that I will give is my flesh, which I will give for the life of the world. 52  The Jews therefore strove among themselves, saying, How can this man give us his flesh to eat? 53  Then Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except ye eat the flesh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, ye have no life in you. 54  Whoso eateth my flesh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternal life; and I will raise him up at the last day. 55  For my flesh is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed. 56  He that eateth my flesh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him. 57  As the living Father hath sent me, and I live by the Father: so he that eateth me, even he shall live by me. 58  This is that bread which came down from heaven: not as your fathers did eat manna, and are dead: he that eateth of this bread shall live for ever. 59  These things said he in the synagogue, as he taught in Capernaum. 60  Many therefore of his disciples, when they had heard this, said, This is an hard saying; who can hear it? 61  When Jesus knew in himself that his disciples murmured at it, he said unto them, Doth this offend you? 62 [*] What and if ye shall see the Son of man ascend up where he was before? 63  It is the spirit that quickeneth; the flesh profiteth nothing: the words that I speak unto you, they are spirit, and they are life. 64  But there are some of you that believe not. For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were that believed not, and who should betray him. 65  And he said, Therefore said I unto you, that no man can come unto me, except it were given unto him of my Father.

66 ¶ From that time many of his disciples went back, and walked no more with him. 67  Then said Jesus unto the twelve, Will ye also go away? 68  Then Simon Peter answered him, Lord, to whom shall we go? thou hast the words of eternal life. 69 [*] And we believe and are sure that thou art that Christ, the Son of the living God. 70  Jesus answered them, Have not I chosen you twelve, and one of you is a devil? 71  He spake of Judas Iscariot the son of Simon: for he it was that should betray him, being one of the twelve.

7

1  After these things Jesus walked in Galilee: for he would not walk in Jewry, because the Jews sought to kill him. 2 [*] Now the Jews’ feast of tabernacles was at hand. 3  His brethren therefore said unto him, Depart hence, and go into Judæa, that thy disciples also may see the works that thou doest. 4  For there is no man that doeth any thing in secret, and he himself seeketh to be known openly. If thou do these things, shew thyself to the world. 5  For neither did his brethren believe in him. 6  Then Jesus said unto them, My time is not yet come: but your time is alway ready. 7  The world cannot hate you; but me it hateth, because I testify of it, that the works thereof are evil. 8  Go ye up unto this feast: I go not up yet unto this feast; [*]for my time is not yet full come. 9  When he had said these words unto them, he abode still in Galilee.

10 ¶ But when his brethren were gone up, then went he also up unto the feast, not openly, but as it were in secret. 11  Then the Jews sought him at the feast, and said, Where is he? 12  And there was much murmuring among the people concerning him: for some said, He is a good man: others said, Nay; but he deceiveth the people. 13  Howbeit no man spake openly of him for fear of the Jews.

14 ¶ Now about the midst of the feast Jesus went up into the temple, and taught. 15  And the Jews marvelled, saying, How knoweth this man [∥]letters, having never learned? 16  Jesus answered them, [‡]and said, My doctrine is not mine, but his that sent me. 17  If any man will do his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I speak of myself. 18  He that speaketh of himself seeketh his own glory: but he that seeketh his glory that sent him, the same is true, and no unrighteousness is in him. 19 [*] Did not Moses give you the law, and yet none of you keepeth the law? [*]Why go ye about to kill me? 20  The people answered and said, Thou hast a devil: who goeth about to kill thee? 21  Jesus answered and said unto them, I have done one work, and ye all marvel. 22 [*] Moses therefore gave unto you circumcision; (not because it is of Moses, [*]but of the fathers;) and ye on the sabbath day circumcise a man. 23  If a man on the sabbath day receive circumcision, [∥]that the law of Moses should not be broken; are ye angry at me, because I have made a man every whit whole on the sabbath day? 24 [*] Judge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous judgment. 25  Then said some of them of Jerusalem, Is not this he, whom they seek to kill? 26  But, lo, he speaketh boldly, and they say nothing unto him. Do the rulers know indeed that this is the very Christ? 27  Howbeit we know this man whence he is: but when Christ cometh, no man knoweth whence he is. 28  Then cried Jesus in the temple as he taught, saying, Ye both know me, and ye know whence I am: and I am not come of myself, but he that sent me is true, whom ye know not. 29  But I know him: for I am from him, and he hath sent me. 30  Then they sought to take him: but no man laid hands on him, because his hour was not yet come. 31  And many of the people believed on him, and said, When Christ cometh, will he do more miracles than these which this man hath done?

32 ¶ The Pharisees heard that the people murmured such things concerning him; and the Pharisees and the chief priests sent officers to take him. 33  Then said Jesus unto them, Yet a little while am I with you, and then I go unto him that sent me. 34 [*] Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me: and where I am, thither ye cannot come. 35  Then said the Jews among themselves, Whither will he go, that we shall not find him? will he go unto the dispersed among the [∥]Gentiles, and teach the Gentiles? 36  What manner of saying is this that he said, Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me: and where I am, thither ye cannot come? 37 [*] In the last day, that great day of the feast, Jesus stood and cried, saying, If any man thirst, let him come unto me, and drink. 38 [*] He that believeth on me, as the scripture hath said, out of his belly shall flow rivers of living water. 39 ([*]But this spake he of the Spirit, which they that believe on him should receive: for the Holy Ghost was not yet given; because that Jesus was not yet glorified.)

40 ¶ Many of the people therefore, when they heard this saying, said, Of a truth this is the Prophet. 41  Others said, This is the Christ. But some said, Shall Christ come out of Galilee? 42 [*] Hath not the scripture said, That Christ cometh of the seed of David, and out of the town of Bethlehem, where David was? 43  So there was a division among the people because of him. 44  And some of them would have taken him; but no man laid hands on him.

45 ¶ Then came the officers to the chief priests and Pharisees; and they said unto them, Why have ye not brought him? 46  The officers answered, Never man spake like this man. 47  Then answered them the Pharisees, Are ye also deceived? 48  Have any of the rulers or of the Pharisees believed on him? 49  But this people who knoweth not the law are cursed. 50  Nicodemus saith unto them, ([*]he that came to Jesus by night, being one of them,) 51 [*]Doth our law judge any man, before it hear him, and know what he doeth? 52  They answered and said unto him, Art thou also of Galilee? Search, and look: for out of Galilee ariseth no prophet. 53  And every man went unto his own house.

8

1  Jesus went unto the mount of Olives. 2  And early in the morning he came again into the temple, and all the people came unto him; and he sat down, and taught them. 3  And the scribes and Pharisees brought unto him a woman taken in adultery; and when they had set her in the midst, 4  They say unto him, Master, this woman was taken in adultery, in the very act. 5 [*] Now Moses in the law commanded us, that such should be stoned: but what sayest thou? 6  This they said, tempting him, that they might have to accuse him. But Jesus stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground, as though he heard them not. 7  So when they continued asking him, he lifted up himself, and said unto them, [*]He that is without sin among you, let him first cast a stone at her. 8  And again he stooped down, and wrote on the ground. 9  And they which heard it, being convicted by their own conscience, went out one by one, beginning at the eldest, even unto the last: and Jesus was left alone, and the woman standing in the midst. 10  When Jesus had lifted up himself, and saw none but the woman, he said unto her, Woman, where are those thine accusers? hath no man condemned thee? 11  She said, No man, Lord. And Jesus said unto her, Neither do I condemn thee: go, and sin no more.

12 ¶ Then spake Jesus again unto them, saying, [*]I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life. 13  The Pharisees therefore said unto him, Thou bearest record of thyself; thy record is not true. 14  Jesus answered and said unto them, [*]Though I bear record of myself, yet my record is true: for I know whence I came, and whither I go; but ye cannot tell whence I come, and whither I go. 15  Ye judge after the flesh; I judge no man. 16  And yet if I judge, my judgment is true: for I am not alone, but I and the Father that sent me. 17 [*] It is also written in your law, that the testimony of two men is true. 18  I am one that bear witness of myself, and the Father that sent me beareth witness of me. 19  Then said they unto him, Where is thy Father? Jesus answered, Ye neither know me, nor my Father: if ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also. 20  These words spake Jesus in the treasury, as he taught in the temple: and no man laid hands on him; for his hour was not yet come. 21  Then said Jesus again unto them, I go my way, and ye shall seek me, and shall die in your sins: whither I go, ye cannot come. 22  Then said the Jews, Will he kill himself? because he saith, Whither I go, ye cannot come. 23  And he said unto them, Ye are from beneath; I am from above: ye are of this world; I am not of this world. 24  I said therefore unto you, that ye shall die in your sins: for if ye believe not that I am he, ye shall die in your sins. 25  Then said they unto him, Who art thou? And Jesus saith unto them, Even the same that I said unto you from the beginning. 26  I have many things to say and to judge of you: but he that sent me is true; and I speak to the world those things which I have heard of him. 27  They understood not that he spake to them of the Father. 28  Then said Jesus unto them, When ye have lifted up the Son of man, then shall ye know that I am he, and that I do nothing of myself; but as my Father hath taught me, I speak these things. 29  And he that sent me is with me: the Father hath not left me alone; for I do always those things that please him. 30  As he spake [‡]these words, many believed on him. 31  Then said Jesus to those Jews which believed on him, If ye continue in my word, then are ye my disciples indeed; 32  And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free.

33 ¶ They answered him, We be Abraham’s seed, and were never in bondage to any man: how sayest thou, Ye shall be made free? 34  Jesus answered them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, [*]Whosoever committeth sin is the servant of sin. 35  And the servant abideth not in the house for ever: but the Son abideth ever. 36  If the Son therefore shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed. 37  I know that ye are Abraham’s seed; but ye seek to kill me, because my word hath no place in you. 38  I speak that which I have seen with my Father: and ye do that which ye have seen with your father. 39  They answered and said unto him, Abraham is our father. Jesus saith unto them, If ye were Abraham’s children, ye would do the works of Abraham. 40  But now ye seek to kill me, a man that hath told you the truth, which I have heard of God: this did not Abraham. 41  Ye do the deeds of your father. Then said they to him, We be not born of fornication; we have one Father, even God. 42  Jesus said unto them, If God were your Father, ye would love me: for I proceeded forth and came from God; neither came I of myself, but he sent me. 43  Why do ye not understand my speech? even because ye cannot hear my word. 44 [*] Ye are of your father the devil, and the lusts of your father ye will do. He was a murderer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he speaketh a lie, he speaketh of his own: for he is a liar, and the father of it. 45  And because I tell you the truth, ye believe me not. 46  Which of you convinceth me of sin? And if I say the truth, why do ye not believe me? 47 [*] He that is of God heareth God’s words: ye therefore hear them not, because ye are not of God. 48  Then answered the Jews, and said unto him, Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan, and hast a devil? 49  Jesus answered, I have not a devil; but I honour my Father, and ye do dishonour me. 50  And I seek not mine own glory: there is one that seeketh and judgeth. 51  Verily, verily, I say unto you, If a man keep my saying, he shall never see death. 52  Then said the Jews unto him, Now we know that thou hast a devil. Abraham is dead, and the prophets; and thou sayest, If a man keep my saying, he shall never taste of death. 53  Art thou greater than our father Abraham, which is dead? and the prophets are dead: whom makest thou thyself? 54  Jesus answered, If I honour myself, my honour is nothing: it is my Father that honoureth me; of whom ye say, that he is your God: 55  Yet ye have not known him; but I know him: and if I should say, I know him not, I shall be a liar like unto you: but I know him, and keep his saying. 56  Your father Abraham rejoiced to see my day: and he saw it, and was glad. 57  Then said the Jews unto him, Thou art not yet fifty years old, and hast thou seen Abraham? 58  Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Before Abraham was, I am. 59  Then took they up stones to cast at him: but Jesus hid himself, and went out of the temple, going through the midst of them, and so passed by.

9

1  And as Jesus passed by, he saw a man which was blind from his birth. 2  And his disciples asked him, saying, Master, who did sin, this man, or his parents, that he was born blind? 3  Jesus answered, Neither hath this man sinned, nor his parents: but that the works of God should be made manifest in him. 4  I must work the works of him that sent me, while it is day: the night cometh, when no man can work. 5  As long as I am in the world, [*]I am the light of the world. 6  When he had thus spoken, he spat on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, and he [∥]anointed the eyes of the blind man with the clay, 7  And said unto him, Go, wash in the pool of Siloam, (which is by interpretation, Sent.) He went his way therefore, and washed, and came seeing.

8 ¶ The neighbours therefore, and they which before had seen him that he was blind, said, Is not this he that sat and begged? 9  Some said, This is he: others said, He is like him: but he said, I am he. 10  Therefore said they unto him, How were thine eyes opened? 11  He answered and said, A man that is called Jesus made clay, and anointed mine eyes, and said unto me, Go to the pool of Siloam, and wash: and I went and washed, and I received sight. 12  Then said they unto him, Where is he? He said, I know not.

13 ¶ They brought to the Pharisees him that aforetime was blind. 14  And it was the sabbath day when Jesus made the clay, and opened his eyes. 15  Then again the Pharisees also asked him how he had received his sight. He said unto them, He put clay upon mine eyes, and I washed, and do see. 16  Therefore said some of the Pharisees, This man is not of God, because he keepeth not the sabbath day. Others said, How can a man that is a sinner do such miracles? And there was a division among them. 17  They say unto the blind man again, What sayest thou of him, that he hath opened thine eyes? He said, He is a prophet. 18  But the Jews did not believe concerning him, that he had been blind, and received his sight, until they called the parents of him that had received his sight. 19  And they asked them, saying, Is this your son, who ye say was born blind? how then doth he now see? 20  His parents answered them and said, We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind: 21  But by what means he now seeth, we know not; or who hath opened his eyes, we know not: he is of age; ask him: he shall speak for himself. 22  These words spake his parents, because they feared the Jews: for the Jews had agreed already, that if any man did confess that he was Christ, he should be put out of the synagogue. 23  Therefore said his parents, He is of age; ask him. 24  Then again called they the man that was blind, and said unto him, Give God the praise: we know that this man is a sinner. 25  He answered and said, Whether he be a sinner or no, I know not: one thing I know, that, whereas I was blind, now I see. 26  Then said they to him again, What did he to thee? how opened he thine eyes? 27  He answered them, I have told you already, and ye did not hear: wherefore would ye hear it again? will ye also be his disciples? 28  Then they reviled him, and said, Thou art his disciple; but we are Moses’ disciples. 29  We know that God spake unto Moses: as for this fellow, we know not from whence he is. 30  The man answered and said unto them, Why herein is a marvellous thing, that ye know not from whence he is, and yet he hath opened mine eyes. 31  Now we know that God heareth not sinners: but if any man be a worshipper of God, and doeth his will, him he heareth. 32  Since the world began was it not heard that any man opened the eyes of one that was born blind. 33  If this man were not of God, he could do nothing. 34  They answered and said unto him, Thou wast altogether born in sins, and dost thou teach us? And they [∥]cast him out. 35  Jesus heard that they had cast him out; and when he had found him, he said unto him, Dost thou believe on the Son of God? 36  He answered and said, Who is he, Lord, that I might believe on him? 37  And Jesus said unto him, Thou hast both seen him, and it is he that talketh with thee. 38  And he said, Lord, I believe. And he worshipped him.

39 ¶ And Jesus said, For judgment I am come into this world, that they which see not might see; and that they which see might be made blind. 40  And some of the Pharisees which were with him heard these words, and said unto him, Are we blind also? 41  Jesus said unto them, If ye were blind, ye should have no sin: but now ye say, We see; therefore your sin remaineth.

10

1  Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that entereth not by the door into the sheepfold, but climbeth up some other way, the same is a thief and a robber. 2  But he that entereth in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep. 3  To him the porter openeth; and the sheep hear his voice: and he calleth his own sheep by name, and leadeth them out. 4  And when he putteth forth his own sheep, he goeth before them, and the sheep follow him: for they know his voice. 5  And a stranger will they not follow, but will flee from him: for they know not the voice of strangers. 6  This parable spake Jesus unto them: but they understood not what things they were which he spake unto them. 7  Then said Jesus unto them again, Verily, verily, I say unto you, I am the door of the sheep. 8  All that ever came before me are thieves and robbers: but the sheep did not hear them. 9  I am the door: by me if any man enter in, he shall be saved, and shall go in and out, and find pasture. 10  The thief cometh not, but for to steal, and to kill, and to destroy: I am come that they might have life, and that they might have it more abundantly. 11 [*] I am the good shepherd: the good shepherd giveth his life for the sheep. 12  But he that is an hireling, and not the shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, seeth the wolf coming, and leaveth the sheep, and fleeth: and the wolf catcheth them, and scattereth the sheep. 13  The hireling fleeth, because he is an hireling, and careth not for the sheep. 14  I am the good shepherd, and know my sheep, and am known of mine. 15  As the Father knoweth me, even so know I the Father: and I lay down my life for the sheep. 16  And other sheep I have, which are not of this fold: them also I must bring, and they shall hear my voice; [*]and there shall be one fold, and one shepherd. 17  Therefore doth my Father love me, [*]because I lay down my life, that I might take it again. 18  No man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of myself. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again. [*]This commandment have I received of my Father.

19 ¶ There was a division therefore again among the Jews for these sayings. 20  And many of them said, He hath a devil, and is mad; why hear ye him? 21  Others said, These are not the words of him that hath a devil. Can a devil open the eyes of the blind?

22 ¶ And it was at Jerusalem the [*]feast of the dedication, and it was winter. 23  And Jesus walked in the temple in Solomon’s porch. 24  Then came the Jews round about him, and said unto him, How long dost thou [∥]make us to doubt? If thou be the Christ, tell us plainly. 25  Jesus answered them, I told you, and ye believed not: the works that I do in my Father’s name, they bear witness of me. 26  But ye believe not, because ye are not of my sheep, as I said unto you. 27  My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me: 28  And I give unto them eternal life; and they shall never perish, neither shall any man pluck them out of my hand. 29  My Father, which gave them me, is greater than all; and no man is able to pluck them out of my Father’s hand. 30  I and my Father are one. 31  Then the Jews took up stones again to stone him. 32  Jesus answered them, Many good works have I shewed you from my Father; for which of those works do ye stone me? 33  The Jews answered him, saying, For a good work we stone thee not; but for blasphemy; and because that thou, being a man, makest thyself God. 34  Jesus answered them, [*]Is it not written in your law, I said, Ye are gods? 35  If he called them gods, unto whom the word of God came, and the scripture cannot be broken; 36  Say ye of him, whom the Father hath sanctified, and sent into the world, Thou blasphemest; because I said, I am the Son of God? 37  If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not. 38  But if I do, though ye believe not me, believe the works: that ye may know, and believe, that the Father is in me, and I in him. 39  Therefore they sought again to take him: but he escaped out of their hand, 40  And went away again beyond Jordan into the place where John at first baptized; and there he abode. 41  And many resorted unto him, and said, John did no miracle: but all things that John spake of this man were true. 42  And many believed on him there.

11

1  Now a certain man was sick, named Lazarus, of Bethany, the town of Mary and her sister Martha. 2 ([*]It was that Mary which anointed the Lord with ointment, and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick.) 3  Therefore his sisters sent unto him, saying, Lord, behold, he whom thou lovest is sick. 4  When Jesus heard that, he said, This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God might be glorified thereby. 5  Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus. 6  When he had heard therefore that he was sick, he abode two days still in the same place where he was. 7  Then after that saith he to his disciples, Let us go into Judæa again. 8  His disciples say unto him, Master, the Jews of late sought to stone thee; and goest thou thither again? 9  Jesus answered, Are there not twelve hours in the day? If any man walk in the day, he stumbleth not, because he seeth the light of this world. 10  But if a man walk in the night, he stumbleth, because there is no light in him. 11  These things said he: and after that he saith unto them, Our friend Lazarus sleepeth; but I go, that I may awake him out of sleep. 12  Then said his disciples, Lord, if he sleep, he shall do well. 13  Howbeit Jesus spake of his death: but they thought that he had spoken of taking of rest in sleep. 14  Then said Jesus unto them plainly, Lazarus is dead. 15  And I am glad for your sakes that I was not there, to the intent ye may believe; nevertheless let us go unto him. 16  Then said Thomas, which is called Didymus, unto his fellowdisciples, Let us also go, that we may die with him. 17  Then when Jesus came, he found that he had lain in the grave four days already. 18  Now Bethany was nigh unto Jerusalem, [∥]about fifteen furlongs off: 19  And many of the Jews came to Martha and Mary, to comfort them concerning their brother. 20  Then Martha, as soon as she heard that Jesus was coming, went and met him: but Mary sat still in the house. 21  Then said Martha unto Jesus, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died. 22  But I know, that even now, whatsoever thou wilt ask of God, God will give it thee. 23  Jesus saith unto her, Thy brother shall rise again. 24  Martha saith unto him, [*]I know that he shall rise again in the resurrection at the last day. 25  Jesus said unto her, I am the resurrection, and the [*]life: he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet shall he live: 26  And whosoever liveth and believeth in me shall never die. Believest thou this? 27  She saith unto him, Yea, Lord: I believe that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, which should come into the world. 28  And when she had so said, she went her way, and called Mary her sister secretly, saying, The Master is come, and calleth for thee. 29  As soon as she heard that, she arose quickly, and came unto him. 30  Now Jesus was not yet come into the town, but was in that place where Martha met him. 31  The Jews then which were with her in the house, and comforted her, when they saw Mary, that she rose up hastily and went out, followed her, saying, She goeth unto the grave to weep there. 32  Then when Mary was come where Jesus was, and saw him, she fell down at his feet, saying unto him, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died. 33  When Jesus therefore saw her weeping, and the Jews also weeping which came with her, he groaned in the spirit, and [†]was troubled, 34  And said, Where have ye laid him? They [‡]said unto him, Lord, come and see. 35  Jesus wept. 36  Then said the Jews, Behold how he loved him! 37  And some of them said, Could not this man, [*]which opened the eyes of the blind, have caused that even this man should not have died? 38  Jesus therefore again groaning in himself cometh to the grave. It was a cave, and a stone lay upon it. 39  Jesus said, Take ye away the stone. Martha, the sister of him that was dead, saith unto him, Lord, by this time he stinketh: for he hath been dead four days. 40  Jesus saith unto her, Said I not unto thee, that, if thou wouldest believe, thou shouldest see the glory of God? 41  Then they took away the stone from the place where the dead was laid. And Jesus lifted up his eyes, and said, Father, I thank thee that thou hast heard me. 42  And I knew that thou hearest me always: but because of the people which stand by I said it, that they may believe that thou hast sent me. 43  And when he thus had spoken, he cried with a loud voice, Lazarus, come forth. 44  And he that was dead came forth, bound hand and foot with graveclothes: and his face was bound about with a napkin. Jesus saith unto them, Loose him, and let him go. 45  Then many of the Jews which came to Mary, and had seen the things which Jesus did, believed on him. 46  But some of them went their ways to the Pharisees, and told them what things Jesus had done.

47 ¶ Then gathered the chief priests and the Pharisees a council, and said, What do we? for this man doeth many miracles. 48  If we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him: and the Romans shall come and take away both our place and nation. 49  And one of them, named Caiaphas, being the high priest that same year, said unto them, Ye know nothing at all, 50 [*] Nor consider that it is expedient for us, that one man should die for the people, and that the whole nation perish not. 51  And this spake he not of himself: but being high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus should die for that nation; 52  And not for that nation only, but that also he should gather together in one the children of God that were scattered abroad. 53  Then from that day forth they took counsel together for to put him to death. 54  Jesus therefore walked no more openly among the Jews; but went thence unto a country near to the wilderness, into a city called Ephraim, and there continued with his disciples.

55 ¶ And the Jews’ passover was nigh at hand: and many went out of the country up to Jerusalem before the passover, to purify themselves. 56  Then sought they for Jesus, and spake among themselves, as they stood in the temple, What think ye, that he will not come to the feast? 57  Now both the chief priests and the Pharisees had given a commandment, that, if any man knew where he were, he should shew it, that they might take him.

12

1  Then Jesus six days before the passover came to Bethany, where Lazarus was which had been dead, whom he raised from the dead. 2  There they made him a supper; and Martha served: but Lazarus was one of them that sat at the table with him. 3  Then took Mary a pound of ointment of spikenard, very costly, and anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped his feet with her hair: and the house was filled with the odour of the ointment. 4  Then saith one of his disciples, Judas Iscariot, Simon’s son, which should betray him, 5  Why was not this ointment sold for three hundred pence, and given to the poor? 6  This he said, not that he cared for the poor; but because he was a thief, and [*]had the bag, and bare what was put therein. 7  Then said Jesus, Let her alone: against the day of my burying hath she kept this. 8  For the poor always ye have with you; but me ye have not always. 9  Much people of the Jews therefore knew that he was there: and they came not for Jesus’ sake only, but that they might see Lazarus also, whom he had raised from the dead.

10 ¶ But the chief priests consulted that they might put Lazarus also to death; 11  Because that by reason of him many of the Jews went away, and believed on Jesus.

12 ¶ [*]On the next day much people that were come to the feast, when they heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem, 13  Took branches of palm trees, and went forth to meet him, and cried, Hosanna: Blessed is the King of Israel that cometh in the name of the Lord. 14  And Jesus, when he had found a young ass, sat thereon; as it is written, 15 [*] Fear not, daughter of Sion: behold, thy King cometh, sitting on an ass’s colt. 16  These things understood not his disciples at the first: but when Jesus was glorified, then remembered they that these things were written of him, and that they had done these things unto him. 17  The people therefore that was with him when he called Lazarus out of his grave, and raised him from the dead, bare record. 18  For this cause the people also met him, for that they heard that he had done this miracle. 19  The Pharisees therefore said among themselves, Perceive ye how ye prevail nothing? behold, the world is gone after him.

20 ¶ And there were certain Greeks among them that came up to worship at the feast: 21  The same came therefore to Philip, which was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and desired him, saying, Sir, we would see Jesus. 22  Philip cometh and telleth Andrew: and again Andrew and Philip [‡]tell Jesus.

23 ¶ And Jesus answered them, saying, The hour is come, that the Son of man should be glorified. 24  Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except a corn of wheat fall into the ground and die, it abideth alone: but if it die, it bringeth forth much fruit. 25 [*] He that loveth his life shall lose it; and he that hateth his life in this world shall keep it unto life eternal. 26  If any man serve me, let him follow me; and where I am, there shall also my servant be: if any man serve me, him will my Father honour. 27  Now is my soul troubled; and what shall I say? Father, save me from this hour: but for this cause came I unto this hour. 28  Father, glorify thy name. Then came there a voice from heaven, saying, I have both glorified it, and will glorify it again. 29  The people therefore, that stood by, and heard it, said that it thundered: others said, An angel spake to him. 30  Jesus answered and said, This voice came not because of me, but for your sakes. 31  Now is the judgment of this world: now shall the prince of this world be cast out. 32  And I, if I be lifted up from the earth, will draw all men unto me. 33  This he said, signifying what death he should die. 34  The people answered him, [*]We have heard out of the law that Christ abideth for ever: and how sayest thou, The Son of man must be lifted up? who is this Son of man? 35  Then Jesus said unto them, Yet a little while is the light with you. Walk while ye have the light, lest darkness come upon you: for he that walketh in darkness knoweth not whither he goeth. 36  While ye have light, believe in the light, that ye may be the children of light. These things spake Jesus, and departed, and did hide himself from them.

37 ¶ But though he had done so many miracles before them, yet they believed not on him: 38  That the saying of Esaias the prophet might be fulfilled, which he spake, [*]Lord, who hath believed our report? and to whom hath the arm of the Lord been revealed? 39  Therefore they could not believe, because that Esaias said again, 40 [*] He hath blinded their eyes, and hardened their heart; that they should not see with their eyes, nor understand with their heart, and be converted, and I should heal them. 41  These things said Esaias, when he saw his glory, and spake of him.

42 ¶ Nevertheless among the chief rulers also many believed on him; but because of the Pharisees they did not confess him, lest they should be put out of the synagogue: 43 [*] For they loved the praise of men more than the praise of God.

44 ¶ Jesus cried and said, He that believeth on me, believeth not on me, but on him that sent me. 45  And he that seeth me seeth him that sent me. 46 [*] I am come a light into the world, that whosoever believeth on me should not abide in darkness. 47 [*] And if any man hear my words, and believe not, I judge him not: for I came not to judge the world, but to save the world. 48  He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my words, hath one that judgeth him: [*]the word that I have spoken, the same shall judge him in the last day. 49  For I have not spoken of myself; but the Father which sent me, he gave me a commandment, what I should say, and what I should speak. 50  And I know that his commandment is life everlasting: whatsoever I speak therefore, even as the Father said unto me, so I speak.

13

1  Now [*]before the feast of the passover, when Jesus knew that his hour was come that he should depart out of this world unto the Father, having loved his own which were in the world, he loved them unto the end. 2  And supper being ended, the devil having now put into the heart of Judas Iscariot, Simon’s son, to betray him; 3  Jesus knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands, and that he was come from God, and went to God; 4  He riseth from supper, and laid aside his garments; and took a towel, and girded himself. 5  After that he poureth water into a bason, and began to wash the disciples’ feet, and to wipe them with the towel wherewith he was girded. 6  Then cometh he to Simon Peter: and Peter saith unto him, Lord, dost thou wash my feet? 7  Jesus answered and said unto him, What I do thou knowest not now; but thou shalt know hereafter. 8  Peter saith unto him, Thou shalt never wash my feet. Jesus answered him, If I wash thee not, thou hast no part with me. 9  Simon Peter saith unto him, Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head. 10  Jesus saith to him, He that is washed needeth not save to wash his feet, but is clean every whit: and ye are clean, but not all. 11  For he knew who should betray him; therefore said he, Ye are not all clean. 12  So after he had washed their feet, and had taken his garments, and was set down again, he said unto them, Know ye what I have done to you? 13  Ye call me Master and Lord: and ye say well; for so I am. 14  If I then, your Lord and Master, have washed your feet; ye also ought to wash one another’s feet. 15  For I have given you an example, that ye should do as I have done to you. 16 [*] Verily, verily, I say unto you, The servant is not greater than his lord; neither he that is sent greater than he that sent him. 17  If ye know these things, happy are ye if ye do them.

18 ¶ I speak not of you all: I know whom I have chosen: but that the scripture may be fulfilled, [*]He that eateth bread with me hath lifted up his heel against me. 19 [∥] Now I tell you before it come, that, when it is come to pass, ye may believe that I am he. 20 [*] Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that receiveth whomsoever I send receiveth me; and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me. 21 [*] When Jesus had thus said, he was troubled in spirit, and testified, and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, that one of you shall betray me. 22  Then the disciples looked one on another, doubting of whom he spake. 23  Now there was leaning on Jesus’ bosom one of his disciples, whom Jesus loved. 24  Simon Peter therefore beckoned to him, that he should ask who it should be of whom he spake. 25  He then lying on Jesus’ breast saith unto him, Lord, who is it? 26  Jesus answered, He it is, to whom I shall give a [∥]sop, when I have dipped it. And when he had dipped the sop, he gave it to Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon. 27  And after the sop Satan entered into him. Then said Jesus unto him, That thou doest, do quickly. 28  Now no man at the table knew for what intent he spake this unto him. 29  For some of them thought, because Judas had the bag, that Jesus had said unto him, Buy those things that we have need of against the feast; or, that he should give something to the poor. 30  He then having received the sop went immediately out: and it was night.

31 ¶ Therefore, when he was gone out, Jesus said, Now is the Son of man glorified, and God is glorified in him. 32  If God be glorified in him, God shall also glorify him in himself, and shall straightway glorify him. 33  Little children, yet a little while I am with you. Ye shall seek me: [*]and as I said unto the Jews, Whither I go, ye cannot come; so now I say to you. 34 [*] A new commandment I give unto you, That ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye also love one another. 35  By this shall all men know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another.

36 ¶ Simon Peter said unto him, Lord, whither goest thou? Jesus answered him, Whither I go, thou canst not follow me now; but thou shalt follow me afterwards. 37  Peter said unto him, Lord, why cannot I follow thee now? I will [*]lay down my life for thy sake. 38  Jesus answered him, Wilt thou lay down thy life for my sake? Verily, verily, I say unto thee, The cock shall not crow, till thou hast denied me thrice.

14

1  Let not your heart be troubled: ye believe in God, believe also in me. 2  In my Father’s house are many mansions: if it were not so, I would have told you. I go to prepare a place for you. 3  And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you unto myself; that where I am, there ye may be also. 4  And whither I go ye know, and the way ye know. 5  Thomas saith unto him, Lord, we know not whither thou goest; and how can we know the way? 6  Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father, but by me. 7  If ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also: and from henceforth ye know him, and have seen him. 8  Philip saith unto him, Lord, shew us the Father, and it sufficeth us. 9  Jesus saith unto him, Have I been so long time with you, and yet hast thou not known me, Philip? he that hath seen me hath seen the Father; and how sayest thou then, Shew us the Father? 10  Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? the words that I speak unto you I speak not of myself: but the Father that dwelleth in me, he doeth the works. 11  Believe me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works’ sake. 12  Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth on me, the works that I do shall he do also; and greater works than these shall he do; because I go unto my Father. 13 [*] And whatsoever ye shall ask in my name, that will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son. 14  If ye shall ask any thing in my name, I will do it.

15 ¶ If ye love me, keep my commandments. 16  And I will pray the Father, and he shall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever; 17  Even the Spirit of truth; whom the world cannot receive, because it seeth him not, neither knoweth him: but ye know him; for he dwelleth with you, and shall be in you. 18  I will not leave you [∥]comfortless: I will come to you. 19  Yet a little while, and the world seeth me no more; but ye see me: because I live, ye shall live also. 20  At that day ye shall know that I am in my Father, and ye in me, and I in you. 21  He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me: and he that loveth me shall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest myself to him. 22  Judas saith unto him, not Iscariot, Lord, how is it that thou wilt manifest thyself unto us, and not unto the world? 23  Jesus answered and said unto him, If a man love me, he will keep my words: and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him. 24  He that loveth me not keepeth not my sayings: and the word which ye hear is not mine, but the Father’s which sent me. 25  These things have I spoken unto you, being yet present with you. 26  But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto you. 27  Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid. 28  Ye have heard how I said unto you, I go away, and come again unto you. If ye loved me, ye would rejoice, because I said, I go unto the Father: for my Father is greater than I. 29  And now I have told you before it come to pass, that, when it is come to pass, ye might believe. 30  Hereafter I will not talk much with you: for the prince of this world cometh, and hath nothing in me. 31  But that the world may know that I love the Father; and as the Father gave me commandment, even so I do. Arise, let us go hence.

15

1  I am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman. 2 [*] Every branch in me that beareth not fruit he taketh away: and every branch that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit. 3 [*] Now ye are clean through the word which I have spoken unto you. 4  Abide in me, and I in you. As the branch cannot bear fruit of itself, except it abide in the vine; no more can ye, except ye abide in me. 5  I am the vine, ye are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the same bringeth forth much fruit: for [∥]without me ye can do nothing. 6  If a man abide not in me, he is cast forth as a branch, and is withered; and men gather them, and cast them into the fire, and they are burned. 7  If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ye shall ask what ye will, and it shall be done unto you. 8  Herein is my Father glorified, that ye bear much fruit; so shall ye be my disciples. 9  As the Father hath loved me, so have I loved you: continue ye in my love. 10  If ye keep my commandments, ye shall abide in my love; even as I have kept my Father’s commandments, and abide in his love. 11  These things have I spoken unto you, that my joy might remain in you, and that your joy might be full. 12 [*] This is my commandment, That ye love one another, as I have loved you. 13  Greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends. 14  Ye are my friends, if ye do whatsoever I command you. 15  Henceforth I call you not servants; for the servant knoweth not what his lord doeth: but I have called you friends; for all things that I have heard of my Father I have made known unto you. 16  Ye have not chosen me, but I have chosen you, and [*]ordained you, that ye should go and bring forth fruit, and that your fruit should remain: that whatsoever ye shall ask of the Father in my name, he may give it you. 17  These things I command you, that ye love one another. 18  If the world hate you, ye know that it hated me before it hated you. 19  If ye were of the world, the world would love his own: but because ye are not of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you. 20  Remember the word that I said unto you, [*]The servant is not greater than [‡]his lord. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they have kept my saying, they will keep yours also. 21  But all these things will they do unto you for my name’s sake, because they know not him that sent me. 22  If I had not come and spoken unto them, they had not had sin: but now they have no [∥]cloke for their sin. 23  He that hateth me hateth my Father also. 24  If I had not done among them the works which none other man did, they had not had sin: but now have they both seen and hated both me and my Father. 25  But this cometh to pass, that the word might be fulfilled that is written in their law, [*]They hated me without a cause. 26 [*] But when the Comforter is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of truth, which proceedeth from the Father, he shall testify of me: 27  And ye also shall bear witness, because ye have been with me from the beginning.

16

1  These things have I spoken unto you, that ye should not be offended. 2  They shall put you out of the synagogues: yea, the time cometh, that whosoever killeth you will think that he doeth God service. 3  And these things will they do unto you, because they have not known the Father, nor me. 4  But these things have I told you, that when the time shall come, ye may remember that I told you of them. And these things I said not unto you at the beginning, because I was with you. 5  But now I go my way to him that sent me; and none of you asketh me, Whither goest thou? 6  But because I have said these things unto you, sorrow hath filled your heart. 7  Nevertheless I tell you the truth; It is expedient for you that I go away: for if I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will send him unto you. 8  And when he is come, he will [∥]reprove the world of sin, and of righteousness, and of judgment: 9  Of sin, because they believe not on me; 10  Of righteousness, because I go to my Father, and ye see me no more; 11  Of judgment, because the prince of this world is judged. 12  I have yet many things to say unto you, but ye cannot bear them now. 13  Howbeit when he, the Spirit of truth, is come, he will guide you into all truth: for he shall not speak of himself; but whatsoever he shall hear, that shall he speak: and he will shew you things to come. 14  He shall glorify me: for he shall receive of mine, and shall shew it unto you. 15  All things that the Father hath are mine: therefore said I, that he shall take of mine, and shall shew it unto you. 16  A little while, and ye shall not see me: and again, a little while, and ye shall see me, because I go to the Father. 17  Then said some of his disciples among themselves, What is this that he saith unto us, A little while, and ye shall not see me: and again, a little while, and ye shall see me: and, Because I go to the Father? 18  They said therefore, What is this that he saith, A little while? we cannot tell what he saith. 19  Now Jesus knew that they were desirous to ask him, and said unto them, Do ye enquire among yourselves of that I said, A little while, and ye shall not see me: and again, a little while, and ye shall see me? 20  Verily, verily, I say unto you, That ye shall weep and lament, but the world shall rejoice: and ye shall be sorrowful, but your sorrow shall be turned into joy. 21  A woman when she is in travail hath sorrow, because her hour is come: but as soon as she is delivered of the child, she remembereth no more the anguish, for joy that a man is born into the world. 22  And ye now therefore have sorrow: but I will see you again, and your heart shall rejoice, and your joy no man taketh from you. 23  And in that day ye shall ask me nothing. [*]Verily, verily, I say unto you, Whatsoever ye shall ask the Father in my name, he will give it you. 24  Hitherto have ye asked nothing in my name: ask, and ye shall receive, that your joy may be full. 25  These things have I spoken unto you in [∥]proverbs: [‡]but the time cometh, when I shall no more speak unto you in [∥]proverbs, but I shall shew you plainly of the Father. 26  At that day ye shall ask in my name: and I say not unto you, that I will pray the Father for you: 27  For the Father himself loveth you, because ye have loved me, and have believed that I came out from God. 28  I came forth from the Father, and am come into the world: again, I leave the world, and go to the Father. 29  His disciples said unto him, Lo, now speakest thou plainly, and speakest no [∥]proverb. 30  Now are we sure that thou knowest all things, and needest not that any man should ask thee: by this we believe that thou camest forth from God. 31  Jesus answered them, Do ye now believe? 32 [*] Behold, the hour cometh, yea, is now come, that ye shall be scattered, every man to [∥]his own, and shall leave me alone: and yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me. 33  These things I have spoken unto you, that in me ye might have peace. In the world ye shall have tribulation: but be of good cheer; I have overcome the world.

17

1  These words spake Jesus, and lifted up his eyes to heaven, and said, Father, the hour is come; glorify thy Son, that thy Son also may glorify thee: 2 [*] As thou hast given him power over all flesh, that he should give eternal life to as many as thou hast given him. 3  And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent. 4  I have glorified thee on the earth: I have finished the work which thou gavest me to do. 5  And now, O Father, glorify thou me with thine own self with the glory which I had with thee before the world was. 6  I have manifested thy name unto the men which thou gavest me out of the world: thine they were, and thou gavest them me; and they have kept thy word. 7  Now they have known that all things whatsoever thou hast given me are of thee. 8  For I have given unto them the words which thou gavest me; and they have received them, [*]and have known surely that I came out from thee, and they have believed that thou didst send me. 9  I pray for them: I pray not for the world, but for them which thou hast given me; for they are thine. 10  And all mine are thine, and thine are mine; and I am glorified in them. 11  And now I am no more in the world, but these are in the world, and I come to thee. Holy Father, keep through thine own name those whom thou hast given me, that they may be one, as we are. 12  While I was with them in the world, I kept them in thy name: those that thou gavest me I have kept, and none of them is lost, but the son of perdition; [*]that the scripture might be fulfilled. 13  And now come I to thee; and these things I speak in the world, that they might have my joy fulfilled in themselves. 14  I have given them thy word; and the world hath hated them, because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world. 15  I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that thou shouldest keep them from the evil. 16  They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world. 17  Sanctify them through thy truth: thy word is truth. 18  As thou hast sent me into the world, even so have I also sent them into the world. 19  And for their sakes I sanctify myself, that they also might be [∥]sanctified through the truth. 20  Neither pray I for these alone, but for them also which shall believe on me through their word; 21  That they all may be one; as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be one in us: that the world may believe that thou hast sent me. 22  And the glory which thou gavest me I have given them; that they may be one, even as we are one: 23  I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one; and that the world may know that thou hast sent me, and hast loved them, as thou hast loved me. 24 [*] Father, I will that they also, whom thou hast given me, be with me where I am; that they may behold my glory, which thou hast given me: for thou lovedst me before the foundation of the world. 25  O righteous Father, the world hath not known thee: but I have known thee, and these have known that thou hast sent me. 26  And I have declared unto them thy name, and will declare it: that the love wherewith thou hast loved me may be in them, and I in them.

18

1  When Jesus had spoken these words, [*]he went forth with his disciples over the brook Cedron, where was a garden, into the which he entered, and his disciples. 2  And Judas also, which betrayed him, knew the place: for Jesus ofttimes resorted thither with his disciples. 3 [*] Judas then, having received a band of men and officers from the chief priests and Pharisees, cometh thither with lanterns and torches and weapons. 4  Jesus therefore, knowing all things that should come upon him, went forth, and said unto them, Whom seek ye? 5  They answered him, Jesus of Nazareth. Jesus saith unto them, I am he. And Judas also, which betrayed him, stood with them. 6  As soon then as he had said unto them, I am he, they went backward, and fell to the ground. 7  Then asked he them again, Whom seek ye? And they said, Jesus of Nazareth. 8  Jesus answered, I have told you that I am he: if therefore ye seek me, let these go their way: 9  That the saying might be fulfilled, which he spake, [*]Of them which thou gavest me have I lost none. 10  Then Simon Peter having a sword drew it, and smote the high priest’s servant, and cut off his right ear. The servant’s name was Malchus. 11  Then said Jesus unto Peter, Put up thy sword into the sheath: the cup which my Father hath given me, shall I not drink it? 12  Then the band and the captain and officers of the Jews took Jesus, and bound him, 13  And led him away to Annas first; for he was father in law to Caiaphas, which was the high priest that same year.[∥] 14 [*] Now Caiaphas was he, which gave counsel to the Jews, that it was expedient that one man should die for the people.

15 ¶ [*]And Simon Peter followed Jesus, and so did another disciple: that disciple was known unto the high priest, and went in with Jesus into the palace of the high priest. 16  But Peter stood at the door without. Then went out that other disciple, which was known unto the high priest, and spake unto her that kept the door, and brought in Peter. 17  Then saith the damsel that kept the door unto Peter, Art not thou also one of this man’s disciples? He saith, I am not. 18  And the servants and officers stood there, who had made a fire of coals; for it was cold: and they warmed themselves: and Peter stood with them, and warmed himself.

19 ¶ The high priest then asked Jesus of his disciples, and of his doctrine. 20  Jesus answered him, I spake openly to the world; I ever taught in the synagogue, and in the temple, whither the Jews always resort; and in secret have I said nothing. 21  Why askest thou me? ask them which heard me, what I have said unto them: behold, they know what I said. 22  And when he had thus spoken, one of the officers which stood by struck Jesus [∥]with the palm of his hand, saying, Answerest thou the high priest so? 23  Jesus answered him, If I have spoken evil, bear witness of the evil: but if well, why smitest thou me? 24 [*] Now Annas had sent him bound unto Caiaphas the high priest. 25  And Simon Peter stood and warmed himself. [*]They said therefore unto him, Art not thou also one of his disciples? He denied it, and said, I am not. 26  One of the servants of the high priest, being his kinsman whose ear Peter cut off, saith, Did not I see thee in the garden with him? 27  Peter then denied again: and immediately the cock crew.

28 ¶ [*]Then led they Jesus from Caiaphas unto [∥]the hall of judgment: and it was early; [*]and they themselves went not into the judgment hall, lest they should be defiled; but that they might eat the passover. 29  Pilate then went out unto them, and said, What accusation bring ye against this man? 30  They answered and said unto him, If he were not a malefactor, we would not have delivered him up unto thee. 31  Then said Pilate unto them, Take ye him, and judge him according to your law. The Jews therefore said unto him, It is not lawful for us to put any man to death: 32 [*] That the saying of Jesus might be fulfilled, which he spake, signifying what death he should die. 33 [*] Then Pilate entered into the judgment hall again, and called Jesus, and said unto him, Art thou the King of the Jews? 34  Jesus answered him, Sayest thou this thing of thyself, or did others tell it thee of me? 35  Pilate answered, Am I a Jew? Thine own nation and the chief priests have delivered thee unto me: what hast thou done? 36  Jesus answered, My kingdom is not of this world: if my kingdom were of this world, then would my servants fight, that I should not be delivered to the Jews: but now is my kingdom not from hence. 37  Pilate therefore said unto him, Art thou a king then? Jesus answered, Thou sayest that I am a king. To this end was I born, and for this cause came I into the world, that I should bear witness unto the truth. Every one that is of the truth heareth my voice. 38  Pilate saith unto him, What is truth? And when he had said this, he went out again unto the Jews, and saith unto them, I find in him no fault at all. 39 [*] But ye have a custom, that I should release unto you one at the passover: will ye therefore that I release unto you the King of the Jews? 40 [*] Then cried they all again, saying, Not this man, but Barabbas. Now Barabbas was a robber.

19

1  Then [*]Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged him. 2  And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put it on his head, and they put on him a purple robe, 3  And said, Hail, King of the Jews! and they smote him with their hands. 4  Pilate therefore went forth again, and saith unto them, Behold, I bring him forth to you, that ye may know that I find no fault in him. 5  Then came Jesus forth, wearing the crown of thorns, and the purple robe. And Pilate saith unto them, Behold the man! 6  When the chief priests therefore and officers saw him, they cried out, saying, Crucify him, crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Take ye him, and crucify him: for I find no fault in him. 7  The Jews answered him, We have a law, and by our law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God.

8 ¶ When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he was the more afraid; 9  And went again into the judgment hall, and saith unto Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer. 10  Then saith Pilate unto him, Speakest thou not unto me? knowest thou not that I have power to crucify thee, and have power to release thee? 11  Jesus answered, Thou couldest have no power at all against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the greater sin. 12  And from thenceforth Pilate sought to release him: but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou let this man go, thou art not Cæsar’s friend: whosoever maketh himself a king speaketh against Cæsar.

13 ¶ When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he brought Jesus forth, and sat down in the judgment seat in a place that is called the Pavement, but in the Hebrew, Gabbatha. 14  And it was the preparation of the passover, and about the sixth hour: and he saith unto the Jews, Behold your King! 15  But they cried out, Away with him, away with him, crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Shall I crucify your King? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Cæsar. 16 [*] Then delivered he him therefore unto them to be crucified. And they took Jesus, and led him away. 17  And he bearing his cross went forth into a place called the place of a skull, which is called in the Hebrew Golgotha: 18  Where they crucified him, and two other with him, on either side one, and Jesus in the midst.

19 ¶ And Pilate wrote a title, and put it on the cross. And the writing was, JESUS OF NAZARETH THE KING OF THE JEWS. 20  This title then read many of the Jews: for the place where Jesus was crucified was nigh to the city: and it was written in Hebrew, and Greek, and Latin. 21  Then said the chief priests of the Jews to Pilate, Write not, The King of the Jews; but that he said, I am King of the Jews. 22  Pilate answered, What I have written I have written.

23 ¶ [*]Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments, and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also his coat: now the coat was without seam, [∥]woven from the top throughout. 24  They said therefore among themselves, [‡]Let us not rend it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be: that the scripture might be fulfilled, which saith, [*]They parted my raiment among them, and for my vesture they did cast lots. These things therefore the soldiers did.

25 ¶ Now there stood by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother’s sister, Mary the wife of [∥]Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene. 26  When Jesus therefore saw his mother, and the disciple standing by, whom he loved, he saith unto his mother, Woman, behold thy son! 27  Then saith he to the disciple, Behold thy mother! And from that hour that disciple took her unto his own home.

28 ¶ After this, Jesus knowing that all things were now accomplished, [*]that the scripture might be fulfilled, saith, I thirst. 29  Now there was set a vessel full of vinegar: and they filled a spunge with vinegar, and put it upon hyssop, and put it to his mouth. 30  When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up the ghost. 31  The Jews therefore, because it was the preparation, that the bodies should not remain upon the cross on the sabbath day, (for that sabbath day was an high day,) besought Pilate that their legs might be broken, and that they might be taken away. 32  Then came the soldiers, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other which was crucified with him. 33  But when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, they brake not his legs: 34  But one of the soldiers with a spear pierced his side, and forthwith came there out blood and water. 35  And he that saw it bare record, and his record is true: and he knoweth that he saith true, that ye might believe. 36  For these things were done, that the scripture should be fulfilled, [*]A bone of him shall not be broken. 37  And again another scripture saith, [*]They shall look on him whom they pierced.

38 ¶ [*]And after this Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, besought Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus: and Pilate gave him leave. He came therefore, and took the body of Jesus. 39  And there came also Nicodemus, which at the first came to Jesus by night, and brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about an hundred pound weight. 40  Then took they the body of Jesus, and wound it in linen clothes with the spices, as the manner of the Jews is to bury. 41  Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden; and in the garden a new sepulchre, wherein was never man yet laid. 42  There laid they Jesus therefore because of the Jews’ preparation day; for the sepulchre was nigh at hand.

20

1  The [*]first day of the week cometh Mary Magdalene early, when it was yet dark, unto the sepulchre, and seeth the stone taken away from the sepulchre. 2  Then she runneth, and cometh to Simon Peter, and to the [*]other disciple, whom Jesus loved, and saith unto them, They have taken away the Lord out of the sepulchre, and we know not where they have laid him. 3  Peter therefore went forth, and that other disciple, and came to the sepulchre. 4  So they ran both together: and the other disciple did outrun Peter, and came first to the sepulchre. 5  And he stooping down, and looking in, saw the linen clothes lying; yet went he not in. 6  Then cometh Simon Peter following him, and went into the sepulchre, and seeth the linen clothes lie, 7  And the napkin, that was about his head, not lying with the linen clothes, but wrapped together in a place by itself. 8  Then went in also that other disciple, which came first to the sepulchre, and he saw, and believed. 9  For as yet they knew not the scripture, that he must rise again from the dead. 10  Then the disciples went away again unto their own home.

11 ¶ But Mary stood without at the sepulchre weeping: and as she wept, she stooped down, and looked into the sepulchre, 12  And seeth two angels in white sitting, the one at the head, and the other at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain. 13  And they say unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? She saith unto them, Because they have taken away my Lord, and I know not where they have laid him. 14  And when she had thus said, she turned herself back, and saw Jesus standing, and knew not that it was Jesus. 15  Jesus saith unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? whom seekest thou? She, supposing him to be the gardener, saith unto him, Sir, if thou have borne him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away. 16  Jesus saith unto her, Mary. She turned herself, and saith unto him, Rabboni; which is to say, Master. 17  Jesus saith unto her, Touch me not; for I am not yet ascended to my Father: but go to my brethren, and say unto them, I ascend unto my Father, and your Father; and to my God, and your God. 18  Mary Magdalene came and told the disciples that she had seen the Lord, and that he had spoken these things unto her.

19 ¶ [*]Then the same day at evening, being the first day of the week, when the doors were shut where the disciples were assembled for fear of the Jews, came Jesus and stood in the midst, and saith unto them, Peace be unto you. 20  And when he had so said, he shewed unto them his hands and his side. Then were the disciples glad, when they saw the Lord. 21  Then said Jesus to them again, Peace be unto you: as my Father hath sent me, even so send I you. 22  And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghost: 23 [*] Whose soever sins ye remit, they are remitted unto them; and whose soever sins ye retain, they are retained.

24 ¶ But Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came. 25  The other disciples therefore said unto him, We have seen the Lord. But he said unto them, Except I shall see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the nails, and thrust my hand into his side, I will not believe.

26 ¶ And after eight days again his disciples were within, and Thomas with them: then came Jesus, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst, and said, Peace be unto you. 27  Then saith he to Thomas, Reach hither thy finger, and behold my hands; and reach hither thy hand, and thrust it into my side: and be not faithless, but believing. 28  And Thomas answered and said unto him, My Lord and my God. 29  Jesus saith unto him, Thomas, because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed: blessed are they that have not seen, and yet have believed.

30 ¶ [*]And many other signs truly did Jesus in the presence of his disciples, which are not written in this book: 31  But these are written, that ye might believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God; and that believing ye might have life through his name.

21

1  After these things Jesus shewed himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias; and on this wise shewed he himself. 2  There were together Simon Peter, and Thomas called Didymus, and Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two other of his disciples. 3  Simon Peter saith unto them, I go a fishing. They say unto him, We also go with thee. They went forth, and entered into a ship immediately; and that night they caught nothing. 4  But when the morning was now come, Jesus stood on the shore: but the disciples knew not that it was Jesus. 5  Then Jesus saith unto them, [∥]Children, have ye any meat? They answered him, No. 6  And he said unto them, Cast the net on the right side of the ship, and ye shall find. They cast therefore, and now they were not able to draw it for the multitude of fishes. 7  Therefore that disciple whom Jesus loved saith unto Peter, It is the Lord. Now when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he girt his fisher’s coat unto him, (for he was naked,) and did cast himself into the sea. 8  And the other disciples came in a little ship; (for they were not far from land, but as it were two hundred cubits,) dragging the net with fishes. 9  As soon then as they were come to land, they saw a fire of coals there, and fish laid thereon, and bread. 10  Jesus saith unto them, Bring of the fish which ye have now caught. 11  Simon Peter went up, and drew the net to land full of great fishes, an hundred and fifty and three: and for all there were so many, yet was not the net broken. 12  Jesus saith unto them, Come and dine. And none of the disciples durst ask him, Who art thou? knowing that it was the Lord. 13  Jesus then cometh, and taketh bread, and giveth them, and fish likewise. 14  This is now the third time that Jesus shewed himself to his disciples, after that he was risen from the dead.

15 ¶ So when they had dined, Jesus saith to Simon Peter, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me more than these? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my lambs. 16  He saith to him again the second time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my sheep. 17  He [‡]saith unto him the third time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? Peter was grieved because he said unto him the third time, Lovest thou me? And he said unto him, Lord, thou knowest all things; thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith unto him, Feed my sheep. 18  Verily, verily, I say unto thee, When thou wast young, thou girdedst thyself, and walkedst whither thou wouldest: but when thou shalt be old, thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another shall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldest not. 19  This spake he, signifying by what death he should glorify God. And when he had spoken this, he saith unto him, Follow me. 20  Then Peter, turning about, seeth the disciple [*]whom Jesus loved following; which also leaned on his breast at supper, and said, Lord, which is he that betrayeth thee? 21  Peter seeing him saith to Jesus, Lord, and what shall this man do? 22  Jesus saith unto him, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? follow thou me. 23  Then went this saying abroad among the brethren, that that disciple should not die: yet Jesus said not unto him, He shall not die; but, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? 24  This is the disciple which testifieth of these things, and wrote these things: and we know that his testimony is true. 25 [*] And there are also many other things which Jesus did, the which, if they should be written every one, I suppose that even the world itself could not contain the books that should be written. Amen.

* 1.2 Gen. 1. 1.

* 1.3 Col. 1. 16.

* 1.6 Matt. 3. 1.

* 1.10 Heb. 11. 3.

∥ 1.12 Or, the right, or, privilege.

* 1.14 Matt. 1. 16.

* 1.16 Col. 1. 19.

* 1.18 1 Tim. 6 16. 1 John 4. 12.

∥ 1.21 Or, a prophet.

* 1.23 Matt. 3. 3.

* 1.27 Matt. 3. 11. Acts 19. 4.

∥ 1.29 Or, beareth.

* 1.32 Matt. 3. 16.

∥ 1.38 Or, abidest.

∥ 1.39 That was two hours before night.

∥ 1.41 Or, the Anointed.

∥ 1.42 Or, Peter.

* 1.45 Gen. 49. 10. Deut. 18. 18.

* 1.45 Is. 4. 2.

* 2.17 Ps. 69. 9.

* 2.19 Matt. 26. 61.

∥ 3.3 Or, from above.

∥ 3.7 Or, from above.

* 3.14 Num. 21. 9.

* 3.16 1 John 4. 9.

* 3.17 ch. 12. 47.

* 3.19 ch. 1. 4.

∥ 3.20 Or, discovered.

* 3.22 ch. 4. 2.

* 3.26 ch. 1. 7, 34.

* 3.27 Heb. 5. 4.

∥ 3.27 Or, take unto himself.

* 3.28 ch. 1. 20.

* 3.33 Rom. 3. 4.

* 3.35 Matt. 11. 27.

* 3.36 Hab. 2. 4. 1 John 5. 10.

* 4.5 Gen. 33. 19. & 48. 22. Josh. 24. 32.

* 4.20 Deut. 12. 5.

* 4.24 2 Cor. 3. 17.

* 4.35 Matt. 9. 37.

* 4.44 Matt. 13. 57.

* 4.46 ch. 2. 1.

∥ 4.46 Or, courtier, or, ruler.

* 5.1 Lev. 23. 2. Deut. 16. 1.

∥ 5.2 Or, gate.

* 5.10 Jer. 17 22.

∥ 5.13 Or, from the multitude that was.

‡ 5.18 [1611 not only because he]

* 5.29 Matt. 25. 46.

* 5.31 ch. 8. 14.

* 5.32 Matt. 3. 17.

* 5.33 ch. 1. 7.

* 5.37 Matt. 3. 17. & 17. 5.

* 5.37 Deut. 4. 12.

* 5.44 ch. 12. 43.

* 5.46 Gen. 3. 15. Deut. 18. 15.

* 6.4 Lev. 23. 5. Deut. 16. 1.

* 6.5 Matt. 14. 14.

* 6.16 Matt. 14. 23.

∥ 6.27 Or, Work not

* 6.27 Matt. 3. 17.

* 6.29 1 John 3. 23.

* 6.31 Ex. 16. 15. Num 11. 7

* 6.31 Ps. 78. 24.

* 6.42 Matt 13. 55.

* 6.45 Is. 54. 13. Jer. 31. 34.

* 6.46 Matt. 11. 27.

* 6.62 ch. 8. 13.

* 6.69 Matt. 16. 16.

* 7.2 Lev. 23. 34.

* 7.8 ch. 8. 20.

∥ 7.15 Or, learning.

‡ 7.16 [1611 omits and said]

* 7.19 Ex. 24. 3.

* 7.19 ch. 5. 16, 18.

* 7.22 Lev. 12. 3.

* 7.22 Gen. 17. 10.

∥ 7.23 Or, without breaking the law of Moses.

* 7.24 Deut. 1. 16.

* 7.34 ch. 13. 33.

∥ 7.35 Or, Greeks.

* 7.37 Lev. 23. 36.

* 7.38 Deut. 18. 15.

* 7.39 Is. 44. 3. Joel 2. 28.

* 7.42 Matt. 2. 5.

* 7.50 ch. 3. 2.

* 7.51 Deut. 17 8. & 19. 15.

* 8.5 Lev. 20. 10.

* 8.7 Deut. 17. 7.

* 8.12 ch. 1. 5. & 9. 5.

* 8.14 ch. 5 81.

* 8.17 Deut. 17 6. Matt. 18. 16.

‡ 8.30 [1611 those]

* 8.34 Rom. 6. 20. 2 Pet. 2. 19.

* 8.44 1 John 3. 8.

* 8.47 1 John 4. 6.

* 9.5 ch. 1. 9.

∥ 9.6 Or, spread the clay upon the eyes of the blind man.

∥ 9.34 Or, excommunicated him.

* 10.11 Is, 40. 11. Ezek. 84. 23.

* 10.16 Ezek. 37. 22.

* 10.17 Is 53. 7, 8.

* 10.18 Acts 2. 24.

* 10.22 1 Macc. 4 59.

∥ 10.24 Or, hold us in suspense?

* 10.34 Ps. 82. 6.

* 11.2 Matt. 26. 7.

∥ 11.18 That is, about two miles.

* 11.24 Luke 14 14. ch. 5. 29.

* 11.25 ch. 6. 35.

† 11.33 Gr. he troubled himself.

‡ 11.34 [1611 say]

* 11.37 ch. 9. 6.

* 11.50 ch. 18. 14.

* 12.6 ch. 13. 29.

* 12.12 Matt. 21. 8.

* 12.15 Zech. 9. 9.

‡ 12.22 [1611 told]

* 12.25 Matt. 10. 39.

* 12.34 Ps. 110. 4.

* 12.38 Is. 53. 1 Rom. 10. 16.

* 12.40 Matt. 13. 14.

* 12.43 ch. 5. 44.

* 12.46 ch. 3. 19.

* 12.47 ch. 3. 17.

* 12.48 Mark 16. 16.

* 13.1 Matt. 26. 2.

* 13.16 Matt. 10. 24. ch. 15. 20.

* 13.18 Ps. 41. 9.

∥ 13.19 Or, From henceforth.

* 13.20 Matt. 10. 40.

* 13.21 Matt. 26. 21.

∥ 13.26 Or, morsel.

* 13.33 ch. 7. 34.

* 13.34 Lev. 19. 18. ch. 15. 12, 17. 1 John 4. 21.

* 13.37 Matt. 26. 33.

* 14.13 Matt. 7. 7.

∥ 14.18 Or, orphans.

* 15.2 Matt. 15. 13.

* 15.3 ch. 13. 10.

∥ 15.5 Or, severed from me.

* 15.12 ch. 13. 34. 1 Thess. 4. 9. 1 John 3. 11.

* 15.16 Matt. 28. 19.

* 15.20 Matt 10. 24. ch 13. 16

‡ 15.20 [1611 the Lord]

∥ 15.22 Or, excuse.

* 15.25 Ps. 35. 19.

* 15.26 Luke 24. 49 ch 14 26.

∥ 16.8 Or, convince.

* 16.23 Matt. 7. 7.

∥ 16.25 Or, parables

‡ 16.25 [1611 omits but]

∥ 16.25 Or, parables.

∥ 16.29 Or, parable.

* 16.32 Matt. 26 31.

∥ 16.32 Or, his own home.

* 17.2 Matt. 28. 18.

* 17.8 ch. 16. 27.

* 17.12 Ps. 109. 8.

∥ 17.19 Or, truly sanctified.

* 17.24 ch. 12. 26.

* 18.1 Matt. 26. 36.

* 18.3 Matt. 26. 47.

* 18.9 ch. 17. 12.

∥ 18.13 ver. 24.

* 18.14 ch. 11. 50.

* 18.15 Matt. 26. 58.

∥ 18.22 Or, with a rod.

* 18.24 Matt. 26. 57.

* 18.25 Matt. 26. 69.

* 18.28 Matt. 27. 2.

∥ 18.28 Or, Pilate’s house.

* 18.28 Acts 10. 28.

* 18.32 Matt. 20. 19.

* 18.33 Matt. 27. 11.

* 18.39 Matt. 27. 15.

* 18.40 Acts 3. 14.

* 19.1 Matt. 27. 26.

* 19.16 Matt. 27. 31.

* 19.23 Matt. 27. 35.

∥ 19.23 Or, wrought.

‡ 19.24 [1611 Let not us]

* 19.24 Ps. 22. 18.

∥ 19.25 Or, Clopas.

* 19.28 Ps 69. 21.

* 19.36 Ex. 12. 46. Num. 9. 12. Ps. 34. 20.

* 19.37 Zech. 12. 10.

* 19.38 Matt. 27. 57.

* 20.1 Matt. 28. 1. Mark 16. 1.

* 20.2 ch. 13. 23. & 21. 20.

* 20.19 Mark 16. 14.

* 20.23 Matt. 18. 18.

* 20.30 ch. 21. 25.

∥ 21.5 Or, Sirs.

‡ 21.17 [1611 said]

* 21.20 ch. 13. 23. & 20. 2.

* 21.25 ch. 20. 30.

Job

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40

41
42

The Book of Job

1

1  There was a man in the land of Uz, whose name was Job; and that man was [*]perfect and upright, and one that feared God, and eschewed evil. 2  And there were born unto him seven sons and three daughters. 3  His [∥]substance also was seven thousand sheep, and three thousand camels, and five hundred yoke of oxen, and five hundred she asses, and a very great [∥]household; so that this man was the greatest of all the [†]men of the east.

4  And his sons went and feasted in their houses, every one his day; and sent and called for their three sisters to eat and to drink with them. 5  And it was so, when the days of their feasting were gone about, that Job sent and sanctified them, and rose up early in the morning, and offered burnt offerings according to the number of them all: for Job said, It may be that my sons have sinned, and [*]cursed God in their hearts. Thus did Job [†]continually.

6 ¶ Now there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the LORD, and [†]Satan came also [†]among them. 7  And the LORD said unto Satan, Whence comest thou? Then Satan answered the LORD, and said, From [*]going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it. 8  And the LORD said unto Satan, [†]Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil? 9  Then Satan answered the LORD, and said, Doth Job fear God for nought? 10  Hast not thou made an hedge about him, and about his house, and about all that he hath on every side? thou hast blessed the work of his hands, and his [∥]substance is increased in the land. 11  But put forth thine hand now, and touch all that he hath, [†]and he will curse thee to thy face. 12  And the LORD said unto Satan, Behold, all that he hath is in thy [†]power; only upon himself put not forth thine hand. So Satan went forth from the presence of the LORD.

13 ¶ And there was a day when his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house: 14  And there came a messenger unto Job, and said, The oxen were plowing, and the asses feeding beside them: 15  And the Sabeans fell upon them, and took them away; yea, they have slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee. 16 While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, [∥]The fire of God is fallen from heaven, and hath burned up the sheep, and the servants, and consumed them; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee. 17 While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The Chaldeans made out three bands, and [†]fell upon the camels, and have carried them away, yea, and slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee. 18 While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, Thy sons and thy daughters were eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house: 19  And, behold, there came a great wind [†]from the wilderness, and smote the four corners of the house, and it fell upon the young men, and they are dead; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.

20  Then Job arose, and rent his [∥]mantle, and shaved his head, and fell down upon the ground, and worshipped, 21  And said, [*]Naked came I out of my mother’s womb, and naked shall I return thither: the LORD gave, and the LORD hath taken away; blessed be the name of the LORD. 22  In all this Job sinned not, nor [∥]charged God foolishly.

2

1  Again there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the LORD, and Satan came also among them to present himself before the LORD. 2  And the LORD said unto Satan, From whence comest thou? And [*]Satan answered the LORD, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it. 3  And the LORD said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, [*]a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil? and still he holdeth fast his integrity, although thou movedst me against him, [†]to destroy him without cause. 4  And Satan answered the LORD, and said, Skin for skin, yea, all that a man hath will he give for his life. 5  But put forth thine hand now, and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will curse thee to thy face. 6  And the LORD said unto Satan, Behold, he is in thine hand; [∥]but save his life.

7 ¶ So went Satan forth from the presence of the LORD, and smote Job with sore boils from the sole of his foot unto his crown. 8  And he took him a potsherd to scrape himself withal; and he sat down among the ashes.

9 ¶ Then said his wife unto him, Dost thou still retain thine integrity? curse God, and die. 10  But he said unto her, Thou speakest as one of the foolish women speaketh. What? shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil? In all this did not Job sin with his lips.

11 ¶ Now when Job’s three friends heard of all this evil that was come upon him, they came every one from his own place; Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite: for they had made an appointment together to come to mourn with him and to comfort him. 12  And when they lifted up their eyes afar off, and knew him not, they lifted up their voice, and wept; and they rent every one his mantle, and sprinkled dust upon their heads toward heaven. 13  So they sat down with him upon the ground seven days and seven nights, and none spake a word unto him: for they saw that his grief was very great.

3

1  After this opened Job his mouth, and cursed his day. 2  And Job [†]spake, and said, 3 [*] Let the day perish wherein I was born, and the night in which it was said, There is a man child conceived. 4  Let that day be darkness; let not God regard it from above, neither let the light shine upon it. 5  Let darkness and the shadow of death [∥]stain it; let a cloud dwell upon it; [∥]let the blackness of the day terrify it. 6 As for that night, let darkness seize upon it; [∥]let it not be joined unto the days of the year, let it not come into the number of the months. 7  Lo, let that night be solitary, let no joyful voice come therein. 8  Let them curse it that curse the day, who are ready to raise up [∥]their mourning. 9  Let the stars of the twilight thereof be dark; let it look for light, but have none; neither let it see [†]the dawning of the day: 10  Because it shut not up the doors of my mother’s womb, nor hid sorrow from mine eyes.

11  Why died I not from the womb? why did I not give up the ghost when I came out of the belly? 12  Why did the knees prevent me? or why the breasts that I should suck? 13  For now should I have lain still and been quiet, I should have slept: then had I been at rest, 14  With kings and counsellors of the earth, which built desolate places for themselves; 15  Or with princes that had gold, who filled their houses with silver: 16  Or as an hidden untimely birth I had not been; as infants which never saw light. 17  There the wicked cease from troubling; and there the [†]weary be at rest. 18  There the prisoners rest together; they hear not the voice of the oppressor. 19  The small and great are there; and the servant is free from his master.

20  Wherefore is light given to him that is in misery, and life unto the bitter in soul; 21  Which [†]long for death, but it cometh not; and dig for it more than for hid treasures; 22  Which rejoice exceedingly, and are glad, when they can find the grave? 23  Why is light given to a man whose way is hid, [*]and whom God hath hedged in? 24  For my sighing cometh [†]before I eat, and my roarings are poured out like the waters. 25  For [†]the thing which I greatly feared is come upon me, and that which I was afraid of is come unto me. 26  I was not in safety, neither had I rest, neither was I quiet; yet trouble came.

4

1  Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said, 2  If we assay [†]to commune with thee, wilt thou be grieved? but [†]who can withhold himself from speaking? 3  Behold, thou hast instructed many, and thou hast strengthened the weak hands. 4  Thy words have upholden him that was falling, and thou hast strengthened [†]the feeble knees. 5  But now it is come upon thee, and thou faintest; it toucheth thee, and thou art troubled. 6  Is not this thy fear, thy [‡]confidence, thy hope, and the uprightness of thy ways?

7  Remember, I pray thee, who ever perished, being innocent? or where were the righteous cut off? 8  Even as I have seen, [*]they that plow iniquity, and sow wickedness, reap the same. 9  By the blast of God they perish, and [∥]by the breath of his nostrils are they consumed. 10  The roaring of the lion, and the voice of the fierce lion, and the teeth of the young lions, are broken. 11  The old lion perisheth for lack of prey, and the stout lion’s whelps are scattered abroad.

12  Now a thing was [†]secretly brought to me, and mine ear received a little thereof. 13  In thoughts from the visions of the night, when deep sleep falleth on men, 14  Fear [†]came upon me, and trembling, which made [†]all my bones to shake. 15  Then a spirit passed before my face; the hair of my flesh stood up: 16  It stood still, but I could not discern the form thereof: an image was before mine eyes, [∥]there was silence, and I heard a voice, saying, 17  Shall mortal man be more just than God? shall a man be more pure than his maker? 18  Behold, he [*]put no trust in his servants; [∥]and his angels he charged with folly: 19  How much less [‡]in them that dwell in [*]houses of clay, whose foundation is in the dust, which are crushed before the moth? 20  They are [†]destroyed from morning to evening: they perish for ever without any regarding it. 21  Doth not their excellency which is in them go away? they die, even without wisdom.

5

1  Call now, if there be any that will answer thee; and to which of the saints wilt thou [∥]turn? 2  For wrath killeth the foolish man, and [∥]envy slayeth the silly one. 3  I have seen the foolish taking root: but suddenly I cursed his habitation. 4  His children are far from safety, and they are crushed in the gate, neither is there any to deliver them. 5  Whose harvest the hungry eateth up, and taketh it even out of the thorns, and the robber swalloweth up their substance.

6  Although [∥]affliction cometh not forth of the dust, neither doth trouble spring out of the ground; 7  Yet man is born unto [∥]trouble, as [†]the sparks fly upward. 8  I would seek unto God, and unto God would I commit my cause: 9 [*] Which doeth great things [†]and unsearchable; marvellous things [†]without number: 10  Who giveth rain upon the earth, and sendeth waters upon the [†]fields: 11 [*] To set up on high those that be low; that those which mourn may be exalted to safety. 12 [*] He disappointeth the devices of the crafty, so that their hands [∥]cannot perform their enterprise. 13 [*] He taketh the wise in their own craftiness: and the counsel of the froward is carried headlong. 14 [*] They [∥]meet with darkness in the daytime, and grope in the noonday as in the night. 15  But he saveth the poor from the sword, from their mouth, and from the hand of the mighty. 16 [*] So the poor hath hope, and iniquity stoppeth her mouth.

17 [*] Behold, happy is the man whom God correcteth: therefore despise not thou the chastening of the Almighty: 18 [*] For he maketh sore, and bindeth up: he woundeth, and his hands make whole. 19 [*] He shall deliver thee in six troubles: yea, in seven there shall no evil touch thee. 20  In famine he shall redeem thee from death: and in war [†]from the power of the sword. 21  Thou shalt be hid [∥]from the scourge of the tongue: neither shalt thou be afraid of destruction when it cometh. 22  At destruction and famine thou shalt laugh: neither shalt thou be afraid of the beasts of the earth. 23 [*] For thou shalt be in league with the stones of the field: and the beasts of the field shall be at peace with thee. 24  And thou shalt know [∥]that thy tabernacle shall be in peace; and thou shalt visit thy habitation, and shalt not [∥]sin. 25  Thou shalt know also that thy seed shall be [∥]great, and thine offspring as the grass of the earth. 26  Thou shalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a shock of corn [†]cometh in in his season. 27  Lo this, we have searched it, so it is; hear it, and know thou it [†]for thy good.

6

1  But Job answered and said, 2  Oh that my grief were throughly weighed, and my calamity [†]laid in the balances together! 3  For now it would be heavier than the sand of the sea: therefore [∥]my words are swallowed up. 4 [*] For the arrows of the Almighty are within me, the poison whereof drinketh up my spirit: the terrors of God do set themselves in array against me. 5  Doth the wild ass bray [†]when he hath grass? or loweth the ox over his fodder? 6  Can that which is unsavoury be eaten without salt? or is there any taste in the white of an egg? 7 The things that my soul refused to touch are as my sorrowful meat.

8  Oh that I might have my request; and that God would grant me [†]the thing that I long for! 9  Even that it would please God to destroy me; that he would let loose his hand, and cut me off! 10  Then should I yet have comfort; yea, I would harden myself in sorrow: let him not spare; for I have not concealed the words of the Holy One. 11 What is my strength, that I should hope? and what is mine end, that I should prolong my life? 12  Is my strength the strength of stones? or is my flesh [†]of brass? 13  Is not my help in me? and is wisdom driven quite from me?

14 [†] To him that is afflicted pity should be shewed from his friend; but he forsaketh the fear of the Almighty. 15  My brethren have dealt deceitfully as a brook, and as the stream of brooks they pass away; 16  Which are blackish by reason of the ice, and wherein the snow is hid: 17  What time they wax warm, [†]they vanish: [†]when it is hot, they are [†]consumed out of their place. 18  The paths of their way are turned aside; they go to nothing, and perish. 19  The troops of Tema looked, the companies of Sheba waited for them. 20  They were confounded because they had hoped; they came thither, and were ashamed. 21 [∥] For now ye are [†]nothing; ye see my casting down, and are afraid.

22  Did I say, Bring unto me? or, Give a reward for me of your substance? 23  Or, Deliver me from the enemy’s hand? or, Redeem me from the hand of the mighty? 24  Teach me, and I will hold my tongue: and cause me to understand wherein I have erred. 25  How forcible are right words! but what doth your arguing reprove? 26  Do ye imagine to reprove words, and the speeches of one that is desperate, which are as wind? 27  Yea, [†]ye overwhelm the fatherless, and ye dig a pit for your friend. 28  Now therefore be content, look upon me; for it is [†]evident unto you if I lie. 29  Return, I pray you, let it not be iniquity; yea, return again, my righteousness is [∥]in it. 30  Is there iniquity in my tongue? cannot [†]my taste discern perverse things?

7

1  Is there not [∥]an appointed time to man upon earth? are not his days also like the days of an hireling? 2  As a servant [†]earnestly desireth the shadow, and as an hireling looketh for the reward of his work: 3  So am I made to possess months of vanity, and wearisome nights are appointed to me. 4  When I lie down, I say, When shall I arise, and [†]the night be gone? and I am full of tossings to and fro unto the dawning of the day. 5  My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust; my skin is broken, and become loathsome. 6 [*] My days are swifter than a weaver’s shuttle, and are spent without hope.

7  O remember that my life is wind: mine eye [†]shall no more [∥]see good. 8  The eye of him that hath seen me shall see me no more: thine eyes are upon me, and [∥]I am not. 9  As the cloud is consumed and vanisheth away: so he that goeth down to the grave shall come up no more. 10  He shall return no more to his house, neither shall his place know him any more. 11  Therefore I will not refrain my mouth; I will speak in the anguish of my spirit; I will complain in the bitterness of my soul. 12  Am I a sea, or a whale, that thou settest a watch over me? 13  When I say, My bed shall comfort me, my couch shall ease my complaint; 14  Then thou scarest me with dreams, and terrifiest me through visions: 15  So that my soul chooseth strangling, and death rather [†]than my life. 16  I loathe it; I would not live alway: let me alone; for my days are vanity.

17 [*]What is man, that thou shouldest magnify him? and that thou shouldest set thine heart upon him? 18 And that thou shouldest visit him every morning, and try him every moment? 19  How long wilt thou not depart from me, nor let me alone till I swallow down my spittle? 20  I have sinned; what shall I do unto thee, O thou preserver of men? why hast thou set me as a mark against thee, so that I am a burden to myself? 21  And why dost thou not pardon my transgression, and take away mine iniquity? for now shall I sleep in the dust; and thou shalt seek me in the morning, but I shall not be.

8

1  Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said, 2  How long wilt thou speak these things? and how long shall the words of thy mouth be like a strong wind? 3 [*] Doth God pervert judgment? or doth the Almighty pervert justice? 4  If thy children have sinned against him, and he have cast them away [†]for their transgression; 5 [*] If thou wouldest seek unto God betimes, and make thy supplication to the Almighty; 6 If thou wert pure and upright; surely now he would awake for thee, and make the habitation of thy righteousness prosperous. 7  Though thy beginning was small, yet thy latter end should greatly increase.

8 [*] For enquire, I pray thee, of the former age, and prepare thyself to the search of their fathers: 9 (For [*]we are but of yesterday, and know [†]nothing, because our days upon earth are a shadow:) 10  Shall not they teach thee, and tell thee, and utter words out of their heart? 11  Can the rush grow up without mire? can the flag grow without water? 12 [*]Whilst it is yet in his greenness, and not cut down, it withereth before any other herb. 13 So are the paths of all that forget God; and the [*]hypocrite’s hope shall perish: 14  Whose hope shall be cut off, and whose trust shall be [†]a spider’s web. 15  He shall lean upon his house, but it shall not stand: he shall hold it fast, but it shall not endure. 16 He is green before the sun, and his branch shooteth forth in his garden. 17  His roots are wrapped about the heap, and seeth the place of stones. 18  If he destroy him from his place, then it shall deny him, saying, I have not seen thee. 19 Behold, this is the joy of his way, and out of the earth shall others grow.

20  Behold, God will not cast away a perfect man, neither will he [†]help the evil doers: 21  Till he fill thy mouth with laughing, and thy lips with [†]rejoicing. 22  They that hate thee shall be clothed with shame; and the dwelling place of the wicked [†]shall come to nought.

9

1  Then Job answered and said, 2  I know it is so of a truth: but how should [*]man be just [∥]with God? 3  If he will contend with him, he cannot answer him one of a thousand. 4  He is wise in heart, and mighty in strength: who hath hardened himself against him, and hath prospered? 5  Which removeth the mountains, and they know not: which overturneth them in his anger. 6  Which shaketh the earth out of her place, and the pillars thereof tremble. 7  Which commandeth the sun, and it riseth not; and sealeth up the stars. 8 [*] Which alone spreadeth out the heavens, and treadeth upon the [†]waves of the sea. 9 [*] Which maketh [†]Arcturus, Orion, and Pleiades, and the chambers of the south. 10 [*] Which doeth great things past finding out; yea, and wonders without number. 11  Lo, he goeth by me, and I see him not: he passeth on also, but I perceive him not. 12 [*] Behold, he taketh away, [†]who can hinder him? who will say unto him, What doest thou? 13  If God will not withdraw his anger, the [†]proud helpers do stoop under him.

14  How much less shall I answer him, and choose out my words to reason with him? 15  Whom, though I were righteous, yet would I not answer, but I would make supplication to my judge. 16  If I had called, and he had answered me; yet would I not believe that he had hearkened unto my voice. 17  For he breaketh me with a tempest, and multiplieth my wounds without cause. 18  He will not suffer me to take my breath, but filleth me with bitterness. 19 If I speak of strength, lo, he is strong: and if of judgment, who shall set me a time to plead? 20  If I justify myself, mine own mouth shall condemn me: if I say, I am perfect, it shall also prove me perverse. 21  Though I were perfect, yet would I not know my soul: I would despise my life.

22 This is one thing, therefore I said it, He destroyeth the perfect and the wicked. 23  If the scourge slay suddenly, he will laugh at the trial of the innocent. 24  The earth is given into the hand of the wicked: he covereth the faces of the judges thereof; if not, where, and who is he?

25  Now my days are swifter than a post: they flee away, they see no good. 26  They are passed away as the [†][∥]swift ships: as the eagle that hasteth to the prey. 27  If I say, I will forget my complaint, I will leave off my heaviness, and comfort myself: 28  I am afraid of all my sorrows, I know that thou wilt not hold me innocent. 29  If I be wicked, why then labour I in vain? 30  If I wash myself with snow water, and make my hands never so clean; 31  Yet shalt thou plunge me in the ditch, and mine own clothes shall [∥]abhor me. 32 For he is not a man, as I am, that I should answer him, and we should come together in judgment. 33  Neither is there [†]any [∥]daysman betwixt us, that might lay his hand upon us both. 34  Let him take his rod away from me, and let not his fear terrify me: 35  Then would I speak, and not fear him; [†]but it is not so with me.

10

1  My soul is [∥]weary of my life; I will leave my complaint upon myself; I will speak in the bitterness of my soul. 2  I will say unto God, Do not condemn me; shew me wherefore thou contendest with me. 3  Is it good unto thee that thou shouldest oppress, that thou shouldest despise [†]the work of thine hands, and shine upon the counsel of the wicked? 4  Hast thou eyes of flesh? or seest thou as man seeth? 5  Are thy days as the days of man? are thy years as man’s days, 6  That thou enquirest after mine iniquity, and searchest after my sin? 7 [†] Thou knowest that I am not wicked; and there is none that can deliver out of thine hand.

8  Thine hands [†]have made me and fashioned me together round about; yet thou dost destroy me. 9  Remember, I beseech thee, that thou hast made me as the clay; and wilt thou bring me into dust again? 10 [*] Hast thou not poured me out as milk, and [‡]curdled me like cheese? 11  Thou hast clothed me with skin and flesh, and hast [†]fenced me with bones and sinews. 12  Thou hast granted me life and favour, and thy visitation hath preserved my spirit. 13 And these things hast thou hid in thine heart: I know that this is with thee.

14  If I sin, then thou markest me, and thou wilt not acquit me from mine iniquity. 15  If I be wicked, woe unto me; and if I be righteous, yet will I not lift up my head. I am full of confusion; therefore see thou mine affliction; 16  For it increaseth. Thou huntest me as a fierce lion: and again thou shewest thyself marvellous upon me. 17  Thou renewest [∥]thy witnesses against me, and increasest thine indignation upon me; changes and war are against me. 18 [*] Wherefore then hast thou brought me forth out of the womb? Oh that I had given up the ghost, and no eye had seen me! 19  I should have been as though I had not been; I should have been carried from the womb to the grave. 20 [*] Are not my days few? cease then, and let me alone, that I may take comfort a little, 21  Before I go whence I shall not return, even to the land of darkness and the shadow of death; 22  A land of darkness, as darkness itself; and of the shadow of death, without any order, and where the light is as darkness.

11

1  Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said, 2  Should not the multitude of words be answered? and should [†]a man full of talk be justified? 3  Should thy [∥]lies make men hold their peace? and when thou mockest, shall no man make thee ashamed? 4  For thou hast said, My doctrine is pure, and I am clean in thine eyes. 5  But oh that God would speak, and open his lips against thee; 6  And that he would shew thee the secrets of wisdom, that they are double to that which is! Know therefore that God exacteth of thee less than thine iniquity deserveth.

7  Canst thou by searching find out God? canst thou find out the Almighty unto perfection? 8  It is [†]as high as heaven; what canst thou do? deeper than hell; what canst thou know? 9  The measure thereof is longer than the earth, and broader than the sea. 10  If he [∥]cut off, and shut up, or gather together, then [†]who can hinder him? 11  For he knoweth vain men: he seeth wickedness also; will he not then consider it? 12  For [†]vain man would be wise, though man be born like a wild ass’s colt.

13  If thou prepare thine heart, and stretch out thine hands toward him; 14  If iniquity be in thine hand, put it far away, and let not wickedness dwell in thy tabernacles. 15  For then shalt thou lift up thy face without spot; yea, thou shalt be stedfast, and shalt not fear: 16  Because thou shalt forget thy misery, and remember it as waters that pass away: 17 And thine age [†]shall be clearer than the noonday; thou shalt shine forth, thou shalt be as the morning. 18  And thou shalt be secure, because there is hope; yea, thou shalt dig about thee, and thou shalt take thy rest in safety. 19 [*] Also thou shalt lie down, and none shall make thee afraid; yea, many shall [†]make suit unto thee. 20  But the eyes of the wicked shall fail, and [†]they shall not escape, and [*]their hope shall be as [∥]the giving up of the ghost.

12

1  And Job answered and said, 2  No doubt but ye are the people, and wisdom shall die with you. 3  But I have [†]understanding as well as you; [†]I am not inferior to you: yea, [†]who knoweth not such things as these? 4 I am as one mocked of his neighbour, who calleth upon God, and he answereth him: the just upright man is laughed to scorn. 5  He that is ready to slip with his feet is as a lamp despised in the thought of him that is at ease.

6  The tabernacles of robbers prosper, and they that provoke God are secure; into whose hand God bringeth abundantly. 7  But ask now the beasts, and they shall teach thee; and the fowls of the air, and they shall tell thee: 8  Or speak to the earth, and it shall teach thee: and the fishes of the sea shall declare unto thee. 9  Who knoweth not in all these that the hand of the LORD hath wrought this? 10  In whose hand is the [∥]soul of every living thing, and the breath of [†]all mankind. 11 [*] Doth not the ear try words? and the [†]mouth taste his meat?

12  With the ancient is wisdom; and in length of days understanding. 13 [∥]With him is wisdom and strength, he hath counsel and understanding. 14  Behold, he breaketh down, and it cannot be built again: he [*]shutteth [†]up a man, and there can be no opening. 15  Behold, he withholdeth the waters, and they dry up: also he sendeth them out, and they overturn the earth. 16 With him is strength and wisdom: the deceived and the deceiver are his. 17  He leadeth counsellors away spoiled, and maketh the judges fools. 18  He looseth the bond of kings, and girdeth their loins with a girdle. 19  He leadeth princes away spoiled, and overthroweth the mighty. 20 [*] He removeth away [†]the speech of the trusty, and taketh away the understanding of the aged. 21  He poureth contempt upon princes, and [∥]weakeneth the strength of the mighty. 22  He discovereth deep things out of darkness, and bringeth out to light the shadow of death. 23  He increaseth the nations, and destroyeth them: he enlargeth the nations, and [†]straiteneth them again. 24  He taketh away the heart of the chief of the people of the earth, and causeth them to wander in a wilderness where there is no way. 25  They grope in the dark without light, and he maketh them to [†]stagger like a drunken man.

13

1  Lo, mine eye hath seen all this, mine ear hath heard and understood it. 2  What ye know, the same do I know also: I am not inferior unto you. 3  Surely I would speak to the Almighty, and I desire to reason with God. 4  But ye are forgers of lies, ye are all physicians of no value. 5  O that ye would altogether hold your peace! and it should be your wisdom. 6  Hear now my reasoning, and hearken to the pleadings of my lips. 7  Will ye speak wickedly for God? and talk deceitfully for him? 8  Will ye accept his person? will ye contend for God? 9  Is it good that he should search you out? or as one man mocketh another, do ye so mock him? 10  He will surely reprove you, if ye do secretly accept persons. 11  Shall not his excellency make you afraid? and his dread fall upon you? 12  Your remembrances are like unto ashes, your bodies to bodies of clay.

13 [†] Hold your peace, let me alone, that I may speak, and let come on me what will. 14  Wherefore do I take my flesh in my teeth, and put my life in mine hand? 15  Though he slay me, yet will I trust in him: but I will [†]maintain mine own ways before him. 16 He also shall be my salvation: for an hypocrite shall not come before him. 17  Hear diligently my speech, and my declaration with your ears. 18  Behold now, I have ordered my cause; I know that I shall be justified. 19 Who is he that will plead with me? for now, if I hold my tongue, I shall give up the ghost. 20  Only do not two things unto me: then will I not hide myself from thee. 21  Withdraw thine hand far from me: and let not thy dread make me afraid. 22  Then call thou, and I will answer: or let me speak, and answer thou me.

23 How many are mine iniquities and sins? make me to know my transgression and my sin. 24  Wherefore hidest thou thy face, and holdest me for thine enemy? 25  Wilt thou break a leaf driven to and fro? and wilt thou pursue the dry stubble? 26  For thou writest bitter things against me, and [*]makest me to possess the iniquities of my youth. 27  Thou puttest my feet also in the stocks, and [†]lookest narrowly unto all my paths; thou settest a print upon the [†]heels of my feet. 28  And he, as a rotten thing, consumeth, as a garment that is moth eaten.

14

1  Man that is born of a woman is [†]of few days, and full of trouble. 2 [*] He cometh forth like a flower, and is cut down: he fleeth also as a shadow, and continueth not. 3  And dost thou open thine eyes upon such an one, and bringest me into judgment with thee? 4 [†] Who [*]can bring a clean thing out of an unclean? not one. 5 [*] Seeing his days are determined, the number of his months are with thee, thou hast appointed his bounds that he cannot pass; 6  Turn from him, that he may [†]rest, till he shall accomplish, as an hireling, his day.

7  For there is hope of a tree, if it be cut down, that it will sprout again, and that the tender branch thereof will not cease. 8  Though the root thereof wax old in the earth, and the stock thereof die in the ground; 9  Yet through the scent of water it will bud, and bring forth boughs like a plant. 10  But man dieth, and [†]wasteth away: yea, man giveth up the ghost, and where is he? 11  As the waters fail from the sea, and the flood decayeth and drieth up: 12  So man lieth down, and riseth not: till the heavens be no more, they shall not awake, nor be raised out of their sleep. 13  O that thou wouldest hide me in the grave, that thou wouldest keep me secret, until thy wrath be past, that thou wouldest appoint me a set time, and remember me! 14  If a man die, shall he live again? all the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come. 15  Thou shalt call, and I will answer thee: thou wilt have a desire to the work of thine hands.

16 [*] For now thou numberest my steps: dost thou not watch over my sin? 17  My transgression is sealed up in a bag, and thou sewest up mine iniquity. 18  And surely the mountain falling [†]cometh to nought, and the rock is removed out of his place. 19  The waters wear the stones: thou [†]washest away the things which grow out of the dust of the earth; and thou destroyest the hope of man. 20  Thou prevailest for ever against him, and he passeth: thou changest his countenance, and sendest him away. 21  His sons come to honour, and he knoweth it not; and they are brought low, but he perceiveth it not of them. 22  But his flesh upon him shall have pain, and his soul within him shall mourn.

15

1  Then answered Eliphaz the Temanite, and said, 2  Should a wise man utter [†]vain knowledge, and fill his belly with the east wind? 3  Should he reason with unprofitable talk? or with speeches wherewith he can do no good? 4  Yea, [†]thou castest off fear, and restrainest [∥]prayer before God. 5  For thy mouth [†]uttereth thine iniquity, and thou choosest the tongue of the crafty. 6  Thine own mouth condemneth thee, and not I: yea, thine own lips testify against thee. 7  Art thou the first man that was born? or wast thou made before the hills? 8 [*] Hast thou heard the secret of God? and dost thou restrain wisdom to thyself? 9  What knowest thou, that we know not? what understandest thou, which is not in us? 10 With us are both the grayheaded and very aged men, much elder than thy father. 11  Are the consolations of God small with thee? is there any secret thing with thee? 12  Why doth thine heart carry thee away? and what do thy eyes wink at, 13  That thou turnest thy spirit against God, and lettest such words go out of thy mouth? 14 [*]What is man, that he should be clean? and he which is born of a woman, that he should be righteous? 15 [*] Behold, he putteth no trust in his saints; yea, the heavens are not clean in his sight. 16  How much more abominable and filthy is man, which drinketh iniquity like water?

17  I will shew thee, hear me; and that which I have seen I will declare; 18  Which wise men have told from their fathers, and have not hid it: 19  Unto whom alone the earth was given, and no stranger passed among them. 20  The wicked man travaileth with pain all his days, and the number of years is hidden to the oppressor. 21 [†] A dreadful sound is in his ears: in prosperity the destroyer shall come upon him. 22  He believeth not that he shall return out of darkness, and he is waited for of the sword. 23  He wandereth abroad for bread, saying, Where is it? he knoweth that the day of darkness is ready at his hand. 24  Trouble and anguish shall make him afraid; they shall prevail against him, as a king ready to the battle. 25  For he stretcheth out his hand against God, and strengtheneth himself against the Almighty. 26  He runneth upon him, even on his neck, upon the thick bosses of his bucklers: 27  Because he covereth his face with his fatness, and maketh collops of fat on his flanks. 28  And he dwelleth in desolate cities, and in houses which no man inhabiteth, which are ready to become heaps. 29  He shall not be rich, neither shall his substance continue, neither shall he prolong the perfection thereof upon the earth. 30  He shall not depart out of darkness; the flame shall dry up his branches, and by the breath of his mouth shall he go away. 31  Let not him that is deceived trust in vanity: for vanity shall be his recompence. 32  It shall be [∥]accomplished before his time, and his branch shall not be green. 33  He shall shake off his unripe grape as the vine, and shall cast off his flower as the olive. 34  For the congregation of hypocrites shall be desolate, and fire shall consume the tabernacles of bribery. 35 [*] They conceive mischief, and bring forth [∥]vanity, and their belly prepareth deceit.

16

1  Then Job answered and said, 2  I have heard many such things: [∥][*]miserable comforters are ye all. 3  Shall [†]vain words have an end? or what emboldeneth thee that thou answerest? 4  I also could speak as ye do: if your soul were in my soul’s stead, I could heap up words against you, and shake mine head at you. 5  But I would strengthen you with my mouth, and the moving of my lips should asswage your grief.

6  Though I speak, my grief is not asswaged: and though I forbear, [†]what am I eased? 7  But now he hath made me weary: thou hast made desolate all my company. 8  And thou hast filled me with wrinkles, which is a witness against me: and my leanness rising up in me beareth witness to my face. 9  He teareth me in his wrath, who hateth me: he gnasheth upon me with his teeth; mine enemy sharpeneth his eyes upon me. 10  They have gaped upon me with their mouth; they have smitten me upon the cheek reproachfully; they have gathered themselves together against me. 11  God [†]hath delivered me to the ungodly, and turned me over into the hands of the wicked. 12  I was at ease, but he hath broken me asunder: he hath also taken me by my neck, and shaken me to pieces, and set me up for his mark. 13  His archers compass me round about, he cleaveth my reins asunder, and doth not spare; he poureth out my gall upon the ground. 14  He breaketh me with breach upon breach, he runneth upon me like a giant. 15  I have sewed sackcloth upon my skin, and defiled my horn in the dust. 16  My face is foul with weeping, and on my eyelids is the shadow of death;

17 Not for any injustice in mine hands: also my prayer is pure. 18  O earth, cover not thou my blood, and let my cry have no place. 19  Also now, behold, my witness is in heaven, and my record is [†]on high. 20  My friends [†]scorn me: but mine eye poureth out tears unto God. 21  O that one might plead for a man with God, as a man pleadeth for his [∥]neighbour! 22  When [†]a few years are come, then I shall go the way whence I shall not return.

17

1  My [∥]breath is corrupt, my days are extinct, the graves are ready for me. 2  Are there not mockers with me? and doth not mine eye [†]continue in their provocation? 3  Lay down now, put me in a surety with thee; who is he that will strike hands with me? 4  For thou hast hid their heart from understanding: therefore shalt thou not exalt them. 5  He that speaketh flattery to his friends, even the eyes of his children shall fail. 6  He hath made me also a byword of the people; and [∥]aforetime I was as a tabret. 7  Mine eye also is dim by reason of sorrow, and all [∥]my members are as a shadow. 8  Upright men shall be astonied at this, and the innocent shall stir up himself against the hypocrite. 9  The righteous also shall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands [†]shall be stronger and stronger.

10  But as for you all, do ye return, and come now: for I cannot find one wise man among you. 11  My days are past, my purposes are broken off, even [†]the thoughts of my heart. 12  They change the night into day: the light is [†]short because of darkness. 13  If I wait, the grave is mine house: I have made my bed in the darkness. 14  I have [†]said to corruption, Thou art my father: to the worm, Thou art my mother, and my sister. 15 And where is now my hope? as for my hope, who shall see it? 16  They shall go down to the bars of the pit, when our rest together is in the dust.

18

1  Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said, 2  How long will it be ere ye make an end of words? mark, and afterwards we will speak. 3  Wherefore are we counted as beasts, and reputed vile in your sight? 4  He teareth [†]himself in his anger: shall the earth be forsaken for thee? and shall the rock be removed out of his place?

5  Yea, the light of the wicked shall be put out, and the spark of his fire shall not shine. 6  The light shall be dark in his tabernacle, and his [∥]candle shall be put out with him. 7  The steps of his strength shall be straitened, and his own counsel shall cast him down. 8  For he is cast into a net by his own feet, and he walketh upon a snare. 9  The [‡]gin shall take him by the heel, and the robber shall prevail against him. 10  The snare is [†]laid for him in the ground, and a trap for him in the way.

11  Terrors shall make him afraid on every side, and shall [†]drive him to his feet. 12  His strength shall be hungerbitten, and destruction shall be ready at his side. 13  It shall devour the [†]strength of his skin: even the firstborn of death shall devour his strength. 14 [*] His confidence shall be rooted out of his tabernacle, and it shall bring him to the king of terrors. 15  It shall dwell in his tabernacle, because it is none of his: brimstone shall be scattered upon his habitation. 16  His roots shall be dried up beneath, and above shall his branch be cut off. 17 [*] His remembrance shall perish from the earth, and he shall have no name in the street. 18 [†] He shall be driven from light into darkness, and chased out of the world. 19  He shall neither have son nor nephew among his people, nor any remaining in his dwellings. 20  They that come after him shall be astonied at his day, as they that [∥]went before [†]were affrighted. 21 Surely such are the dwellings of the wicked, and this is the place of him that knoweth not God.

19

1  Then Job answered and said, 2  How long will ye vex my soul, and break me in pieces with words? 3  These ten times have ye reproached me: ye are not ashamed that ye [∥]make yourselves strange to me. 4  And be it indeed that I have erred, mine error remaineth with myself. 5  If indeed ye will magnify yourselves against me, and plead against me my reproach: 6  Know now that God hath overthrown me, and hath compassed me with his net. 7  Behold, I cry out of [∥]wrong, but I am not heard: I cry aloud, but there is no judgment.

8  He hath fenced up my way that I cannot pass, and he hath set darkness in my paths. 9  He hath stripped me of my glory, and taken the crown from my head. 10  He hath destroyed me on every side, and I am gone: and mine hope hath he removed like a tree. 11  He hath also kindled his wrath against me, and he counteth me unto him as one of his enemies. 12  His troops come together, and raise up their way against me, and encamp round about my tabernacle. 13  He hath put my brethren far from me, and mine acquaintance are verily estranged from me. 14  My kinsfolk have failed, and my familiar friends have forgotten me. 15  They that dwell in mine house, and my maids, count me for a stranger: I am an alien in their sight. 16  I called my servant, and he gave me no answer; I intreated him with my mouth. 17  My breath is strange to my wife, though I intreated for the children’s sake of [†]mine own body. 18  Yea, [∥]young children despised me; I arose, and they spake against me. 19 [*] All [†]my inward friends abhorred me: and they whom I loved are turned against me. 20  My bone cleaveth to my skin [∥]and to my flesh, and I am escaped with the skin of my teeth. 21  Have pity upon me, have pity upon me, O ye my friends; for the hand of God hath touched me. 22  Why do ye persecute me as God, and are not satisfied with my flesh?

23 [†] Oh that my words were now written! oh that they were printed in a book! 24  That they were graven with an iron pen and lead in the rock for ever! 25  For I know that my redeemer liveth, and that he shall stand at the latter day upon the earth: 26 [∥]And though after my skin worms destroy this body, yet in my flesh shall I see God: 27  Whom I shall see for myself, and mine eyes shall behold, and not [†]another; though my reins be consumed [†]within me. 28  But ye should say, Why persecute we him, [∥]seeing the root of the matter is found in me? 29  Be ye afraid of the sword: for wrath bringeth the punishments of the sword, that ye may know there is a judgment.

20

1  Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said, 2  Therefore do my thoughts cause me to answer, and for this [†]I make haste. 3  I have heard the check of my reproach, and the spirit of my understanding causeth me to answer. 4  Knowest thou not this of old, since man was placed upon earth, 5 [*] That the triumphing of the wicked is [†]short, and the joy of the hypocrite but for a moment? 6  Though his excellency mount up to the heavens, and his head reach unto the [†]clouds; 7  Yet he shall perish for ever like his own dung: they which have seen him shall say, Where is he? 8  He shall fly away as a dream, and shall not be found: yea, he shall be chased away as a vision of the night. 9  The eye also which saw him shall see him no more; neither shall his place any more behold him.

10 [∥] His children shall seek to please the poor, and his hands shall restore their goods. 11  His bones are full of the sin of his youth, which shall lie down with him in the dust. 12  Though wickedness be sweet in his mouth, though he hide it under his tongue; 13  Though he spare it, and forsake it not; but keep it still [†]within his mouth: 14  Yet his meat in his bowels is turned, it is the gall of asps within him. 15  He hath swallowed down riches, and he shall vomit them up again: God shall cast them out of his belly. 16  He shall suck the poison of asps: the viper’s tongue shall slay him. 17  He shall not see the rivers, [∥]the floods, the brooks of honey and butter. 18  That which he laboured for shall he restore, and shall not swallow it down: [†]according to his substance shall the restitution be, and he shall not rejoice therein. 19  Because he hath [†]oppressed and hath forsaken the poor; because he hath violently taken away an house which he builded not; 20 [*] Surely he shall not [†]feel quietness in his belly, he shall not save of that which he desired. 21 [∥] There shall none of his meat be left; therefore shall no man look for his goods. 22  In the fulness of his sufficiency he shall be in straits: every hand of the [∥]wicked shall come upon him.

23  When he is about to fill his belly, God shall cast the fury of his wrath upon him, and shall rain it upon him while he is eating. 24  He shall flee from the iron weapon, and the bow of steel shall strike him through. 25  It is drawn, and cometh out of the body; yea, the [‡]glittering sword cometh out of his gall: terrors are upon him. 26  All darkness shall be hid in his secret places: a fire not blown shall consume him; it shall go ill with him that is left in his tabernacle. 27  The heaven shall reveal his iniquity; and the earth shall rise up against him. 28  The increase of his house shall depart, and his goods shall flow away in the day of his wrath. 29 This is the portion of a wicked man from God, and the heritage [†]appointed unto him by God.

21

1  But Job answered and said, 2  Hear diligently my speech, and let this be your consolations. 3  Suffer me that I may speak; and after that I have spoken, mock on. 4 As for me, is my complaint to man? and if it were so, why should not my spirit be [†]troubled? 5 [†] Mark me, and be astonished, and lay your hand upon your mouth. 6  Even when I remember I am afraid, and trembling taketh hold on my flesh.

7 [*] Wherefore do the wicked live, become old, yea, are mighty in power? 8  Their seed is established in their sight with them, and their offspring before their eyes. 9  Their houses [†]are safe from fear, neither is the rod of God upon them. 10  Their bull gendereth, and faileth not; their cow calveth, and casteth not her calf. 11  They send forth their little ones like a flock, and their children dance. 12  They take the timbrel and harp, and rejoice at the sound of the organ. 13  They spend their days [∥]in wealth, and in a moment go down to the grave. 14 [*] Therefore they say unto God, Depart from us; for we desire not the knowledge of thy ways. 15 What is the Almighty, that we should serve him? and what profit should we have, if we pray unto him? 16  Lo, their good is not in their hand: the counsel of the wicked is far from me.

17  How oft is the [∥]candle of the wicked put out! and how oft cometh their destruction upon them! God distributeth sorrows in his anger. 18  They are as stubble before the wind, and as chaff that the storm [†]carrieth away. 19  God layeth up [∥]his iniquity for his children: he rewardeth him, and he shall know it. 20  His eyes shall see his destruction, and he shall drink of the wrath of the Almighty. 21  For what pleasure hath he in his house after him, when the number of his months is cut off in the midst? 22 Shall any teach God knowledge? seeing he judgeth those that are high. 23  One dieth [†]in his full strength, being wholly at ease and quiet. 24  His [∥]breasts are full of milk, and his bones are moistened with marrow. 25  And another dieth in the bitterness of his soul, and never eateth with pleasure. 26  They shall lie down alike in the dust, and the worms shall cover them.

27  Behold, I know your thoughts, and the devices which ye wrongfully imagine against me. 28  For ye say, Where is the house of the prince? and where are [†]the dwelling places of the wicked? 29  Have ye not asked them that go by the way? and do ye not know their tokens, 30 [*] That the wicked is reserved to the day of destruction? they shall be brought forth to [†]the day of wrath. 31  Who shall declare his way to his face? and who shall repay him what he hath done? 32  Yet shall he be brought to the [†]grave, and shall [†]remain in the tomb. 33  The clods of the valley shall be sweet unto him, and every man shall draw after him, as there are innumerable before him. 34  How then comfort ye me in vain, seeing in your answers there remaineth [†]falsehood?

22

1  Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said, 2  Can a man be profitable unto God, [∥]as he that is wise may be profitable unto himself? 3  Is it any pleasure to the Almighty, that thou art righteous? or is it gain to him, that thou makest thy ways perfect? 4  Will he reprove thee for fear of thee? will he enter with thee into judgment?

5  Is not thy wickedness great? and thine iniquities infinite? 6  For thou hast taken a pledge from thy brother for nought, and [†]stripped the naked of their clothing. 7  Thou hast not given water to the weary to drink, and thou hast withholden bread from the hungry. 8 But as for [†]the mighty man, he had the earth; and the [†]honourable man dwelt in it. 9  Thou hast sent widows away empty, and the arms of the fatherless have been broken. 10  Therefore snares are round about thee, and sudden fear troubleth thee; 11  Or darkness, that thou canst not see; and abundance of waters cover thee. 12  Is not God in the height of heaven? and behold [†]the height of the stars, how high they are! 13  And thou sayest, [∥]How doth God know? can he judge through the dark cloud? 14  Thick clouds are a covering to him, that he seeth not; and he walketh in the circuit of heaven.

15  Hast thou marked the old way which wicked men have trodden? 16  Which were cut down out of time, [†]whose foundation was overflown with a flood: 17 [*] Which said unto God, Depart from us: and what can the Almighty do [∥]for them? 18  Yet he filled their houses with good things: but [*]the counsel of the wicked is far from me. 19 [*] The righteous see it, and are glad: and the innocent laugh them to scorn. 20  Whereas our [∥]substance is not cut down, but [∥]the remnant of them the fire consumeth.

21  Acquaint now thyself [∥]with him, and be at peace: thereby good shall come unto thee. 22  Receive, I pray thee, the law from his mouth, and lay up his words in thine heart. 23 [*] If thou return to the Almighty, thou shalt be built up, thou shalt put away iniquity far from thy tabernacles. 24  Then shalt thou lay up gold [∥]as dust, and the gold of Ophir as the stones of the brooks. 25  Yea, the Almighty shall be thy [∥]defence, and thou shalt have [†]plenty of silver. 26  For then shalt thou have thy delight in the Almighty, and shalt lift up thy face unto God. 27  Thou shalt make thy prayer unto him, and he shall hear thee, and thou shalt pay thy vows. 28  Thou shalt also decree a thing, and it shall be established unto thee: and the light shall shine upon thy ways. 29 When men are cast down, then thou shalt say, There is lifting up; and he shall save [†]the humble person. 30 [∥] He shall deliver the island of the innocent: and it is delivered by the pureness of thine hands.

23

1  Then Job answered and said, 2  Even to day is my complaint bitter: [†]my stroke is heavier than my groaning. 3  Oh that I knew where I might find him! that I might come even to his seat! 4  I would order my cause before him, and fill my mouth with arguments. 5  I would know the words which he would answer me, and understand what he would say unto me. 6  Will he plead against me with his great power? No; but he would put strength in me. 7  There the righteous might dispute with him; so should I be delivered for ever from my judge.

8  Behold, I go forward, but he is not there; and backward, but I cannot perceive him: 9  On the left hand, where he doth work, but I cannot behold him: he hideth himself on the right hand, that I cannot see him: 10  But he knoweth [†]the way that I take: when he hath tried me, I shall come forth as gold. 11  My foot hath held his steps, his way have I kept, and not declined. 12  Neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips; [†]I have esteemed the words of his mouth more than [∥]my necessary food.

13 But he is in one mind, and who can turn him? and what [*]his soul desireth, even that he doeth. 14  For he performeth the thing that is appointed for me: and many such things are with him. 15  Therefore am I troubled at his presence: when I consider, I am afraid of him. 16  For God maketh my heart soft, and the Almighty troubleth me: 17  Because I was not cut off before the darkness, neither hath he covered the darkness from my face.

24

1  Why, seeing times are not hidden from the Almighty, do they that know him not see his days? 2  Some remove the [*]landmarks; they violently take away flocks, and [∥]feed thereof. 3  They drive away the ass of the fatherless, they take the widow’s ox for a pledge. 4  They turn the needy out of the way: the poor of the earth hide themselves together. 5 Behold, as wild asses in the desert, go they forth to their work; rising betimes for a prey: the wilderness yieldeth food for them and for their children. 6  They reap every one his [†]corn in the field: and [†]they gather the vintage of the wicked. 7  They cause the naked to lodge without clothing, that they have no covering in the cold. 8  They are wet with the showers of the mountains, and embrace the rock for want of a shelter. 9  They pluck the fatherless from the breast, and take a pledge of the poor. 10 They cause him to go naked without clothing, and they take away the sheaf from the hungry; 11  Which make oil within their walls, and tread their winepresses, and suffer thirst. 12  Men groan from out of the city, and the soul of the wounded crieth out: yet God layeth not folly to them.

13  They are of those that rebel against the light; they know not the ways thereof, nor abide in the paths thereof. 14  The murderer rising with the light killeth the poor and needy, and in the night is as a thief. 15  The eye also of the adulterer waiteth for the twilight, saying, No eye shall see me: and [†]disguiseth his face. 16  In the dark they dig through houses, which they had marked for themselves in the daytime: they know not the light. 17  For the morning is to them even as the shadow of death: if one know them, they are in the terrors of the shadow of death.

18 He is swift as the waters; their portion is cursed in the earth: he beholdeth not the way of the vineyards. 19  Drought and heat [†]consume the snow waters: so doth the grave those which have sinned. 20  The womb shall forget him; the worm shall feed sweetly on him; he shall be no more remembered; and wickedness shall be broken as a tree. 21  He evil entreateth the barren that beareth not: and doeth not good to the widow. 22  He draweth also the mighty with his power: he riseth up, [∥]and no man is sure of life. 23  Though it be given him to be in safety, whereon he resteth; yet his eyes are upon their ways. 24  They are exalted for a little while, but [†]are gone and brought low; they are [†]taken out of the way as all other, and cut off as the tops of the ears of corn. 25 And if it be not so now, who will make me a liar, and make my speech nothing worth?

25

1  Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said, 2  Dominion and fear are with him, he maketh peace in his high places. 3  Is there any number of his armies? and upon whom doth not his light arise? 4 [*] How then can man be justified with God? or how can he be clean that is born of a woman? 5  Behold even to the moon, and it shineth not; yea, the stars are not pure in his sight. 6  How much less man, that is [*]a worm? and the son of man, which is a worm?

26

1  But Job answered and said, 2  How hast thou helped him that is without power? how savest thou the arm that hath no strength? 3  How hast thou counselled him that hath no wisdom? and how hast thou plentifully declared the thing as it is? 4  To whom hast thou uttered words? and whose spirit came from thee?

5  Dead things are formed from under the waters, [∥]and the inhabitants thereof. 6 [*] Hell is naked before him, and destruction hath no covering. 7  He stretcheth out the north over the empty place, and hangeth the earth upon nothing. 8  He bindeth up the waters in his thick clouds; and the cloud is not rent under them. 9  He holdeth back the face of his throne, and spreadeth his cloud upon it. 10  He hath compassed the waters with bounds, [†]until the day and night come to an end. 11  The pillars of heaven tremble and are astonished at his reproof. 12  He divideth the sea with his power, and by his understanding he smiteth through [†]the proud. 13  By his spirit he hath garnished the heavens; his hand hath formed the crooked serpent. 14 Lo, these are parts of his ways: but how little a portion is heard of him? but the thunder of his power who can understand?

27

1  Moreover Job [†]continued his parable, and said, 2  As God liveth, who hath taken away my judgment; and the Almighty, who hath [†]vexed my soul; 3  All the while my breath is in me, and [∥]the spirit of God is in my nostrils; 4  My lips shall not speak wickedness, nor my tongue utter deceit. 5  God forbid that I should justify you: till I die I will not remove mine integrity from me. 6  My righteousness I hold fast, and will not let it go: my heart shall not reproach me [†]so long as I live.

7  Let mine enemy be as the wicked, and he that riseth up against me as the unrighteous. 8 [*]For what is the hope of the hypocrite, though he hath gained, when God taketh away his soul? 9 [*] Will God hear his cry when trouble cometh upon him? 10  Will he delight himself in the Almighty? will he always call upon God?

11  I will teach you [∥]by the hand of God: that which is with the Almighty will I not conceal. 12  Behold, all ye yourselves have seen it; why then are ye thus altogether vain? 13 This is the portion of a wicked man with God, and the heritage of oppressors, which they shall receive of the Almighty. 14  If his children be multiplied, it is for the sword: and his offspring shall not be satisfied with bread. 15  Those that remain of him shall be buried in death: and [*]his widows shall not weep. 16  Though he heap up silver as the dust, and prepare raiment as the clay; 17  He may prepare it, but the just shall put it on, and the innocent shall divide the silver. 18  He buildeth his house as a moth, and as a booth that the keeper maketh. 19  The rich man shall lie down, but he shall not be gathered: he openeth his eyes, and he is not. 20 [*] Terrors take hold on him as waters, a tempest stealeth him away in the night. 21  The east wind carrieth him away, and he departeth: and as a storm hurleth him out of his place. 22 For God shall cast upon him, and not spare: [†]he would fain flee out of his hand. 23  Men shall clap their hands at him, and shall hiss him out of his place.

28

1  Surely there is [∥]a vein for the silver, and a place for gold where they fine it. 2  Iron is taken out of the [∥]earth, and brass is molten out of the stone. 3  He setteth an end to darkness, and searcheth out all perfection: the stones of darkness, and the shadow of death. 4  The flood breaketh out from the inhabitant; even the waters forgotten of the foot: they are dried up, they are gone away from men. 5  As for the earth, out of it cometh bread: and under it is turned up as it were fire. 6  The stones of it are the place of sapphires: and it hath [∥]dust of gold. 7  There is a path which no fowl knoweth, and which the vulture’s eye hath not seen: 8  The lion’s whelps have not trodden it, nor the fierce lion passed by it. 9  He putteth forth his hand upon the [∥]rock; he overturneth the mountains by the roots. 10  He cutteth out rivers among the rocks; and his eye seeth every precious thing. 11  He bindeth the floods [†]from overflowing; and the thing that is hid bringeth he forth to light. 12  But where shall wisdom be found? and where is the place of understanding? 13  Man knoweth not the price thereof; neither is it found in the land of the living.

14 [*] The depth saith, It is not in me: and the sea saith, It is not with me. 15 [†] It [*]cannot be gotten for gold, neither shall silver be weighed for the price thereof. 16  It cannot be valued with the gold of Ophir, with the precious onyx, or the sapphire. 17  The gold and the crystal cannot equal it: and the exchange of it shall not be for [∥]jewels of fine gold. 18  No mention shall be made of [∥]coral, or of pearls: for the price of wisdom is above rubies. 19  The topaz of Ethiopia shall not equal it, neither shall it be valued with pure gold.

20 [*] Whence then cometh wisdom? and where is the place of understanding? 21  Seeing it is hid from the eyes of all living, and kept close from the fowls of the [∥]air. 22  Destruction and death say, We have heard the fame thereof with our ears. 23  God understandeth the way thereof, and he knoweth the place thereof. 24  For he looketh to the ends of the earth, and seeth under the whole heaven; 25  To make the weight for the winds; and he weigheth the waters by measure. 26  When he made a decree for the rain, and a way for the lightning of the thunder: 27  Then did he see it, and [∥]declare it; he prepared it, yea, and searched it out. 28  And unto man he said, Behold, [*]the fear of the Lord, that is wisdom; and to depart from evil is understanding.

29

1  Moreover Job [†]continued his parable, and said, 2  Oh that I were as in months past, as in the days when God preserved me; 3  When his [∥]candle shined upon my head, and when by his light I walked through darkness; 4  As I was in the days of my youth, when the secret of God was upon my tabernacle; 5  When the Almighty was yet with me, when my children were about me; 6  When I washed my steps with butter, and the rock poured [†]me out rivers of oil;

7  When I went out to the gate through the city, when I prepared my seat in the street! 8  The young men saw me, and hid themselves: and the aged arose, and stood up. 9  The princes refrained talking, and laid their hand on their mouth. 10 [†] The nobles held their peace, and their tongue cleaved to the roof of their mouth. 11  When the ear heard me, then it blessed me; and when the eye saw me, it gave witness to me: 12  Because I delivered the poor that cried, and the fatherless, and him that had none to help him. 13  The blessing of him that was ready to perish came upon me: and I caused the widow’s heart to sing for joy. 14  I put on righteousness, and it clothed me: my judgment was as a robe and a diadem. 15  I was eyes to the blind, and feet was I to the lame. 16 I was a father to the poor: and the cause which I knew not I searched out. 17  And I brake [†]the jaws of the wicked, and [†]plucked the spoil out of his teeth.

18  Then I said, I shall die in my nest, and I shall multiply my days as the sand. 19  My root was [†]spread out by the waters, and the dew lay all night upon my branch. 20  My glory was [†]fresh in me, and my bow was [†]renewed in my hand. 21 Unto me men gave ear, and waited, and kept silence at my counsel. 22  After my words they spake not again; and my speech dropped upon them. 23  And they waited for me as for the rain; and they opened their mouth wide as for the latter rain. 24  If I laughed on them, they believed it not; and the light of my countenance they cast not down. 25  I chose out their way, and sat chief, and dwelt as a king in the army, as one that comforteth the mourners.

30

1 But now they that are [†]younger than I have me in derision, whose fathers I would have disdained to have set with the dogs of my flock. 2  Yea, whereto might the strength of their hands profit me, in whom old age was perished? 3  For want and famine they were [∥]solitary; [‡]fleeing into the wilderness [†]in former time desolate and waste. 4  Who cut up mallows by the bushes, and juniper roots for their meat. 5  They were driven forth from among men, (they cried after them as after a thief;) 6  To dwell in the [‡]clifts of the valleys, in [†]caves of the earth, and in the rocks. 7  Among the bushes they brayed; under the nettles they were gathered together. 8  They were children of fools, yea, children of [†]base men: they were viler than the earth. 9 [*] And now am I their song, yea, I am their byword. 10  They abhor me, they flee far from me, [†]and spare not to spit in my face. 11  Because he hath loosed my cord, and afflicted me, they have also let loose the bridle before me. 12 Upon my right hand rise the youth; they push away my feet, and they raise up against me the ways of their destruction. 13  They mar my path, they set forward my calamity, they have no helper. 14  They came upon me as a wide breaking in of waters: in the desolation they rolled themselves upon me.

15  Terrors are turned upon me: they pursue [†]my soul as the wind: and my welfare passeth away as a cloud. 16  And now my soul is poured out upon me; the days of affliction have taken hold upon me. 17  My bones are pierced in me in the night season: and my sinews take no rest. 18  By the great force of my disease is my garment changed: it bindeth me about as the collar of my coat. 19  He hath cast me into the mire, and I am become like dust and ashes. 20  I cry unto thee, and thou dost not hear me: I stand up, and thou regardest me not. 21  Thou art [†]become cruel to me: with [†]thy strong hand thou opposest thyself against me. 22  Thou liftest me up to the wind; thou causest me to ride upon it, and dissolvest my [∥]substance. 23  For I know that thou wilt bring me to death, and to the house appointed for all living. 24  Howbeit he will not stretch out his hand to the [†]grave, though they cry in his destruction. 25 [*] Did not I weep [†]for him that was in trouble? was not my soul grieved for the poor? 26  When I looked for good, then evil came unto me: and when I waited for light, there came darkness. 27  My bowels boiled, and rested not: the days of affliction prevented me. 28  I went mourning without the sun: I stood up, and I cried in the congregation. 29 [*] I am a brother to dragons, and a companion to [∥]owls. 30  My skin is black upon me, and my bones are burned with heat. 31  My harp also is turned to mourning, and my organ into the voice of them that weep.

31

1  I made a covenant with mine eyes; why then should I think upon a maid? 2  For what portion of God is there from above? and what inheritance of the Almighty from on high? 3  Is not destruction to the wicked? and a strange punishment to the workers of iniquity? 4 [*] Doth not he see my ways, and count all my steps? 5  If I have walked with vanity, or if my foot hath hasted to deceit; 6 [†] Let me be weighed in an even balance, that God may know mine integrity. 7  If my step hath turned out of the way, and mine heart walked after mine eyes, and if any blot hath cleaved to mine hands; 8  Then let me sow, and let another eat; yea, let my offspring be rooted out.

9  If mine heart have been deceived by a woman, or if I have laid wait at my neighbour’s door; 10  Then let my wife grind unto another, and let others bow down upon her. 11 For this is an heinous crime; yea, it is an iniquity to be punished by the judges. 12 For it is a fire that consumeth to destruction, and would root out all mine increase. 13  If I did despise the cause of my manservant or of my maidservant, when they contended with me; 14  What then shall I do when God riseth up? and when he visiteth, what shall I answer him? 15  Did not he that made me in the womb make him? and [∥]did not one fashion us in the womb?

16  If I have withheld the poor from their desire, or have caused the eyes of the widow to fail; 17  Or have eaten my morsel myself alone, and the fatherless hath not eaten thereof; 18 (For from my youth he was brought up with me, as with a father, and I have guided [∥]her from my mother’s womb;) 19  If I have seen any perish for want of clothing, or any poor without covering; 20  If his loins have not blessed me, and if he were not warmed with the fleece of my sheep; 21  If I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless, when I saw my help in the gate: 22  Then let mine arm fall from my shoulder blade, and mine arm be broken from [∥]the bone. 23  For destruction from God was a terror to me, and by reason of his highness I could not endure.

24  If I have made gold my hope, or have said to the fine gold, Thou art my confidence; 25  If I rejoiced because my wealth was great, and because mine hand had [†]gotten much; 26  If I beheld [†]the sun when it shined, or the moon walking [†] in brightness; 27  And my heart hath been secretly enticed, or [†]my mouth hath kissed my hand: 28 This also were an iniquity to be punished by the judge: for I should have denied the God that is above. 29  If I rejoiced at the destruction of him that hated me, or lifted up myself when evil found him: 30  Neither have I suffered [†]my mouth to sin by wishing a curse to his soul. 31  If the men of my tabernacle said not, Oh that we had of his flesh! we cannot be satisfied. 32  The stranger did not lodge in the street: but I opened my doors [∥]to the traveller.

33  If I covered my transgressions [∥]as Adam, by hiding mine iniquity in my bosom: 34  Did I fear a great multitude, or did the contempt of families terrify me, that I kept silence, and went not out of the door? 35  Oh that one would hear me! [∥]behold, my desire is, that the Almighty would answer me, and that mine adversary had written a book. 36  Surely I would take it upon my shoulder, and bind it as a crown to me. 37  I would declare unto him the number of my steps; as a prince would I go near unto him. 38  If my land cry against me, or that the furrows likewise thereof [†]complain; 39  If I have eaten [†]the fruits thereof without money, or have [†]caused the owners thereof to lose their life: 40  Let thistles grow instead of wheat, and [∥]cockle instead of barley. The words of Job are ended.

32

1  So these three men ceased [†]to answer Job, because he was righteous in his own eyes. 2  Then was kindled the wrath of Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite, of the kindred of Ram: against Job was his wrath kindled, because he justified [†]himself rather than God. 3  Also against his three friends was his wrath kindled, because they had found no answer, and yet had condemned Job. 4  Now Elihu had [†]waited till Job had spoken, because they were [†]elder than he. 5  When Elihu saw that there was no answer in the mouth of these three men, then his wrath was kindled.

6  And Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered and said, I am [†]young, and ye are very old; wherefore I was afraid, and [†]durst not shew you mine opinion. 7  I said, Days should speak, and multitude of years should teach wisdom. 8  But there is a spirit in man: and [*]the inspiration of the Almighty giveth them understanding. 9  Great men are not always wise: neither do the aged understand judgment. 10  Therefore I said, Hearken to me; I also will shew mine opinion. 11  Behold, I waited for your words; I gave ear to your [†]reasons, whilst ye searched out [†]what to say. 12  Yea, I attended unto you, and, behold, there was none of you that convinced Job, or that answered his words: 13  Lest ye should say, We have found out wisdom: God thrusteth him down, not man. 14  Now he hath not [∥]directed his words against me: neither will I answer him with your speeches.

15  They were amazed, they answered no more: [†]they left off speaking. 16  When I had waited, (for they spake not, but stood still, and answered no more;) 17  I said, I will answer also my part, I also will shew mine opinion. 18  For I am full of [†]matter, [†]the spirit within me constraineth me. 19  Behold, my belly is as wine which [†]hath no vent; it is ready to burst like new bottles. 20  I will speak, [†]that I may be refreshed: I will open my lips and answer. 21  Let me not, I pray you, accept any man’s person, neither let me give flattering titles unto man. 22  For I know not to give flattering titles; in so doing my maker would soon take me away.

33

1  Wherefore, Job, I pray thee, hear my speeches, and hearken to all my words. 2  Behold, now I have opened my mouth, my tongue hath spoken [†]in my mouth. 3  My words shall be of the uprightness of my heart: and my lips shall utter knowledge clearly. 4  The Spirit of God hath made me, and the breath of the Almighty hath given me life. 5  If thou canst answer me, set thy words in order before me, stand up. 6 [*]Behold, I am [†]according to thy wish in God’s stead: I also am [†]formed out of the clay. 7  Behold, my terror shall not make thee afraid, neither shall my hand be heavy upon thee.

8  Surely thou hast spoken [†]in mine hearing, and I have heard the voice of thy words, saying, 9  I am clean without transgression, I am innocent; neither is there iniquity in me. 10  Behold, he findeth occasions against me, he counteth me for his enemy, 11  He putteth my feet in the stocks, he marketh all my paths. 12 Behold, in this thou art not just: I will answer thee, that God is greater than man. 13  Why dost thou strive against him? for [†]he giveth not account of any of his matters.

14  For God speaketh once, yea twice, yet man perceiveth it not. 15  In a dream, in a vision of the night, when deep sleep falleth upon men, in slumberings upon the bed; 16  Then [†]he openeth the ears of men, and sealeth their instruction, 17  That he may withdraw man from his [†]purpose, and hide pride from man. 18  He keepeth back his soul from the pit, and his life [†]from perishing by the sword.

19  He is chastened also with pain upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with strong pain: 20 [*] So that his life abhorreth bread, and his soul [†]dainty meat. 21  His flesh is consumed away, that it cannot be seen; and his bones that were not seen stick out. 22 [‡] Yea, his soul draweth near unto the grave, and his life to the destroyers. 23  If there be a messenger with him, an interpreter, one among a thousand, to shew unto man his uprightness: 24  Then he is gracious unto him, and saith, Deliver him from going down to the pit: I have found [∥]a ransom. 25  His flesh shall be fresher [†]than a child’s: he shall return to the days of his youth: 26  He shall pray unto God, and he will be favourable unto him: and he shall see his face with joy: for he will render unto man his righteousness. 27 [∥] He looketh upon men, and if any say, I have sinned, and perverted that which was right, and it profited me not; 28 [∥] He will deliver his soul from going into the pit, and his life shall see the light.

29 Lo, all these things worketh God [†]oftentimes with man, 30  To bring back his soul from the pit, to be enlightened with the light of the living. 31  Mark well, O Job, hearken unto me: hold thy peace, and I will speak. 32  If thou hast any thing to say, answer me: speak, for I desire to justify thee. 33  If not, hearken unto me: hold thy peace, and I shall teach thee wisdom.

34

1  Furthermore Elihu answered and said, 2  Hear my words, O ye wise men; and give ear unto me, ye that have knowledge. 3 [*] For the ear trieth words, as the [†]mouth tasteth meat. 4  Let us choose to us judgment: let us know among ourselves what is good. 5  For Job hath said, I am righteous: and God hath taken away my judgment. 6  Should I lie against my right? [†]my wound is incurable without transgression. 7  What man is like Job, who drinketh up scorning like water? 8  Which goeth in company with the workers of iniquity, and walketh with wicked men. 9  For he hath said, It profiteth a man nothing that he should delight himself with God.

10  Therefore hearken unto me, ye [†]men of understanding: [*]far be it from God, that he should do wickedness; and from the Almighty, that he should commit iniquity. 11 [*] For the work of a man shall he render unto him, and cause every man to find according to his ways. 12  Yea, surely God will not do wickedly, neither will the Almighty pervert judgment. 13  Who hath given him a charge over the earth? or who hath disposed [†]the whole world? 14 [*] If he set his heart [†]upon man, if he gather unto himself his spirit and his breath; 15 [*] All flesh shall perish together, and man shall turn again unto dust.

16 If now thou hast understanding, hear this: hearken to the voice of my words. 17  Shall even he that hateth right [†]govern? and wilt thou condemn him that is most just? 18  Is it fit to say to a king, Thou art wicked? and to princes, Ye are ungodly? 19  How much less to him that [*]accepteth not the persons of princes, nor regardeth the rich more than the poor? for they all are the work of his hands. 20  In a moment shall they die, and the people shall be troubled at midnight, and pass away: and [†]the mighty shall be taken away without hand. 21 [*] For his eyes are upon the ways of man, and he seeth all his goings. 22  There is no darkness, nor shadow of death, where the workers of iniquity may hide themselves. 23  For he will not lay upon man more than right; that he should [†]enter into judgment with God. 24  He shall break in pieces mighty men [†]without number, and set others in their stead. 25  Therefore he knoweth their works, and he overturneth them in the night, so that they are [†]destroyed. 26  He striketh them as wicked men [†]in the open sight of others; 27  Because they turned back [†]from him, and would not consider any of his ways: 28  So that they cause the cry of the poor to come unto him, and he heareth the cry of the afflicted. 29  When he giveth quietness, who then can make trouble? and when he hideth his face, who then can behold him? whether it be done against a nation, or against a man only: 30  That the hypocrite reign not, lest the people be ensnared.

31  Surely it is meet to be said unto God, I have borne chastisement, I will not offend any more: 32  That which I see not teach thou me: if I have done iniquity, I will do no more. 33 [†] Should it be according to thy mind? he will recompense it, whether thou refuse, or whether thou choose; and not I: therefore speak what thou knowest. 34  Let men [†]of understanding tell me, and let a wise man hearken unto me. 35  Job hath spoken without knowledge, and his words were without wisdom. 36 [∥] My desire is that Job may be tried unto the end because of his answers for wicked men. 37  For he addeth rebellion unto his sin, he clappeth his hands among us, and multiplieth his words against God.

35

1  Elihu spake moreover, and said, 2  Thinkest thou this to be right, that thou saidst, My righteousness is more than God’s? 3  For thou saidst, What advantage will it be unto thee? and, What profit shall I have, [∥]if I be cleansed from my sin? 4 [†] I will answer thee, and thy companions with thee. 5  Look unto the heavens, and see; and behold the clouds which are higher than thou. 6  If thou sinnest, what doest thou against him? or if thy transgressions be multiplied, what doest thou unto him? 7 [*] If thou be righteous, what givest thou him? or what receiveth he of thine hand? 8  Thy wickedness may hurt a man as thou art; and thy righteousness may profit the son of man.

9  By reason of the multitude of oppressions they make the oppressed to cry: they cry out by reason of the arm of the mighty. 10  But none saith, Where is God my maker, who giveth songs in the night; 11  Who teacheth us more than the beasts of the earth, and maketh us wiser than the fowls of heaven? 12  There they cry, but none giveth answer, because of the pride of evil men. 13 [*] Surely God will not hear vanity, neither will the Almighty regard it.

14  Although thou sayest thou shalt not see him, yet judgment is before him; therefore trust thou in him. 15 But now, because it is not so, [∥]he hath visited in his anger; yet [∥]he knoweth it not in great extremity: 16  Therefore doth Job open his mouth in vain; he multiplieth words without knowledge.

36

1  Elihu also proceeded, and said, 2  Suffer me a little, and I will shew thee [†]that I have yet to speak on God’s behalf. 3  I will fetch my knowledge from afar, and will ascribe righteousness to my Maker. 4  For truly my words shall not be false: he that is perfect in knowledge is with thee.

5  Behold, God is mighty, and despiseth not any: he is mighty in strength and [†]wisdom. 6  He preserveth not the life of the wicked: but giveth right to the [∥]poor. 7 [*] He withdraweth not his eyes from the righteous: but with kings are they on the throne; yea, he doth establish them for ever, and they are exalted. 8 And if they be bound in fetters, and be holden in cords of affliction; 9  Then he sheweth them their work, and their transgressions that they have exceeded. 10  He openeth also their ear to discipline, and commandeth that they return from iniquity. 11  If they obey and serve him, they shall [*]spend their days in prosperity, and their years in pleasures. 12  But if they obey not, [†]they shall perish by the sword, and they shall die without knowledge. 13  But the hypocrites in heart heap up wrath: they cry not when he bindeth them. 14 [†] They die in youth, and their life is among the [∥]unclean.

15  He delivereth the [∥]poor in his affliction, and openeth their ears in oppression. 16  Even so would he have removed thee out of the strait into a broad place, where there is no straitness; and [†]that which should be set on thy table should be full of fatness. 17  But thou hast fulfilled the judgment of the wicked: [∥]judgment and justice take hold on thee. 18 Because there is wrath, beware lest he take thee away with his stroke: then a great ransom cannot [†]deliver thee. 19  Will he esteem thy riches? no, not gold, nor all the forces of strength. 20  Desire not the night, when people are cut off in their place. 21  Take heed, regard not iniquity: for this hast thou chosen rather than affliction. 22  Behold, God exalteth by his power: who teacheth like him? 23  Who hath enjoined him his way? or who can say, Thou hast wrought iniquity?

24  Remember that thou magnify his work, which men behold. 25  Every man may see it; man may behold it afar off. 26  Behold, God is great, and we know him not, neither can the number of his years be searched out. 27  For he maketh small the drops of water: they pour down rain according to the vapour thereof: 28  Which the clouds do drop and distil upon man abundantly. 29 Also can any understand the spreadings of the clouds, or the noise of his tabernacle? 30  Behold, he spreadeth his light upon it, and covereth [†]the bottom of the sea. 31  For by them judgeth he the people; he giveth meat in abundance. 32  With clouds he covereth the light; and commandeth it not to shine by the cloud that cometh betwixt. 33  The noise thereof sheweth concerning it, the cattle also concerning [†]the vapour.

37

1  At this also my heart trembleth, and is moved out of his place. 2 [†] Hear attentively the noise of his voice, and the sound that goeth out of his mouth. 3  He directeth it under the whole heaven, and his [†]lightning unto the [†]ends of the earth. 4  After it a voice roareth: he thundereth with the voice of his excellency; and he will not stay them when his voice is heard. 5  God thundereth marvellously with his voice; great things doeth he, which we cannot comprehend.

6  For [*]he saith to the snow, Be thou on the earth; [†]likewise to the small rain, and to the great rain of his strength. 7  He sealeth up the hand of every man; that all men may know his work. 8  Then the beasts go into dens, and remain in their places. 9 [†] Out of the south cometh the whirlwind: and cold out of the [†]north. 10  By the breath of God frost is given: and the breadth of the waters is straitened. 11  Also by watering he wearieth the thick cloud: he scattereth [†]his bright cloud: 12  And it is turned round about by his counsels: that they may do whatsoever he commandeth them upon the face of the world in the earth. 13  He causeth it to come, whether for [†]correction, or for his land, or for mercy.

14  Hearken unto this, O Job: stand still, and consider the wondrous works of God. 15  Dost thou know when God disposed them, and caused the light of his cloud to shine? 16  Dost thou know the balancings of the clouds, the wondrous works of him which is perfect in knowledge? 17  How thy garments are warm, when he quieteth the earth by the south wind? 18  Hast thou with him spread out the sky, which is strong, and as a molten looking glass? 19  Teach us what we shall say unto him; for we cannot order our speech by reason of darkness. 20  Shall it be told him that I speak? if a man speak, surely he shall be swallowed up.

21 And now men see not the bright light which is in the clouds: but the wind passeth, and cleanseth them. 22 [†] Fair weather cometh out of the north: with God is terrible majesty. 23  Touching the Almighty, we cannot find him out: he is excellent in power, and in judgment, and in plenty of justice: he will not afflict. 24  Men do therefore fear him: he respecteth not any that are wise of heart.

38

1  Then the LORD answered Job out of the whirlwind, and said, 2 Who is this that darkeneth counsel by words without knowledge? 3  Gird up now thy loins like a man; for I will demand of thee, and [†]answer thou me.

4 [*] Where wast thou when I laid the foundations of the earth? declare, [†]if thou hast understanding. 5  Who hath laid the measures thereof, if thou knowest? or who hath stretched the line upon it? 6  Whereupon are the [†]foundations thereof [†]fastened? or who laid the corner stone thereof; 7  When the morning stars sang together, and all the sons of God shouted for joy? 8 [*]Or who shut up the sea with doors, when it brake forth, as if it had issued out of the womb? 9  When I made the cloud the garment thereof, and thick darkness a swaddlingband for it, 10  And [∥]brake up for it my decreed place, and set bars and doors, 11  And said, Hitherto shalt thou come, but no further: and here shall [†]thy proud waves be stayed?

12  Hast thou commanded the morning since thy days; and caused the dayspring to know his place; 13  That it might take hold of the [†]ends of the earth, that the wicked might be shaken out of it? 14  It is turned as clay to the seal; and they stand as a garment. 15  And from the wicked their light is withholden, and the high arm shall be broken. 16  Hast thou entered into the springs of the sea? or hast thou walked in the search of the depth? 17  Have the gates of death been opened unto thee? or hast thou seen the doors of the shadow of death? 18  Hast thou perceived the breadth of the earth? declare if thou knowest it all. 19 Where is the way where light dwelleth? and as for darkness, where is the place thereof, 20  That thou shouldest take it [∥]to the bound thereof, and that thou shouldest know the paths to the house thereof? 21  Knowest thou it, because thou wast then born? or because the number of thy days is great? 22  Hast thou entered into the treasures of the snow? or hast thou seen the treasures of the hail, 23  Which I have reserved against the time of trouble, against the day of battle and war? 24  By what way is the light parted, which scattereth the east wind upon the earth?

25  Who hath divided a watercourse for the overflowing of waters, or a way for the lightning of thunder; 26  To cause it to rain on the earth, where no man is; on the wilderness, wherein there is no man; 27  To satisfy the desolate and waste ground; and to cause the bud of the tender herb to spring forth? 28  Hath the rain a father? or who hath begotten the drops of dew? 29  Out of whose womb came the ice? and the hoary frost of heaven, who hath gendered it? 30  The waters are hid as with a stone, and the face of the deep [†]is frozen. 31  Canst thou bind the sweet influences of [∥][†]Pleiades, or loose the bands of [†]Orion? 32  Canst thou bring forth [∥]Mazzaroth in his season? or canst thou [†]guide Arcturus with his sons? 33  Knowest thou the ordinances of heaven? canst thou set the dominion thereof in the earth? 34  Canst thou lift up thy voice to the clouds, that abundance of waters may cover thee? 35  Canst thou send lightnings, that they may go, and say unto thee, [†]Here we are? 36 [*] Who hath put wisdom in the inward parts? or who hath given understanding to the heart? 37  Who can number the clouds in wisdom? or [†]who can stay the bottles of heaven, 38 [∥] When the dust [†]groweth into hardness, and the clods cleave fast together? 39 [*] Wilt thou hunt the prey for the lion? or fill [†]the appetite of the young lions, 40  When they couch in their dens, and abide in the covert to lie in wait? 41 [*] Who provideth for the raven his food? when his young ones cry unto God, they wander for lack of meat.

39

1  Knowest thou the time when the wild goats of the rock bring forth? or canst thou mark when [*]the hinds do calve? 2  Canst thou number the months that they fulfil? or knowest thou the time when they bring forth? 3  They bow themselves, they bring forth their young ones, they cast out their sorrows. 4  Their young ones are in good liking, they grow up with corn; they go forth, and return not unto them. 5  Who hath sent out the wild ass free? or who hath loosed the bands of the wild ass? 6  Whose house I have made the wilderness, and the [†]barren land his dwellings. 7  He scorneth the multitude of the city, neither regardeth he the crying [†]of the driver. 8  The range of the mountains is his pasture, and he searcheth after every green thing. 9  Will the unicorn be willing to serve thee, or abide by thy crib? 10  Canst thou bind the unicorn with his band in the furrow? or will he harrow the valleys after thee? 11  Wilt thou trust him, because his strength is great? or wilt thou leave thy labour to him? 12  Wilt thou believe him, that he will bring home thy seed, and gather it into thy barn?

13  Gavest thou the goodly wings unto the peacocks? or [∥]wings and feathers unto the ostrich? 14  Which leaveth her eggs in the earth, and warmeth them in dust, 15  And forgetteth that the foot may crush them, or that the wild beast may break them. 16  She is hardened against her young ones, as though they were not hers: her labour is in vain without fear; 17  Because God hath deprived her of wisdom, neither hath he imparted to her understanding. 18  What time she lifteth up herself on high, she scorneth the horse and his rider.

19  Hast thou given the horse strength? hast thou clothed his neck with thunder? 20  Canst thou make him afraid as a grasshopper? the glory of his nostrils is [†]terrible. 21 [∥] He paweth in the valley, and rejoiceth in his strength: he goeth on to meet [†]the armed men. 22  He mocketh at fear, and is not affrighted; neither turneth he back from the sword. 23  The quiver rattleth against him, the glittering spear and the shield. 24  He swalloweth the ground with fierceness and rage: neither believeth he that it is the sound of the trumpet. 25  He saith among the trumpets, Ha, ha; and he smelleth the battle afar off, the thunder of the captains, and the shouting.

26  Doth the hawk fly by thy wisdom, and stretch her wings toward the south? 27  Doth the eagle mount up [†]at thy command, and make her nest on high? 28  She dwelleth and abideth on the rock, upon the crag of the rock, and the strong place. 29  From thence she seeketh the prey, and her eyes behold afar off. 30  Her young ones also suck up blood: and [*]where the slain are, there is [‡]she.

40

1  Moreover the LORD answered Job, and said, 2  Shall he that contendeth with the Almighty instruct him? he that reproveth God, let him answer it.

3 ¶ Then Job answered the LORD, and said, 4  Behold, I am vile; what shall I answer thee? I will lay mine hand upon my mouth. 5  Once have I spoken; but I will not answer: yea, twice; but I will proceed no further.

6 ¶ Then answered the LORD unto Job out of the whirlwind, and said, 7 [*] Gird up thy loins now like a man: I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me. 8 [*] Wilt thou also disannul my judgment? wilt thou condemn me, that thou mayest be righteous? 9  Hast thou an arm like God? or canst thou thunder with a voice like him? 10 [*] Deck thyself now with majesty and excellency; and array thyself with glory and beauty. 11  Cast abroad the rage of thy wrath: and behold every one that is proud, and abase him. 12  Look on every one that is proud, and bring him low; and tread down the wicked in their place. 13  Hide them in the dust together; and bind their faces in secret. 14  Then will I also confess unto thee that thine own right hand can save thee.

15 ¶ Behold now [∥]behemoth, which I made with thee; he eateth grass as an ox. 16  Lo now, his strength is in his loins, and his force is in the navel of his belly. 17 [∥] He moveth his tail like a cedar: the sinews of his stones are wrapped together. 18  His bones are as strong pieces of brass; his bones are like bars of iron. 19 He is the chief of the ways of God: he that made him can make his sword to approach unto him. 20  Surely the mountains bring him forth food, where all the beasts of the field play. 21  He lieth under the shady trees, in the covert of the reed, and fens. 22  The shady trees cover him with their shadow; the willows of the brook compass him about. 23  Behold, [†]he drinketh up a river, and hasteth not: he trusteth that he can draw up Jordan into his mouth. 24 [∥] He taketh it with his eyes: his nose pierceth through snares.

41

1  Canst thou draw out [∥]leviathan with an hook? or his tongue with a cord [†]which thou lettest down? 2  Canst thou put an hook into his nose? or bore his jaw through with a thorn? 3  Will he make many supplications unto thee? will he speak soft words unto thee? 4  Will he make a covenant with thee? wilt thou take him for a servant for ever? 5  Wilt thou play with him as with a bird? [‡]or wilt thou bind him for thy maidens? 6  Shall the companions make a banquet of him? shall they part him among the merchants? 7  Canst thou fill his skin with barbed irons? or his head with fish spears? 8  Lay thine hand upon him, remember the battle, do no more. 9  Behold, the hope of him is in vain: shall not one be cast down even at the sight of him? 10 None is so fierce that dare stir him up: who then is able to stand before me?

11  Who hath prevented me, that I should repay him? [*]whatsoever is under the whole heaven is mine. 12  I will not conceal his parts, nor his power, nor his comely proportion. 13  Who can discover the face of his garment? or who can come to him [∥]with his double bridle? 14  Who can open the doors of his face? his teeth are terrible round about. 15  His [†]scales are his pride, shut up together as with a close seal. 16  One is so near to another, that no air can come between them. 17  They are joined one to another, they stick together, that they cannot be sundered. 18  By his neesings a light doth shine, and his eyes are like the eyelids of the morning. 19  Out of his mouth go burning lamps, and sparks of fire leap out. 20  Out of his nostrils goeth smoke, as out of a seething pot or caldron. 21  His breath kindleth coals, and a flame goeth out of his mouth. 22  In his neck remaineth strength, and [†]sorrow is turned into joy before him. 23 [†] The flakes of his flesh are joined together: they are firm in themselves; they cannot be moved. 24  His heart is as firm as a stone; yea, as hard as a piece of the nether millstone. 25  When he raiseth up himself, the mighty are afraid: by reason of breakings they purify themselves. 26  The sword of him that layeth at him cannot hold: the spear, the dart, nor the [∥]habergeon. 27  He esteemeth iron as straw, and brass as rotten wood. 28  The arrow cannot make him flee: slingstones are turned with him into stubble. 29  Darts are counted as stubble: he laugheth at the shaking of a spear. 30 [†] Sharp stones are under him: he spreadeth sharp pointed things upon the mire. 31  He maketh the deep to boil like a pot: he maketh the sea like a pot of ointment. 32  He maketh a path to shine after him; one would think the deep to be hoary. 33  Upon earth there is not his like, [∥]who is made without fear. 34  He beholdeth all high things: he is a king over all the children of pride.

42

1  Then Job answered the LORD, and said, 2  I know that thou canst do every thing, and that [∥]no thought can be withholden from thee. 3 [*]Who is he that hideth counsel without knowledge? therefore have I uttered that I understood not; things too wonderful for me, which I knew not. 4  Hear, I beseech thee, and I will speak: I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me. 5  I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear: but now mine eye seeth thee. 6  Wherefore I abhor myself, and repent in dust and ashes.

7 ¶ And it was so, that after the LORD had spoken these words unto Job, the LORD said to Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is kindled against thee, and against thy two friends: for ye have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job hath. 8  Therefore take unto you now seven bullocks and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer up for yourselves a burnt offering; and my servant Job shall pray for you: for [†]him will I accept: lest I deal with you after your folly, in that ye have not spoken of me the thing which is right, like my servant Job. 9  So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite went, and did according as the LORD commanded them: the LORD also accepted [†]Job.

10  And the LORD turned the captivity of Job, when he prayed for his friends: also the LORD [†]gave Job twice as much as he had before. 11  Then came there unto him all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all they that had been of his acquaintance before, and did eat bread with him in his house: and they bemoaned him, and comforted him over all the evil that the LORD had brought upon him: every man also gave him a piece of money, and every one an earring of gold. 12  So the LORD blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning: for he had fourteen thousand sheep, and six thousand camels, and a thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand she asses. 13  He had also seven sons and three daughters. 14  And he called the name of the first, Jemima; and the name of the second, Kezia; and the name of the third, Keren-happuch. 15  And in all the land were no women found so fair as the daughters of Job: and their father gave them inheritance among their brethren. 16  After this lived Job an hundred and forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons’ sons, even four generations. 17  So Job died, being old and full of days.

* 1.1 ch. 2. 3.

∥ 1.3 Or, cattle.

∥ 1.3 Or, husbandry.

† 1.3 Heb. sons of the cast.

* 1.5 1 Kings 21. 10, 13.

† 1.5 Heb all the days.

† 1.6 Heb. the adversary.

† 1.6 Heb. in the midst of them.

* 1.7 1 Pet. 5. 8.

† 1.8 Heb. Hast thou set thy heart on.

∥ 1.10 Or, cattle.

† 1.11 Heb. if he curse thee not to thy face.

† 1.12 Heb. hand.

∥ 1.16 Or, A great fire.

† 1.17 Heb. rushed.

† 1.19 Heb. from aside, &c.

∥ 1.20 Or, robe.

* 1.21 Eccles. 5. 15. 1 Tim. 6. 7.

∥ 1.22 Or, attributed folly to God.

* 2.2 ch. 1. 7.

* 2.3 ch. 1. 1, 8.

† 2.3 Heb. to swallow him up.

∥ 2.6 Or, only.

† 3.2 Heb. answered.

* 3.3 ch. 10. 13, 19. Jer. 20. 14.

∥ 3.5 Or, challenge it.

∥ 3.5 Or, let them terrify it, as those who have a bitter day.

∥ 3.6 Or, let it not rejoice among the days.

∥ 3.8 Or, a leviathan.

† 3.9 Heb. the eyelids of the morning.

† 3.17 Heb. wearied in strength.

† 3.21 Heb. wait.

* 3.23 ch. 19. 8.

† 3.24 Heb. before my meat.

† 3.25 Heb. I feared a fear, and it came upon me.

† 4.2 Heb. a word.

† 4.2 Heb. who can refrain from words?

† 4.4 Heb. the bowing knees.

‡ 4.6 [1611 confidence; the uprightness of thy ways and thy hope?]

* 4.8 Prov. 22. 8. Hos. 10. 13.

∥ 4.9 Isai. 30. 33.

† 4.12 Heb. by stealth.

† 4.14 Heb. met me.

† 4.14 Heb. the multitude of my bones.

∥ 4.16 Or, I heard a still voice.

* 4.18 ch. 15. 15 2 Pet. 2. 4.

∥ 4.18 Or, nor in his angels, in whom he put light.

‡ 4.19 [1611 on]

* 4.19 2 Cor. 5 1.

† 4.20 Heb. beaten in pieces.

∥ 5.1 Or, look?

∥ 5.2 Or, indignation.

∥ 5.6 Or, iniquity.

∥ 5.7 Or, labour.

† 5.7 Heb. the sons of the burning coal let up to fly

* 5.9 ch 9. 10. Ps. 72. 18 Rom 11 33.

† 5.9 Heb. and there is no search.

† 5.9 Heb. till there be no number.

† 5.10 Heb. outplaces.

* 5.11 1 Sam. 2 7 Ps. 113. 7.

* 5.12 Neh. 4. 15 Ps. 33. 10. Isai 8. 10.

∥ 5.12 Or, cannot perform any thing.

* 5.13 1 Cor. 3. 19

* 5.14 Deut. 28 29.

∥ 5.14 Or, run into.

* 5.16 Ps. 107. 42.

* 5.17 Prov. 3. 12. Heb. 12. 5. James 1. 12. Rev. 3. 19.

* 5.18 32. 39. 1 Sam. 2. 6 Isai. 30. 26. Hos. 6. 1.

* 5.19 Ps. 91. 3.

† 5.20 Heb. from the hands.

∥ 5.21 Or, when the tongue scourgeth.

* 5.23 Hos. 2. 18.

∥ 5.24 Or, that peace is thy tabernacle.

∥ 5.24 Or, err.

∥ 5.25 Or, much.

† 5.26 Heb. ascendeth.

† 5.27 Heb. for thyself.

† 6.2 Heb. lifted up

∥ 6.3 That is, I want words to express my grief.

* 6.4 Ps. 38. 2.

† 6.5 Heb at grass.

† 6.8 Heb my expectation

† 6.12 Heb. brasen.

† 6.14 Heb. To him that melteth.

† 6.17 Heb. they are cut off.

† 6.17 Heb. in the heat thereof.

† 6.17 Heb. extinguished.

∥ 6.21 Or, For now ye are like to them. Heb. to it.

† 6.21 Heb. not.

† 6.27 Heb. ye cause to fall upon.

† 6.28 Heb. before your face.

∥ 6.29 That is, in this matter.

† 6.30 Heb. my palate.

∥ 7.1 Or, a warfare.

† 7.2 Heb. gapeth after.

† 7.4 Heb. the evening be measured?

* 7.6 ch. 16. 22. Pa. 90. 6. &c 102. 11. &c 103. 15. &c 144. 4. Isai. 40. 6 James 4. 14.

† 7.7 Heb. shall not return.

∥ 7.7 to see, that is, to enjoy.

∥ 7.8 That is, I can live no longer.

† 7.15 Heb. than my bones.

* 7.17 Ps. 8 4 &c 144. 3. Heb. 2. 6.

* 8.3 Deut. 32. 4. 2 Chr. 19. 7. Dan. 9. 14.

† 8.4 Heb. in the hand of their transgression.

* 8.5 ch. 22. 23.

* 8.8 Deut. 4. 32.

* 8.9 Gen. 47. 9. 1 Chr. 29. 15. ch. 7. 6. Ps. 89. 5. &c 144. 4.

† 8.9 Heb. not.

* 8.12 Ps. 129. 6. Jer. 17. 6.

* 8.13 ch. 11. 20. &c 18. 14. Ps. 112. 10 Prov. 10. 28.

† 8.14 Heb. a spider's house.

† 8.20 Heb take the ungodly by the hand.

† 8.21 Heb. shouting for joy.

† 8.22 Heb. shall not be.

* 9.2 Ps. 143. 2.

∥ 9.2 Or, before God?

* 9.8 Gen. 1. 6.

† 9.8 Heb heights.

* 9.9 ch. 38. 31, &c. Amos 5. 8.

† 9.9 Heb. Ash. Cesil, and Cimah.

* 9.10 ch. 5 9.

* 9.12 Isai. 45. 9. Jer. 18. 6. Rom. 9. 20.

† 9.12 Heb. who can turn him away?

† 9.13 Heb. helpers of pride, or, strength.

† 9.26 Heb. ships of desire.

∥ 9.26 Or, ships of Ebeh.

∥ 9.31 Or, make me to be abhorred.

† 9.33 Heb. one that should argue.

∥ 9.33 Or, umpire.

† 9.35 Heb but I am not so with myself.

∥ 10.1 Or, cut off while I live.

† 10.3 Heb. the labour of thine hands.

† 10.7 Heb. It is upon thy knowledge.

† 10.8 Heb. took pains about me

* 10.10 Ps. 139 14, 15, 16.

‡ 10.10 [1611 cruddled]

† 10.11 Heb hedged.

∥ 10.17 That is, thy plagues.

* 10.18 ch. 3. 11.

* 10.20 ch. 7. 6. &c 8. 9.

† 11.2 Heb a man of lips.

∥ 11.3 Or, devices

† 11.8 Heb. the heights of heaven.

∥ 11.10 Or, make a change.

† 11.10 Heb. who can turn him away?

† 11.12 Heb. empty.

† 11.17 Heb. shalt arise above the noonday

* 11.19 Lev. 26. 6.

† 11.19 Heb. intreat thy face.

† 11.20 Heb. flight shall perish from them

* 11.20 ch. 8. 14. &c 18 14.

∥ 11.20 Or, a puff of breath.

† 12.3 Heb. an heart.

† 12.3 Heb. I fall not lower than you.

† 12.3 Heb. with whom are not such as these?

∥ 12.10 Or, life.

† 12.10 Heb. all flesh of man.

* 12.11 ch. 34. 3.

† 12.11 Heb palate.

∥ 12.13 That is, With God.

* 12.14 Isai. 22. 22. Rev. 3. 7.

† 12.14 Heb. upon.

* 12.20 ch. 32. 9.

† 12.20 Heb. the lip of the faithful.

∥ 12.21 Or, looseth the girdle of the strong.

† 12.23 Heb. leadeth in.

† 12.25 Heb. wander.

† 13.13 Heb. Be silent from me.

† 13.15 Heb. prove, or, argue.

* 13.26 Ps. 25. 7.

† 13.27 Heb. observest.

† 13.27 Heb. roots.

† 14.1 Heb. short of days.

* 14.2 ch. 8. 9. Ps. 102. 11. &c 103. 15. &c 144. 4.

† 14.4 Heb. Who will give.

* 14.4 Ps. 51. 5.

* 14.5 ch. 7. 1.

† 14.6 Heb. cease.

† 14.10 Heb. is weakened, or, cut off.

* 14.16 Ps. 139. 2.

† 14.18 Heb. fadeth.

† 14.19 Heb. overflowest.

† 15.2 Heb. knowledge of wind.

† 15.4 Heb. thou makest void.

∥ 15.4 Or, speech.

† 15.5 Heb. teacheth.

* 15.8 Rom. 11 34.

* 15.14 1 Kings 8. 46 2 Chr. 6. 36. ch. 14. 4 Ps. 14. 3. Prov. 20. 9. 1 John 1. 8.

* 15.15 ch. 4. 18.

† 15.21 Heb. A sound of fears.

∥ 15.32 Or, cut off.

* 15.35 Ps. 7. 14 Isai. 59. 4.

∥ 15.35 Or, iniquity.

∥ 16.2 Or, troublesome.

* 16.2 ch. 13 4.

† 16.3 Heb. words of wind.

† 16.6 Heb. what goeth from me?

† 16.11 Heb. hath shut me up.

† 16.19 Heb. in the high places.

† 16.20 Heb. are my scorners.

∥ 16.21 Or, friend.

† 16.22 Heb. years of number.

∥ 17.1 Or, spirit is spent.

† 17.2 Heb. lodge.

∥ 17.6 Or, before them.

∥ 17.7 Or, my thoughts.

† 17.9 Heb. shall add strength

† 17.11 Heb. the possessions.

† 17.12 Heb. near.

† 17.14 Heb. cried, or, called.

† 18.4 Heb. his soul.

∥ 18.6 Or, lamp.

‡ 18.9 [1611 grin]

† 18.10 Heb. hidden.

† 18.11 Heb. scatter him.

† 18.13 Heb. bars.

* 18.14 ch. 8. 14. &c 11. 20. Ps. 112. 10. Prov. 10. 28.

* 18.17 Prov. 2. 22.

† 18.18 Heb. They shall drive him.

∥ 18.20 Or, lived with him.

† 18.20 Heb. laid hold on horror,

∥ 19.3 Or, harden yourselves against me.

∥ 19.7 Or, violence.

† 19.17 Heb. my belly

∥ 19.18 Or, the wicked.

* 19.19 Ps 41. 9. &c 55. 20.

† 19.19 Heb. the men of my secret.

∥ 19.20 Or, as.

† 19.23 Heb. Who will give, &c.

∥ 19.26 Or, After I shall awake, though this body be destroyed, yet out of my flesh shall I see God.

† 19.27 Heb. a stranger.

† 19.27 Heb. in my bosom.

∥ 19.28 Or, and what root of matter is found in me?

† 20.2 Heb. my haste is in me.

* 20.5 Ps. 37. 35, 35.

† 20.5 Heb. from near.

† 20.6 Heb. cloud.

∥ 20.10 Or, The poor shall oppress his children.

† 20.13 Heb. in the midst of his palate.

∥ 20.17 Or, streaming brooks.

† 20.18 Heb. according to the substance of his exchange.

† 20.19 Heb. crushed.

* 20.20 Eccles. 5. 13, 14.

† 20.20 Heb. know.

∥ 20.21 Or, There shall be none left for his meat.

∥ 20.22 Or, troublesome.

‡ 20.25 [1611 glistering]

† 20.29 Heb. of his decree from God.

† 21.4 Heb. shortened?

† 21.5 Heb. Look unto me.

* 21.7 Ps. 17. 10. &c 73. 12. Jer. 12. 1. Hab. 1. 16.

† 21.9 Heb. are peace from fear.

∥ 21.13 Or, in mirth.

* 21.14 ch. 22. 17.

∥ 21.17 Or, lamp.

† 21.18 Heb. stealeth away

∥ 21.19 That is, the punishment of his iniquity.

† 21.23 Heb. in his very perfection, or, in the strength of his perfection.

∥ 21.24 Or, milk pails.

† 21.28 Heb. the tent of the tabernacles of the wicked?

* 21.30 Prov. 16. 4.

† 21.30 Heb. the day of wraths.

† 21.32 Heb. graves.

† 21.32 Heb. watch in the heap.

† 21.34 Heb. transgression?

∥ 22.2 Or, if he may be profitable, doth his good success depend thereon?

† 22.6 Heb. stripped the clothes of the naked.

† 22.8 Heb. the man of arm.

† 22.8 Heb. eminent, or, accepted for countenance.

† 22.12 Heb the head of the stars.

∥ 22.13 Or, What.

† 22.16 Heb. a flood was poured upon their foundation.

* 22.17 ch. 21. 14.

∥ 22.17 Or, to them?

* 22.18 ch. 21. 16.

* 22.19 Ps. 107. 42.

∥ 22.20 Or, estate.

∥ 22.20 Or, their excellency.

∥ 22.21 That is, with God.

* 22.23 ch. 8. 5.

∥ 22.24 Or, on the dust.

∥ 22.25 Or, gold.

† 22.25 Heb. silver of strength.

† 22.29 Heb. him that hath low eyes.

∥ 22.30 Or, The innocent shall deliver the island.

† 23.2 Heb. my hand.

† 23.10 Heb. the way that is with me.

† 23.12 Heb. I have hid, or, laid up.

∥ 23.12 Or, my appointed portion

* 23.13 Ps. 115. 8.

* 24.2 Deut. 19. 14. &c 27. 17.

∥ 24.2 Or, feed them.

† 24.6 Heb. mingled corn, or, dredge.

† 24.6 Heb. the wicked gather the vintage.

† 24.15 Heb. setteth his face in secret.

† 24.19 Heb. violently take.

∥ 24.22 Or, he trusteth not his own life

† 24.24 Heb. are not.

† 24.24 Heb. closed up.

* 25.4 ch. 4. 17, &c. &c 15. 14, &c.

* 25.6 Ps. 22. 6.

∥ 26.5 Or, with the inhabitants.

* 26.6 Prov. 15. 11.

† 26.10 Heb. until the end of light with darkness.

† 26.12 Heb. pride.

† 27.1 Heb. added to take up.

† 27.2 Heb. made my soul bitter.

∥ 27.3 That is, the breath which God gave him.

† 27.6 Heb. from my days.

* 27.8 Matt. 16. 26.

* 27.9 Prov. 1. 28. Ezek. 8. 18. John 9. 31. James 4. 3.

∥ 27.11 Or, being in the hand, &c.

* 27.15 Ps. 78. 64

* 27.20 ch. 18. 11.

† 27.22 Heb. in fleeing he would flee.

∥ 28.1 Or, a mine.

∥ 28.2 Or, dust.

∥ 28.6 Or, gold ore.

∥ 28.9 Or, flint.

† 28.11 Heb. from weeping.

* 28.14 Rom. 11. 33, 34.

† 28.15 Heb. Fine gold shall not be given for it.

* 28.15 Prov. 3. 14. &c 8. 11, 19. &c 16. 16.

∥ 28.17 Or, vessels of fine gold.

∥ 28.18 Or, Ramoth.

* 28.20 ver. 12

∥ 28.21 Or, heaven.

∥ 28.27 Or, did number it.

* 28.28 Ps. 111 10. Prov. 1. 7. &c 9 10.

† 29.1 Heb. added to take up

∥ 29.3 Or, lamp.

† 29.6 Heb. with me

† 29.10 Heb. The voice of the nobles was hid.

† 29.17 Heb the jawteeth, or, the grinders.

† 29.17 Heb. I cast.

† 29.19 Heb opened.

† 29.20 Heb. new.

† 29.20 Heb. changed.

† 30.1 Heb. of fewer days than I.

∥ 30.3 Or, dark as the night.

‡ 30.3 [1611 flying]

† 30.3 Heb. yester-night.

‡ 30.6 [1611 clifts]

† 30.6 Heb. holes.

† 30.8 Heb. men of no name

* 30.9 Ps. 35. 15 &c 69. 12.

† 30.10 Heb. and withhold not spittle from my face.

† 30.15 Heb. my principal one.

† 30.21 Heb turned to be cruel.

† 30.21 Heb. the strength of thy hand.

∥ 30.22 Or, wisdom.

† 30.24 Heb. heap.

* 30.25 Ps. 35. 13. Rom. 12. 15.

† 30.25 Heb. for him that was hard of day?

* 30.29 Ps. 102. 6.

∥ 30.29 Or, ostriches.

* 31.4 2 Chr. 16 9. ch. 34. 21. Prov. 5. 21. &c 15. 3.

† 31.6 Heb. Let him weigh me in balances of justice.

∥ 31.15 Or, did he not fashion us in one womb?

∥ 31.18 That is, the widow.

∥ 31.22 Or, the chanelbone.

† 31.25 Heb. found much.

† 31.26 Heb. the light.

† 31.26 Heb bright.

† 31.27 Heb. my hand hath kissed my mouth.

† 31.30 Heb. my palate.

∥ 31.32 Or, to the way.

∥ 31.33 Or, after the manner of men.

∥ 31.35 Or, behold, my sign is that the Almighty will answer me.

† 31.38 Heb. weep.

† 31.39 Heb. the strength thereof.

† 31.39 Heb. caused the soul of the owners thereof to expire, or, breathe out.

∥ 31.40 Or, noisome weeds.

† 32.1 Heb. from answering.

† 32.2 Heb. his soul.

† 32.4 Heb. expected Job in words.

† 32.4 Heb. elder for days

† 32.6 Heb. few of days.

† 32.6 Heb. I feared.

* 32.8 ch. 38. 36. Prov. 2. 6. Eccles. 2. 26. Dan. 1. 17. &c 2. 21.

† 32.11 Heb. understandings.

† 32.11 Heb words.

∥ 32.14 Or, ordered his words.

† 32.15 Heb. they removed speeches from themselves.

† 32.18 Heb. words.

† 32.18 Heb. the spirit of my belly.

† 32.19 Heb. is not opened.

† 32.20 Heb. that I may breathe.

† 33.2 Heb. in my palate.

* 33.6 ch. 9. 35. &c 13 20.

† 33.6 Heb according to thy mouth.

† 33.6 Heb cut out of the clay.

† 33.8 Heb. in mine ears.

† 33.13 Heb. he answereth not.

† 33.16 Heb. he revealeth, or, uncovereth.

† 33.17 Heb. work.

† 33.18 Heb from passing by the sword.

* 33.20 Ps. 107. 18.

† 33.20 Heb. meat of desire.

‡ 33.22 [1611 omits Yea,]

∥ 33.24 Or, an atonement.

† 33.25 Heb. than childhood.

∥ 33.27 Or, He shall look upon men, and say, I have sinned, &c.

∥ 33.28 Or, He hath delivered my soul, &c. and my life.

† 33.29 Heb. twice and thrice.

* 34.3 ch. 12. 11.

† 34.3 Heb. palate.

† 34.6 Heb. mine arrow.

† 34.10 Heb. men of heart.

* 34.10 Deut. 32. 4 ch. 8. 3. &c 36. 23. Ps. 92. 15. Rom. 9. 14.

* 34.11 Ps. 62. 12. Prov. 24. 12 Jer. 32. 19. Ezek. 33. 20. Matt. 16. 27. Rom. 2. 6 2 Cor. 5. 10. 1 Pet. 1. 17. Rev. 22. 12.

† 34.13 Heb all of it?

* 34.14 Ps. 104. 29.

† 34.14 Heb. upon him.

* 34.15 Gen. 3. 19. Eccles 12. 7.

† 34.17 Heb. bind?

* 34.19 Deut. 10. 17. 2 Chr. 19. 7. Acts 10. 34. Rom. 2. 11. Gal 2. 6 Eph. 6 9. Col. 3. 25 1 Pet. 1. 17.

† 34.20 Heb. they shall take away the mighty.

* 34.21 2 Chr. 16. 9. ch. 31. 4. Prov. 5. 21. &c 15. 3. Jer. 16. 17.

† 34.23 Heb. go.

† 34.24 Heb. without searching out.

† 34.25 Heb. crushed.

† 34.26 Heb. in the place of beholders.

† 34.27 Heb. from after him.

† 34.33 Heb. Should it be from with thee?

† 34.34 Heb. of heart.

∥ 34.36 Or, My father, let Job be tried.

∥ 35.3 Or, by it more than by my sin?

† 35.4 Heb. I will return to thee words.

* 35.7 ch. 22. 3. Ps. 16. 2. Rom. 11. 35.

* 35.13 ch. 27. 9. Prov. 1. 28. Isai. 1. 15. Jer. 11. 11.

∥ 35.15 That is, God.

∥ 35.15 That is, Job.

† 36.2 Heb. that there are yet words for God.

† 36.5 Heb. heart.

∥ 36.6 Or, afflicted.

* 36.7 Ps. 34. 15.

* 36.11 ch. 21. 13.

† 36.12 Heb. they shall pass away by the sword.

† 36.14 Heb. Their soul dieth.

∥ 36.14 Or, sodomites.

∥ 36.15 Or, afflicted.

† 36.16 Heb. the rest of thy table.

∥ 36.17 Or, judgment and justice should uphold thee.

† 36.18 Heb. turn thee aside.

† 36.30 Heb. the roots.

† 36.33 Heb. that which goeth up.

† 37.2 Heb. Hear in hearing.

† 37.3 Heb. light.

† 37.3 Heb. wings of the earth.

* 37.6 Ps. 147. 16, 17.

† 37.6 Heb. and to the shower of rain, and to the showers of rain of his strength.

† 37.9 Heb. Out of the chamber.

† 37.9 Heb. scattering winds.

† 37.11 Heb. the cloud of his light.

† 37.13 Heb. a rod.

† 37.22 Heb. Gold.

† 38.3 Heb make me know.

* 38.4 Ps. 104. 5. Prov. 30. 4.

† 38.4 Heb. if thou knowest understanding.

† 38.6 Heb. sockets.

† 38.6 Heb. made to sink?

* 38.8 Ps. 104. 9.

∥ 38.10 Or, established my decree upon it.

† 38.11 Heb. the pride of thy waves.

† 38.13 Heb. wings.

∥ 38.20 Or, at.

† 38.30 Heb. is taken.

∥ 38.31 Or, the seven stars.

† 38.31 Heb. Cimah.

† 38.31 Heb. Cesil?

∥ 38.32 Or, the twelve signs.

† 38.32 Heb. guide them.

† 38.35 Heb. Behold us?

* 38.36 ch. 32. 8. Eccles. 2. 26.

† 38.37 Heb who can cause to lie down.

∥ 38.38 Or, When the dust is turned into mire.

† 38.38 Heb. is poured.

* 38.39 Ps. 104. 21.

† 38.39 Heb. the life.

* 38.41 Ps. 147. 9. Matt. 6. 26.

* 39.1 Ps. 29. 9.

† 39.6 Heb. salt places.

† 39.7 Heb. of the exactor.

∥ 39.13 Or, the feathers of the stork and ostrich.

† 39.20 Heb. terror.

∥ 39.21 Or, His feet dig.

† 39.21 Heb. the armour.

† 39.27 Heb. by thy mouth.

* 39.30 Matt. 24. 28. Luke 17. 37.

‡ 39.30 [1611 he]

* 40.7 ch. 38. 3.

* 40.8 Ps. 50. 21. Rom. 3. 4.

* 40.10 Ps. 104. 1.

∥ 40.15 Or, the elephant, as some think.

∥ 40.17 Or, He setteth up.

† 40.23 Heb. he oppresseth.

∥ 40.24 Or, Will any take him in his sight, or, bore his nose with a gin?

∥ 41.1 That is, a whale, or, a whirlpool.

† 41.1 Heb. which thou drownest?

‡ 41.5 [1611 omits or]

* 41.11 Ps. 24. 1. &c 50. 12. 1 Cor. 10. 26.

∥ 41.13 Or, within.

† 41.15 Heb. strong pieces of shields.

† 41.22 Heb. sorrow rejoiceth.

† 41.23 Heb. The fallings.

∥ 41.26 Or, breast-plate.

† 41.30 Heb. Sharp pieces of the potsherd.

∥ 41.33 Or, who behave themselves without fear.

∥ 42.2 Or, no thought of thine can be hindered.

* 42.3 ch. 33. 2.

† 42.8 Heb. his face, or, person.

† 42.9 Heb. the face of Job.

† 42.10 Heb. added [all that had been] to Job unto the double.

Joel

1
2
3

Joel

1

1  The word of the LORD that came to Joel the son of Pethuel. 2  Hear this, ye old men, and give ear, all ye inhabitants of the land. Hath this been in your days, or even in the days of your fathers? 3  Tell ye your children of it, and let your children tell their children, and their children another generation. 4 [†] That which the palmerworm hath left hath the locust eaten; and that which the locust hath left hath the cankerworm eaten; and that which the cankerworm hath left hath the caterpiller eaten. 5  Awake, ye drunkards, and weep; and howl, all ye drinkers of wine, because of the new wine; for it is cut off from your mouth. 6  For a nation is come up upon my land, strong, and without number, whose teeth are the teeth of a lion, and he hath the cheek teeth of a great lion. 7  He hath laid my vine waste, and [†]barked my fig tree: he hath made it clean bare, and cast it away; the branches thereof are made white.

8 ¶ Lament like a virgin girded with sackcloth for the husband of her youth. 9  The meat offering and the drink offering is cut off from the house of the LORD; the priests, the LORD’s ministers, mourn. 10  The field is wasted, the land mourneth; for the corn is wasted: the new wine is [∥]dried up, the oil languisheth. 11  Be ye ashamed, O ye husbandmen; howl, O ye vinedressers, for the wheat and for the barley; because the harvest of the field is perished. 12  The vine is dried up, and the fig tree languisheth; the pomegranate tree, the palm tree also, and the apple tree, even all the trees of the field, are withered: because joy is withered away from the sons of men. 13  Gird yourselves, and lament, ye priests: howl, ye ministers of the altar: come, lie all night in sackcloth, ye ministers of my God: for the meat offering and the drink offering is withholden from the house of your God.

14 ¶ [*]Sanctify ye a fast, call a [∥]solemn assembly, gather the elders and all the inhabitants of the land into the house of the LORD your God, and cry unto the LORD, 15  Alas for the day! for [*]the day of the LORD is at hand, and as a destruction from the Almighty shall it come. 16  Is not the meat cut off before [‡]our eyes, yea, joy and gladness from the house of our God? 17  The [†]seed is rotten under their clods, the garners are laid desolate, the barns are broken down; for the corn is withered. 18  How do the beasts groan! the herds of cattle are perplexed, because they have no pasture; yea, the flocks of sheep are made desolate. 19  O LORD, to thee will I cry: for the fire hath devoured the [∥]pastures of the wilderness, and the flame hath burned all the trees of the field. 20  The beasts of the field cry also unto thee: for the rivers of waters are dried up, and the fire hath devoured the pastures of the wilderness.

2

1  Blow ye the [∥]trumpet in Zion, and sound an alarm in my holy mountain: let all the inhabitants of the land tremble: for the day of the LORD cometh, for it is nigh at hand; 2  A day of darkness and of gloominess, a day of clouds and of thick darkness, as the morning spread upon the mountains: a great people and a strong; there hath not been ever the like, neither shall be any more after it, even to the years [†]of many generations. 3  A fire devoureth before them; and behind them a flame burneth: the land is as the garden of Eden before them, and behind them a desolate wilderness; yea, and nothing shall escape them. 4  The appearance of them is as the appearance of horses; and as horsemen, so shall they run. 5  Like the noise of chariots on the tops of mountains shall they leap, like the noise of a flame of fire that devoureth the stubble, as a strong people set in battle array. 6  Before their face the people shall be much pained: all faces shall gather [†]blackness. 7  They shall run like mighty men; they shall climb the wall like men of war; and they shall march every one on his ways, and they shall not break their ranks: 8  Neither shall one thrust another; they shall walk every one in his path: and when they fall upon the [∥]sword, they shall not be wounded. 9  They shall run to and fro in the city; they shall run upon the wall, they shall climb up upon the houses; they shall enter in at the windows like a thief. 10  The earth shall quake before them; the heavens shall tremble: [*]the sun and the moon shall be dark, and the stars shall withdraw their shining: 11  And the LORD shall utter his voice before his army: for his camp is very great: for he is strong that executeth his word: for the [*]day of the LORD is great and very terrible; and who can abide it?

12 ¶ Therefore also now, saith the LORD, [*]turn ye even to me with all your heart, and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning: 13  And rend your heart, and not your garments, and turn unto the LORD your God: for he is [*]gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and repenteth him of the evil. 14 [*] Who knoweth if he will return and repent, and leave a blessing behind him; even a meat offering and a drink offering unto the LORD your God?

15 ¶ Blow the trumpet in Zion, [*]sanctify a fast, call a solemn assembly: 16  Gather the people, sanctify the congregation, assemble the elders, gather the children, and those that suck the breasts: let the bridegroom go forth of his chamber, and the bride out of her closet. 17  Let the priests, the ministers of the LORD, weep between the porch and the altar, and let them say, Spare thy people, O LORD, and give not thine heritage to reproach, that the heathen should [∥]rule over them: [*]wherefore should they say among the people, Where is their God?

18 ¶ Then will the LORD be jealous for his land, and pity his people. 19  Yea, the LORD will answer and say unto his people, Behold, I will send you corn, and wine, and oil, and ye shall be satisfied therewith: and I will no more make you a reproach among the heathen: 20  But I will remove far off from you the northern army, and will drive him into a land barren and desolate, with his face toward the east sea, and his hinder part toward the utmost sea, and his stink shall come up, and his ill savour shall come up, because [†]he hath done great things.

21 ¶ Fear not, O land; be glad and rejoice: for the LORD will do great things. 22  Be not afraid, ye beasts of the field: for the pastures of the wilderness do spring, for the tree beareth her fruit, the fig tree and the vine do yield their strength. 23  Be glad then, ye children of Zion, and rejoice in the LORD your God: for he hath given you [∥]the former rain [†]moderately, and he [*]will cause to come down for you the rain, the former rain, and the latter rain in the first month. 24  And the floors shall be full of wheat, and the fats shall overflow with wine and oil. 25  And I will restore to you the years that the locust hath eaten, the cankerworm, and the caterpiller, and the palmerworm, my great army which I sent among you. 26  And ye shall eat in plenty, and be satisfied, and praise the name of the LORD your God, that hath dealt wondrously with you: and my people shall never be ashamed. 27  And ye shall know that I am in the midst of Israel, and that I am the LORD your God, and none else: and my people shall never be ashamed.

28 ¶ And it shall come to pass afterward, that I [*]will pour out my spirit upon all flesh; and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, your old men shall dream dreams, your young men shall see visions: 29  And also upon the servants and upon the handmaids in those days will I pour out my spirit. 30  And I will shew wonders in the heavens and in the earth, blood, and fire, and pillars of smoke. 31 [*] The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the great and the terrible day of the LORD come. 32 And it shall come to pass, that [*]whosoever shall call on the name of the LORD shall be delivered: for in mount Zion and in Jerusalem shall be deliverance, as the LORD hath said, and in the remnant whom the LORD shall call.

3

1  For, behold, in those days, and in that time, when I shall bring again the captivity of Judah and Jerusalem, 2  I will also gather all nations, and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat, and will plead with them there for my people and for my heritage Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations, and parted my land. 3  And they have cast lots for my people; and have given a boy for an harlot, and sold a girl for wine, that they might drink. 4  Yea, and what have ye to do with me, O Tyre, and Zidon, and all the coasts of Palestine? will ye render me a recompence? and if ye recompense me, swiftly and speedily will I return your recompence upon your own head; 5  Because ye have taken my silver and my gold, and have carried into your temples my goodly [†]pleasant things: 6  The children also of Judah and the children of Jerusalem have ye sold unto [†]the Grecians, that ye might remove them far from their border. 7  Behold, I will raise them out of the place whither ye have sold them, and will return your recompence upon your own head: 8  And I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hand of the children of Judah, and they shall sell them to the Sabeans, to a people far off: for the LORD hath spoken it.

9 ¶ Proclaim ye this among the Gentiles; [†]Prepare war, wake up the mighty men, let all the men of war draw near; let them come up: 10 [*] Beat your plowshares into swords, and your [∥]pruninghooks into spears: let the weak say, I am strong. 11  Assemble yourselves, and come, all ye heathen, and gather yourselves together round about: thither [∥]cause thy mighty ones to come down, O LORD. 12  Let the heathen be wakened, and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat: for there will I sit to judge all the heathen round about. 13 [*] Put ye in the sickle, for the harvest is ripe: come, get you down; for the press is full, the fats overflow; for [‡]their wickedness is great. 14  Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of [∥]decision: for the day of the LORD is near in the valley of decision. 15  The [*]sun and the moon shall be darkened, and the stars shall withdraw their shining. 16  The LORD also shall [*]roar out of Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the heavens and the earth shall shake: but the LORD will be the [†]hope of his people, and the strength of the children of Israel. 17  So shall ye know that I am the LORD your God dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain: then shall Jerusalem be [†]holy, and there shall no [*]strangers pass through her any more.

18 ¶ And it shall come to pass in that day, that the mountains shall [*]drop down new wine, and the hills shall flow with milk, and all the rivers of Judah shall [†]flow with waters, and a fountain shall come forth of the house of the LORD, and shall water the valley of Shittim. 19  Egypt shall be a desolation, and Edom shall be a desolate wilderness, for the violence against the children of Judah, because they have shed innocent blood in their land. 20  But Judah shall [∥]dwell for ever, and Jerusalem from generation to generation. 21  For I will cleanse their blood that I have not cleansed: [∥]for the LORD dwelleth in Zion.

† 1.4 Heb. The residue of the palmerworm.

† 1.7 Heb. laid my fig tree for a barking

∥ 1.10 Or, ashamed.

* 1.14 ch 2. 15.

∥ 1.14 Or, day of restraint.

* 1.15 Is. 13. 6.

‡ 1.16 [1611 your]

† 1.17 Heb. grains.

∥ 1.19 Or, habitations.

∥ 2.1 Or, cornet.

† 2.2 Heb. of generation and generation.

† 2.6 Heb. pot.

∥ 2.8 Or, dart.

* 2.10 Is. 13 10. Ezek. 32. 7.

* 2.11 Jer. 30. 7. Amos 5. 18. Zeph. 1. 15.

* 2.12 Jer. 4 1.

* 2.13 Ex 34 6 Ps. 86 5. Jonah 4 2.

* 2.14 Jonah 3. 9.

* 2.15 ch 1 14.

∥ 2.17 Or, use a byword against them.

* 2.17 Ps. 42. 10. &c 79. 10. &c 115. 2.

† 2.20 Heb. he hath magnified to do.

∥ 2.23 Or, a teacher of righteousness.

† 2.23 Heb. according to righteousness.

* 2.23 Lev. 26. 4. Deut. 11. 14.

* 2.28 Is. 44. 3. Acts 2. 17.

* 2.31 ch. 3 15.

* 2.32 Rom. 10. 13.

† 3.5 Heb. desirable.

† 3.6 Heb. the sons of the Grecians.

† 3.9 Heb. Sanctify.

* 3.10 Is. 2. 4.

∥ 3.10 Or, scythes.

∥ 3.11 Or, the Lord shall bring down.

* 3.13 Rev. 14. 15.

‡ 3.13 [1611 the]

∥ 3.14 Or, concision, or, threshing.

* 3.15 ch. 2. 31.

* 3.16 Jer 25. 30. Amos 1. 2.

† 3.16 Heb. place of repair, or, harbour.

† 3.17 Heb holiness

* 3.17 Rev. 21. 27.

* 3.18 Amos 9 13.

† 3.18 Heb. go.

∥ 3.20 Or, abide.

∥ 3.21 Or, even I the Lord that dwelleth in Zion.

Jude

THE GENERAL EPISTLE OF JUDE

1

1  Jude, the servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to them that are sanctified by God the Father, and preserved in Jesus Christ, and called: 2  Mercy unto you, and peace, and love, be multiplied.

3  Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common salvation, it was needful for me to write unto you, and exhort you that ye should earnestly contend for the faith which was once delivered unto the saints. 4  For there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained to this condemnation, ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into lasciviousness, and denying the only Lord God, and our Lord Jesus Christ. 5  I will therefore put you in remembrance, though ye once knew this, how that the Lord, having saved the people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed them that believed not. 6  And the angels which kept not their first estate, but left their own habitation, he hath reserved in everlasting chains under darkness unto the judgment of the great day. 7  Even as Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities about them in like manner, giving themselves over to fornication, and going after strange flesh, are set forth for an example, suffering the vengeance of eternal fire. 8  Likewise also these filthy dreamers defile the flesh, despise dominion, and speak evil of dignities. 9  Yet Michael the archangel, when contending with the devil he disputed about the body of Moses, durst not bring against him a railing accusation, but said, The Lord rebuke thee. 10  But these speak evil of those things which they know not: but what they know naturally, as brute beasts, in those things they corrupt themselves. 11  Woe unto them! for they have gone in the way of Cain, and ran greedily after the error of Balaam for reward, and perished in the gainsaying of Core. 12  These are spots in your feasts of charity, when they feast with you, feeding themselves without fear: clouds they are without water, carried about of winds; trees whose fruit withereth, without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots; 13  Raging waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, to whom is reserved the blackness of darkness for ever. 14  And Enoch also, the seventh from Adam, prophesied of these, saying, Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thousands of his saints, 15  To execute judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly among them of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard speeches which ungodly sinners have spoken against him. 16  These are murmurers, complainers, walking after their own lusts; and their mouth speaketh great swelling words, having men’s persons in admiration because of advantage.

17  But, beloved, remember ye the words which were spoken before of the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ; 18  How that they told you there should be mockers in the last time, who should walk after their own ungodly lusts. 19  These be they who separate themselves, sensual, having not the Spirit. 20  But ye, beloved, building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Ghost, 21  Keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life. 22  And of some have compassion, making a difference: 23  And others save with fear, pulling them out of the fire; hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.

24  Now unto him that is able to keep you from falling, and to present you faultless before the presence of his glory with exceeding joy, 25  To the only wise God our Saviour, be glory and majesty, dominion and power, both now and ever. Amen.

Lamentations

1
2
3
4
5

The Lamentations of Jeremiah

1

1  How doth the city sit solitary, that was full of people! how is she become as a widow! she that was great among the nations, and princess among the provinces, how is she become tributary! 2  She [*]weepeth sore in the [*]night, and her tears are on her cheeks: among all her lovers she hath none to comfort her: all her friends have dealt treacherously with her, they are become her enemies. 3  Judah is gone into captivity because of affliction, and [†]because of great servitude: she dwelleth among the heathen, she findeth no rest: all her persecutors overtook her between the straits. 4  The ways of Zion do mourn, because none come to the solemn feasts: all her gates are desolate: her priests sigh, her virgins are afflicted, and she is in bitterness. 5  Her adversaries [*]are the chief, her enemies prosper; for the LORD hath afflicted her for the multitude of her transgressions: her [*]children are gone into captivity before the enemy. 6  And from the daughter of Zion all her beauty is departed: her princes are become like harts that find no pasture, and they are gone without strength before the pursuer. 7  Jerusalem remembered in the days of her affliction and of her miseries all her [∥]pleasant things that she had in the days of old, when her people fell into the hand of the enemy, and none did help her: the adversaries saw her, and did mock at her sabbaths. 8  Jerusalem hath grievously sinned; therefore she [†]is removed: all that honoured her despise her, because they have seen her nakedness: yea, she sigheth, and turneth backward. 9  Her filthiness is in her skirts; she remembereth not her last end; therefore she came down wonderfully: she had no comforter. O LORD, behold my affliction: for the enemy hath magnified himself. 10  The adversary hath spread out his hand upon all her [∥]pleasant things: for she hath seen that the heathen entered into her sanctuary, whom thou didst command that [*]they should not enter into thy congregation. 11  All her people sigh, they seek bread; they have given their pleasant things for meat [∥]to relieve the soul: see, O LORD, and consider; for I am become vile.

12 ¶ [∥]Is it nothing to you, all ye that [†]pass by? behold, and see if there be any sorrow like unto my sorrow, which is done unto me, wherewith the LORD hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger. 13  From above hath he sent fire into my bones, and it prevaileth against them: he hath spread a net for my feet, he hath turned me back: he hath made me desolate and faint all the day. 14  The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand: they are wreathed, and come up upon my neck: he hath made my strength to fall, the Lord hath delivered me into their hands, from whom I am not able to rise up. 15  The Lord hath trodden under foot all my mighty men in the midst of me: he hath called an assembly against me to crush my young men: the Lord hath trodden [∥]the virgin, the daughter of Judah, as in a winepress. 16 For these things I weep; [*]mine eye, mine eye runneth down with water, because the comforter that should [†]relieve my soul is far from me: my children are desolate, because the enemy prevailed. 17  Zion spreadeth forth her hands, and there is none to comfort her: the LORD hath commanded concerning Jacob, that his adversaries should be round about him: Jerusalem is as a menstruous woman among them.

18 ¶ The LORD is [*]righteous; for I have rebelled against his [†]commandment: hear, I pray you, all people, and behold my sorrow: my virgins and my young men are gone into captivity. 19  I called for my lovers, but they deceived me: my priests and mine elders gave up the ghost in the city, while they sought their meat to relieve their souls. 20  Behold, O LORD; for I am in distress: my [*]bowels are troubled; mine heart is turned within me; for I have grievously rebelled: abroad the sword bereaveth, at home there is as death. 21  They have heard that I sigh: there is none to comfort me: all mine enemies have heard of my trouble; they are glad that thou hast done it: thou wilt bring the day that thou hast [∥]called, and they shall be like unto me. 22  Let all their wickedness come before thee; and do unto them, as thou hast done unto me for all my transgressions: for my sighs are many, and my heart is faint.

2

1  How hath the Lord covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger, and cast down from heaven unto the earth the beauty of Israel, and remembered not his footstool in the day of his anger! 2  The Lord hath swallowed up all the habitations of Jacob, and hath not pitied: he hath thrown down in his wrath the strong holds of the daughter of Judah; he hath [†]brought them down to the ground: he hath polluted the kingdom and the princes thereof. 3  He hath cut off in his fierce anger all the horn of Israel: he hath drawn back his right hand from before the enemy, and he burned against Jacob like a flaming fire, which devoureth round about. 4  He hath bent his bow like an enemy: he stood with his right hand as an adversary, and slew [†]all that were pleasant to the eye in the tabernacle of the daughter of Zion: he poured out his fury like fire. 5  The Lord was as an enemy: he hath swallowed up Israel, he hath swallowed up all her palaces: he hath destroyed his strong holds, and hath increased in the daughter of Judah mourning and lamentation. 6  And he hath violently [*]taken away his [∥]tabernacle, as if it were of a garden: he hath destroyed his places of the assembly: the LORD hath caused the solemn feasts and sabbaths to be forgotten in Zion, and hath despised in the indignation of his anger the king and the priest. 7  The Lord hath cast off his altar, he hath abhorred his sanctuary, he hath [†]given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces; they have made a noise in the house of the LORD, as in the day of a solemn feast. 8  The LORD hath purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion: he hath stretched out a line, he hath not withdrawn his hand from [†]destroying: therefore he made the rampart and the wall to lament; they languished together. 9  Her gates are sunk into the ground; he hath destroyed and broken her bars: her king and her princes are among the Gentiles: the law is no more; her [*]prophets also find no vision from the LORD.

10  The elders of the daughter of Zion sit upon the ground, and keep silence: they have cast up dust upon their heads; they have girded themselves with sackcloth: the virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground. 11  Mine eyes do fail with tears, my bowels are troubled, my liver is poured upon the earth, for the destruction of the daughter of my people; because the children and the sucklings [∥]swoon in the streets of the city. 12  They say to their mothers, Where is corn and wine? when they swooned as the wounded in the streets of the city, when their soul was poured out into their mothers’ bosom. 13  What thing shall I take to witness for thee? what thing shall I liken to thee, O daughter of Jerusalem? what shall I equal to thee, that I may comfort thee, O virgin daughter of Zion? for thy breach is great like the sea: who can heal thee? 14  Thy [*]prophets have seen vain and foolish things for thee: and they have not discovered thine iniquity, to turn away thy captivity; but have seen for thee false burdens and causes of banishment. 15  All that pass [†]by clap their hands at thee; they hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying, Is this the city that men call [*]The perfection of beauty, The joy of the whole earth? 16  All thine enemies have opened their mouth against thee: they hiss and gnash the teeth: they say, We have swallowed her up: certainly this is the day that we looked for; we have found, we have seen it. 17  The LORD hath done that which he had [*]devised; he hath fulfilled his word that he had commanded in the days of old: he hath thrown down, and hath not pitied: and he hath caused thine enemy to rejoice over thee, he hath set up the horn of thine adversaries. 18  Their heart cried unto the Lord, O wall of the daughter of Zion, [*]let tears run down like a river day and night: give thyself no rest; let not the apple of thine eye cease. 19  Arise, cry out in the night: in the beginning of the watches pour out thine heart like water before the face of the Lord: lift up thy hands toward him for the life of thy young children, that faint for hunger in the top of every street.

20 ¶ Behold, O LORD, and consider to whom thou hast done this. Shall the women eat their fruit, and children [∥]of a span long? shall the priest and the prophet be slain in the sanctuary of the Lord? 21  The young and the old lie on the ground in the streets: my virgins and my young men are fallen by the sword; thou hast slain them in the day of thine anger; thou hast killed, and not pitied. 22  Thou hast called as in a solemn day my terrors round about, so that in the day of the LORD’s anger none escaped nor remained: those that I have swaddled and brought up hath mine enemy consumed.

3

1 I am the man that hath seen affliction by the rod of his wrath. 2  He hath led me, and brought me into darkness, but not into light. 3  Surely against me is he turned; he turneth his hand against me all the day. 4  My flesh and my skin hath he made old; he hath broken my bones. 5  He hath builded against me, and compassed me with gall and travail. 6  He hath set me in dark places, as they that be dead of old. 7  He hath hedged me about, that I cannot get out: he hath made my chain heavy. 8  Also when I cry and shout, he shutteth out my prayer. 9  He hath inclosed my ways with hewn stone, he hath made my paths crooked. 10 He was unto me as a bear lying in wait, and as a lion in secret places. 11  He hath turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces: he hath made me desolate. 12  He hath bent his bow, and set me as a mark for the arrow. 13  He hath caused the [†]arrows of his quiver to enter into my reins. 14  I was a [*]derision to all my people; and their song all the day. 15  He hath filled me with [†]bitterness, he hath made me drunken with wormwood. 16  He hath also broken my teeth with gravel stones, he hath [∥]covered me with ashes. 17  And thou hast removed my soul far off from peace: I forgat [†]prosperity. 18  And I said, My strength and my hope is perished from the LORD: 19 [∥] Remembering mine affliction and my misery, the wormwood and the gall. 20  My soul hath them still in remembrance, and is [†]humbled in me.

21  This I [†]recall to my mind, therefore have I hope.

22 ¶ It is of the LORD’s mercies that we are not consumed, because his compassions fail not. 23  They are new every morning: great is thy faithfulness. 24  The LORD is my [*]portion, saith my soul; therefore will I hope in him. 25  The LORD is good unto them that wait for him, to the soul that seeketh him. 26  It is good that a man should both hope and quietly wait for the salvation of the LORD. 27  It is good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth. 28  He sitteth alone and keepeth silence, because he hath borne it upon him. 29  He putteth his mouth in the dust; if so be there may be hope. 30  He giveth his cheek to him that smiteth him: he is filled full with reproach. 31  For the Lord will not cast off for ever: 32  But though he cause grief, yet will he have compassion according to the multitude of his mercies. 33  For he doth not afflict [†]willingly nor grieve the children of men. 34  To crush under his feet all the prisoners of the earth, 35  To turn aside the right of a man before the face of [∥]the most High, 36  To subvert a man in his cause, the Lord [∥]approveth not.

37 ¶ Who is he [*]that saith, and it cometh to pass, when the Lord commandeth it not? 38  Out of the mouth of the most High proceedeth not [*]evil and good? 39  Wherefore doth a living man [∥]complain, a man for the punishment of his sins? 40  Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to the LORD. 41  Let us lift up our heart with our hands unto God in the heavens.

42  We have transgressed and have rebelled: thou hast not pardoned. 43  Thou hast covered with anger, and persecuted us: thou hast slain, thou hast not pitied. 44  Thou hast covered thyself with a cloud, that our prayer should not pass through. 45  Thou hast made us as the [*]offscouring and refuse in the midst of the people. 46  All our enemies have opened their mouths against us. 47 [*] Fear and a snare is come upon us, desolation and destruction. 48  Mine eye runneth down with rivers of water for the destruction of the daughter of my people. 49  Mine eye trickleth down, and ceaseth not, without any intermission, 50  Till the LORD look down, and behold from heaven. 51  Mine eye affecteth [†]mine heart [∥]because of all the daughters of my city. 52  Mine enemies chased me sore, like a bird, without cause. 53  They have cut off my life in the dungeon, and cast a stone upon me. 54  Waters flowed over mine head; then I said, I am cut off.

55 ¶ I called upon thy name, O LORD, out of the low dungeon. 56  Thou hast heard my voice: hide not thine ear at my breathing, at my cry. 57  Thou drewest near in the day that I called upon thee: thou saidst, Fear not. 58  O Lord, thou hast pleaded the causes of my soul; thou hast redeemed my life. 59  O LORD, thou hast seen my wrong: judge thou my cause. 60  Thou hast seen all their vengeance and all their imaginations against me. 61  Thou hast heard their reproach, O LORD, and all their imaginations against me; 62  The lips of those that rose up against me, and their device against me all the day. 63  Behold their sitting down, and their rising up; I am their musick.

64 ¶ Render unto them a recompence, O LORD, according to the work of their hands. 65  Give them [∥]sorrow of heart, thy curse unto them. 66  Persecute and destroy them in anger from under the [*]heavens of the LORD.

4

1  How is the gold become dim! how is the most fine gold changed! the stones of the sanctuary are poured out in the top of every street. 2  The precious sons of Zion, comparable to fine gold, how are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the potter! 3  Even the [∥]sea monsters draw out the breast, they give suck to their young ones: the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the ostriches in the wilderness. 4  The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for thirst: the young children ask bread, and no man breaketh it unto them. 5  They that did feed delicately are desolate in the streets: they that were brought up in scarlet embrace dunghills. 6  For the [∥]punishment of the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the punishment of the sin of Sodom, that was [*]overthrown as in a moment, and no hands stayed on her. 7  Her Nazarites were purer than snow, they were whiter than milk, they were more ruddy in body than rubies, their polishing was of sapphire: 8  Their visage is [†]blacker than a coal; they are not known in the streets: their skin cleaveth to their bones; it is withered, it is become like a stick. 9  They that be slain with the sword are better than they that be slain with hunger: for these [†]pine away, stricken through for want of the fruits of the field. 10  The hands of the pitiful women have [*]sodden their own children: they were their meat in the destruction of the daughter of my people. 11  The LORD hath accomplished his fury; he hath poured out his fierce anger, and hath kindled a fire in Zion, and it hath devoured the foundations thereof. 12  The kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world, would not have believed that the adversary and the enemy should have entered into the gates of Jerusalem.

13 ¶ [*]For the sins of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests, that have shed the blood of the just in the midst of her, 14  They have wandered as blind men in the streets, they have polluted themselves with blood, [∥]so that men could not touch their garments. 15  They cried unto them, Depart ye; [∥]it is unclean; depart, depart, touch not: when they fled away and wandered, they said among the heathen, They shall no more sojourn there. 16  The [∥]anger of the LORD hath divided them; he will no more regard them: they respected not the persons of the priests, they favoured not the elders. 17  As for us, our eyes as yet failed for our vain help: in our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save us. 18  They hunt our steps, that we cannot go in our streets: our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come. 19  Our persecutors are swifter than the eagles of the heaven: they pursued us upon the mountains, they laid wait for us in the wilderness. 20  The [*]breath of our nostrils, the anointed of the LORD, was taken in their pits, of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall live among the heathen.

21 ¶ Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the land of Uz; the cup also shall pass through unto thee: thou shalt be drunken, and shalt make thyself naked.

22 ¶ [∥]The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O daughter of Zion; he will no more carry thee away into captivity: he will visit thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he will [∥]discover thy sins.

5

1  Remember, O LORD, what is come upon us: consider, and behold our reproach. 2  Our inheritance is turned to strangers, our houses to aliens. 3  We are orphans and fatherless, our mothers are as widows. 4  We have drunken our water for money; our wood [†]is sold unto us. 5 [†] Our necks are under persecution: we labour, and have no rest. 6  We have given the hand to the Egyptians, and to the Assyrians, to be satisfied with bread. 7 [*] Our fathers have sinned, and are not; and we have borne their iniquities. 8  Servants have ruled over us: there is none that doth deliver us out of their hand. 9  We gat our bread with the peril of our lives because of the sword of the wilderness. 10  Our [*]skin was black like an oven because of the [∥]terrible famine. 11  They ravished the women in Zion, and the maids in the cities of Judah. 12  Princes are hanged up by their hand: the faces of elders were not honoured. 13  They took the young men to grind, and the children fell under the wood. 14  The elders have ceased from the gate, the young men from their musick. 15  The joy of our heart is ceased; our dance is turned into mourning. 16 [†] The crown is fallen from our head: woe unto us, that we have sinned!

17  For this our heart is faint; for these things our eyes are dim. 18  Because of the mountain of Zion, which is desolate, the foxes walk upon it. 19  Thou, O LORD, [*]remainest for ever; thy throne from generation to generation. 20  Wherefore dost thou forget us for ever, and forsake us [†]so long time? 21 [*] Turn thou us unto thee, O LORD, and we shall be turned; renew our days as of old. 22 [∥] But thou hast utterly rejected us; thou art very wroth against us.

* 1.2 Jer. 13. 17.

* 1.2 Job 7. 3.

† 1.3 Heb. for the greatness of servitude.

* 1.5 Deut. 28 13, 43, 44.

* 1.5 Jer. 52. 28.

∥ 1.7 Or, desirable.

† 1.8 Heb. is become a removing, or, wandering.

∥ 1.10 Or, desirable.

* 1.10 Deut. 23. 3.

∥ 1.11 Or, to make the soul to come again.

∥ 1.12 Or, It is nothing.

† 1.12 Heb. pass by the way?

∥ 1.15 Or, the winepress of the virgin, &c.

* 1.16 Jer. 13. 17 &c 14. 17. ch. 2. 18.

† 1.16 Heb bring back.

* 1.18 Dan. 9 7.

† 1.18 Heb. mouth.

* 1.20 Is. 16 11. Jer. 48. 36.

∥ 1.21 Or, proclaimed.

† 2.2 Heb made to touch.

† 2.4 Heb. all the desirable of the eye.

* 2.6 Ps. 80. 12. &c 89. 40 Is. 5. 5.

∥ 2.6 Or, hedge.

† 2.7 Heb. shut up.

† 2.8 Heb. swallowing up.

* 2.9 Ps. 74. 9.

∥ 2.11 Or, faint.

* 2.14 Jer. 2 8. &c 5. 31. &c 14. 14. &c 23. 16.

† 2.15 Heb. by the way.

* 2.15 Ps. 48. 2.

* 2.17 Lev. 26. 16. Deut. 28. 15.

* 2.18 Jer. 14. 17 ch. 1. 16.

∥ 2.20 Or, swaddled with their hands?

† 3.13 Heb. sons.

* 3.14 Jer. 20. 7.

† 3.15 Heb. bitternesses.

∥ 3.16 Or, rolled me in the ashes.

† 3.17 Heb. good.

∥ 3.19 Or, Remember.

† 3.20 Heb. bowed.

† 3.21 Heb. make to return to my heart.

* 3.24 Ps. 16 5. &c 73. 26. &c 119 57. Jer. 10. 16.

† 3.33 Heb. from his heart.

∥ 3.35 Or, a superior,

∥ 3.36 Or, seeth not.

* 3.37 Ps. 33. 9.

* 3.38 Amos 3. 6.

∥ 3.39 Or, murmur.

* 3.45 1 Cor. 4. 13.

* 3.47 Is. 24. 17.

† 3.51 Heb. my soul.

∥ 3.51 Or, more than all.

∥ 3.65 Or, obstinacy of heart.

* 3.66 Ps. 8. 3.

∥ 4.3 Or, sea calves.

∥ 4.6 Or, iniquity.

* 4.6 Gen. 19. 25.

† 4.8 Heb. darker than blackness.

† 4.9 Heb flow out.

* 4.10 Deut. 28 57. 2 Kings 6 29.

* 4.13 Jer 5. 31 &c 23. 21.

∥ 4.14 Or, in that they could not but touch.

∥ 4.15 Or, ye polluted.

∥ 4.16 Or, face.

* 4.20 Gen. 2. 7.

∥ 4.22 Or, Thine iniquity.

∥ 4.22 Or, carry thee captive for thy sins.

† 5.4 Heb. cometh for price.

† 5.5 Heb. On our necks are we persecuted.

* 5.7 Jer. 31. 29. Ezek. 18. 2.

* 5.10 Ps. 119. 83.

∥ 5.10 Or, terrors, or, storms.

† 5.16 Heb. The crown of our head is fallen

* 5.19 Ps. 9. 7. &c 29. 10. &c 102. 12 &c 145 13.

† 5.20 Heb. for length of days?

* 5.21 Jer. 31. 18.

∥ 5.22 Or, For wilt thou utterly reject us?

Malachi

1
2
3
4

Malachi

1

1  The burden of the word of the LORD to Israel [†]by Malachi. 2  I have loved you, saith the LORD. Yet ye say, Wherein hast thou loved us? Was not Esau Jacob’s brother? saith the LORD: yet I [*]loved Jacob, 3  And I hated Esau, and laid his mountains and his heritage waste for the dragons of the wilderness. 4  Whereas Edom saith, We are impoverished, but we will return and build the desolate places; thus saith the LORD of hosts, They shall build, but I will throw down; and they shall call them, The border of wickedness, and, The people against whom the LORD hath indignation for ever. 5  And your eyes shall see, and ye shall say, The LORD will be magnified [∥][†]from the border of Israel.

6 ¶ A son honoureth his father, and a servant his master: if then I be a father, where is mine honour? and if I be a master, where is my fear? saith the LORD of hosts unto you, O priests, that despise my name. And ye say, Wherein have we despised thy name? 7 [∥] Ye offer polluted bread upon mine altar; and ye say, Wherein have we polluted thee? In that ye say, The table of the LORD is contemptible. 8  And if ye offer the blind [†]for sacrifice, is it not evil? and if ye offer the lame and sick, is it not evil? offer it now unto thy governor; will he be pleased with thee, or accept thy person? saith the LORD of hosts. 9  And now, I pray you, beseech [†]God that he will be gracious unto us: this hath been [†]by your means: will he regard your persons? saith the LORD of hosts. 10 Who is there even among you that would shut the doors for nought? neither do ye kindle fire on mine altar for nought. I have no pleasure in you, saith the LORD of hosts, neither will I accept an [*]offering at your hand. 11  For from the rising of the sun even unto the going down of the same my name shall be great among the Gentiles; and in every place incense shall be offered unto my name, and a pure offering: for my name shall be great among the heathen, saith the LORD of hosts.

12 ¶ But ye have profaned it, in that ye say, The table of the LORD is polluted; and the fruit thereof, even his meat, is contemptible. 13  Ye said also, Behold, what a weariness is it! [∥]and ye have snuffed at it, saith the LORD of hosts; and ye brought that which was torn, and the lame, and the sick; thus ye brought an offering: should I accept this of your hand? saith the LORD. 14  But cursed be the deceiver, [∥]which hath in his flock a male, and voweth, and sacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing: for I am a great King, saith the LORD of hosts, and my name is dreadful among the heathen.

2

1  And now, O ye priests, this commandment is for you. 2 [*] If ye will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my name, saith the LORD of hosts, I will even send a curse upon you, and I will curse your blessings: yea, I have cursed them already, because ye do not lay it to heart. 3  Behold, I will [∥]corrupt your seed, and [†]spread dung upon your faces, even the dung of your solemn feasts; and [∥]one shall take you away with it. 4  And ye shall know that I have sent this commandment unto you, that my covenant might be with Levi, saith the LORD of hosts. 5  My covenant was with him of life and peace; and I gave them to him for the fear wherewith he feared me, and was afraid before my name. 6  The law of truth was in his mouth, and iniquity was not found in his lips: he walked with me in peace and equity, and did turn many away from iniquity. 7  For the priest’s lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the law at his mouth: for he is the messenger of the LORD of hosts. 8  But ye are departed out of the way; ye have caused many to [∥]stumble at the law; ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi, saith the LORD of hosts. 9  Therefore have I also made you contemptible and base before all the people, according as ye have not kept my ways, but [∥][†]have been partial in the law.

10 [*] Have we not all one father? hath not one God created us? why do we deal treacherously every man against his brother, by profaning the covenant of our fathers?

11 ¶ Judah hath dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah hath profaned the holiness of the LORD which he [∥]loved, and hath married the daughter of a strange god. 12  The LORD will cut off the man that doeth this, [∥]the master and the scholar, out of the tabernacles of Jacob, and him that offereth an offering unto the LORD of hosts. 13  And this have ye done again, covering the altar of the LORD with tears, with weeping, and with crying out, insomuch that he regardeth not the offering any more, or receiveth it with good will at your hand.

14 ¶ Yet ye say, Wherefore? Because the LORD hath been witness between thee and the wife of thy youth, against whom thou hast dealt treacherously: yet is she thy companion, and the wife of thy covenant. 15  And did not he make one? Yet had he the [∥]residue of the spirit. And wherefore one? That he might seek [†]a godly seed. Therefore take heed to your spirit, and let none deal [∥]treacherously against the wife of his youth. 16  For the LORD, the God of Israel, saith [∥]that he hateth [†]putting away: for one covereth violence with his garment, saith the LORD of hosts: therefore take heed to your spirit, that ye deal not treacherously.

17 ¶ Ye have wearied the LORD with your words. Yet ye say, Wherein have we wearied him? When ye say, Every one that doeth evil is good in the sight of the LORD, and he delighteth in them; or, Where is the God of judgment?

3

1  Behold, [*]I will send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me: and the Lord, whom ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple, even the messenger of the covenant, whom ye delight in: behold, he shall come, saith the LORD of hosts. 2  But who may abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is like a refiner’s fire, and like fullers’ soap: 3  And he shall sit as a refiner and purifier of silver: and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and purge them as gold and silver, that they may offer unto the LORD an offering in righteousness. 4  Then shall the [‡]offering of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant unto the LORD, as in the days of old, and as in [∥]former years. 5  And I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against false swearers, and against those that [∥]oppress the hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and that turn aside the stranger from his right, and fear not me, saith the LORD of hosts. 6 For I am the LORD, I change not; therefore ye sons of Jacob are not consumed.

7 ¶ Even from the days of your fathers ye are gone away from mine ordinances, and have not kept them. [*]Return unto me, and I will return unto you, saith the LORD of hosts. But ye said, Wherein shall we return?

8 ¶ Will a man rob God? Yet ye have robbed me. But ye say, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings. 9 Ye are cursed with a curse: for ye have robbed me, even this whole nation. 10  Bring ye all the tithes into the storehouse, that there may be meat in mine house, and prove me now herewith, saith the LORD of hosts, if I will not open you the [*]windows of heaven, and [†]pour you out a blessing, that there shall not be room enough to receive it. 11  And I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall not [†]destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine cast her fruit before the time in the field, saith the LORD of hosts. 12  And all nations shall call you blessed: for ye shall be a delightsome land, saith the LORD of hosts.

13 ¶ Your words have been [*]stout against me, saith the LORD. Yet ye say, What have we spoken so much against thee? 14  Ye have said, It is vain to serve God: and what profit is it that we have kept [†]his ordinance, and that we have walked [†]mournfully before the LORD of hosts? 15  And now we call the proud happy; yea, they that work wickedness [†]are set up; yea, they that [*]tempt God are even delivered.

16 ¶ Then they that feared the LORD spake often one to another: and the LORD hearkened, and heard it, and a book of remembrance was written before him for them that feared the LORD, and that thought upon his name. 17  And they shall be mine, saith the LORD of hosts, in that day when I make up my [∥]jewels; and I will spare them, as a man spareth his own son that serveth him. 18  Then shall ye return, and discern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that serveth God and him that serveth him not.

4

1  For, behold, the day cometh, that shall burn as an oven; and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly, shall be stubble: and the day that cometh shall burn them up, saith the LORD of hosts, that it shall leave them neither root nor branch.

2 ¶ But unto you that fear my name shall the [*]Sun of righteousness arise with healing in his wings; and [‡]ye shall go forth, and grow up as calves of the stall. 3  And ye shall tread down the wicked; for they shall be ashes under the soles of your feet in the day that I shall do this, saith the LORD of hosts.

4 ¶ Remember ye the [*]law of Moses my servant, which I commanded unto him in Horeb for all Israel, with the statutes and judgments.

5 ¶ Behold, I will send you [*]Elijah the prophet before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the LORD: 6  And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their fathers, lest I come and smite the earth with a curse.

† 1.1 Heb. by the hand of Malachi.

* 1.2 Rom. 9. 13.

∥ 1.5 Or, upon.

† 1.5 Heb. from upon.

∥ 1.7 Or, Bring unto, &c.

† 1.8 Heb. to sacrifice.

† 1.9 Heb. the face of God.

† 1.9 Heb. from your hand.

* 1.10 Is. 1 11. Jer. 6. 20 Amos 5. 21.

∥ 1.13 Or, where as ye might have blown it away.

∥ 1.14 Or, in whose flock is.

* 2.2 Lev. 26. 14. Deut. 28. 15.

∥ 2.3 Or, reprove.

† 2.3 Heb. scatter.

∥ 2.3 Or, it shall take you away to it,

∥ 2.8 Or, fall in the law.

∥ 2.9 Or, lifted up the face against.

† 2.9 Heb. accepted faces.

* 2.10 Eph. 4. 6.

∥ 2.11 Or, ought to love.

∥ 2.12 Or him that waketh, and him that answereth.

∥ 2.15 Or, excellency.

† 2.15 Heb. a seed of God.

∥ 2.15 Or, unfaithfully.

∥ 2.16 Or, if he hate her, put her away.

† 2.16 Heb. to put away.

* 3.1 Matt. 11. 10. Mark 1. 2. Luke 1. 76. &c 7. 27.

‡ 3.4 [1611 offerings]

∥ 3.4 Or, ancient.

∥ 3.5 Or, defraud.

* 3.7 Zech. 1. 3.

* 3.10 Gen. 7. 11.

† 3.10 Heb. empty out.

† 3.11 Heb. corrupt.

* 3.13 Job 21. 14.

† 3.14 Heb. his observation

† 3.14 Heb. in black

† 3.15 Heb. are built

* 3.15 Ps 95. 9.

∥ 3.17 Or, special treasure.

* 4.2 Luke 1. 78

‡ 4.2 [1611 omits ye]

* 4.4 Ex. 20. 3.

* 4.5 Matt. 11 14 Mark 9. 11. Luke 1. 17.

Matthew

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28

THE GOSPEL ACCORDING TO ST. MATTHEW

1

1  The book of the [*]generation of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham. 2 [*] Abraham begat Isaac; and [*]Isaac begat Jacob; and [*]Jacob begat Judas and his brethren; 3  And [*]Judas begat Phares and Zara of Thamar; and [*]Phares begat Esrom; and Esrom begat Aram; 4  And Aram begat Aminadab; and Aminadab begat Naasson; and Naasson begat Salmon; 5  And Salmon begat Booz of Rachab; and Booz begat Obed of Ruth; and Obed begat Jesse; 6  And [*]Jesse begat David the king; and [*]David the king begat Solomon of her that had been the wife of Urias; 7  And [*]Solomon begat Roboam; and Roboam begat Abia; and Abia begat Asa; 8  And Asa begat Josaphat; and Josaphat begat Joram; and Joram begat Ozias; 9  And Ozias begat Joatham; and Joatham begat Achaz; and Achaz begat Ezekias; 10  And [*]Ezekias begat Manasses; and Manasses begat Amon; and Amon begat Josias; 11  And [∥]Josias begat Jechonias and his brethren, about the time they were carried away to Babylon: 12  And after they were brought to Babylon, [*]Jechonias begat Salathiel; and Salathiel begat Zorobabel; 13  And Zorobabel begat Abiud; and Abiud begat Eliakim; and Eliakim begat Azor; 14  And Azor begat Sadoc; and Sadoc begat Achim; and Achim begat Eliud; 15  And Eliud begat Eleazar; and Eleazar begat Matthan; and Matthan begat Jacob; 16  And Jacob begat Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ. 17  So all the generations from Abraham to David are fourteen generations; and from David until the carrying away into Babylon are fourteen generations; and from the carrying away into Babylon unto Christ are fourteen generations.

18 ¶ Now the [*]birth of Jesus Christ was on this wise: When as his mother Mary was espoused to Joseph, before they came together, she was found with child of the Holy Ghost. 19  Then Joseph her husband, being a just man, and not willing to make her a publick example, was minded to put her away privily. 20  But while he thought on these things, behold, the angel of the Lord appeared unto him in a dream, saying, Joseph, thou son of David, fear not to take unto thee Mary thy wife: for that which is conceived in her is of the Holy Ghost. 21 [*] And she shall bring forth a son, and thou shalt call his name JESUS: for he shall save his people from their sins. 22  Now all this was done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken of the Lord by the prophet, saying, 23 [*] Behold, a virgin shall be with child, and shall bring forth a son, and [∥]they shall call his name Emmanuel, which being interpreted is, God with us. 24  Then Joseph being raised from sleep did as the angel of the Lord had bidden him, and took unto him his wife: 25  And knew her not till she had brought forth her firstborn son: and he called his name JESUS.

2

1  Now when [*]Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judaea in the days of Herod the king, behold, there came wise men from the east to Jerusalem, 2  Saying, Where is he that is born King of the Jews? for we have seen his star in the east, and are come to worship him. 3  When Herod the king had heard these things, he was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him. 4  And when he had gathered all the chief priests and scribes of the people together, he demanded of them where Christ should be born. 5  And they said unto him, In Bethlehem of Judaea: for thus it is written by the prophet, 6 [*] And thou Bethlehem, in the land of Juda, art not the least among the princes of Juda: for out of thee shall come a Governor, that shall [∥]rule my people Israel. 7  Then Herod, when he had privily called the wise men, enquired of them diligently what time the star appeared. 8  And he sent them to Bethlehem, and said, Go and search diligently for the young child; and when ye have found him, bring me word again, that I may come and worship him also. 9  When they had heard the king, they departed; and, lo, the star, which they saw in the east, went before them, till it came and stood over where the young child was. 10  When they saw the star, they rejoiced with exceeding great joy.

11 ¶ And when they were come into the house, they saw the young child with Mary his mother, and fell down, and worshipped him: and when they had opened their treasures, they [∥]presented unto him gifts; gold, and frankincense, and myrrh. 12  And being warned of God in a dream that they should not return to Herod, they departed into their own country another way. 13  And when they were departed, behold, the angel of the Lord appeareth to Joseph in a dream, saying, Arise, and take the young child and his mother, and flee into Egypt, and be thou there until I bring thee word: for Herod will seek the young child to destroy him. 14  When he arose, he took the young child and his mother by night, and departed into Egypt: 15  And was there until the death of Herod: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken of the Lord by the prophet, saying, [*]Out of Egypt have I called my son.

16 ¶ Then Herod, when he saw that he was mocked of the wise men, was exceeding wroth, and sent forth, and slew all the children that were in Bethlehem, and in all the coasts thereof, from two years old and under, according to the time which he had diligently enquired of the wise men. 17  Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by [*]Jeremy the prophet, saying, 18  In Rama was there a voice heard, lamentation, and weeping, and great mourning, Rachel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, because they are not.

19 ¶ But when Herod was dead, behold, an angel of the Lord appeareth in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, 20  Saying, Arise, and take the young child and his mother, and go into the land of Israel: for they are dead which sought the young child’s life. 21  And he arose, and took the young child and his mother, and came into the land of Israel. 22  But when he heard that Archelaus did reign in Judaea in the room of his father Herod, he was afraid to go thither: notwithstanding, being warned of God in a dream, he turned aside into the parts of Galilee: 23  And he came and dwelt in a city called Nazareth: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophets, He shall be called a Nazarene.

3

1  In those days came [*]John the Baptist, preaching in the wilderness of Judaea, 2  And saying, Repent ye: for the kingdom of heaven is at hand. 3  For this is he that was spoken of by the prophet Esaias, saying, [*]The voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths straight. 4  And the same John had his raiment of camel’s hair, and a leathern girdle about his loins; and his meat was locusts and wild honey. 5  Then went out to him Jerusalem, and all Judaea, and all the region round about Jordan, 6  And were baptized of him in Jordan, confessing their sins.

7 ¶ But when he saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees come to his baptism, he said unto them, [*]O generation of vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come? 8  Bring forth therefore fruits [∥]meet for repentance: 9  And think not to say within yourselves, [*]We have Abraham to our father: for I say unto you, that God is able of these stones to raise up children unto Abraham. 10  And now also the axe is laid unto the root of the trees: [*]therefore every tree which bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire. 11 [*] I indeed baptize you with water unto repentance: but he that cometh after me is mightier than I, whose shoes I am not worthy to bear: he shall baptize you with the Holy Ghost, and with fire: 12  Whose fan is in his hand, and he will throughly purge his floor, and gather his wheat into the garner; but [‡]he will burn up the chaff with unquenchable fire.

13 ¶ [*]Then cometh Jesus from Galilee to Jordan unto John, to be baptized of him. 14  But John forbad him, saying, I have need to be baptized of thee, and comest thou to me? 15  And Jesus answering said unto him, Suffer it to be so now: for thus it becometh us to fulfil all righteousness. Then he suffered him. 16  And Jesus, when he was baptized, went up straightway out of the water: and, lo, the heavens were opened unto him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove, and lighting upon him: 17  And lo a voice from heaven, saying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.

4

1  Then was [*]Jesus led up of the Spirit into the wilderness to be tempted of the devil. 2  And when he had fasted forty days and forty nights, he was afterward an hungred. 3  And when the tempter came to him, he said, If thou be the Son of God, command that these stones be made bread. 4  But he answered and said, It is written, [*]Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God. 5  Then the devil taketh him up into the holy city, and setteth him on a pinnacle of the temple, 6  And saith unto him, If thou be the Son of God, cast thyself down: for it is written, [*]He shall give his angels charge concerning thee: and in their hands they shall bear thee up, lest at any time thou dash thy foot against a stone. 7  Jesus said unto him, It is written again, [*]Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God. 8  Again, the devil taketh him up into an exceeding high mountain, and sheweth him all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them; 9  And saith unto him, All these things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worship me. 10  Then saith Jesus unto him, Get thee hence, Satan: for it is written, [*]Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve. 11  Then the devil leaveth him, and, behold, angels came and ministered unto him.

12 ¶ [*]Now when Jesus had heard that John was [∥]cast into prison, he departed into Galilee; 13  And leaving Nazareth, he came and dwelt in Capernaum, which is upon the sea coast, in the borders of Zabulon and Nephthalim: 14  That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Esaias the prophet, saying, 15 [*] The land of Zabulon, and the land of Nephthalim, by the way of the sea, beyond Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles; 16  The people which sat in darkness saw great light; and to them which sat in the region and shadow of death light is sprung up.

17 ¶ [*]From that time Jesus began to preach, and to say, Repent: for the kingdom of heaven is at hand.

18 ¶ [*]And Jesus, walking by the sea of Galilee, saw two brethren, Simon called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea: for they were fishers. 19  And he saith unto them, Follow me, and I will make you fishers of men. 20  And they straightway left their nets, and followed him. 21  And going on from thence, he saw other two brethren, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, in a ship with Zebedee their father, mending their nets; and he called them. 22  And they immediately left the ship and their father, and followed him.

23 ¶ And Jesus went about all Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing all manner of sickness and all manner of disease among the people. 24  And his fame went throughout all Syria: and they brought unto him all sick people that were taken with divers diseases and torments, and those which were possessed with devils, and those which were lunatick, and those that had the palsy; and he healed them. 25  And there followed him great multitudes of people from Galilee, and from Decapolis, and from Jerusalem, and from Judaea, and from beyond Jordan.

5

1  And seeing the multitudes, he went up into a mountain: and when he was set, his disciples came unto him: 2  And he opened his mouth, and taught them, saying, 3 [*] Blessed are the poor in spirit: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven. 4  Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted. 5 [*] Blessed are the meek: for they shall inherit the earth. 6  Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after righteousness: [*]for they shall be filled. 7  Blessed are the merciful: for they shall obtain mercy. 8 [*] Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see God. 9  Blessed are the peacemakers: for they shall be called the children of God. 10 [*] Blessed are they which are persecuted for righteousness’ sake: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven. 11  Blessed are ye, when men shall revile you, and persecute you, and shall say all manner of [*]evil against you [†]falsely, for my sake. 12  Rejoice, and be exceeding glad: for great is your reward in heaven: for so persecuted they the prophets which were before you.

13 ¶ Ye are the salt of the earth: [*]but if the salt have lost his savour, wherewith shall it be salted? it is thenceforth good for nothing, but to be cast out, and to be trodden under foot of men. 14  Ye are the light of the world. A city that is set on an hill cannot be hid. 15  Neither do men [*]light a candle, and put it under [∥]a bushel, but on a candlestick; and it giveth light unto all that are in the house. 16  Let your light so shine before men, [*]that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father which is in heaven.

17 ¶ Think not that I am come to destroy the law, or the prophets: I am not come to destroy, but to fulfil. 18  For verily I say unto you, [*]Till heaven and earth pass, one jot or one tittle shall in no wise pass from the law, till all be fulfilled. 19 [*] Whosoever therefore shall break one of these least commandments, and shall teach men so, he shall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven: but whosoever shall do and teach them, the same shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven. 20  For I say unto you, That except your righteousness shall exceed the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no case enter into the kingdom of heaven.

21 ¶ Ye have heard that it was said [∥]by them of old time, [*]Thou shalt not kill; and whosoever shall kill shall be in danger of the judgment: 22  But I say unto you, That whosoever is angry with his brother without a cause shall be in danger of the judgment: and whosoever shall say to his brother, Raca, shall be in danger of the council: but whosoever shall say, Thou fool, shall be in danger of hell fire. 23  Therefore if thou bring thy gift to the altar, and there rememberest that thy brother hath ought against thee; 24  Leave there thy gift before the altar, and go thy way; first be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift. 25 [*] Agree with thine adversary quickly, whiles thou art in the way with him; lest at any time the adversary deliver thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and thou be cast into prison. 26  Verily I say unto thee, Thou shalt by no means come out thence, till thou hast paid the uttermost farthing.

27 ¶ Ye have heard that it was said by them of old time, [*]Thou shalt not commit adultery: 28  But I say unto you, That whosoever looketh on a woman to lust after her hath committed adultery with her already in his heart. 29 [*] And if thy right eye [∥]offend thee, pluck it out, and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not that thy whole body should be cast into hell. 30  And if thy right hand offend thee, cut it off, and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not that thy whole body should be cast into hell. 31  It hath been said, [*]Whosoever shall put away his wife, let him give her a writing of divorcement: 32  But I say unto you, That whosoever shall put away his wife, saving for the cause of fornication, causeth her to commit adultery: and whosoever shall marry her that is divorced committeth adultery.

33 ¶ Again, ye have heard that it hath been said by them of old time, [*]Thou shalt not forswear thyself, but shalt perform unto the Lord thine oaths: 34  But I say unto you, Swear not at all; neither by heaven; for it is God’s throne: 35  Nor by the earth; for it is his footstool: neither by Jerusalem; for it is the city of the great King. 36  Neither shalt thou swear by thy head, because thou canst not make one hair white or black. 37 [*] But let your communication be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay: for whatsoever is more than these cometh of evil.

38 ¶ Ye have heard that it hath been said, [*]An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth: 39  But I say unto you, [*]That ye resist not evil: but whosoever shall smite thee on thy right cheek, turn to him the other also. 40  And if any man will sue thee at the law, and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloke also. 41  And whosoever shall compel thee to go a mile, go with him twain. 42  Give to him that asketh thee, and [*]from him that would borrow of thee turn not thou away.

43 ¶ Ye have heard that it hath been said, [*]Thou shalt love thy neighbour, and hate thine enemy. 44  But I say unto you, [*]Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate you, and [*]pray for them which despitefully use you, and persecute you; 45  That ye may be the children of your Father which is in heaven: for he maketh his sun to rise on the evil and on the good, and sendeth rain on the just and on the unjust. 46 [*] For if ye love them which love you, what reward have ye? do not even the publicans the same? 47  And if ye salute your brethren only, what do ye more than others? do not even the publicans so? 48  Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect.

6

1  Take heed that ye do not your alms before men, to be seen of them: otherwise ye have no reward [∥]of your Father which is in heaven. 2  Therefore [*]when thou doest thine alms, [∥]do not sound a trumpet before thee, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, that they may have glory of men. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward. 3  But when thou doest alms, let not thy left hand know what thy right [‡]hand doeth: 4  That thine alms may be in secret: and thy Father which seeth in secret himself shall reward thee openly.

5 ¶ And when thou prayest, thou shalt not be as the hypocrites are: for they love to pray standing in the synagogues and in the corners of the streets, that they may be seen of men. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward. 6  But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut thy door, pray to thy Father which is in secret; and thy Father which seeth in secret shall reward thee openly. 7  But when ye pray, use not vain [*]repetitions, as the heathen do: for they think that they shall be heard for their much speaking. 8  Be not ye therefore like unto them: for your Father knoweth what things ye have need of, before ye ask him. 9  After this manner therefore pray ye: [*]Our Father which art in heaven, Hallowed be thy name. 10  Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven. 11  Give us this day our daily bread. 12  And forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors. 13  And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil: For thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, for ever. Amen. 14 [*] For if ye forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you: 15  But if ye forgive not men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.

16 ¶ Moreover when ye fast, be not, as the hypocrites, of a sad countenance: for they disfigure their faces, that they may appear unto men to fast. Verily I say unto you, They have their reward. 17  But thou, when thou fastest, anoint thine head, and wash thy face; 18  That thou appear not unto men to fast, but unto thy Father which is in secret: and thy Father, which seeth in secret, shall reward thee openly.

19 ¶ Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and rust doth corrupt, and where thieves break through and steal: 20 [*] But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust doth corrupt, and where thieves do not break through nor steal: 21  For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also. 22 [*] The light of the body is the eye: if therefore thine eye be single, thy whole body shall be full of light. 23  But if thine eye be evil, thy whole body shall be full of darkness. If therefore the light that is in thee be darkness, how great is that darkness!

24 ¶ [*]No man can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon. 25  Therefore I say unto you, [*]Take no thought for your life, what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink; nor yet for your body, what ye shall put on. Is not the life more than meat, and the body than raiment? 26  Behold the fowls of the air: for they sow not, neither do they reap, nor gather into barns; yet your heavenly Father feedeth them. Are ye not much better than they? 27  Which of you by taking thought can add one cubit unto his stature? 28  And why take ye thought for raiment? Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow; they toil not, neither do they spin: 29  And yet I say unto you, That even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these. 30  Wherefore, if God so clothe the grass of the field, which to day is, and to morrow is cast into the oven, shall he not much more clothe you, O ye of little faith? 31  Therefore take no thought, saying, What shall we eat? or, What shall we drink? or, Wherewithal shall we be clothed? 32  (For after all these things do the Gentiles seek:) for your heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all these things. 33  But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness; and all these things shall be added unto you. 34  Take therefore no thought for the morrow: for the morrow shall take thought for the things of itself. Sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof.

7

1  Judge [*]not, that ye be not judged. 2  For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged: [*]and with what measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you again. 3 [*] And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother’s eye, but considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye? 4  Or how wilt thou say to thy brother, Let me pull out the mote out of thine eye; and, behold, a beam is in thine own eye? 5  Thou hypocrite, first cast out the beam out of thine own eye; and then shalt thou see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother’s eye.

6 ¶ Give not that which is holy unto the dogs, neither cast ye your pearls before swine, lest they trample them under their feet, and turn again and rend you.

7 ¶ [*]Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you: 8  For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth; and to him that knocketh it shall be opened. 9  Or what man is there of you, whom if his son ask bread, will he give him a stone? 10  Or if he ask a fish, will he give him a serpent? 11  If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your children, how much more shall your Father which is in heaven give good things to them that ask him? 12  Therefore all things [*]whatsoever ye would that men should do to you, do ye even so to them: for this is the law and the prophets.

13 ¶ [*]Enter ye in at the strait gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction, and many there be which go in thereat: 14 [∥] Because strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.

15 ¶ Beware of false prophets, which come to you in sheep’s clothing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves. 16  Ye shall know them by their fruits. [*]Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles? 17  Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit; but a corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit. 18  A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit. 19 [*] Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire. 20  Wherefore by their fruits ye shall know them.

21 ¶ Not every one that saith unto me, [*]Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of my Father which is in heaven. 22  Many will say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in thy name? and in thy name have cast out devils? and in thy name done many wonderful works? 23  And then will I profess unto them, [*]I never knew you: [*]depart from me, ye that work iniquity.

24 ¶ Therefore [*]whosoever heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them, I will liken him unto a wise man, which built his house upon a rock: 25  And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; and it fell not: for it was founded upon a rock. 26  And every one that heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them not, shall be likened unto a foolish man, which built his house upon the sand: 27  And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; and it fell: and great was the fall of it. 28  And it came to pass, when Jesus had ended these sayings, [*]the people were astonished at his doctrine: 29  For he taught them as one having authority, and not as the scribes.

8

1  When he was come down from the mountain, great multitudes followed him. 2 [*] And, behold, there came a leper and worshipped him, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean. 3  And Jesus put forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will; be thou clean. And immediately his leprosy was cleansed. 4  And Jesus saith unto him, See thou tell no man; but go thy way, shew thyself to the priest, and offer the gift that [*]Moses commanded, for a testimony unto them.

5 ¶ [*]And when Jesus was entered into Capernaum, there came unto him a centurion, beseeching him, 6  And saying, Lord, my servant lieth at home sick of the palsy, grievously tormented. 7  And Jesus saith unto him, I will come and heal him. 8  The centurion answered and said, Lord, I am not worthy that thou shouldest come under my roof: but speak the word only, and my servant shall be healed. 9  For I am a man under authority, having soldiers under me: and I say to this man, Go, and he goeth; and to another, Come, and he cometh; and to my servant, Do this, and he doeth it. 10  When Jesus heard it, he marvelled, and said to them that followed, Verily I say unto you, I have not found so great faith, no, not in Israel. 11  And I say unto you, That many shall come from the east and west, and shall sit down with Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, in the kingdom of heaven. 12  But the children of the kingdom shall be cast out into outer darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. 13  And Jesus said unto the centurion, Go thy way; and as thou hast believed, so be it done unto thee. And his servant was healed in the selfsame hour.

14 ¶ [*]And when Jesus was come into Peter’s house, he saw his wife’s mother laid, and sick of a fever. 15  And he touched her hand, and the fever left her: and she arose, and ministered unto them.

16 ¶ [*]When the even was come, they brought unto him many that were possessed with devils: and he cast out the spirits with his word, and healed all that were sick: 17  That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Esaias the prophet, saying, [*]Himself took our infirmities, and bare our sicknesses.

18 ¶ Now when Jesus saw great multitudes about him, he gave commandment to depart unto the other side. 19 [*] And a certain scribe came, and said unto him, Master, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest. 20  And Jesus saith unto him, The foxes have holes, and the birds of the air have nests; but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head. 21  And another of his disciples said unto him, Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father. 22  But Jesus said unto him, Follow me; and let the dead bury their dead.

23 ¶ And when he was entered into a ship, his disciples followed him. 24 [*] And, behold, there arose a great tempest in the sea, insomuch that the ship was covered with the waves: but he was asleep. 25  And his disciples came to him, and awoke him, saying, Lord, save us: we perish. 26  And he saith unto them, Why are ye fearful, O ye of little faith? Then he arose, and rebuked the winds and the sea; and there was a great calm. 27  But the men marvelled, saying, What manner of man is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him!

28 ¶ [*]And when he was come to the other side into the country of the Gergesenes, there met him two possessed with devils, coming out of the tombs, exceeding fierce, so that no man might pass by that way. 29  And, behold, they cried out, saying, What have we to do with thee, Jesus, thou Son of God? art thou come hither to torment us before the time? 30  And there was a good way off from them an herd of many swine feeding. 31  So the devils besought him, saying, If thou cast us out, suffer us to go away into the herd of swine. 32  And he said unto them, Go. And when they were come out, they went into the herd of swine: and, behold, the whole herd of swine ran violently down a steep place into the sea, and perished in the waters. 33  And they that kept them fled, and went their ways into the city, and told every thing, and what was befallen to the possessed of the devils. 34  And, behold, the whole city came out to meet Jesus: and when they saw him, they besought him that he would depart out of their coasts.

9

1  And he entered into a ship, and passed over, and came into his own city. 2 [*] And, behold, they brought to him a man sick of the palsy, lying on a bed: and Jesus seeing their faith said unto the sick of the palsy; Son, be of good cheer; thy sins be forgiven thee. 3  And, behold, certain of the scribes said within themselves, This man blasphemeth. 4  And Jesus knowing their thoughts said, Wherefore think ye evil in your hearts? 5  For whether is easier, to say, Thy sins be forgiven thee; or to say, Arise, and walk? 6  But that ye may know that the Son of man hath power on earth to forgive sins, (then saith he to the sick of the palsy,) Arise, take up thy bed, and go unto thine house. 7  And he arose, and departed to his house. 8  But when the multitudes saw it, they marvelled, and glorified God, which had given such power unto men.

9 ¶ [*]And as Jesus passed forth from thence, he saw a man, named Matthew, sitting at the receipt of custom: and he saith unto him, Follow me. And he arose, and followed him.

10 ¶ And it came to pass, as Jesus sat at meat in the house, behold, many publicans and sinners came and sat down with him and his disciples. 11  And when the Pharisees saw it, they said unto his disciples, Why eateth your Master with publicans and sinners? 12  But when Jesus heard that, he said unto them, They that be whole need not a physician, but they that are sick. 13  But go ye and learn what that meaneth, [*]I will have mercy, and not sacrifice: for I am not come to call the righteous, [*]but sinners to repentance.

14 ¶ Then came to him the disciples of John, saying, [*]Why do we and the Pharisees fast oft, but thy disciples fast not? 15  And Jesus said unto them, Can the children of the bridechamber mourn, as long as the bridegroom is with them? but the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken from them, and then shall they fast. 16  No man putteth a piece of [∥]new cloth unto an old garment, for that which is put in to fill it up taketh from the garment, and the rent is made worse. 17  Neither do men put new wine into old bottles: else the bottles break, and the wine runneth out, and the bottles perish: but they put new wine into new bottles, and both are preserved.

18 ¶ [*]While he spake these things unto them, behold, there came a certain ruler, and worshipped him, saying, My daughter is even now dead: but come and lay thy hand upon her, and she shall live. 19  And Jesus arose, and followed him, and so did his disciples.

20 ¶ And, behold, a woman, which was diseased with an issue of blood twelve years, came behind him, and touched the hem of his garment: 21  For she said within herself, If I may but touch his garment, I shall be whole. 22  But Jesus turned him about, and when he saw her, he said, Daughter, be of good comfort; thy faith hath made thee whole. And the woman was made whole from that hour. 23  And when Jesus came into the ruler’s house, and saw the minstrels and the people making a noise, 24  He said unto them, Give place: for the maid is not dead, but sleepeth. And they laughed him to scorn. 25  But when the people were put forth, he went in, and took her by the hand, and the maid arose. 26  And [∥]the fame hereof went abroad into all that land.

27 ¶ And when Jesus departed thence, two blind men followed him, crying, and saying, Thou Son of David, have mercy on us. 28  And when he was come into the house, the blind men came to him: and Jesus saith unto them, Believe ye that I am able to do this? They said unto him, Yea, Lord. 29  Then touched he their eyes, saying, According to your faith be it unto you. 30  And their eyes were opened; and Jesus straitly charged them, saying, See that no man know it. 31  But they, when they were departed, spread abroad his fame in all that country.

32 ¶ [*]As they went out, behold, they brought to him a dumb man possessed with a devil. 33  And when the devil was cast out, the dumb spake: and the multitudes marvelled, saying, It was never so seen in Israel. 34  But the Pharisees said, [*]He casteth [‡]out devils through the prince of the devils. 35 [*] And Jesus went about all the cities and villages, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing every sickness and every disease among the people.

36 ¶ [*]But when he saw the multitudes, he was moved with compassion on them, because they [∥]fainted, and were scattered abroad, [*]as sheep having no shepherd. 37  Then saith he unto his disciples, [*]The harvest truly is plenteous, but the labourers are few; 38  Pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he will send forth labourers into his harvest.

10

1  And [*]when he had called unto him his twelve disciples, he gave them power [∥]against unclean spirits, to cast them out, and to heal all manner of sickness and all manner of disease. 2  Now the names of the twelve apostles are these; The first, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother; James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother; 3  Philip, and Bartholomew; Thomas, and Matthew the publican; James the son of Alphaeus, and Lebbaeus, whose surname was Thaddaeus; 4  Simon the Canaanite, and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him. 5  These twelve Jesus sent forth, and commanded them, saying, Go not into the way of the Gentiles, and into any city of the Samaritans enter ye not: 6 [*] But go rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. 7  And as ye go, preach, saying, [*]The kingdom of heaven is at hand. 8  Heal the sick, cleanse the lepers, raise the dead, cast out devils: freely ye have received, freely give. 9 [*][∥] Provide neither gold, nor silver, nor brass in your purses, 10  Nor scrip for your journey, neither two coats, neither shoes, nor yet staves: [*]for the workman is worthy of his meat. 11 [*] And into whatsoever city or town ye shall enter, enquire who in it is worthy; and there abide till ye go thence. 12  And when ye come into an house, salute it. 13  And if the house be worthy, let your peace come upon it: but if it be not worthy, let your peace return to you. 14 [*] And whosoever shall not receive you, nor hear your words, when ye depart out of that house or city, [*]shake off the dust of your feet. 15  Verily I say unto you, It shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrha in the day of judgment, than for that city.

16 ¶ [*]Behold, I send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves: be ye therefore wise as serpents, and [∥]harmless as doves. 17  But beware of men: for they will deliver you up to the councils, and they will scourge you in their synagogues; 18  And ye shall be brought before governors and kings for my sake, for a testimony against them and the Gentiles. 19 [*] But when they deliver you up, take no thought how or what ye shall speak: for it shall be given you in that same hour what ye shall speak. 20  For it is not ye that speak, but the Spirit of your Father which speaketh in you. 21 [*] And the brother shall deliver up the brother to death, and the father the child: and the children shall rise up against their parents, and cause them to be put to death. 22  And ye shall be hated of all men for my name’s sake: [*]but he that endureth to the end shall be saved. 23  But when they persecute you in this city, flee ye into another: for verily I say unto you, Ye shall not [∥]have gone over the cities of Israel, till the Son of man be come. 24 [*] The disciple is not above his master, nor the servant above his lord. 25  It is enough for the disciple that he be as his master, and the servant as his lord. If they have called the master of the house Beelzebub, how much more shall they call them of his household? 26  Fear them not therefore: [*]for there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; and hid, that shall not be known. 27  What I tell you in darkness, that speak ye in light: and what ye hear in the ear, that preach ye upon the housetops. 28 [*] And fear not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the soul: but rather fear him which is able to destroy both soul and body in hell. 29  Are not two sparrows sold for a [∥]farthing? and one of them shall not fall on the ground without your Father. 30 [*] But the very hairs of your head are all numbered. 31  Fear ye not therefore, ye are of more value than many sparrows. 32 [*] Whosoever therefore shall confess me before men, him will I confess also before my Father which is in heaven. 33 [*] But whosoever shall deny me before men, him will I also deny before my Father which is in heaven. 34 [*] Think not that I am come to send peace on earth: I came not to send peace, but a sword. 35  For I am come to set a man at variance [*]against his father, and the daughter against her mother, and the daughter in law against her mother in law. 36  And a man’s foes shall be they of his own household. 37 [*] He that loveth father or mother more than me is not worthy of me: and he that loveth son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me. 38 [*] And he that taketh not his cross, and followeth after me, is not worthy of me. 39 [*] He that findeth his life shall lose it: and he that loseth his life for my sake shall find it.

40 ¶ [*]He that receiveth you receiveth me, and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me. 41  He that receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet shall receive a prophet’s reward; and he that receiveth a righteous man in the name of a righteous man shall receive a righteous man’s reward. 42 [*] And whosoever shall give to drink unto one of these little ones a cup of cold water only in the name of a disciple, verily I say unto you, he shall in no wise lose his reward.

11

1  And it came to pass, when Jesus had made an end of commanding his twelve disciples, he departed thence to teach and to preach in their cities. 2 [*] Now when John had heard in the prison the works of Christ, he sent two of his disciples, 3  And said unto him, Art thou he that should come, or do we look for another? 4  Jesus answered and said unto them, Go and shew John again those things which ye do hear and see: 5 [*] The blind receive their sight, and the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, and the deaf hear, the dead are raised up, and [*]the poor have the gospel preached to them. 6  And blessed is he, whosoever shall not be offended in me.

7 ¶ And as they departed, Jesus began to say unto the multitudes concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness to see? A reed shaken with the wind? 8  But what went ye out for to see? A man clothed in soft raiment? behold, they that wear soft clothing are in kings’ houses. 9  But what went ye out for to see? A prophet? yea, I say unto you, and more than a prophet. 10  For this is he, of whom it is written, [*]Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, which shall prepare thy way before thee. 11  Verily I say unto you, Among them that are born of women there hath not risen a greater than John the Baptist: notwithstanding he that is least in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he. 12 [*] And from the days of John the Baptist until now the kingdom of heaven [∥]suffereth violence, and the violent take it by force. 13  For all the prophets and the law prophesied until John. 14  And if ye will receive it, this is [*]Elias, which was for to come. 15  He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.

16 ¶ [*]But whereunto shall I liken this generation? It is like unto children sitting in the markets, and calling unto their fellows, 17  And saying, We have piped unto you, and ye have not danced; we have mourned unto you, and ye have not lamented. 18  For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, He hath a devil. 19  The Son of man came eating and drinking, and they say, Behold a man gluttonous, and a winebibber, a friend of publicans and sinners. But wisdom is justified of her children.

20 ¶ [*]Then began he to upbraid the cities wherein most of his mighty works were done, because they repented not: 21  Woe unto thee, Chorazin! woe unto thee, Bethsaida! for if the mighty works, which were done in you, had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes. 22  But I say unto you, It shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon at the day of judgment, than for you. 23  And thou, Capernaum, which art exalted unto heaven, shalt be brought down to hell: for if the mighty works, which have been done in thee, had been done in Sodom, it would have remained until this day. 24  But I say unto you, That it shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom in the day of judgment, than for thee.

25 ¶ [*]At that time Jesus answered and said, I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes. 26  Even so, Father: for so it seemed good in thy sight. 27 [*] All things are delivered unto me of my Father: and no man knoweth the Son, but the Father; [*]neither knoweth any man the Father, save the Son, and he to whomsoever the Son will reveal him.

28 ¶ Come unto me, all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest. 29  Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: [*]and ye shall find rest unto your souls. 30 [*] For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.

12

1  At that time [*]Jesus went on the sabbath day through the corn; and his disciples were an hungred, and began to pluck the ears of corn, and to eat. 2  But when the Pharisees saw it, they said unto him, Behold, thy disciples do that which is not lawful to do upon the sabbath day. 3  But he said unto them, Have ye not read [*]what David did, when he was an hungred, and they that were with him; 4  How he entered into the house of God, and did eat the shewbread, which was not lawful for him to eat, neither for them which were with him, [*]but only for the priests? 5  Or have ye not read in the [*]law, how that on the sabbath days the priests in the temple profane the sabbath, and are blameless? 6  But I say unto you, That in this place is one greater than the temple. 7  But if ye had known what this meaneth, [*]I will have mercy, and not sacrifice, ye would not have condemned the guiltless. 8  For the Son of man is Lord even of the sabbath day. 9 [*] And when he was departed thence, he went into their synagogue:

10 ¶ And, behold, there was a man which had his hand withered. And they asked him, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath days? that they might accuse him. 11  And he said unto them, What man shall there be among you, that shall have one sheep, and if it fall into a pit on the sabbath day, will he not lay hold on it, and lift it out? 12  How much then is a man better than a sheep? Wherefore it is lawful to do well on the sabbath days. 13  Then saith he to the man, Stretch forth thine hand. And he stretched it forth; and it was restored whole, like as the other.

14 ¶ Then the Pharisees went out, and [∥]held a council against him, how they might destroy him. 15  But when Jesus knew it, he withdrew himself from thence: and great multitudes followed him, and he healed them all; 16  And charged them that they should not make him known: 17  That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Esaias the prophet, saying, 18 [*] Behold my servant, whom I have chosen; my beloved, in whom my soul is well pleased: I will put my spirit upon him, and he shall shew judgment to the Gentiles. 19  He shall not strive, nor cry; neither shall any man hear his voice in the streets. 20  A bruised reed shall he not break, and smoking flax shall he not quench, till he send forth judgment unto victory. 21  And in his name shall the Gentiles trust.

22 ¶ [*]Then was brought unto him one possessed with a devil, blind, and dumb: and he healed him, insomuch that the blind and dumb both spake and saw. 23  And all the people were amazed, and said, [‡]Is not this the son of David? 24 [*] But when the Pharisees heard it, they said, This fellow doth not cast out devils, but by Beelzebub the prince of the devils. 25  And Jesus knew their thoughts, and said unto them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation; and every city or house divided against itself shall not stand: 26  And if Satan cast out Satan, he is divided against himself; how shall then his kingdom stand? 27  And if I by Beelzebub cast out devils, by whom do your children cast them out? therefore they shall be your judges. 28  But if I cast out devils by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God is come unto you. 29  Or else how can one enter into a strong man’s house, and spoil his goods, except he first bind the strong man? and then he will spoil his house. 30  He that is not with me is against me; and he that gathereth not with me scattereth abroad.

31 ¶ Wherefore I say unto you, [*]All manner of sin and blasphemy shall be forgiven unto men: but the blasphemy against the Holy Ghost shall not be forgiven unto men. 32  And whosoever speaketh a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him: but whosoever speaketh against the Holy Ghost, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this world, neither in the world to come. 33  Either make the tree good, and his fruit good; or else make the tree corrupt, and his fruit corrupt: for the tree is known by his fruit. 34  O generation of vipers, how can ye, being evil, speak good things? [*]for out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh. 35  A good man out of the good treasure of the heart bringeth forth good things: and an evil man out of the evil treasure bringeth forth evil things. 36  But I say unto you, That every idle word that men shall speak, they shall give account thereof in the day of judgment. 37  For by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned.

38 ¶ [*]Then certain of the scribes and of the Pharisees answered, saying, Master, we would see a sign from thee. 39  But he answered and said unto them, An evil and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign; and there shall no sign be given to it, but the sign of the prophet Jonas: 40 [*] For as Jonas was three days and three nights in the whale’s belly; so shall the Son of man be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth. 41  The men of Nineveh shall rise in judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: [*]because they repented at the preaching of Jonas; and, behold, a greater than Jonas is here. 42 [*] The queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for she came from the uttermost parts of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and, behold, a greater than Solomon is here. 43 [*] When the unclean spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through dry places, seeking rest, and findeth none. 44  Then he saith, I will return into my house from whence I came out; and when he is come, he findeth it empty, swept, and garnished. 45  Then goeth he, and taketh with himself seven other spirits more wicked than himself, and they enter in and dwell there: [*]and the last state of that man is worse than the first. Even so shall it be also unto this wicked generation.

46 ¶ While he yet talked to the people, [*]behold, his mother and his brethren stood without, desiring to speak with him. 47  Then one said unto him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren stand without, desiring to speak with thee. 48  But he answered and said unto him that told him, Who is my mother? and who are my brethren? 49  And he stretched forth his hand toward his disciples, and said, Behold my mother and my brethren! 50  For whosoever shall do the will of my Father which is in heaven, the same is my brother, and sister, and mother.

13

1  The same day went Jesus out of the house, [*]and sat by the sea side. 2  And great multitudes were gathered together unto him, so that he went into a ship, and sat; and the whole multitude stood on the shore. 3  And he spake many things unto them in parables, saying, [*]Behold, a sower went forth to sow; 4  And when he sowed, some seeds fell by the way side, and the fowls came and devoured them up: 5  Some fell upon stony places, where they had not much earth: and forthwith they sprung up, because they had no deepness of earth: 6  And when the sun was up, they were scorched; and because they [‡]had no root, they withered away. 7  And some fell among thorns; and the thorns sprung up, and choked them: 8  But other fell into good ground, and brought forth fruit, some an hundredfold, some sixtyfold, some thirtyfold. 9  Who hath ears to hear, let him hear. 10  And the disciples came, and said unto him, Why speakest thou unto them in parables? 11  He answered and said unto them, Because it is given unto you to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to them it is not given. 12 [*] For whosoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have more abundance: but whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that he hath. 13  Therefore speak I to them in parables: because they seeing see not; and hearing they hear not, neither do they understand. 14  And in them is fulfilled the prophecy of Esaias, which saith, [*]By hearing ye shall hear, and shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and shall not perceive: 15  For this people’s heart is waxed gross, and their ears are dull of hearing, and their eyes they have closed; lest at any time they should see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and should understand with their heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them. 16  But blessed are your eyes, for they see: and your ears, for they hear. 17  For verily I say unto you, [*]That many prophets and righteous men have desired to see those things which ye see, and have not seen them; and to hear those things which ye hear, and have not heard them.

18 ¶ Hear ye therefore the parable of the sower. 19  When any one heareth the word of the kingdom, and understandeth it not, then cometh the wicked one, and catcheth away that which was sown in his heart. This is he which received seed by the way side. 20  But he that received the seed into stony places, the same is he that heareth the word, and anon with joy receiveth it; 21  Yet hath he not root in himself, but dureth for a while: for when tribulation or persecution ariseth because of the word, by and by he is offended. 22  He also that received seed among the thorns is he that heareth the word; and the care of this world, and the deceitfulness of riches, choke the word, and he becometh unfruitful. 23  But he that received seed into the good ground is he that heareth the word, and understandeth it; which also beareth fruit, and bringeth forth, some an hundredfold, some sixty, some thirty.

24 ¶ Another parable put he forth unto them, saying, The kingdom of heaven is likened unto a man which sowed good seed in his field: 25  But while men slept, his enemy came and sowed tares among the wheat, and went his way. 26  But when the blade was sprung up, and brought forth fruit, then appeared the tares also. 27  So the servants of the householder came and said unto him, Sir, didst not thou sow good seed in thy field? from whence then hath it tares? 28  He said unto them, An enemy hath done this. The servants said unto him, Wilt thou then that we go and gather them up? 29  But he said, Nay; lest while ye gather up the tares, ye root up also the wheat with them. 30  Let both grow together until the harvest: and in the time of harvest I will say to the reapers, Gather ye together first the tares, and bind them in bundles to burn them: but gather the wheat into my barn.

31 ¶ Another parable put he forth unto them, saying, [*]The kingdom of heaven is like to a grain of mustard seed, which a man took, and sowed in his field: 32  Which indeed is the least of all seeds: but when it is grown, it is the greatest among herbs, and becometh a tree, so that the birds of the air come and lodge in the branches thereof.

33 ¶ [*]Another parable spake he unto them; The kingdom of heaven is like unto leaven, which a woman took, and hid in three [†]measures of meal, till the whole was leavened. 34 [*] All these things spake Jesus unto the multitude in parables; and without a parable spake he not unto them: 35  That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, saying, [*]I will open my mouth in parables; I will utter things which have been kept secret from the foundation of the world. 36  Then Jesus sent the multitude away, and went into the house: and his disciples came unto him, saying, Declare unto us the parable of the tares of the field. 37  He answered and said unto them, He that soweth the good seed is the Son of man; 38  The field is the world; the good seed are the children of the kingdom; but the tares are the children of the wicked one; 39  The enemy that sowed them is the devil; [*]the harvest is the end of the world; and the reapers are the angels. 40  As therefore the tares are gathered and burned in the fire; so shall it be in the end of this world. 41  The Son of man shall send forth his angels, and they shall gather out of his kingdom all [∥]things that offend, and them which do iniquity; 42  And shall cast them into a furnace of fire: there shall be wailing and gnashing of teeth. 43 [*] Then shall the righteous shine forth as the sun in the kingdom of their Father. Who hath ears to hear, let him hear.

44 ¶ Again, the kingdom of heaven is like unto treasure hid in a field; the which when a man hath found, he hideth, and for joy thereof goeth and selleth all that he hath, and buyeth that field.

45 ¶ Again, the kingdom of heaven is like unto a merchant man, seeking goodly pearls: 46  Who, when he had found one pearl of great price, [‡]went and sold all that he had, and bought it.

47 ¶ Again, the kingdom of heaven is like unto a net, that was cast into the sea, and gathered of every kind: 48  Which, when it was full, they drew to shore, and sat down, and gathered the good into vessels, but cast the bad away. 49  So shall it be at the end of the world: the angels shall come forth, and sever the wicked from among the just, 50  And shall cast them into the furnace of fire: there shall be wailing and gnashing of teeth. 51  Jesus saith unto them, Have ye understood all these things? They say unto him, Yea, Lord. 52  Then said he unto them, Therefore every scribe which is instructed unto the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man that is an householder, which bringeth forth out of his treasure things new and old.

53 ¶ And it came to pass, that when Jesus had finished these parables, he departed thence. 54 [*] And when he was come into his own country, he taught them in their synagogue, insomuch that they were astonished, and said, Whence hath this man this wisdom, and these mighty works? 55 [*] Is not this the carpenter’s son? is not his mother called Mary? and his brethren, James, and Joses, and Simon, and Judas? 56  And his sisters, are they not all with us? Whence then hath this man all these things? 57  And they were offended in him. But Jesus said unto them, [*]A prophet is not without honour, save in his own country, and in his own house. 58  And he did not many mighty works there because of their unbelief.

14

1  At that time [*]Herod the tetrarch heard of the fame of Jesus, 2  And said unto his servants, This is John the Baptist; he is risen from the dead; and therefore mighty works [∥]do shew forth themselves in him.

3 ¶ [*]For Herod had laid hold on John, and bound him, and put him in prison for Herodias’ sake, his brother Philip’s wife. 4  For John said unto him, [*]It is not lawful for thee to have her. 5  And when he would have put him to death, he feared the multitude, [*]because they counted him as a prophet. 6  But when Herod’s birthday was kept, the daughter of Herodias danced before them, and pleased Herod. 7  Whereupon he promised with an oath to give her whatsoever she would ask. 8  And she, being before instructed of her mother, said, Give me here John Baptist’s head in a charger. 9  And the king was sorry: nevertheless for the oath’s sake, and them which sat with him at meat, he commanded it to be given her. 10  And he sent, and beheaded John in the prison. 11  And his head was brought in a charger, and given to the damsel: and she brought it to her mother. 12  And his disciples came, and took up the body, and buried it, and went and told Jesus.

13 ¶ [*]When Jesus heard of it, he departed thence by ship into a desert place apart: and when the people had heard thereof, they followed him on foot out of the cities. 14  And Jesus went forth, and saw a great multitude, and was moved with compassion toward them, and he healed their sick.

15 ¶ [*]And when it was evening, his disciples came to him, saying, This is a desert place, and the time is now past; send the multitude away, that they may go into the villages, and buy themselves victuals. 16  But Jesus said unto them, They need not depart; give ye them to eat. 17  And they say unto him, We have here but five loaves, and two fishes. 18  He said, Bring them hither to me. 19  And he commanded the multitude to sit down on the grass, and took the five loaves, and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, he blessed, and brake, and gave the loaves to his disciples, and the disciples to the multitude. 20  And they did all eat, and were filled: and they took up of the fragments that remained twelve baskets full. 21  And they that had eaten were about five thousand men, beside women and children.

22 ¶ And straightway Jesus constrained his disciples to get into a ship, and to go before him unto the other side, while he sent the multitudes away. 23 [*] And when he had sent the multitudes away, he went up into a mountain apart to pray: [*]and when the evening was come, he was there alone. 24  But the ship was now in the midst of the sea, tossed with waves: for the wind was contrary. 25  And in the fourth watch of the night Jesus went unto them, walking on the sea. 26  And when the disciples saw him walking on the sea, they were troubled, saying, It is a spirit; and they cried out for fear. 27  But straightway Jesus spake unto them, saying, Be of good cheer; it is I; be not afraid. 28  And Peter answered him and said, Lord, if it be thou, bid me come unto thee on the water. 29  And he said, Come. And when Peter was come down out of the ship, he walked on the water, to go to Jesus. 30  But when he saw the wind [∥]boisterous, he was afraid; and beginning to sink, he cried, saying, Lord, save me. 31  And immediately Jesus stretched forth his hand, and caught him, and said unto him, O thou of little faith, wherefore didst thou doubt? 32  And when they were come into the ship, the wind ceased. 33  Then they that were in the ship came and worshipped him, saying, Of a truth thou art the Son of God.

34 ¶ [*]And when they were gone over, they came into the land of Gennesaret. 35  And when the men of that place had knowledge of him, they sent out into all that country round about, and brought unto him all that were diseased; 36  And besought him that they might only touch the hem of his garment: and as many as touched were made perfectly whole.

15

1  Then [*]came to Jesus scribes and Pharisees, which were of Jerusalem, saying, 2  Why do thy disciples transgress the tradition of the elders? for they wash not their hands when they eat bread. 3  But he answered and said unto them, Why do ye also transgress the commandment of God by your tradition? 4  For God commanded, saying, [*]Honour thy father and mother: and, [*]He that curseth father or mother, let him die the death. 5  But ye say, Whosoever shall say to his father or his mother, [*]It is a gift, by whatsoever thou mightest be profited by me; 6  And honour not his father or his mother, he shall be free. Thus have ye made the commandment of God of none effect by your tradition. 7  Ye hypocrites, well did Esaias prophesy of you, saying, 8 [*] This people draweth nigh unto me with their mouth, and honoureth me with their lips; but their heart is far from me. 9  But in vain they do worship me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men.

10 ¶ [*]And he called the multitude, and said unto them, Hear, and understand: 11  Not that which goeth into the mouth defileth a man; but that which cometh out of the mouth, this defileth a man. 12  Then came his disciples, and said unto him, Knowest thou that the Pharisees were offended, after they heard this saying? 13  But he answered and said, [*]Every plant, which my heavenly Father hath not planted, shall be rooted up. 14  Let them alone: [*]they be blind leaders of the blind. And if the blind lead the blind, both shall fall into the ditch. 15 [*] Then answered Peter and said unto him, Declare unto us this parable. 16  And Jesus said, Are ye also yet without understanding? 17  Do not ye yet understand, that whatsoever entereth in at the mouth goeth into the belly, and is cast out into the draught? 18  But those things which proceed out of the mouth come forth from the heart; and they defile the man. 19 [*] For out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false witness, blasphemies: 20  These are the things which defile a man: but to eat with unwashen hands defileth not a man.

21 ¶ [*]Then Jesus went thence, and departed into the coasts of Tyre and Sidon. 22  And, behold, a woman of Canaan came out of the same coasts, and cried unto him, saying, Have mercy on me, O Lord, thou Son of David; my daughter is grievously vexed with a devil. 23  But he answered her not a word. And his disciples came and besought him, saying, Send her away; for she crieth after us. 24  But he answered and said, [*]I am not sent but unto the lost sheep of the house of Israel. 25  Then came she and worshipped him, saying, Lord, help me. 26  But he answered and said, It is not meet to take the children’s bread, and to cast it to dogs. 27  And she said, Truth, Lord: yet the dogs eat of the crumbs which fall from their masters’ table. 28  Then Jesus answered and said unto her, O woman, great is thy faith: be it unto thee even as thou wilt. And her daughter was made whole from that very hour. 29 [*] And Jesus departed from thence, and came nigh unto the sea of Galilee; and went up into a mountain, and sat down there. 30 [*] And great multitudes came unto him, having with them those that were lame, blind, dumb, maimed, and many others, and cast them down at Jesus’ feet; and he healed them: 31  Insomuch that the multitude wondered, when they saw the dumb to speak, the maimed to be whole, the lame to walk, and the blind to see: and they glorified the God of Israel.

32 ¶ [*]Then Jesus called his disciples unto him, and said, I have compassion on the multitude, because they continue with me now three days, and have nothing to eat: and I will not send them away fasting, lest they faint in the way. 33  And his disciples say unto him, Whence should we have so much bread in the wilderness, as to fill so great a multitude? 34  And Jesus saith unto them, How many loaves have ye? And they said, Seven, and a few little fishes. 35  And he commanded the multitude to sit down on the ground. 36  And he took the seven loaves and the fishes, and gave thanks, and brake them, and gave to his disciples, and the disciples to the multitude. 37  And they did all eat, and were filled: and they took up of the broken meat that was left seven baskets full. 38  And they that did eat were four thousand men, beside women and children. 39  And he sent away the multitude, and took ship, and came into the coasts of Magdala.

16

1  The [*]Pharisees also with the Sadducees came, and tempting desired him that he would shew them a sign from heaven. 2  He answered and said unto them, When it is evening, ye say, It will be fair weather: for the sky is red. 3  And in the morning, It will be foul weather to day: for the sky is red and lowring. O ye hypocrites, ye can discern the face of the sky; but can ye not discern the signs of the times? 4  A wicked and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign; and there shall no sign be given unto it, but the sign of the prophet Jonas. And he left them, and departed. 5  And when his disciples were come to the other side, they had forgotten to take bread.

6 ¶ Then Jesus said unto them, Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees. 7  And they reasoned among themselves, saying, It is because we have taken no bread. 8  Which when Jesus perceived, he said unto them, O ye of little faith, why reason ye among yourselves, because ye have brought no bread? 9 [*] Do ye not yet understand, neither remember the five loaves of the five thousand, and how many baskets ye took up? 10 [*] Neither the seven loaves of the four thousand, and how many baskets ye took up? 11  How is it that ye do not understand that I spake it not to you concerning bread, that ye should beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees? 12  Then understood they how that he bade them not beware of the leaven of bread, but of the doctrine of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees.

13 ¶ When Jesus came into the coasts of Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, saying, [*]Whom do men say that I the Son of man am? 14  And they said, Some say that thou art John the Baptist: some, Elias; and others, Jeremias, or one of the prophets. 15  He saith unto them, But whom say ye that I am? 16  And Simon Peter answered and said, [*]Thou [‡]art the Christ, the Son of the living God. 17  And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-jona: for flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven. 18  And I say also unto thee, That [*]thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church; and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it. 19 [*] And I will give unto thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven: [‡]and whatsoever thou shalt bind on earth shall be bound in heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. 20  Then charged he his disciples that they should tell no man that he was Jesus the Christ.

21 ¶ From that time forth began Jesus to shew unto his disciples, how that he must go unto Jerusalem, and suffer many things of the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and be raised again the third day. 22  Then Peter took him, and began to rebuke him, saying, Be it far from thee, Lord: this shall not be unto thee. 23  But he turned, and said unto Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan: thou art an offence unto me: for thou savourest not the things that be of God, but those that be of men.

24 ¶ [*]Then said Jesus unto his disciples, If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me. 25  For whosoever will save his life shall lose it: and whosoever will lose his life for my sake shall find it. 26  For what is a man profited, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul? or what shall a man give in exchange for his soul? 27  For the Son of man shall come in the glory of his Father with his angels; [*]and then he shall reward every man according to his works. 28  Verily I say unto you, [*]There be some standing here, which shall not taste of death, till they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom.

17

1  And [*]after six days Jesus taketh Peter, James, and John his brother, and bringeth them up into an high mountain apart, 2  And was transfigured before them: and his face did shine as the sun, and his raiment was white as the light. 3  And, behold, there appeared unto them Moses and Elias talking with him. 4  Then answered Peter, and said unto Jesus, Lord, it is good for us to be here: if thou wilt, let us make here three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias. 5 [*] While he yet spake, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them: and behold a voice out of the cloud, which said, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased; hear ye him. 6  And when the disciples heard it, they fell on their face, and were sore afraid. 7  And Jesus came and touched them, and said, Arise, and be not afraid. 8  And when they had lifted up their eyes, they saw no man, save Jesus only. 9  And as they came down from the mountain, Jesus charged them, saying, Tell the vision to no man, until the Son of man be risen again from the dead. 10  And his disciples asked him, saying, [*]Why then say the scribes that Elias must first come? 11  And Jesus answered and said unto them, Elias truly shall first come, and restore all things. 12  But I say unto you, That Elias is come already, and they knew him not, but have done unto him whatsoever they listed. Likewise shall also the Son of man suffer of them. 13  Then the disciples understood that he spake unto them of John the Baptist.

14 ¶ [*]And when they were come to the multitude, there came to him a certain man, kneeling down to him, and saying, 15  Lord, have mercy on my son: for he is lunatick, and sore vexed: for ofttimes he falleth into the fire, and oft into the water. 16  And I brought him to thy disciples, and they could not cure him. 17  Then Jesus answered and said, O faithless and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you? how long shall I suffer you? bring him hither to me. 18  And Jesus rebuked the devil; and he departed out of him: and the child was cured from that very hour. 19  Then came the disciples to Jesus apart, and said, Why could not we cast him out? 20  And Jesus said unto them, Because of your unbelief: for verily I say unto you, [*]If ye have faith as a grain of mustard seed, ye shall say unto this mountain, Remove hence to yonder place; and it shall remove; and nothing shall be impossible unto you. 21  Howbeit this kind goeth not out but by prayer and fasting.

22 ¶ [*]And while they abode in Galilee, Jesus said unto them, The Son of man shall be betrayed into the hands of men: 23  And they shall kill him, and the third day he shall be raised again. And they were exceeding sorry.

24 ¶ And when they were come to Capernaum, they that received [∥]tribute money came to Peter, and said, Doth not your master pay tribute? 25  He saith, Yes. And when he was come into the house, Jesus prevented him, saying, What thinkest thou, Simon? of whom do the kings of the earth take custom or tribute? of their own children, or of strangers? 26  Peter saith unto him, Of strangers. Jesus saith unto him, Then are the children free. 27  Notwithstanding, lest we should offend them, go thou to the sea, and cast an hook, and take up the fish that first cometh up; and when thou hast opened his mouth, thou shalt find [∥]a piece of money: that take, and give unto them for me and thee.

18

1  At [*]the same time came the disciples unto Jesus, saying, Who is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven? 2  And Jesus called a little child unto him, and set him in the midst of them, 3  And said, Verily I say unto you, [*]Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven. 4  Whosoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, the same is greatest in the kingdom of heaven. 5  And whoso shall receive one such little child in my name receiveth me. 6 [*] But whoso shall offend one of these little ones which believe in me, it were better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the sea.

7 ¶ Woe unto the world because of offences! for it must needs be that offences come; but woe to that man by whom the offence cometh! 8 [*] Wherefore if thy hand or thy foot offend thee, cut them off, and cast them from thee: it is better for thee to enter into life halt or maimed, rather than having two hands or two feet to be cast into everlasting fire. 9  And if thine eye offend thee, pluck it out, and cast it from thee: it is better for thee to enter into life with one eye, rather than having two eyes to be cast into hell fire. 10  Take heed that ye despise not one of these little ones; for I say unto you, That in heaven their angels do always behold the face of my Father which is in heaven. 11 [*] For the Son of man is come to save that which was lost. 12 [*] How think ye? if a man have an hundred sheep, and one of them be gone astray, doth he not leave the ninety and nine, and goeth into the mountains, and seeketh that which is gone astray? 13  And if so be that he find it, verily I say unto you, he rejoiceth more of that sheep, than of the ninety and nine which went not astray. 14  Even so it is not the will of your Father which is in heaven, that one of these little ones should perish.

15 ¶ Moreover [*]if thy brother shall trespass against thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone: if he shall hear thee, thou hast gained thy brother. 16  But if he will not hear thee, then take with thee one or two more, that in [*]the mouth of two or three witnesses every word may be established. 17  And if he shall neglect to hear them, tell it unto the church: but if he neglect to hear the church, let him be unto thee as an [*]heathen man and a publican. 18  Verily I say unto you, [*]Whatsoever ye shall bind on earth shall be bound in heaven: and whatsoever ye shall loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. 19  Again I say unto you, That if two of you shall agree on earth as touching any thing that they shall ask, it shall be done for them of my Father which is in heaven. 20  For where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midst of them.

21 ¶ Then came Peter to him, and said, Lord, how oft shall my brother sin against me, and I forgive him? [*]till seven times? 22  Jesus saith unto him, I say not unto thee, Until seven times: but, Until seventy times seven.

23 ¶ Therefore is the kingdom of heaven likened unto a certain king, which would take account of his servants. 24  And when he had begun to reckon, one was brought unto him, which owed him ten thousand [∥]talents. 25  But forasmuch as he had not to pay, his lord commanded him to be sold, and his wife, and children, and all that he had, and payment to be made. 26  The servant therefore fell down, and [∥]worshipped him, saying, Lord, have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. 27  Then the lord of that servant was moved with compassion, and loosed him, and forgave him the debt. 28  But the same servant went out, and found one of his fellowservants, which owed him an hundred [∥]pence: and he laid hands on him, and took him by the throat, saying, Pay me that thou owest. 29  And his fellowservant fell down at his feet, and besought him, saying, Have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. 30  And he would not: but went and cast him into prison, till he should pay the debt. 31  So when his fellowservants saw what was done, they were very sorry, and came and told unto their lord all that was done. 32  Then his lord, after that he had called him, said unto him, O thou wicked servant, I forgave thee all that debt, because thou desiredst me: 33  Shouldest not thou also have had compassion on thy fellowservant, even as I had pity on thee? 34  And his lord was wroth, and delivered him to the tormentors, till he should pay all that was due unto him. 35  So likewise shall my heavenly Father do also unto you, if ye from your hearts forgive not every one his brother their trespasses.

19

1  And it came to pass, [*]that when Jesus had finished these sayings, he departed from Galilee, and came into the coasts of Judaea beyond Jordan; 2  And great multitudes followed him; and he healed them there.

3 ¶ The Pharisees also came unto him, tempting him, and saying unto him, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every cause? 4  And he answered and said unto them, Have ye not read, [*]that he which made them at the beginning made them male and female, 5  And said, [*]For this cause shall a man leave father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife: and [*]they twain shall be one flesh? 6  Wherefore they are no more twain, but one flesh. What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder. 7  They say unto him, [*]Why did Moses then command to give a writing of divorcement, and to put her away? 8  He saith unto them, Moses because of the hardness of your hearts suffered you to put away your wives: but from the beginning it was not so. 9 [*] And I say unto you, Whosoever shall put away his wife, except it be for fornication, and shall marry another, committeth adultery: and whoso marrieth her which is put away doth commit adultery.

10 ¶ His disciples say unto him, If the case of the man be so with his wife, it is not good to marry. 11  But he said unto them, All men cannot receive this saying, save they to whom it is given. 12  For there are some eunuchs, which were so born from their mother’s womb: and there are some eunuchs, which were made eunuchs of men: and there be eunuchs, which have made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven’s sake. He that is able to receive it, let him receive it.

13 ¶ [*]Then were there brought unto him little children, that he should put his hands on them, and pray: and the disciples rebuked them. 14  But Jesus said, Suffer little children, and forbid them not, to come unto me: for of such is the kingdom of heaven. 15  And he laid his hands on them, and departed thence.

16 ¶ [*]And, behold, one came and said unto him, Good Master, what good thing shall I do, that I may have eternal life? 17  And he said unto him, Why callest thou me good? there is none good but one, that is, God: but if thou wilt enter into life, keep the commandments. 18  He saith unto him, Which? Jesus said, [*]Thou shalt do no murder, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, 19  Honour thy father and thy mother: and, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. 20  The young man saith unto him, All these things have I kept from my youth up: what lack I yet? 21  Jesus said unto him, If thou wilt be perfect, go and sell that thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come and follow me. 22  But when the young man heard that saying, he went away sorrowful: for he had great possessions.

23 ¶ Then said Jesus unto his disciples, Verily I say unto you, That a rich man shall hardly enter into the kingdom of heaven. 24  And again I say unto you, It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. 25  When his disciples heard it, they were exceedingly amazed, saying, Who then can be saved? 26  But Jesus beheld them, and said unto them, With men this is impossible; but with God all things are possible.

27 ¶ [*]Then answered Peter and said unto him, Behold, we have forsaken all, and followed thee; what shall we have therefore? 28  And Jesus said unto them, Verily I say unto you, That ye which have followed me, in the regeneration when the Son of man shall sit in the throne of his glory, [*]ye also shall sit upon twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel. 29  And every one that hath forsaken houses, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my name’s sake, shall receive an hundredfold, and shall inherit everlasting life. 30 [*] But many that are first shall be last; and the last shall be first.

20

1  For the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man that is an householder, which went out early in the morning to hire labourers into his vineyard. 2  And when he had agreed with the labourers for a [∥]penny a day, he sent them into his vineyard. 3  And he went out about the third hour, and saw others standing idle in the marketplace, 4  And said unto them; Go ye also into the vineyard, and whatsoever is right I will give you. And they went their way. 5  Again he went out about the sixth and ninth hour, and did likewise. 6  And about the eleventh hour he went out, and found others standing idle, and saith unto them, Why stand ye here all the day idle? 7  They say unto him, Because no man hath hired us. He saith unto them, Go ye also into the vineyard; and whatsoever is right, that shall ye receive. 8  So when even was come, the lord of the vineyard saith unto his steward, Call the labourers, and give them their hire, beginning from the last unto the first. 9  And when they came that were hired about the eleventh hour, they received every man a penny. 10  But when the first came, they supposed that they should have received more; and they likewise received every man a penny. 11  And when they had received it, they murmured against the goodman of the house, 12  Saying, These last [∥]have wrought but one hour, and thou hast made them equal unto us, which have borne the burden and heat of the day. 13  But he answered one of them, and said, Friend, I do thee no wrong: didst not thou agree with me for a penny? 14  Take that thine is, and go thy way: I will give unto this last, even as unto thee. 15  Is it not lawful for me to do what I will with mine own? Is thine eye evil, because I am good? 16 [*] So the last shall be first, and the first last: for many be called, but few chosen.

17 ¶ [*]And Jesus going up to Jerusalem took the twelve disciples apart in the way, and said unto them, 18  Behold, we go up to Jerusalem; and the Son of man shall be betrayed unto the chief priests and unto the scribes, and they shall condemn him to death, 19 [*] And shall deliver him to the Gentiles to mock, and to scourge, and to crucify him: and the third day he shall rise again.

20 ¶ [*]Then came to him the mother of Zebedee’s children with her sons, worshipping him, and desiring a certain thing of him. 21  And he said unto her, What wilt thou? She saith unto him, Grant that these my two sons may sit, the one on thy right hand, and the other on the left, in thy kingdom. 22  But Jesus answered and said, Ye know not what ye ask. Are ye able to drink of the cup that I shall drink of, and to be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with? They say unto him, We are able. 23  And he saith unto them, Ye shall drink indeed of my cup, and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with: but to sit on my right hand, and on my left, is not mine to give, but it shall be given to them for whom it is prepared of my Father. 24  And when the ten heard it, they were moved with indignation against the two brethren. 25  But Jesus called them unto him, and said, [*]Ye know that the princes of the Gentiles exercise dominion over them, and they that are great exercise authority upon them. 26  But it shall not be so among you: but whosoever will be great among you, let him be your minister; 27  And whosoever will be chief among you, let him be your servant: 28  Even as the [*]Son of man came not to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many. 29 [*] And as they departed from Jericho, a great multitude followed him.

30 ¶ And, behold, two blind men sitting by the way side, when they heard that Jesus passed by, cried out, saying, Have mercy on us, O Lord, thou Son of David. 31  And the multitude rebuked them, because they should hold their peace: but they cried the more, saying, Have mercy on us, O Lord, thou Son of David. 32  And Jesus stood still, and called them, and said, What will ye that I shall do unto you? 33  They say unto him, Lord, that our eyes may be opened. 34  So Jesus had compassion on them, and touched their eyes: and immediately their eyes received sight, and they followed him.

21

1  And [*]when they drew nigh unto Jerusalem, and were come to Bethphage, unto the mount of Olives, then sent Jesus two disciples, 2  Saying unto them, Go into the village over against you, and straightway ye shall find an ass tied, and a colt with her: loose them, and bring them unto me. 3  And if any man say ought unto you, ye shall say, The Lord hath need of them; and straightway he will send them. 4  All this was done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, saying, 5 [*] Tell ye the daughter of Sion, Behold, thy King cometh unto thee, meek, and sitting upon an ass, and a colt the foal of an ass. 6 [*] And the disciples went, and did as Jesus commanded them, 7  And brought the ass, and the colt, and put on them their clothes, and they set him thereon. 8  And a very great multitude spread their garments in the way; others cut down branches from the trees, and strawed them in the way. 9  And the multitudes that went before, and that followed, cried, saying, Hosanna to the Son of David: Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord; Hosanna in the highest. 10 [*] And when he was come into Jerusalem, all the city was moved, saying, Who is this? 11  And the multitude said, This is Jesus the prophet of Nazareth of Galilee.

12 ¶ And Jesus went into the temple of God, and cast out all them that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the moneychangers, and the seats of them that sold doves, 13  And said unto them, It is written, [*]My house shall be called the house of prayer; [*]but ye have made it a den of thieves. 14  And the blind and the lame came to him in the temple; and he healed them. 15  And when the chief priests and scribes saw the wonderful things that he did, and the children crying in the temple, and saying, Hosanna to the Son of David; they were sore displeased, 16  And said unto him, Hearest thou what these say? And Jesus saith unto them, Yea; have ye never read, [*]Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings thou hast perfected praise?

17 ¶ And he left them, and went out of the city into Bethany; and he lodged there. 18  Now in the morning as he returned into the city, he hungered. 19 [*] And when he saw a fig tree in the way, he came to it, and found nothing thereon, but leaves only, and said unto it, Let no fruit grow on thee henceforward for ever. And presently the fig tree withered away. 20  And when the disciples saw it, they marvelled, saying, How soon is the fig tree withered away! 21  Jesus answered and said unto them, Verily I say unto you, If ye have faith, and doubt not, ye shall not only do this which is done to the fig tree, but also if ye shall say unto this mountain, Be thou removed, and be thou cast into the sea; it shall be done. 22  And all things, whatsoever ye shall ask in prayer, believing, ye shall receive.

23 ¶ [*]And when he was come into the temple, the chief priests and the elders of the people came unto him as he was teaching, and said, By what authority doest thou these things? and who gave thee this authority? 24  And Jesus answered and said unto them, I also will ask you one thing, which if ye tell me, I in like wise will tell you by what authority I do these things. 25  The baptism of John, whence was it? from heaven, or of men? And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we shall say, From heaven; he will say unto us, Why did ye not then believe him? 26  But if we shall say, Of men; we fear the people; [*]for all hold John as a prophet. 27  And they answered Jesus, and said, We cannot tell. And he said unto them, Neither tell I you by what authority I do these things.

28 ¶ But what think ye? A certain man had two sons; and he came to the first, and said, Son, go work to day in my vineyard. 29  He answered and said, I will not: but afterward he repented, and went. 30  And he came to the second, and said likewise. And he answered and said, I go, sir: and went not. 31  Whether of them twain did the will of his father? They say unto him, The first. Jesus saith unto them, Verily I say unto you, That the publicans and the harlots go into the kingdom of God before you. 32  For [*]John came unto you in the way of righteousness, and ye believed him not: but the publicans and the harlots believed him: and ye, when ye had seen it, repented not afterward, that ye might believe him.

33 ¶ Hear another parable: There was a certain householder, [*]which planted a vineyard, and hedged it round about, and digged a winepress in it, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into a far country: 34  And when the time of the fruit drew near, he sent his servants to the husbandmen, that they might receive the fruits of it. 35  And the husbandmen took his servants, and beat one, and killed another, and stoned another. 36  Again, he sent other servants more than the first: and they did unto them likewise. 37  But last of all he sent unto them his son, saying, They will reverence my son. 38  But when the husbandmen saw the son, they said among themselves, This is the heir; [*]come, let us kill him, and let us seize on his inheritance. 39  And they caught him, and cast him out of the vineyard, and slew him. 40  When the lord therefore of the vineyard cometh, what will he do unto those husbandmen? 41  They say unto him, He will miserably destroy those wicked men, and will let out his vineyard unto other husbandmen, which shall render him the fruits in their seasons. 42  Jesus saith unto them, [*]Did ye never read in the scriptures, The stone which the builders rejected, the same is become the head of the corner: this is the Lord’s doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes? 43  Therefore say I unto you, The kingdom of God shall be taken from you, and given to a nation bringing forth the fruits thereof. 44  And [*]whosoever shall fall on this stone shall be broken: but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder. 45  And when the chief priests and Pharisees had heard his parables, they perceived that he spake of them. 46  But when they sought to lay hands on him, they feared the multitude, because they took him for a prophet.

22

1  And Jesus answered [*]and spake unto them again by parables, and said, 2  The kingdom of heaven is like unto a certain king, which made a marriage for his son, 3  And sent forth his servants to call them that were bidden to the wedding: and they would not come. 4  Again, he sent forth other servants, saying, Tell them which are bidden, Behold, I have prepared my dinner: my oxen and my fatlings are killed, and all things are ready: come unto the marriage. 5  But they made light of it, and went their ways, one to his farm, another to his merchandise: 6  And the remnant took his servants, and entreated them spitefully, and slew them. 7  But when the king heard thereof, he was wroth: and he sent forth his armies, and destroyed those murderers, and burned up their city. 8  Then saith he to his servants, The wedding is ready, but they which were bidden were not worthy. 9  Go ye therefore into the highways, and as many as ye shall find, bid to the marriage. 10  So those servants went out into the highways, and gathered together all as many as they found, both bad and good: and the wedding was furnished with guests.

11 ¶ And when the king came in to see the guests, he saw there a man which had not on a wedding garment: 12  And he saith unto him, Friend, how camest thou in hither not having a wedding garment? And he was speechless. 13  Then said the king to the servants, Bind him hand and foot, and take him away, and cast him into outer darkness; there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. 14 [*] For many are called, but few are chosen.

15 ¶ [*]Then went the Pharisees, and took counsel how they might entangle him in his talk. 16  And they sent out unto him their disciples with the Herodians, saying, Master, we know that thou art true, and teachest the way of God in truth, neither carest thou for any man: for thou regardest not the person of men. 17  Tell us therefore, What thinkest thou? Is it lawful to give tribute unto Caesar, or not? 18  But Jesus perceived their wickedness, and said, Why tempt ye me, ye hypocrites? 19  Shew me the tribute money. And they brought unto him a [∥]penny. 20  And he saith unto them, Whose is this image and [∥]superscription? 21  They say unto him, Cæsar’s. Then saith he unto them, [*]Render therefore unto Cæsar the things which are Cæsar’s; and unto God the things that are God’s. 22  When they had heard these words, they marvelled, and left him, and went their way.

23 ¶ [*]The same day came to him the Sadducees, [*]which say that there is no resurrection, and asked him, 24  Saying, Master, [*]Moses said, If a man die, having no children, his brother shall marry his wife, and raise up seed unto his brother. 25  Now there were with us seven brethren: and the first, when he had married a wife, deceased, and, having no issue, left his wife unto his brother: 26  Likewise the second also, and the third, unto the seventh. 27  And last of all the woman died also. 28  Therefore in the resurrection whose wife shall she be of the seven? for they all had her. 29  Jesus answered and said unto them, Ye do err, not knowing the scriptures, nor the power of God. 30  For in the resurrection they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are as the angels of God in heaven. 31  But as touching the resurrection of the dead, have ye not read that which was spoken unto you by God, saying, 32 [*] I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? God is not the God of the dead, but of the living. 33  And when the multitude heard this, they were astonished at his doctrine.

34 ¶ [*]But when the Pharisees had heard that he had put the Sadducees to silence, they were gathered together. 35  Then one of them, which was a lawyer, asked him a question, tempting him, and saying, 36  Master, which is the great commandment in the law? 37  Jesus said unto him, [*]Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind. 38  This is the first and great commandment. 39  And the second is like unto it, [*]Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. 40  On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets.

41 ¶ [*]While the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus asked them, 42  Saying, What think ye of Christ? whose son is he? They say unto him, The Son of David. 43  He saith unto them, How then doth David in spirit call him Lord, saying, 44 [*] The LORD said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, till I make thine enemies thy footstool? 45  If David then call him Lord, how is he his son? 46  And no man was able to answer him a word, neither durst any man from that day forth ask him any more questions.

23

1  Then spake Jesus to the multitude, and to his disciples, 2  Saying, The scribes and the Pharisees sit in Moses’ seat: 3  All therefore whatsoever they bid you observe, that observe and do; but do not ye after their works: for they say, and do not. 4 [*] For they bind heavy burdens and grievous to be borne, and lay them on men’s shoulders; but they themselves will not move them with one of their fingers. 5  But all their works they do for to be seen of men: [*]they make broad their phylacteries, and enlarge the borders of their garments, 6 [*] And love the uppermost rooms at feasts, and the chief seats in the synagogues, 7  And greetings in the markets, and to be called of men, Rabbi, Rabbi. 8 [*] But be not ye called Rabbi: for one is your Master, even Christ; and all ye are brethren. 9  And call no man your father upon the earth: [*]for one is your Father, which is in heaven. 10  Neither be ye called masters: for one is your Master, even Christ. 11  But he that is greatest among you shall be your servant. 12 [*] And whosoever shall exalt himself shall be abased; and he that shall humble himself shall be exalted.

13 ¶ But [*]woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye shut up the kingdom of heaven against men: for ye neither go in yourselves, neither suffer ye them that are entering to go in. 14  Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! [*]for ye devour widows’ houses, and for a pretence make long prayer: therefore ye shall receive the greater damnation. 15  Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye compass sea and land to make one proselyte, and when he is made, ye make him twofold more the child of hell than yourselves. 16  Woe unto you, ye blind guides, which say, Whosoever shall swear by the temple, it is nothing; but whosoever shall swear by the gold of the temple, he is a debtor! 17  Ye fools and blind: for whether is greater, the gold, or the temple that sanctifieth the gold? 18  And, Whosoever shall swear by the altar, it is nothing; but whosoever sweareth by the gift that is upon it, he is [∥]guilty. 19  Ye fools and blind: for whether is greater, the gift, or the altar that sanctifieth the gift? 20  Whoso therefore shall swear by the altar, sweareth by it, and by all things thereon. 21  And whoso shall swear by the temple, sweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth therein. 22  And he that shall swear by heaven, sweareth by the throne of God, and by him that sitteth thereon. 23  Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! [*]for ye pay tithe of mint and anise and cummin, and have omitted the weightier matters of the law, judgment, mercy, and faith: these ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone. 24  Ye blind guides, which strain at a gnat, and swallow a camel. 25  Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! [*]for ye make clean the outside of the cup and of the platter, but within they are full of extortion and excess. 26  Thou blind Pharisee, cleanse first that which is within the cup and platter, that the outside of them may be clean also. 27  Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye are like unto whited sepulchres, which indeed appear beautiful outward, but are within full of dead men’s bones, and of all uncleanness. 28  Even so ye also outwardly appear righteous unto men, but within ye are full of hypocrisy and iniquity. 29  Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye build the tombs of the prophets, and garnish the sepulchres of the righteous, 30  And say, If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets. 31  Wherefore ye be witnesses unto yourselves, that ye are the children of them which killed the prophets. 32  Fill ye up then the measure of your fathers. 33  Ye serpents, ye generation of vipers, how can ye escape the damnation of hell?

34 ¶ Wherefore, behold, I send unto you prophets, and wise men, and scribes: and some of them ye shall kill and crucify; and some of them shall ye scourge in your synagogues, and persecute them from city to city: 35  That upon you may come all the righteous blood shed upon the earth, [*]from the blood of righteous Abel unto the blood of Zacharias son of Barachias, whom ye slew between the temple and the altar. 36  Verily I say unto you, All these things shall come upon this generation. 37 [*] O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the prophets, [*]and stonest them which are sent unto thee, how often would [*]I have gathered thy children together, even as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and ye would not! 38  Behold, your house is left unto you desolate. 39  For I say unto you, Ye shall not see me henceforth, till ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.

24

1  And [*]Jesus went out, and departed from the temple: and his disciples came to him for to shew him the buildings of the temple. 2  And Jesus said unto them, See ye not all these things? verily I say unto you, [*]There shall not be left here one stone upon another, that shall not be thrown down.

3 ¶ And as he sat upon the mount of Olives, the disciples came unto him privately, saying, Tell us, when shall these things be? and what shall be the sign of thy coming, and of the end of the world? 4  And Jesus answered and said unto them, Take heed that no man deceive you. 5  For many shall come in my name, saying, I am Christ; and shall deceive many. 6  And ye shall hear of wars and rumours of wars: see that ye be not troubled: for all these things must come to pass, but the end is not yet. 7  For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: and there shall be famines, and pestilences, and earthquakes, in divers places. 8  All these are the beginning of sorrows. 9 [*] Then shall they deliver you up to be afflicted, and shall kill you: and ye shall be hated of all nations for my name’s sake. 10  And then shall many be offended, and shall betray one another, and shall hate one another. 11  And many false prophets shall rise, and shall deceive many. 12  And because iniquity shall abound, the love of many shall wax cold. 13  But he that shall endure unto the end, the same shall be saved. 14  And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto all nations; and then shall the end come. 15 [*] When ye therefore shall see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by [*]Daniel the prophet, stand in the holy place, (whoso readeth, let him understand:) 16  Then let them which be in Judaea flee into the mountains: 17  Let him which is on the housetop not come down to take any thing out of his house: 18  Neither let him which is in the field return back to take his clothes. 19  And woe unto them that are with child, and to them that give suck in those days! 20  But pray ye that your flight be not in the winter, neither on the sabbath day: 21  For then shall be great tribulation, such as was not since the beginning of the world to this time, no, nor ever shall be. 22  And except those days should be shortened, there should no flesh be saved: but for the elect’s sake those days shall be shortened. 23 [*] Then if any man shall say unto you, Lo, here is Christ, or there; believe it not. 24  For there shall arise false Christs, and false prophets, and shall shew great signs and wonders; insomuch that, if it were possible, they shall deceive the very elect. 25  Behold, I have told you before. 26  Wherefore if they shall say unto you, Behold, he is in the desert; go not forth: behold, he is in the secret chambers; believe it not. 27  For as the lightning cometh out of the east, and shineth even unto the west; so shall also the coming of the Son of man be. 28 [*] For wheresoever the carcase is, there will the eagles be gathered together.

29 ¶ Immediately after the tribulation of those days [*]shall the sun be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light, and the stars shall fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens shall be shaken: 30  And then shall appear the sign of the Son of man in heaven: and then shall all the tribes of the earth mourn, [*]and they shall see the Son of man coming in the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. 31 [*] And he shall send his angels [∥]with a great sound of a trumpet, and they shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from one end of heaven to the other. 32  Now learn a parable of the fig tree; When his branch is yet tender, and putteth forth leaves, ye know that summer is nigh: 33  So likewise ye, when ye shall see all these things, know that it is near, even at the doors. 34  Verily I say unto you, This generation shall not pass, till all these things be fulfilled. 35 [*] Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away.

36 ¶ But of that day and hour knoweth no man, no, not the angels of heaven, but my Father only. 37  But as the days of Noe were, so shall also the coming of the Son of man be. 38 [*] For as in the days that were before the flood they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day that Noe entered into the ark, 39  And knew not until the flood came, and took them all away; so shall also the coming of the Son of man be. 40 [*] Then shall two be in the field; the one shall be taken, and the other left. 41  Two women shall be grinding at the mill; the one shall be taken, and the other left.

42 ¶ [*]Watch therefore: for ye know not what hour your Lord doth come. 43 [*] But know this, that if the goodman of the house had known in what watch the thief would come, he would have watched, and would not have suffered his house to be broken up. 44  Therefore be ye also ready: for in such an hour as ye think not the Son of man cometh. 45 [*] Who then is a faithful and wise servant, whom his lord hath made ruler over his household, to give them meat in due season? 46  Blessed is that servant, whom his lord when he cometh shall find so doing. 47  Verily I say unto you, That he shall make him ruler over all his goods. 48  But and if that evil servant shall say in his heart, My lord delayeth his coming; 49  And shall begin to smite his fellowservants, and to eat and drink with the drunken; 50  The lord of that servant shall come in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour that he is not aware of, 51  And shall [∥]cut him asunder, and appoint him his portion with the hypocrites: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.

25

1  Then shall the kingdom of heaven be likened unto ten virgins, which took their lamps, and went forth to meet the bridegroom. 2  And five of them were wise, and five were foolish. 3  They that were foolish took their lamps, and took no oil with them: 4  But the wise took oil in their vessels with their lamps. 5  While the bridegroom tarried, they all slumbered and slept. 6  And at midnight there was a cry made, Behold, the bridegroom cometh; go ye out to meet him. 7  Then all those virgins arose, and trimmed their lamps. 8  And the foolish said unto the wise, Give us of your oil; for our lamps are [∥]gone out. 9  But the wise answered, saying, Not so; lest there be not enough for us and you: but go ye rather to them that sell, and buy for yourselves. 10  And while they went to buy, the bridegroom came; and they that were ready went in with him to the marriage: and the door was shut. 11  Afterward came also the other virgins, saying, Lord, Lord, open to us. 12  But he answered and said, Verily I say unto you, I know you not. 13 [*] Watch therefore, for ye know neither the day nor the hour wherein the Son of man cometh.

14 ¶ [*]For the kingdom of heaven is as a man travelling into a far country, who called his own servants, and delivered unto them his goods. 15  And unto one he gave five [∥]talents, to another two, and to another one; to every man according to his several ability; and straightway took his journey. 16  Then he that had received the five talents went and traded with the same, and made them other five talents. 17  And likewise he that had received two, he also gained other two. 18  But he that had received one went and digged in the earth, and hid his lord’s money. 19  After a long time the lord of those servants cometh, and reckoneth with them. 20  And so he that had received five talents came and brought other five talents, saying, Lord, thou deliveredst unto me five talents: behold, I have gained beside them five talents more. 21  His lord said unto him, Well done, thou good and faithful servant: thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord. 22  He also that had received two talents came and said, Lord, thou deliveredst unto me two talents: behold, I have gained two other talents beside them. 23  His lord said unto him, Well done, good and faithful servant; thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord. 24  Then he which had received the one talent came and said, Lord, I knew thee that thou art an hard man, reaping where thou hast not sown, and gathering where thou hast not strawed: 25  And I was afraid, and went and hid thy talent in the earth: lo, there thou hast that is thine. 26  His lord answered and said unto him, Thou wicked and slothful servant, thou knewest that I reap where I sowed not, and gather where I have not strawed: 27  Thou oughtest therefore to have put my money to the exchangers, and then at my coming I should have received mine own with usury. 28  Take therefore the talent from him, and give it unto him which hath ten talents. 29 [*] For unto every one that hath shall be given, and he shall have abundance: but from him that hath not shall be taken away even that which he hath. 30  And cast ye the unprofitable servant into outer darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.

31 ¶ When the Son of man shall come in his glory, and all the holy angels with him, then shall he sit upon the throne of his glory: 32  And before him shall be gathered all nations: and he shall separate them one from another, as a shepherd divideth his sheep from the goats: 33  And he shall set the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on the left. 34  Then shall the King say unto them on his right hand, Come, ye blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world: 35 [*] For I was an hungred, and ye gave me meat: I was thirsty, and ye gave me drink: I was a stranger, and ye took me in: 36  Naked, and ye clothed me: I was sick, and ye visited me: I was in prison, and ye came unto me. 37  Then shall the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee an hungred, and fed thee? or thirsty, and gave thee drink? 38  When saw we thee a stranger, and took thee in? or naked, and clothed thee? 39  Or when saw we thee sick, or in prison, and came unto thee? 40  And the King shall answer and say unto them, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it unto me. 41  Then shall he say also unto them on the left hand, [*]Depart from me, ye cursed, into everlasting fire, prepared for the devil and his angels: 42  For I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat: I was thirsty, and ye gave me no drink: 43  I was a stranger, and ye took me not in: naked, and ye clothed me not: sick, and in prison, and ye visited me not. 44  Then shall they also answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee an hungred, or athirst, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and did not minister unto thee? 45  Then shall he answer them, saying, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye did it not to one of the least of these, ye did it not to me. 46  And [*]these shall go away into everlasting punishment: but the righteous into life eternal.

26

1  And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished all these sayings, he said unto his disciples, 2 [*] Ye know that after two days is the feast of the passover, and the Son of man is betrayed to be crucified. 3 [*] Then assembled together the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders of the people, unto the palace of the high priest, who was called Caiaphas, 4  And consulted that they might take Jesus by subtilty, and kill him. 5  But they said, Not on the feast day, lest there be an uproar among the people.

6 ¶ [*]Now when Jesus was in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper, 7  There came unto him a woman having an alabaster box of very precious ointment, and poured it on his head, as he sat at meat. 8  But when his disciples saw it, they had indignation, saying, To what purpose is this waste? 9  For this ointment might have been sold for much, and given to the poor. 10  When Jesus understood it, he said unto them, Why trouble ye the woman? for she hath wrought a good work upon me. 11 [*] For ye have the poor always with you; but me ye have not always. 12  For in that she hath poured this ointment on my body, she did it for my burial. 13  Verily I say unto you, Wheresoever this gospel shall be preached in the whole world, there shall also this, that this woman hath done, be told for a memorial of her.

14 ¶ [*]Then one of the twelve, called Judas Iscariot, went unto the chief priests, 15  And said unto them, What will ye give me, and I will deliver him unto you? And they covenanted with him for thirty pieces of silver. 16  And from that time he sought opportunity to betray him.

17 ¶ [*]Now the first day of the feast of unleavened bread the disciples came to Jesus, saying unto him, Where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to eat the passover? 18  And he said, Go into the city to such a man, and say unto him, The Master saith, My time is at hand; I will keep the passover at thy house with my disciples. 19  And the disciples did as Jesus had appointed them; and they made ready the passover. 20 [*] Now when the even was come, he sat down with the twelve. 21  And as they did eat, he said, Verily I say unto you, that one of you shall betray me. 22  And they were exceeding sorrowful, and began every one of them to say unto him, Lord, is it I? 23  And he answered and said, [*]He that dippeth his hand with me in the dish, the same shall betray me. 24  The Son of man goeth as it is written of him: but woe unto that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed! it had been good for that man if he had not been born. 25  Then Judas, which betrayed him, answered and said, Master, is it I? He said unto him, Thou hast said.

26 ¶ And as they were eating, [*]Jesus took bread, and [∥]blessed it, and brake it, and gave it to the disciples, and said, Take, eat; this is my body. 27  And he took the cup, and gave thanks, and gave it to them, saying, Drink ye all of it; 28  For this is my blood of the new testament, which is shed for many for the remission of sins. 29  But I say unto you, I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in my Father’s kingdom. 30  And when they had sung an [∥]hymn, they went out into the mount of Olives. 31  Then saith Jesus unto them, [*]All ye shall be offended because of me this night: for it is written, [*]I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock shall be scattered abroad. 32  But after I am risen again, [*]I will go before you into Galilee. 33  Peter answered and said unto him, Though all men shall be offended because of thee, yet will I never be offended. 34  Jesus said unto him, [*]Verily I say unto thee, That this night, before the cock crow, thou shalt deny me thrice. 35  Peter said unto him, Though I should die with thee, yet will I not deny thee. Likewise also said all the disciples.

36 ¶ [*]Then cometh Jesus with them unto a place called Gethsemane, and saith unto the disciples, Sit ye here, while I go and pray yonder. 37  And he took with him Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, and began to be sorrowful and very heavy. 38  Then saith he unto them, My soul is exceeding sorrowful, even unto death: tarry ye here, and watch with me. 39  And he went a little further, and fell on his face, and prayed, saying, O my Father, if it be possible, let this cup pass from me: nevertheless not as I will, but as thou wilt. 40  And he cometh unto the disciples, and findeth them asleep, and saith unto Peter, What, could ye not watch with me one hour? 41  Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation: the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak. 42  He went away again the second time, and prayed, saying, O my Father, if this cup may not pass away from me, except I drink it, thy will be done. 43  And he came and found them asleep again: for their eyes were heavy. 44  And he left them, and went away again, and prayed the third time, saying the same words. 45  Then cometh he to his disciples, and saith unto them, Sleep on now, and take your rest: behold, the hour is at hand, and the Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners. 46  Rise, let us be going: behold, he is at hand that doth betray me.

47 ¶ And [*]while he yet spake, lo, Judas, one of the twelve, came, and with him a great multitude with swords and staves, from the chief priests and elders of the people. 48  Now he that betrayed him gave them a sign, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, that same is he: hold him fast. 49  And forthwith he came to Jesus, and said, Hail, master; and kissed him. 50  And Jesus said unto him, Friend, wherefore art thou come? Then came they, and laid hands on Jesus, and took him. 51  And, behold, one of them which were with Jesus stretched out his hand, and drew his sword, and struck a servant of the high priest’s, and smote off his ear. 52  Then said Jesus unto him, Put up again thy sword into his place: [*]for all they that take the sword shall perish with the sword. 53  Thinkest thou that I cannot now pray to my Father, and he shall presently give me more than twelve legions of angels? 54  But how then shall the scriptures be fulfilled, [*]that thus it must be? 55  In that same hour said Jesus to the multitudes, Are ye come out as against a thief with swords and staves for to take me? I sat daily with you teaching in the temple, and ye laid no hold on me. 56  But all this was done, that the [*]scriptures of the prophets might be fulfilled. Then all the disciples forsook him, and fled.

57 ¶ [*]And they that had laid hold on Jesus led him away to Caiaphas the high priest, where the scribes and the elders were assembled. 58  But Peter followed him afar off unto the high priest’s palace, and went in, and sat with the servants, to see the end. 59  Now the chief priests, and elders, and all the council, sought false witness against Jesus, to put him to death; 60  But found none: yea, though many false witnesses came, yet found they none. At the last came two false witnesses, 61  And said, This fellow said, [*]I am able to destroy the temple of God, and to build it in three days. 62  And the high priest arose, and said unto him, Answerest thou nothing? what is it which these witness against thee? 63  But Jesus held his peace. And the high priest answered and said unto him, I adjure thee by the living God, that thou tell us whether thou be the Christ, the Son of God. 64  Jesus saith unto him, Thou hast said: nevertheless I say unto you, [*]Hereafter shall ye see the Son of man sitting on the right hand of power, and coming in the clouds of heaven. 65  Then the high priest rent his clothes, saying, He hath spoken blasphemy; what further need have we of witnesses? behold, now ye have heard his blasphemy. 66  What think ye? They answered and said, He is guilty of death. 67 [*] Then did they spit in his face, and buffeted him; and others smote him with [∥]the palms of their hands, 68  Saying, Prophesy unto us, thou Christ, Who is he that smote thee?

69 ¶ [*]Now Peter sat without in the palace: and a damsel came unto him, saying, Thou also wast with Jesus of Galilee. 70  But he denied before them all, saying, I know not what thou sayest. 71  And when he was gone out into the porch, another maid saw him, and said unto them that were there, This fellow was also with Jesus of Nazareth. 72  And again he denied with an oath, I do not know the man. 73  And after a while came unto him they that stood by, and said to Peter, Surely thou also art one of them; for thy speech bewrayeth thee. 74  Then began he to curse and to swear, saying, I know not the man. And immediately the cock crew. 75  And Peter remembered the [‡]word of Jesus, which said unto him, Before the cock crow, thou shalt deny me thrice. And he went out, and wept bitterly.

27

1  When the morning was come, [*]all the chief priests and elders of the people took counsel against Jesus to put him to death: 2  And when they had bound him, they led him away, and delivered him to Pontius Pilate the governor.

3 ¶ Then Judas, which had betrayed him, when he saw that he was condemned, repented himself, and brought again the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and elders, 4  Saying, I have sinned in that I have betrayed the innocent blood. And they said, What is that to us? see thou to that. 5  And he cast down the pieces of silver in the temple, [*]and departed, and went and hanged himself. 6  And the chief priests took the silver pieces, and said, It is not lawful for to put them into the treasury, because it is the price of blood. 7  And they took counsel, and bought with them the potter’s field, to bury strangers in. 8  Wherefore that field was called, [*]The field of blood, unto this day. 9  Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremy the prophet, saying, [*]And they took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of him that was valued, [∥]whom they of the children of Israel did value; 10  And gave them for the potter’s field, as the Lord appointed me. 11  And Jesus stood before the governor: and the governor asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And Jesus said unto him, Thou sayest. 12  And when he was accused of the chief priests and elders, he answered nothing. 13  Then [‡]said Pilate unto him, Hearest thou not how many things they witness against thee? 14  And he answered him to never a word; insomuch that the governor marvelled greatly. 15 [*] Now at that feast the governor was wont to release unto the people a prisoner, whom they would. 16  And they had then a notable prisoner, called Barabbas. 17  Therefore when they were gathered together, Pilate said unto them, Whom will ye that I release unto you? Barabbas, or Jesus which is called Christ? 18  For he knew that for envy they had delivered him.

19 ¶ When he was set down on the judgment seat, his wife sent unto him, saying, Have thou nothing to do with that just man: for I have suffered many things this day in a dream because of him. 20 [*] But the chief priests and elders persuaded the multitude that they should ask Barabbas, and destroy Jesus. 21  The governor answered and said unto them, Whether of the twain will ye that I release unto you? They said, Barabbas. 22  Pilate [‡]saith unto them, What shall I do then with Jesus which is called Christ? They all [‡]say unto him, Let him be crucified. 23  And the governor said, Why, what evil hath he done? But they cried out the more, saying, Let him be crucified.

24 ¶ When Pilate saw that he could prevail nothing, but that rather a tumult was made, he took water, and washed his hands before the multitude, saying, I am innocent of the blood of this just person: see ye to it. 25  Then answered all the people, and said, His blood be on us, and on our children.

26 ¶ Then released he Barabbas unto them: and when he had scourged Jesus, he delivered him to be crucified. 27 [*] Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus into the [∥]common hall, and gathered unto him the whole band of soldiers. 28  And they stripped him, and put on him a scarlet robe.

29 ¶ And when they had platted a crown of thorns, they put it upon his head, and a reed in his right hand: and they bowed the knee before him, and mocked him, saying, Hail, King of the Jews! 30  And they spit upon him, and took the reed, and smote him on the head. 31  And after that they had mocked him, they took the robe off from him, and put his own raiment on him, and led him away to crucify him. 32 [*] And as they came out, they found a man of Cyrene, Simon by name: him they compelled to bear his cross. 33 [*] And when they were come unto a place called Golgotha, that is to say, a place of a skull,

34 ¶ They gave him vinegar to drink mingled with gall: and when he had tasted thereof, he would not drink. 35  And they crucified him, and parted his garments, casting lots: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, [*]They parted my garments among them, and upon my vesture did they cast lots. 36  And sitting down they watched him there; 37  And set up over his head his accusation written, THIS IS JESUS THE KING OF THE JEWS. 38  Then were there two thieves crucified with him, one on the right hand, and another on the left.

39 ¶ And they that passed by reviled him, wagging their heads, 40  And saying, Thou that destroyest the temple, and buildest it in three days, save thyself. If thou be the Son of God, come down from the cross. 41  Likewise also the chief priests mocking him, with the scribes and elders, said, 42  He saved others; himself he cannot save. If he be the King of Israel, let him now come down from the cross, and we will believe him. 43 [*] He trusted in God; let him deliver him now, if he will have him: for he said, I am the Son of God. 44  The thieves also, which were crucified with him, cast the same in his teeth. 45  Now from the sixth hour there was darkness over all the land unto the ninth hour. 46  And about the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying, Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani? that is to say, [*]My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? 47  Some of them that stood there, when they heard that, said, This man calleth for Elias. 48  And straightway one of them ran, and took a spunge, [*]and filled it with vinegar, and put it on a reed, and gave him to drink. 49  The rest said, Let be, let us see whether Elias will come to save him.

50 ¶ Jesus, when he had cried again with a loud voice, yielded up the ghost. 51  And, behold, the veil of the temple was rent in twain from the top to the bottom; and the earth did quake, and the rocks rent; 52  And the graves were opened; and many bodies [‡]of the saints which slept arose, 53  And came out of the graves after his resurrection, and went into the holy city, and appeared unto many. 54  Now when the centurion, and they that were with him, watching Jesus, saw the earthquake, and those things that were done, they feared greatly, saying, Truly this was the Son of God. 55  And many women were there beholding afar off, which followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering unto him: 56  Among which was Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of Zebedee’s children. 57 [*] When the even was come, there came a rich man of Arimathæa, named Joseph, who also himself was Jesus’ disciple: 58  He went to Pilate, and begged the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded the body to be delivered. 59  And when Joseph had taken the body, he wrapped it in a clean linen cloth, 60  And laid it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn out in the rock: and he rolled a great stone to the door of the sepulchre, and departed. 61  And there was Mary Magdalene, and the other Mary, sitting over against the sepulchre.

62 ¶ Now the next day, that followed the day of the preparation, the chief priests and Pharisees came together unto Pilate, 63  Saying, Sir, we remember that that deceiver said, while he was yet alive, After three days I will rise again. 64  Command therefore that the sepulchre be made sure until the third day, lest his disciples come by night, and steal him away, and say unto the people, He is risen from the dead: so the last error shall be worse than the first. 65  Pilate said unto them, Ye have a watch: go your way, make it as sure as ye can. 66  So they went, and made the sepulchre sure, sealing the stone, and setting a watch.

28

1  In the [*]end of the sabbath, as it began to dawn toward the first day of the week, came Mary Magdalene and the other Mary to see the sepulchre. 2  And, behold, there [∥]was a great earthquake: for the angel of the Lord descended from heaven, and came and rolled back the stone from the door, and sat upon it. 3  His countenance was like lightning, and his raiment white as snow: 4  And for fear of him the keepers did shake, and became as dead men. 5  And the angel answered and said unto the women, Fear not ye: for I know that ye seek Jesus, which was crucified. 6  He is not here: for he is risen, as he said. Come, see the place where the Lord lay. 7  And go quickly, and tell his disciples that he is risen from the dead; and, behold, he goeth before you into Galilee; there shall ye see him: lo, I have told you. 8  And they departed quickly from the sepulchre with fear and great joy; and did run to bring his disciples word.

9 ¶ And as they went to tell his disciples, behold, Jesus met them, saying, All hail. And they came and held him by the feet, and worshipped him. 10  Then said Jesus unto them, Be not afraid: go tell my brethren that they go into Galilee, and there shall they see me.

11 ¶ Now when they were going, behold, some of the watch came into the city, and shewed unto the chief priests all the things that were done. 12  And when they were assembled with the elders, and had taken counsel, they gave large money unto the soldiers, 13  Saying, Say ye, His disciples came by night, and stole him away while we slept. 14  And if this come to the governor’s ears, we will persuade him, and secure you. 15  So they took the money, and did as they were taught: and this saying is commonly reported among the Jews until this day.

16 ¶ Then the eleven disciples went away into Galilee, into a mountain where Jesus had appointed them. 17  And when they saw him, they worshipped him: but some doubted. 18  And Jesus came and spake unto them, saying, All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.

19 ¶ [*]Go ye therefore, and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost: 20  Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you: and, lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world. Amen.

* 1.1 Luke 3. 23.

* 1.2 Gen. 21 3.

* 1.2 Gen. 25. 26.

* 1.2 Gen. 29. 35.

* 1.3 Gen. 38. 27.

* 1.3 Ruth 4. 18. 1 Chr. 2 5.

* 1.6 1 Sam. 16. 1 & 17 12.

* 1.6 2 Sam. 12. 24.

* 1.7 1 Chr. 3. 10.

* 1.10 2 Kin. 20 21. 1 Chr. 3. 13.

∥ 1.11 Some read, Josias begat Jakim, and Jakim begat Jechonias.

* 1.12 1 Chr. 3. 16, 17.

* 1.18 Luke 1. 27.

* 1.21 Luke 1. 31.

* 1.23 Is. 7. 14.

∥ 1.23 Or, his name shall be called.

* 2.1 Luke 2. 6.

* 2.6 Mic. 5. 2. John 7. 42.

∥ 2.6 Or, feed.

∥ 2.11 Or, offered.

* 2.15 Hos. 11. 1.

* 2.17 Jer. 31. 15.

* 3.1 Mark 1. 4. Luke 3. 2.

* 3.3 Is 40. 3. Mark 1. 3.

* 3.7 ch. 12. 34.

∥ 3.8 Or, answerable to amendment of life.

* 3.9 John 8. 39.

* 3.10 ch. 7. 19.

* 3.11 Mark 1. 8. Luke 3. 16. John 1. 26.

‡ 3.12 [1611 omits he]

* 3.13 Mark 1. 9. Luke 3. 21.

* 4.1 Mark 1. 12. Luke 4. 1.

* 4.4 Deut. 8 3.

* 4.6 Ps. 91. 11.

* 4.7 Deut. 6. 16.

* 4.10 Deut. 6. 13. & 10. 20.

* 4.12 Mark 1. 14. Luke 4. 14 John 4. 43.

∥ 4.12 Or, delivered up.

* 4.15 Is. 9. 1.

* 4.17 Mark 1. 14.

* 4.18 Mark 1. 16.

* 5.3 Luke 6. 20.

* 5.5 Ps. 37. 11.

* 5.6 Is. 65. 13.

* 5.8 Ps. 24. 4.

* 5.10 1 Pet. 3. 14.

* 5.11 1 Pet. 4. 14.

† 5.11 Gr. lying.

* 5.13 Mark 9. 50. Luke 14. 34.

* 5.15 Mark 4. 21. Luke 8. 16. & 11. 33.

∥ 5.15 The word in the original signlfieth a measure containing about a pint less than a peck.

* 5.16 1 Pet. 2. 12.

* 5.18 Luke 16. 17.

* 5.19 James 2. 10.

∥ 5.21 Or, to them.

* 5.21 Ex. 20. 13. Deut. 5. 17.

* 5.25 Luke 12. 58.

* 5.27 Ex. 20. 14.

* 5.29 ch. 18. 8. Mark 9. 47.

∥ 5.29 Or, do cause thee to offend.

* 5.31 Deut. 24 1. Luke 16. 18 1 Cor. 7. 10.

* 5.33 Ex. 20. 7. Lev. 19. 12. Deut. 5. 11.

* 5.37 James 5 12.

* 5.38 Ex. 21. 24. Lev. 24. 20. Deut. 19. 21.

* 5.39 Luke 6. 29. Rom. 12. 17. 1 Cor. 6. 7.

* 5.42 Deut. 15. 8.

* 5.43 Lev. 19. 18

* 5.44 Luke 6. 27.

* 5.44 Luke 23. 34. Acts 7. 60.

* 5.46 Luke 6. 32.

∥ 6.1 Or, with.

* 6.2 Rom. 12. 8.

∥ 6.2 Or, cause not a trumpet to be sounded.

‡ 6.3 [1611 omits hand]

* 6.7 7. 14.

* 6.9 Luke 11. 2.

* 6.14 Mark 11. 25.

* 6.20 Luke 12. 33. 1 Tim. 6. 19.

* 6.22 Luke 11. 34.

* 6.24 Luke 16. 13.

* 6.25 Ps. 55. 22. Luke 12. 22. 1 Pet. 5. 7.

* 7.1 Luke 6. 37. Rom. 2. 1.

* 7.2 Mark 4. 24. Luke 6. 38.

* 7.3 Luke 6. 41.

* 7.7 ch. 21. 22. Mark 11. 24. Luke 11. 9. John 16. 24. James 1. 5, 6.

* 7.12 Luke 6. 31.

* 7.13 Luke 13. 24.

∥ 7.14 Or, How.

* 7.16 Luke 6. 43.

* 7.19 ch. 3 10.

* 7.21 Rom. 2. 13. James 1. 22.

* 7.23 Luke 13. 27.

* 7.23 Ps. 6. 8.

* 7.24 Luke 6. 47.

* 7.28 Mark 1 22. Luke 4. 32.

* 8.2 Mark 1. 40. Luke 5. 12.

* 8.4 Lev 14. 4

* 8.5 Luke 7. 1.

* 8.14 Mark 1 29. Luke 4. 38.

* 8.16 Mark 1 32. Luke 4. 40.

* 8.17 Is. 53. 4. 1 Pet 2 24.

* 8.19 Luke 9. 57.

* 8.24 Mark 4. 37. Luke 8. 23

* 8.28 Mark 5. 1. Luke 8. 26.

* 9.2 Mark 2. 8. Luke 5. 18.

* 9.9 Mark 2. 14 Luke 5. 27.

* 9.13 Hos. 6. 6 ch. 12. 7.

* 9.13 1 Tim. 1. 15.

* 9.14 Mark 2. 18. Luke 5. 33.

∥ 9.16 Or, raw, or, unwrought cloth.

* 9.18 Mark 5. 22. Luke 8. 41.

∥ 9.26 Or, this fame.

* 9.32 Luke 11. 14.

* 9.34 ch. 12. 24. Mark 3. 22. Luke 11. 15.

‡ 9.34 [1611 out the devils]

* 9.35 Mark 6 6. Luke 13. 22.

* 9.36 Mark 6. 34.

∥ 9.36 Or, were tired and lay down.

* 9.36 Num. 27. 17.

* 9.37 Luke 10. 2.

* 10.1 Mark 3. 14. Luke 9. 1.

∥ 10.1 Or, over.

* 10.6 Acts 13. 46.

* 10.7 Luke 10 9.

* 10.9 Mark 6. 8. Luke 9. 3. & 22. 35.

∥ 10.9 Or, Get.

* 10.10 Luke 10. 7. 1 Tim. 5. 18

* 10.11 Luke 10. 8.

* 10.14 Mark 6. 11.

* 10.14 Acts 13. 51.

* 10.16 Luke 10. 3.

∥ 10.16 Or, simple.

* 10.19 Mark 13. 11. Luke 12. 11.

* 10.21 Luke 21. 16.

* 10.22 Mark 13. 13.

∥ 10.23 Or, end, or, finish.

* 10.24 Luke 6 40. John 13. 16.

* 10.26 Mark 4 22. Luke 8. 17. & 12. 2.

* 10.28 Luke 12. 4.

∥ 10.29 It is in value half-penny farthing in the original, as being the tenth part of the Roman penny.

* 10.30 2 Sam. 14. 11. Acts 27. 34.

* 10.32 Luke 12. 8.

* 10.33 Mark 8. 38. Luke 9. 26. 2 Tim. 2. 12.

* 10.34 Luke 12. 51.

* 10.35 Mic 7. 6.

* 10.37 Luke 14. 26.

* 10.38 ch. 16. 24. Mark 8. 34. Luke 9. 23.

* 10.39 John 12. 25.

* 10.40 Luke 10. 16. John 13. 20.

* 10.42 Mark 9. 41.

* 11.2 Luke 7. 18.

* 11.5 Is. 35. 6.

* 11.5 Is. 61. 1.

* 11.10 Mal. 3. 1.

* 11.12 Luke 16. 16.

∥ 11.12 Or, is gotten by force, and they that thrust men.

* 11.14 Mal. 4. 5

* 11.16 Luke 7. 31.

* 11.20 Luke 10. 13.

* 11.25 Luke 10. 21.

* 11.27 John 3. 35

* 11.27 John 6. 46.

* 11.29 Jer. 6. 16.

* 11.30 1 John 5. 3.

* 12.1 Deut. 23. 25. Mark 2. 23. Luke 6. 1.

* 12.3 1 Sam. 21. 6.

* 12.4 Ex. 29. 32, 33. Lev. 8. 31. & 24. 9.

* 12.5 Num. 23. 9.

* 12.7 Hos. 6. 6. ch. 9. 13.

* 12.9 Mark 3. 1. Luke 6. 6.

∥ 12.14 Or, took counsel.

* 12.18 Is. 42. 1.

* 12.22 Luke 11. 14.

‡ 12.23 [1611 Is this]

* 12.24 ch. 9. 34.

* 12.31 Mark 3. 28. Luke 12. 10. 1 John 5. 16.

* 12.34 Luke 6. 45.

* 12.38 ch. 16. 1. Luke 11. 29. 1 Cor. 1. 22.

* 12.40 Jonah 1. 17.

* 12.41 Jonah 3. 5.

* 12.42 1 Kin. 10. 1.

* 12.43 Luke 11. 24.

* 12.45 Heb. 6. 4 & 10. 26. 2 Pet. 2. 20

* 12.46 Mark 3. 31. Luke 8. 20.

* 13.1 Mark 4. 1.

* 13.3 Luke 8. 5.

‡ 13.6 [1611 had not root]

* 13.12 ch. 25. 29.

* 13.14 Is. 6. 9. Mark 4. 12. Luke 8. 10. John 12. 40. Acts 28. 26. Rom. 11. 8.

* 13.17 Luke 10. 24.

* 13.31 Mark 4. 30. Luke 13. 19.

* 13.33 Luke 13. 20.

† 13.33 The word in the Greek is a measure containing about a peck and a half, wanting a little more than a pint.

* 13.34 Mark 4. 33.

* 13.35 Ps. 78. 2.

* 13.39 Joel 3. 13 Rev. 14. 15.

∥ 13.41 Or, scandals.

* 13.43 Dan. 12 3.

‡ 13.46 [1611 he went]

* 13.54 Mark 6 1 Luke 4. 16.

* 13.55 John 6. 42.

* 13.57 Mark 6. 4. Luke 4. 24. John 4. 44

* 14.1 Mark 6. 14. Luke 9. 7.

∥ 14.2 Or, are wrought by him.

* 14.3 Luke 3. 19.

* 14.4 Lev. 18. 16. & 20. 21.

* 14.5 ch. 21. 26.

* 14.13 Mark 6 32 Luke 9. 10.

* 14.15 Mark 6 35. John 6. 5.

* 14.23 Mark 6. 46.

* 14.23 John 6 16.

∥ 14.30 Or, strong.

* 14.34 Mark 6. 53.

* 15.1 Mark 7. 1.

* 15.4 Ex. 20. 12. Deut. 5. 16.

* 15.4 Ex. 21. 17. Lev. 20. 9 Prov 20. 20.

* 15.5 Mark 7 11, 12.

* 15.8 Is. 29. 13

* 15.10 Mark 7. 14.

* 15.13 John 15. 2.

* 15.14 Luke 6. 39.

* 15.15 Mark 7 17.

* 15.19 Gen 6. 5. & 8 21.

* 15.21 Mark 7. 24.

* 15.24 ch. 10. 6.

* 15.29 Mark 7. 81.

* 15.30 Is. 25. 5

* 15.32 Mark 8. 1.

* 16.1 Mark 8. 11. Luke 12. 54.

* 16.9 ch. 14. 17.

* 16.10 ch. 15. 84.

* 16.13 Mark 8. 27. Luke 9. 18.

* 16.16 John 6. 69,

‡ 16.16 [1611 art Christ]

* 16.18 John 1. 42.

* 16.19 John 20. 23.

‡ 16.19 [1611 omits and]

* 16.24 ch. 10. 38. Mark 8. 34.

* 16.27 Ps. 62. 12. Rom. 2. 6.

* 16.28 Mark 9 1. Luke 9. 27

* 17.1 Mark 9 2. Luke 9. 28.

* 17.5 2 Pet. 1. 17.

* 17.10 ch. 11. 14 Mark 9. 11.

* 17.14 Mark 9. 17. Luke 9. 38.

* 17.20 Luke 17. 6.

* 17.22 ch. 20. 17. Mark 9. 31. Luke 9. 44.

∥ 17.24 Called in the original didrachma, being in value fifteen pence.

∥ 17.27 Or, a stater. It is half an ounce of silver, in value two shillings and sixpence, after five shillings the ounce.

* 18.1 Mark 9 33. Luke 9. 46.

* 18.3 ch. 19. 14 1 Cor. 14. 20.

* 18.6 Mark 9. 42. Luke 17. 1, 2.

* 18.8 ch. 5. 30. Mark 9. 45.

* 18.11 Luke 19. 10.

* 18.12 Luke 15. 4.

* 18.15 Lev. 19 17 Luke 17 3.

* 18.16 Deut. 19 15. John 8 17 2 Cor. 13. 1 Heb. 10 28

* 18.17 1 Cor. 5 9. 2 Thess. 3. 14

* 18.18 John 20 23 1 Cor. 5. 4.

* 18.21 Luke 17. 4.

∥ 18.24 750 ounces of silver, which after live shillings the ounce is 187l. 10s.

∥ 18.26 Or, besought him.

∥ 18.28 The Roman penny is the eighth part of an ounce, which after five shillings the ounce is seven pence half-penny.

* 19.1 Mark 10. 1.

* 19.4 Gen. 1. 27.

* 19.5 Gen. 2. 24 Eph. 5. 31.

* 19.5 1 Cor. 6. 16.

* 19.7 Deut. 24 1.

* 19.9 ch. 5. 32 Mark 10 11. Luke 16. 18. 1 Cor. 7. 11.

* 19.13 Mark 10. 13. Luke 18. 15.

* 19.16 Mark 10. 17. Luke 18. 18.

* 19.18 Ex. 20. 13.

* 19.27 Mark 10. 28. Luke 18 28.

* 19.28 Luke 22. 80.

* 19.30 ch. 20. 16 Mark 10. 31. Luke 13. 30.

∥ 20.2 The Roman penny is the eighth part of an ounce, which after five shillings the ounce is seven pence half-penny.

∥ 20.12 Or, have continued one hour only.

* 20.16 ch. 19. 30.

* 20.17 Mark 10 32. Luke 18. 31.

* 20.19 John 18. 32.

* 20.20 Mark 10 35.

* 20.25 Luke 22. 25.

* 20.28 Phil. 2. 7.

* 20.29 Mark 10 46. Luke 18. 35.

* 21.1 Mark 11 1. Luke 19. 29.

* 21.5 Is. 62. 11. Zech. 9. 9. John 12. 15.

* 21.6 Mark 11 4.

* 21.10 Mark 11. 15. Luke 19. 45. John 2. 13.

* 21.13 Is. 56. 7.

* 21.13 Jer. 7. 11. Mark 11. 17. Luke 19. 46.

* 21.16 Ps. 8. 2.

* 21.19 Mark 11. 13.

* 21.23 Mark 11 27. Luke 20. 1.

* 21.26 ch. 14. 5.

* 21.32 ch. 3. 1.

* 21.33 Is. 5. 1. Jer 2. 21. Mark 12. 1. Luke 20. 9.

* 21.38 ch. 26 4. John 11. 53.

* 21.42 Ps. 118. 22 Acts 4. 11.

* 21.44 Is. 8. 14. Rom. 9. 33. 1 Pet. 2. 7.

* 22.1 Luke 14. 16. Rev. 19. 9.

* 22.14 ch. 20. 16.

* 22.15 Mark 12. 13. Luke 20. 20.

∥ 22.19 ch. 20. 2.

∥ 22.20 Or, inscription.

* 22.21 Rom. 13. 7.

* 22.23 Mark 12. 18. Luke 20. 27.

* 22.23 Acts 23. 8.

* 22.24 Deut. 25. 5.

* 22.32 Ex. 8. 6.

* 22.34 Mark 12. 28.

* 22.37 Deut. 6 5. Luke 10. 27.

* 22.39 Lev. 19. 18.

* 22.41 Mark 12. 35. Luke 20. 41.

* 22.44 Ps. 110. 1.

* 23.4 Luke 11. 46.

* 23.5 Num. 15. 38. Deut. 22. 12.

* 23.6 Mark 12. 38. Luke 11. 43.

* 23.8 James 3. 1.

* 23.9 Mal. 1. 6.

* 23.12 Luke 14. 11 & 18. 14.

* 23.13 Luke 11. 52.

* 23.14 Mark 12. 40. Luke 20. 47.

∥ 23.18 Or, a debtor, or, bound.

* 23.23 Luke 11. 42.

* 23.25 Luke 11. 39.

* 23.35 Gen. 4. 8.

* 23.37 Luke 13. 34.

* 23.37 2 Chr. 24. 21.

* 23.37 2 Esd. 1. 30.

* 24.1 Mark 13. 1. Luke 21.6.

* 24.2 Luke 19. 44.

* 24.9 ch. 10. 17. Luke 21. 12 John 16. 2

* 24.15 Mark 13. 14.

* 24.15 Dan. 9. 27.

* 24.23 Mark 13 21. Luke 17. 23

* 24.28 Luke 17. 37.

* 24.29 Is. 13. 10 Ezek. 32. 7. Joel 2. 31 Mark 13. 24 Luke 21. 25.

* 24.30 Rev. 1. 7.

* 24.31 1 Cor. 15. 52 1 Thess. 4. 16.

∥ 24.31 Or, with a trumpet, and a great voice.

* 24.35 Mark 13. 31.

* 24.38 Gen. 7. 5. Luke 17. 26.

* 24.40 Luke 17. 36.

* 24.42 Mark 13. 35.

* 24.43 Luke 12. 39. 1 Thess. 5. 2. Rev. 16. 15.

* 24.45 Luke 12. 42.

∥ 24.51 Or, cut him off.

∥ 25.8 Or, going out.

* 25.13 ch. 24. 42. Mark 13. 33.

* 25.14 Luke 19. 12.

∥ 25.15 187l. 10s. ch. 18. 24.

* 25.29 ch. 13. 12. Mark 4. 25 Luke 8. 18.

* 25.35 Is. 58. 7. Ezek. 18. 7.

* 25.41 Ps. 6. 8. ch. 7. 23.

* 25.46 Dan. 12. 2. John 5. 29.

* 26.2 Mark 14. 1. Luke 22. 1. John 13. 1.

* 26.3 John 11. 47.

* 26.6 Mark 14. 3. John 11. 1.

* 26.11 Deut. 15. 11.

* 26.14 Mark 14. 10. Luke 22. 3.

* 26.17 Mark 14. 12. Luke 22. 7.

* 26.20 Mark 14. 17. Luke 22. 14. John 13. 21.

* 26.23 Ps. 41. 9.

* 26.26 1 Cor. 11. 23.

∥ 26.26 Many Greek copies have, gave thanks.

∥ 26.30 Or, psalm.

* 26.31 Mark 14. 27. John 16. 32.

* 26.31 Zech. 13. 7.

* 26.32 Mark 14. 28 & 16. 7.

* 26.34 John 13 38

* 26.36 Mark 14. 32. Luke 22. 89.

* 26.47 Mark 14. 43 Luke 22. 47. John 18. 3.

* 26.52 Gen. 9. 6. Rev. 13. 10.

* 26.54 Is. 53. 10.

* 26.56 Lam. 4 20

* 26.57 Mark 14. 53. Luke 22 54. John 18. 13.

* 26.61 John 2 19.

* 26.64 ch 16. 27. Rom. 14 10. 1 Thess. 4. 16.

* 26.67 Is. 50. 6.

∥ 26.67 Or, rods.

* 26.69 Mark 14 66 Luke 22. 55. John 18. 25.

‡ 26.75 [1611 words]

* 27.1 Mark 15. 1. Luke 22. 66. John 18. 28.

* 27.5 Acts 1. 18.

* 27.8 Acts 1 19.

* 27.9 Zech. 11. 12.

∥ 27.9 Or, whom they bought of the children of Israel.

‡ 27.13 [1611 saith]

* 27.15 Luke 23. 17.

* 27.20 John 18. 40. Acts 3. 14.

‡ 27.22 [1611 said]

‡ 27.22 [1611 said]

* 27.27 John 19. 2.

∥ 27.27 Or, governor’s house.

* 27.32 Mark 15 21. Luke 23. 26.

* 27.33 John 19. 17.

* 27.35 Ps. 22. 18.

* 27.43 Ps. 22. 8. Wisd. 2. 15, 16.

* 27.46 Ps. 22. 1.

* 27.48 Ps. 69. 21.

‡ 27.52 [1611 of Saints]

* 27.57 Mark 15 42. Luke 23. 50. John 19. 38.

* 28.1 Mark 16. 1. John 20 1

∥ 28.2 Or, had been

* 28.19 Mark 16. 15.

Micah

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

Micah

1

1  The word of the LORD that came to Micah the Morasthite in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem. 2 [†] Hear, all ye people; [*]hearken, O earth, and [†]all that therein is: and let the Lord GOD be witness against you, the Lord from his holy temple. 3  For, behold, [*]the LORD cometh forth out of his [*]place, and will come down, and tread upon the [*]high places of the earth. 4  And [*]the mountains shall be molten under him, and the valleys shall be cleft, as wax before the fire, and as the waters that are poured down [†]a steep place. 5  For the transgression of Jacob is all this, and for the sins of the house of Israel. What is the transgression of Jacob? is it not Samaria? and what are the high places of Judah? are they not Jerusalem? 6  Therefore I will make Samaria as an heap of the field, and as plantings of a vineyard: and I will pour down the stones thereof into the valley, and I will discover the foundations thereof. 7  And all the graven images thereof shall be beaten to pieces, and all the hires thereof shall be burned with the fire, and all the idols thereof will I lay desolate: for she gathered it of the hire of an harlot, and they shall return to the hire of an harlot.

8  Therefore I will wail and howl, I will go stripped and naked: I will make a wailing like the dragons, and mourning as the [†]owls. 9  For [∥]her wound is incurable; for it is come unto Judah; he is come unto the gate of my people, even to Jerusalem.

10 ¶ [*]Declare ye it not at Gath, weep ye not at all: in the house of [∥]Aphrah [*]roll thyself in the dust. 11  Pass ye away, [∥]thou [†]inhabitant of Saphir, having thy [*]shame naked: the inhabitant of [∥]Zaanan came not forth in the mourning of [∥]Beth-ezel; he shall receive of you his standing. 12  For the inhabitant of Maroth [∥]waited carefully for good: but evil came down from the LORD unto the gate of Jerusalem. 13  O thou inhabitant of Lachish, bind the chariot to the swift beast: she is the beginning of the sin to the daughter of Zion: for the transgressions of Israel were found in thee. 14  Therefore shalt thou give presents [∥]to Moresheth-gath: the houses of [∥]Achzib shall be a lie to the kings of Israel. 15  Yet will I bring an heir unto thee, O inhabitant of Mareshah: [∥]he shall come unto Adullam the glory of Israel. 16  Make thee [*]bald, and poll thee for thy delicate children; enlarge thy baldness as the eagle; for they are gone into captivity from thee.

2

1  Woe to them that devise iniquity, and work evil upon their beds! when the morning is light, they practise it, because it is in the power of their hand. 2  And they covet [*]fields, and take them by violence; and houses, and take them away: so they [∥]oppress a man and his house, even a man and his heritage. 3  Therefore thus saith the LORD; Behold, against this family do I devise an evil, from which ye shall not remove your necks; neither shall ye go haughtily: for this time is evil.

4 ¶ In that day shall one take up a parable against you, and lament [†]with a doleful lamentation, and say, We be utterly spoiled: he hath changed the portion of my people: how hath he removed it from me! [∥]turning away he hath divided our fields. 5  Therefore thou shalt have none that shall [*]cast a cord by lot in the congregation of the LORD.

6 [∥][†][*] Prophesy ye not, say they to them that prophesy: they shall not prophesy to them, that they shall not take shame.

7 ¶ O thou that art named the house of Jacob, is the spirit of the LORD [∥]straitened? are these his doings? do not my words do good to him that walketh [†]uprightly? 8  Even [†]of late my people is risen up as an enemy: ye pull off the robe [†]with the garment from them that pass by securely as men averse from war. 9  The [∥]women of my people have ye cast out from their pleasant houses; from their children have ye taken away my glory for ever. 10  Arise ye, and depart; for this is not your rest: because it is polluted, it shall destroy you, even with a sore destruction. 11  If a man [∥]walking in the spirit and falsehood do lie, saying, I will prophesy unto thee of wine and of strong drink; he shall even be the prophet of this people.

12 ¶ I will surely assemble, O Jacob, all of thee; I will surely gather the remnant of Israel; I will put them together as the sheep of Bozrah, as the flock in the midst of their fold: they shall make great noise by reason of the multitude of men. 13  The breaker is come up before them: they have broken up, and have passed through the gate, and are gone out by it: and their king shall pass before them, and the LORD on the head of them.

3

1  And I said, Hear, I pray you, O heads of Jacob, and ye princes of the house of Israel; Is it not for you to know judgment? 2  Who hate the good, and love the evil; who pluck off their skin from off them, and their flesh from off their bones; 3  Who also eat the flesh of my people, and flay their skin from off them; and they break their bones, and chop them in pieces, as for the pot, and as flesh within the caldron. 4  Then shall they cry unto the LORD, but he will not hear them: he will even hide his face from them at that time, as they have behaved themselves ill in their doings.

5 ¶ Thus saith the LORD concerning the prophets that make my people err, that [*]bite with their teeth, and cry, Peace; and he that putteth not into their mouths, they even prepare war against him. 6  Therefore night shall be unto you, [†]that ye shall not have a vision; and it shall be dark unto you, [†]that ye shall not divine; and the sun shall go down over the prophets, and the day shall be dark over them. 7  Then shall the seers be ashamed, and the diviners confounded: yea, they shall all cover their [†]lips; for there is no answer of God.

8 ¶ But truly I am full of power by the spirit of the LORD, and of judgment, and of might, to declare unto Jacob his transgression, and to Israel his sin. 9  Hear this, I pray you, ye heads of the house of Jacob, and princes of the house of Israel, that abhor judgment, and pervert all equity. 10  They build up Zion with [*][†]blood, and Jerusalem with iniquity. 11  The heads thereof judge for reward, and the priests thereof teach for hire, and the prophets thereof divine for money: yet will they lean upon the LORD, [†]and say, Is not the LORD among us? none evil can come upon us. 12  Therefore shall Zion for your sake be [*]plowed as a field, and Jerusalem shall become heaps, and the mountain of the house as the high places of the forest.

4

1  But [*]in the last days it shall come to pass, that the mountain of the house of the LORD shall be established in the top of the mountains, and it shall be exalted above the hills; and people shall flow unto it. 2  And many nations shall come, and say, Come, and let us go up to the mountain of the LORD, and to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths: for the law shall go forth of Zion, and the word of the LORD from Jerusalem.

3 ¶ And he shall judge among many people, and rebuke strong nations afar off; and they shall beat their swords into [*]plowshares, and their spears into [∥]pruninghooks: nation shall not lift up a sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more. 4  But they shall sit every man under his vine and under his fig tree; and none shall make them afraid: for the mouth of the LORD of hosts hath spoken it. 5  For all people will walk every one in the name of his god, and we will walk in the name of the LORD our God for ever and ever. 6  In that day, saith the LORD, will I assemble her that halteth, and I will gather her that is driven out, and her that I have afflicted; 7  And I will make her that [*]halted a remnant, and her that was cast far off a strong nation: and the LORD [*]shall reign over them in mount Zion from henceforth, even for ever.

8 ¶ And thou, O tower of the flock, the strong hold of the daughter of Zion, unto thee shall it come, even the first dominion; the kingdom shall come to the daughter of Jerusalem. 9  Now why dost thou cry out aloud? is there no king in thee? is thy counsellor perished? for pangs have taken thee as a woman in travail. 10  Be in pain, and labour to bring forth, O daughter of Zion, like a woman in travail: for now shalt thou go forth out of the city, and thou shalt dwell in the field, and thou shalt go even to Babylon; there shalt thou be delivered; there the LORD shall redeem thee from the hand of thine enemies.

11 ¶ Now also many nations are gathered against thee, that say, Let her be defiled, and let our eye look upon Zion. 12  But they know not the thoughts of the LORD, neither understand they his counsel: for he shall gather them as the sheaves into the floor. 13  Arise and thresh, O daughter of Zion: for I will make thine horn iron, and I will make thy hoofs brass: and thou shalt beat in pieces many people: and I will consecrate their gain unto the LORD, and their substance unto the Lord of the whole earth.

5

1  Now gather thyself in troops, O daughter of troops: he hath laid siege against us: they shall smite the judge of Israel with a rod upon the cheek. 2  But thou, [*]Beth-lehem Ephratah, though thou be little among the thousands of Judah, yet out of thee shall he come forth unto me that is to be ruler in Israel; whose goings forth have been from of old, from [†]everlasting. 3  Therefore will he give them up, until the time that she which travaileth hath brought forth: then the remnant of his brethren shall return unto the children of Israel.

4 ¶ And he shall stand and [∥]feed in the strength of the LORD, in the majesty of the name of the LORD his God; and they shall abide: for now shall he be great unto the ends of the earth. 5 And this man shall be the peace, when the Assyrian shall come into our land: and when he shall tread in our palaces, then shall we raise against him seven shepherds, and eight [†]principal men. 6  And they shall [†]waste the land of Assyria with the sword, and the land of Nimrod [∥]in the entrances thereof: thus shall he deliver us from the Assyrian, when he cometh into our land, and when he treadeth within our borders.

7  And the remnant of Jacob shall be in the midst of many people as a dew from the LORD, as the showers upon the grass, that tarrieth not for man, nor waiteth for the sons of men.

8 ¶ And the remnant of Jacob shall be among the Gentiles in the midst of many people as a lion among the beasts of the forest, as a young lion among the flocks of [∥]sheep: who, if he go through, both treadeth down, and teareth in pieces, and none can deliver. 9  Thine hand shall be lifted up upon thine adversaries, and all thine enemies shall be cut off. 10  And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the LORD, that I will cut off thy horses out of the midst of thee, and I will destroy thy chariots: 11  And I will cut off the cities of thy land, and throw down all thy strong holds: 12  And I will cut off witchcrafts out of thine hand; and thou shalt have no more soothsayers: 13  Thy graven images also will I cut off, and thy [∥]standing images out of the midst of thee; and thou shalt no more worship the work of thine hands. 14  And I will pluck up thy groves out of the midst of thee: so will I destroy thy [∥]cities. 15  And I will execute vengeance in anger and fury upon the heathen, such as they have not heard.

6

1  Hear ye now what the LORD saith; Arise, contend thou [∥]before the [*]mountains, and let the hills hear thy voice. 2  Hear ye, O mountains, the LORD’s controversy, and ye strong foundations of the earth: for the LORD hath a controversy with his people, and he will plead with Israel. 3  O my people, what have I done unto thee? and wherein have I wearied thee? testify against me. 4  For I brought thee up out of the land of [*]Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the house of servants; and I sent before thee Moses, Aaron, and Miriam. 5  O my people, remember now what [*]Balak king of Moab consulted, and what Balaam the son of Beor answered him from [*]Shittim unto Gilgal; that ye may know the righteousness of the LORD.

6 ¶ Wherewith shall I come before the LORD, and bow myself before the high God? shall I come before him with burnt offerings, with calves [†]of a year old? 7  Will the LORD be pleased with thousands of rams, or with ten thousands of rivers of oil? shall I give my firstborn for my transgression, the fruit of my [†]body for the sin of my soul? 8  He hath [*]shewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the LORD require of thee, but to do justly, and to love mercy, and to [†]walk humbly with thy God?

9  The LORD’s voice crieth unto the city, and [∥]the man of wisdom shall see thy name: hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.

10 ¶ [∥]Are there yet the treasures of wickedness in the house of the wicked, and the [†]scant measure that is abominable? 11 [∥]Shall I count them pure with the wicked balances, and with the bag of deceitful weights? 12  For the rich men thereof are full of violence, and the inhabitants thereof have spoken lies, and their tongue is deceitful in their mouth. 13 Therefore also will I make thee sick in smiting thee, in making thee desolate because of thy sins. 14  Thou shalt eat, but not be satisfied; and thy casting down shall be in the midst of thee; and thou shalt take hold, but shalt not deliver; and that which thou deliverest will I give up to the sword. 15  Thou shalt [*]sow, but thou shalt not reap; thou shalt tread the olives, but thou shalt not anoint thee with oil; and sweet wine, but shalt not drink wine.

16 ¶ For [∥]the statutes of [*]Omri are kept, and all the works of the house of [*]Ahab, and ye walk in their counsels; that I should make thee a [∥]desolation, and the inhabitants thereof an hissing: therefore ye shall bear the reproach of my people.

7

1  Woe is me! for I am as [†]when they have gathered the summer fruits, as the grapegleanings of the vintage: there is no cluster to eat: my soul desired the firstripe fruit. 2  The [*][∥]good man is perished out of the earth: and there is none upright among men: they all lie in wait for blood; they hunt every man his brother with a net.

3 ¶ That they may do evil with both hands earnestly, the prince asketh, and the judge asketh for a reward; and the great man, he uttereth [†]his mischievous desire: so they wrap it up. 4  The best of them is as a brier: the most upright is sharper than a thorn hedge: the day of thy watchmen and thy visitation cometh; now shall be their perplexity.

5 ¶ Trust ye not in a friend, put ye not confidence in a guide: keep the doors of thy mouth from her that lieth in thy bosom. 6  For [*]the son dishonoureth the father, the daughter riseth up against her mother, the daughter in law against her mother in law; a man’s enemies are the men of his own house.

7  Therefore I will look unto the LORD; I will wait for the God of my salvation: my God will hear me.

8 ¶ Rejoice not against me, O mine enemy: when I fall, I shall arise; when I sit in darkness, the LORD shall be a light unto me. 9  I will bear the indignation of the LORD, because I have sinned against him, until he plead my cause, and execute judgment for me: he will bring me forth to the light, and I shall behold his righteousness. 10 [∥]Then she that is mine enemy shall see it, and shame shall cover her which said unto me, [*]Where is the LORD thy God? mine eyes shall behold her: now [†]shall she be trodden down as the mire of the streets. 11  In the day that thy [*]walls are to be built, in that day shall the decree be far removed. 12  In that day also he shall come even to thee from Assyria, [∥]and from the fortified cities, and from the fortress even to the river, and from sea to sea, and from mountain to mountain. 13 [∥] Notwithstanding the land shall be desolate because of them that dwell therein, for the fruit of their doings.

14 ¶ [∥]Feed thy people with thy rod, the flock of thine heritage, which dwell solitarily in the wood, in the midst of Carmel: let them feed in Bashan and Gilead, as in the days of old. 15  According to the days of thy coming out of the land of Egypt will I shew unto him marvellous things.

16 ¶ The nations shall see and be confounded at all their might: they shall lay their hand upon their mouth, their ears shall be deaf. 17  They shall lick the [*]dust like a serpent, they shall move out of their holes like [∥]worms of the earth: they shall be afraid of the LORD our God, and shall fear because of thee. 18 Who is a God like unto thee, that [*]pardoneth iniquity, and passeth by the transgression of the remnant of his heritage? he retaineth not his anger for ever, because he delighteth in mercy. 19  He will turn again, he will have compassion upon us; he will subdue our iniquities; and thou wilt cast all their sins into the depths of the sea. 20  Thou wilt perform the truth to Jacob, and the mercy to Abraham, which thou hast sworn unto our fathers from the days of old.

† 1.2 Heb. Hear, ye people, all of them.

* 1.2 Deut. 32. 1. Is 1. 2.

† 1.2 Heb. the fulness thereof.

* 1.3 Is 26 21.

* 1.3 Ps. 115. 3.

* 1.3 Deut. 32 13. &c 33. 29

* 1.4 Ps. 97. 5

† 1.4 Heb. a descent.

† 1.8 Heb. daughters of the owl.

∥ 1.9 Or, she is grievously sick of her wounds.

* 1.10 2 Sam. 1. 20.

∥ 1.10 That is, Dust.

* 1.10 Jer 6. 26

∥ 1.11 Or, thou that dwellest fairly.

† 1.11 Heb. inhabitress.

* 1.11 Is. 47. 2, 3.

∥ 1.11 Or, the country of flocks.

∥ 1.11 Or, a place near.

∥ 1.12 Or, was grieved.

∥ 1.14 Or, for.

∥ 1.14 That is, A lie.

∥ 1.15 Or, the glory of Israel shall come, &c.

* 1.16 Is. 22. 12.

* 2.2 Is. 5. 8.

∥ 2.2 Or, defraud.

† 2.4 Heb. with a lamentation of lamentations.

∥ 2.4 Or, instead of restoring.

* 2.5 Deut. 32 8, 9.

∥ 2.6 Or, Prophesy not as they prophesy.

† 2.6 Heb. Drop, &c.

* 2.6 Is 30. 10.

∥ 2.7 Or, shortened?

† 2.7 Heb. upright?

† 2.8 Heb. yesterday.

† 2.8 Heb. over against a garment.

∥ 2.9 Or, wives.

∥ 2.11 Or, walk with the wind, and lie falsely.

* 3.5 ch. 2. 11.

† 3.6 Heb. from a vision.

† 3.6 Heb. from divining.

† 3.7 Heb upper lip.

* 3.10 Ezek. 22 27. Zeph. 3. 3.

† 3.10 Heb. bloods.

† 3.11 Heb. saying.

* 3.12 Jer. 26. 18.

* 4.1 Is. 2. 2, &c.

* 4.3 Is. 2 4 Joel 3 10

∥ 4.3 Or, scythes.

* 4.7 Zeph. 3 19.

* 4.7 Dan. 7. 14 Luke 1. 33.

* 5.2 Matt. 2. 6. John 7. 42.

† 5.2 Heb the days of eternity.

∥ 5.4 Or, rule.

† 5.5 Heb. princes of men.

† 5.6 Heb. eat up.

∥ 5.6 Or, with her own naked swords.

∥ 5.8 Or, goats.

∥ 5.13 Or, statues.

∥ 5.14 Or, enemies.

∥ 6.1 Or, with

* 6.1 Is 1. 2.

* 6.4 Ex. 12 51 &c 14 30.

* 6.5 Num. 22 5. &c 23 7.

* 6.5 Num. 25 1 Josh 5. 10

† 6.6 Heb. sons of a year?

† 6.7 Heb. belly.

* 6.8 Deut 10 12.

† 6.8 Heb. humble thyself to walk.

∥ 6.9 Or, thy name shall see that which is

∥ 6.10 Or, Is there yet unto every man an house of the wicked, &c.

† 6.10 Heb. measure of leanness.

∥ 6.11 Or, Shall I be pure with, &c.

* 6.15 Deut. 28. 38. Hag. 1. 6.

∥ 6.16 Or, he doth much keep the &c.

* 6.16 1 Kin. 16. 25, 26.

* 6.16 1 Kin. 16 30, &c.

∥ 6.16 Or, astonishment.

† 7.1 Heb. the gatherings of summer.

* 7.2 Ps. 12. 1. Is. 57. 1.

∥ 7.2 Or, godly. or, merciful.

† 7.3 Heb. the mischief of his soul.

* 7.6 Matt. 10 21, 35, 36. Luke 21. 16.

∥ 7.10 Or, And thou wilt see her that is mine enemy, and cover her with shame.

* 7.10 Ps. 79. 10. &c 115. 2. Joel 2. 17.

† 7.10 Heb. she shall be for a treading down.

* 7.11 Amos 9. 11, &c.

∥ 7.12 Or, even to.

∥ 7.13 Or, After that it hath been.

∥ 7.14 Or, Rule.

* 7.17 Ps. 72. 9.

∥ 7.17 Or, creeping things.

* 7.18 Ex. 34. 6, 7.

Nehemiah

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13

The Book of Nehemiah

1

1  The words of Nehemiah the son of Hachaliah. And it came to pass in the month Chisleu, in the twentieth year, as I was in Shushan the palace, 2  That Hanani, one of my brethren, came, he and certain men of Judah; and I asked them concerning the Jews that had escaped, which were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem. 3  And they said unto me, The remnant that are left of the captivity there in the province are in great affliction and reproach: the wall of Jerusalem also [*]is broken down, and the gates thereof are burned with fire.

4 ¶ And it came to pass, when I heard these words, that I sat down and wept, and mourned certain days, and fasted, and prayed before the God of heaven,

5  And said, I beseech thee, [*]O LORD God of heaven, the great and terrible God, that keepeth covenant and mercy for them that love him and observe his commandments: 6  Let thine ear now be attentive, and thine eyes open, that thou mayest hear the prayer of thy servant, which I pray before thee now, day and night, for the children of Israel thy servants, and confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned against thee: both I and my father’s house have sinned. 7  We have dealt very corruptly against thee, and have not kept the commandments, nor the statutes, nor the judgments, which thou commandedst thy servant Moses. 8  Remember, I beseech thee, the word that thou commandedst thy servant Moses, saying, [*]If ye transgress, I will scatter you abroad among the nations: 9 But if ye turn unto me, and keep my commandments, and do them; [*]though there were of you cast out unto the uttermost part of the heaven, yet will I gather them from thence, and will bring them unto the place that I have chosen to set my name there. 10 Now these are thy servants and thy people, whom thou hast redeemed by thy great power, and by thy strong hand. 11  O [‡]Lord, I beseech thee, let now thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant, and to the prayer of thy servants, who desire to fear thy name: and prosper, I pray thee, thy servant this day, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man. For I was the king’s cupbearer.

2

1  And it came to pass in the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that wine was before him: and I took up the wine, and gave it unto the king. Now I had not been beforetime sad in his presence. 2  Wherefore the king said unto me, Why is thy countenance sad, seeing thou art not sick? this is nothing else but sorrow of heart. Then I was very sore afraid, 3  And said unto the king, Let the king live for ever: why should not my countenance be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers’ sepulchres, lieth waste, and the gates thereof are consumed with fire? 4  Then the king said unto me, For what dost thou make request? So I prayed to the God of heaven. 5  And I said unto the king, If it please the king, and if thy servant have found favour in thy sight, that thou wouldest send me unto Judah, unto the city of my fathers’ sepulchres, that I may build it. 6  And the king said unto me, (the [†]queen also sitting by him,) For how long shall thy journey be? and when wilt thou return? So it pleased the king to send me; and I set him a time. 7  Moreover I said unto the king, If it please the king, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the river, that they may convey me over till I come into Judah; 8  And a letter unto Asaph the keeper of the king’s forest, that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace which appertained to the house, and for the wall of the city, and for the house that I shall enter into. And the king granted me, according to the good hand of my God upon me.

9 ¶ Then I came to the governors beyond the river, and gave them the king’s letters. Now the king had sent captains of the army and horsemen with me. 10  When Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard of it, it grieved them exceedingly that there was come a man to seek the welfare of the children of Israel. 11  So I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days.

12 ¶ And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me; neither told I any man what [‡]my God had put in my heart to do at Jerusalem: neither was there any beast with me, save the beast that I rode upon. 13  And I went out by night by the gate of the valley, even before the dragon well, and to the dung port, and viewed the walls of Jerusalem, which were broken down, and the gates thereof were consumed with fire. 14  Then I went on to the gate of the fountain, and to the king’s pool: but there was no place for the beast that was under me to pass. 15  Then went I up in the night by the brook, and viewed the wall, and turned back, and entered by the gate of the valley, and so returned. 16  And the rulers knew not whither I went, or what I did; neither had I as yet told it to the Jews, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did the work.

17 ¶ Then said I unto them, Ye see the distress that we are in, how Jerusalem lieth waste, and the gates thereof are burned with fire: come, and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we be no more a reproach. 18  Then I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me; as also the king’s words that he had spoken unto me. And they said, Let us rise up and build. So they strengthened their hands for this good work. 19  But when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard it, they laughed us to scorn, and despised us, and said, What is this thing that ye do? will ye rebel against the king? 20  Then answered I them, and said unto them, The God of heaven, he will prosper us; therefore we his servants will arise and build: but ye have no portion, nor right, nor memorial, in Jerusalem.

3

1  Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brethren the priests, and they builded the sheep gate; they sanctified it, and set up the doors of it; even unto the tower of Meah they sanctified it, unto the tower of [*]Hananeel. 2  And [†]next unto him builded the men of Jericho. And next to them builded Zaccur the son of Imri. 3  But the fish gate did the sons of Hassenaah build, who also laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof. 4  And next unto them repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah, the son of Koz. And next unto them repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabeel. And next unto them repaired Zadok the son of Baana. 5  And next unto them the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put not their necks to the work of their [‡]Lord. 6  Moreover the old gate repaired Jehoiada the son of Paseah, and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, and the locks thereof, and the bars thereof. 7  And next unto them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon, and of Mizpah, unto the throne of the governor on this side the river. 8  Next unto him repaired Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, of the goldsmiths. Next unto him also repaired Hananiah the son of one of the apothecaries, and they [∥]fortified Jerusalem unto the broad wall. 9  And next unto them repaired Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem. 10  And next unto them repaired Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, even over against his house. And next unto him repaired Hattush the son of Hashabniah. 11  Malchijah the son of Harim, and Hashub the son of Pahath-moab, repaired the [†]other piece, and the tower of the furnaces. 12  And next unto him repaired Shallum the son of Halohesh, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem, he and his daughters. 13  The valley gate repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and a thousand cubits on the wall unto the dung gate. 14  But the dung gate repaired Malchiah the son of Rechab, the ruler of part of Beth-haccerem; he built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof. 15  But the gate of the fountain repaired Shallun the son of Col-hozeh, the ruler of part of Mizpah; he built it, and covered it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and the wall of the pool of [*]Siloah by the king’s garden, and unto the stairs that go down from the city of David. 16  After him repaired Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of the half part of Beth-zur, unto the place over against the sepulchres of David, and to the [*]pool that was made, and unto the house of the mighty. 17  After him repaired the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani. Next unto him repaired Hashabiah, the ruler of the half part of Keilah, in his part. 18  After him repaired their brethren, Bavai the son of Henadad, the ruler of the half part of Keilah. 19  And next to him repaired Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, another piece over against the going up to the armoury at the turning of the wall. 20  After him Baruch the son of [∥]Zabbai earnestly repaired the other piece, from the turning of the wall unto the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest. 21  After him repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah the son of Koz another piece, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib. 22  And after him repaired the priests, the men of the plain. 23  After him repaired Benjamin and Hashub over against their house. After him repaired Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah by his house. 24  After him repaired Binnui the son of Henadad another piece, from the house of Azariah unto the turning of the wall, even unto the corner. 25  Palal the son of Uzai, over against the turning of the wall, and the tower which lieth out from the king’s high house, that was by the [*]court of the prison. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh. 26  Moreover the Nethinims dwelt in [*][∥]Ophel, unto the place over against the water gate toward the east, and the tower that lieth out. 27  After them the Tekoites repaired another piece, over against the great tower that lieth out, even unto the wall of Ophel. 28  From above the horse gate repaired the priests, every one over against his house. 29  After them repaired Zadok the son of Immer over against his house. After him repaired also Shemaiah the son of Shechaniah, the keeper of the east gate. 30  After him repaired Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, another piece. After him repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah over against his chamber. 31  After him repaired Malchiah the goldsmith’s son unto the place of the Nethinims, and of the merchants, over against the gate Miphkad, and to the [∥]going up of the corner. 32  And between the going up of the corner unto the sheep gate repaired the goldsmiths and the merchants.

4

1  But it came to pass, that when Sanballat heard that we builded the wall, he was wroth, and took great indignation, and mocked the Jews. 2  And he spake before his brethren and the army of Samaria, and said, What do these feeble Jews? will they [†]fortify themselves? will they sacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the stones out of the heaps of the rubbish which are burned? 3  Now Tobiah the Ammonite was by him, and he said, Even that which they build, if a fox go up, he shall even break down their stone wall. 4  Hear, O our God; for we are [†]despised: and turn their reproach upon their own head, and give them for a prey in the land of captivity: 5  And cover not their iniquity, and let not their sin be blotted out from before thee: for they have provoked thee to anger before the builders. 6  So built we the wall; and all the wall was joined together unto the half thereof: for the people had a mind to work.

7 ¶ But it came to pass, that when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the walls of Jerusalem [†]were made up, and that the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth, 8  And conspired all of them together to come and to fight against Jerusalem, and [†]to hinder it. 9  Nevertheless we made our prayer unto our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them. 10  And Judah said, The strength of the bearers of burdens is decayed, and there is much rubbish; so that we are not able to build the wall. 11  And our adversaries said, They shall not know, neither see, till we come in the midst among them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease. 12  And it came to pass, that when the Jews which dwelt by them came, they said unto us ten times, [∥]From all places whence ye shall return unto us they will be upon you.

13 ¶ Therefore set I [†]in the lower places behind the wall, and on the higher places, I even set the people after their families with their swords, their spears, and their bows. 14  And I looked, and rose up, and said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, Be not ye afraid of them: remember the Lord, which is great and terrible, and fight for your brethren, your sons, and your daughters, your wives, and your houses. 15  And it came to pass, when our enemies heard that it was known unto us, and God had brought their counsel to nought, that we returned all of us to the wall, every one unto his work.

16  And it came to pass from that time forth, that the half of my servants wrought in the work, and the other half of them held both the spears, the shields, and the bows, and the habergeons; and the rulers were behind all the house of Judah. 17  They which builded on the wall, and they that bare burdens, with those that laded, every one with one of his hands wrought in the work, and with the other hand held a weapon. 18  For the builders, every one had his sword girded [†]by his side, and so builded. And he that sounded the trumpet was by me.

19 ¶ And I said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, The work is great and large, and we are separated upon the wall, one far from another. 20  In what place therefore ye hear the sound of the trumpet, resort ye thither unto us: our God shall fight for us. 21  So we laboured in the work: and half of them held the spears from the rising of the morning till the stars appeared. 22  Likewise at the same time said I unto the people, Let every one with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night they may be a guard to us, and labour on the day. 23  So neither I, nor my brethren, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard which followed me, none of us put off our clothes, [∥]saving that every one put them off for washing.

5

1  And there was a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brethren the Jews. 2  For there were that said, We, our sons, and our daughters, are many: therefore we take up corn for them, that we may eat, and live. 3  Some also there were that said, We have mortgaged our lands, vineyards, and houses, that we might buy corn, because of the dearth. 4  There were also that said, We have borrowed money for the king’s tribute, and that upon our lands and vineyards. 5  Yet now our flesh is as the flesh of our brethren, our children as their children: and, lo, we bring into bondage our sons and our daughters to be servants, and some of our daughters are brought unto bondage already: neither is it in our power to redeem them; for other men have our lands and vineyards.

6 ¶ And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words. 7  Then [†]I consulted with myself, and I rebuked the nobles, and the rulers, and said unto them, Ye exact usury, every one of his brother. And I set a great assembly against them. 8  And I said unto them, We after our ability have [*]redeemed our brethren the Jews, which were sold unto the heathen; and will ye even sell your brethren? or shall they be sold unto us? Then held they their peace, and found nothing to answer. 9  Also I said, It is not good that ye do: ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God because of the reproach of the heathen our enemies? 10 I likewise, and my brethren, and my servants, might exact of them money and corn: I pray you, let us leave off this usury. 11  Restore, I pray you, to them, even this day, their lands, their vineyards, their oliveyards, and their houses, also the hundredth part of the money, and of the corn, the wine, and the oil, that ye exact of them. 12  Then said they, We will restore them, and will require nothing of them; so will we do as thou sayest. Then I called the priests, and took an oath of them, that they should do according to this promise. 13  Also I shook my lap, and said, So God shake out every man from his house, and from his labour, that performeth not this promise, even thus be he shaken out, and [†]emptied. And all the congregation said, Amen, and praised the LORD. And the people did according to this promise.

14 ¶ Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even unto the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that is, twelve years, I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the governor. 15  But the former governors that had been before me were chargeable unto the people, and had taken of them bread and wine, beside forty shekels of silver; yea, even their servants bare rule over the people: but so did not I, because of the fear of God. 16  Yea, also I continued in the work of this wall, neither bought we any land: and all my servants were gathered thither unto the work. 17 Moreover there were at my table an hundred and fifty of the Jews and rulers, beside those that came unto us from among the heathen that are about us. 18 Now that which was prepared for me daily was one ox and six choice sheep; also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten days store of all sorts of wine: yet for all this required not I the bread of the governor, because the bondage was heavy upon this people. 19 [*] Think upon me, my God, for good, according to all that I have done for this people.

6

1  Now it came to pass, when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and Geshem the Arabian, and the rest of our enemies, heard that I had builded the wall, and that there was no breach left therein; (though at that time I had not set up the doors upon the gates;) 2  That Sanballat and Geshem sent unto me, saying, Come, let us meet together in some one of the villages in the plain of Ono. But they thought to do me mischief. 3  And I sent messengers unto them, saying, I am doing a great work, so that I cannot come down: why should the work cease, whilst I leave it, and come down to you? 4  Yet they sent unto me four times after this sort; and I answered them after the same manner. 5  Then sent Sanballat his servant unto me in like manner the fifth time with an open letter in his hand; 6 Wherein was written, It is reported among the heathen, and [∥]Gashmu saith it, that thou and the Jews think to rebel: for which cause thou buildest the wall, that thou mayest be their king, according to these words. 7  And thou hast also appointed prophets to preach of thee at Jerusalem, saying, There is a king in Judah: and now shall it be reported to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together. 8  Then I sent unto him, saying, There are no such things done as thou sayest, but thou feignest them out of thine own heart. 9  For they all made us afraid, saying, Their hands shall be weakened from the work, that it be not done. Now therefore, O God, strengthen my hands.

10  Afterward I came unto the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabeel, who was shut up; and he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, within the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple: for they will come to slay thee; yea, in the night will they come to slay thee. 11  And I said, Should such a man as I flee? and who is there, that, being as I am, would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in. 12  And, lo, I perceived that God had not sent him; but that he pronounced this prophecy against me: for Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him. 13 Therefore was he hired, that I should be afraid, and do so, and sin, and that they might have matter for an evil report, that they might reproach me. 14  My God, think thou upon Tobiah and Sanballat according to these their works, and on the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that would have put me in fear.

15 ¶ So the wall was finished in the twenty and fifth day of the month Elul, in fifty and two days. 16  And it came to pass, that when all our enemies heard thereof, and all the heathen that were about us saw these things, they were much cast down in their own eyes: for they perceived that this work was wrought of our God.

17 ¶ Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah [†]sent many letters unto Tobiah, and the letters of Tobiah came unto them. 18 For there were many in Judah sworn unto him, because he was the son in law of Shechaniah the son of Arah; and his son Johanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah. 19  Also they reported his good deeds before me, and uttered my [∥]words to him. And Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear.

7

1  Now it came to pass, when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the porters and the singers and the Levites were appointed, 2  That I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the ruler of the palace, charge over Jerusalem: for he was a faithful man, and feared God above many. 3  And I said unto them, Let not the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun be hot; and while they stand by, let them shut the doors, and bar them: and appoint watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every one in his watch, and every one to be over against his house. 4  Now the city was [†]large and great: but the people were few therein, and the houses were not builded.

5 ¶ And my God put into mine heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, that they might be reckoned by genealogy. And I found a register of the genealogy of them which came up at the first, and found written therein, 6 [*]These are the children of the province, that went up out of the captivity, of those that had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and came again to Jerusalem and to Judah, every one unto his city; 7  Who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, [∥]Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number, I say, of the men of the people of Israel was this; 8  The children of Parosh, two thousand an hundred seventy and two. 9  The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two. 10  The children of Arah, six hundred fifty and two. 11  The children of Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand and eight hundred and eighteen. 12  The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. 13  The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty and five. 14  The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore. 15  The children of [∥]Binnui, six hundred forty and eight. 16  The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and eight. 17  The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty and two. 18  The children of Adonikam, six hundred threescore and seven. 19  The children of Bigvai, two thousand threescore and seven. 20  The children of Adin, six hundred fifty and five. 21  The children of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight. 22  The children of Hashum, three hundred twenty and eight. 23  The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and four. 24  The children of [∥]Hariph, an hundred and twelve. 25  The children of [∥]Gibeon, ninety and five. 26  The men of Beth-lehem and Netophah, an hundred fourscore and eight. 27  The men of Anathoth, an hundred twenty and eight. 28  The men of [∥]Beth-azmaveth, forty and two. 29  The men of [∥]Kirjath-jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty and three. 30  The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty and one. 31  The men of Michmas, an hundred and twenty and two. 32  The men of Beth-el and Ai, an hundred twenty and three. 33  The men of the other Nebo, fifty and two. 34  The children of the other [*]Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. 35  The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty. 36  The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five. 37  The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and one. 38  The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty.

39 ¶ The priests: the children of [*]Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three. 40  The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two. 41  The children of Pashur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven. 42  The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.

43 ¶ The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, and of the children of [∥]Hodevah, seventy and four.

44 ¶ The singers: the children of Asaph, an hundred forty and eight.

45 ¶ The porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, an hundred thirty and eight.

46 ¶ The Nethinims: the children of Ziha, the children of Hashupha, the children of Tabbaoth, 47  The children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon, 48  The children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Shalmai, 49  The children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, 50  The children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, 51  The children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Phaseah, 52  The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephishesim, 53  The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur, 54  The children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha, 55  The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Tamah, 56  The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.

57 ¶ The children of Solomon’s servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida, 58  The children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel, 59  The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of Zebaim, the children of [∥]Amon. 60  All the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants, were three hundred ninety and two. 61 [*]And these were they which went up also from Tel-melah, Tel-haresha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer: but they could not shew their father’s house, nor their [∥]seed, whether they were of Israel. 62  The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty and two.

63 ¶ And of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the children of Barzillai, which took one of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite to wife, and was called after their name. 64  These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but it was not found: therefore were they, as polluted, put from the priesthood. 65  And [∥]the Tirshatha said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and Thummim.

66 ¶ The whole congregation together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore, 67  Beside their manservants and their maidservants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and they had two hundred forty and five singing men and singing women. 68  Their horses, seven hundred thirty and six: their mules, two hundred forty and five: 69  Their camels, four hundred thirty and five: six thousand seven hundred and twenty asses.

70 ¶ And [†]some of the chief of the fathers gave unto the work. The Tirshatha gave to the treasure a thousand drams of gold, fifty basons, five hundred and thirty priests’ garments. 71 And some of the chief of the fathers gave to the treasure of the work twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand and two hundred pound of silver. 72 And that which the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand pound of silver, and threescore and seven priests’ garments. 73  So the priests, and the Levites, and the porters, and the singers, and some of the people, and the Nethinims, and all Israel, dwelt in their cities; and when the seventh month came, the children of Israel were in their cities.

8

1  And all the people gathered themselves together as one man into the street that was before the water gate; [*]and they spake unto Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which the LORD had commanded to Israel. 2  And Ezra the priest brought the law before the congregation both of men and women, and all [†]that could hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month. 3  And he read therein before the street that was before the water gate [†]from the morning until midday, before the men and the women, and those that could understand; and the ears of all the people were attentive unto the book of the law. 4  And Ezra the scribe stood upon a [†]pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah, and Urijah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchiah, and Hashum, and Hashbadana, Zechariah, and Meshullam. 5  And Ezra opened the book in the [†]sight of all the people; (for he was above all the people;) and when he opened it, all the people stood up: 6  And Ezra blessed the LORD, the great God. And all the people answered, Amen, Amen, with lifting up their hands: and they bowed their heads, and worshipped the LORD with their faces to the ground. 7  Also Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodijah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law: and the people stood in their place. 8  So they read in the book in the law of God distinctly, and gave the sense, and caused them to understand the reading.

9 ¶ And Nehemiah, which is [∥]the Tirshatha, and Ezra the priest the scribe, and the Levites that taught the people, said unto all the people, This day is holy unto the LORD your God; mourn not, nor weep. For all the people wept, when they heard the words of the law. 10  Then he said unto them, Go your way, eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send portions unto them for whom nothing is prepared: for this day is holy unto our [‡]Lord: neither be ye sorry; for the joy of the LORD is your strength. 11  So the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Hold your peace, for the day is holy; neither be ye grieved. 12  And all the people went their way to eat, and to drink, and to send portions, and to make great mirth, because they had understood the words that were declared unto them.

13 ¶ And on the second day were gathered together the chief of the fathers of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, unto Ezra the scribe, even [∥]to understand the words of the law. 14  And they found written in the law which the LORD had commanded [†]by Moses, that the children of Israel should dwell in [*]booths in the feast of the seventh month: 15  And that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, Go forth unto the mount, and fetch olive branches, and pine branches, and myrtle branches, and palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make booths, as it is written.

16 ¶ So the people went forth, and brought them, and made themselves booths, every one upon the roof of his house, and in their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the street of the water gate, and in the street of the gate of Ephraim. 17  And all the congregation of them that were come again out of the captivity made booths, and sat under the booths: for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun unto that day had not the children of Israel done so. And there was very great gladness. 18  Also day by day, from the first day unto the last day, he read in the book of the law of God. And they kept the feast seven days; and on the eighth day was [†]a solemn assembly, according unto the manner.

9

1  Now in the twenty and fourth day of [*]this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting, and with sackclothes, and earth upon them. 2  And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all [†]strangers, and stood and confessed their sins, and the iniquities of their fathers. 3  And they stood up in their place, and read in the book of the law of the LORD their God one fourth part of the day; and another fourth part they confessed, and worshipped the LORD their God.

4 ¶ Then stood up upon the [∥]stairs, of the Levites, Jeshua, and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, and Chenani, and cried with a loud voice unto the LORD their God. 5  Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabniah, Sherebiah, Hodijah, Shebaniah, and Pethahiah, said, Stand up and bless the LORD your God for ever and ever: and blessed be thy glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise. 6 Thou, even thou, art LORD alone; [*]thou hast made heaven, the heaven of heavens, with all their host, the earth, and all things that are therein, the seas, and all that is therein, and thou preservest them all; and the host of heaven worshippeth thee. 7 Thou art the LORD the God, who didst choose [*]Abram, and broughtest him forth out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gavest him the name of Abraham; 8  And foundest his heart [*]faithful before thee, and madest a [*]covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Jebusites, and the Girgashites, to give it, I say, to his seed, and hast performed thy words; for thou art righteous: 9 [*] And didst see the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heardest their cry by the Red sea; 10  And [*]shewedst signs and wonders upon Pharaoh, and on all his servants, and on all the people of his land: for thou knewest that they dealt proudly against them. So didst thou get thee a name, as it is this day. 11 [*] And thou didst divide the sea before them, so that they went through the midst of the sea on the dry land; and their persecutors thou threwest into the deeps, as a stone into the [*]mighty waters. 12  Moreover thou [*]leddest them in the day by a cloudy pillar; and in the night by a pillar of fire, to give them light in the way wherein they should go. 13 [*] Thou camest down also upon mount Sinai, and spakest with them from heaven, and gavest them right judgments, and [†]true laws, good statutes and commandments: 14  And madest known unto them thy holy sabbath, and commandedst them precepts, statutes, and laws, by the hand of Moses thy servant: 15  And [*]gavest them bread from heaven for their hunger, and broughtest forth water for them out of the rock for their thirst, and promisedst them that they should [*]go in to possess the land [†]which thou hadst sworn to give them. 16  But they and our fathers dealt proudly, and hardened their necks, and hearkened not to thy commandments, 17  And refused to obey, neither were mindful of [‡]thy wonders that thou didst among them; but hardened their necks, and in their rebellion appointed [*]a captain to return to their bondage: but thou art [†]a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and forsookest them not. 18  Yea, [*]when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This is thy God that brought thee up out of Egypt, and had wrought great provocations; 19  Yet thou in thy manifold mercies forsookest them not in the wilderness: the [*]pillar of the cloud departed not from them by day, to lead them in the way; neither the pillar of fire by night, to shew them light, and the way wherein they should go. 20  Thou gavest also thy [*]good spirit to instruct them, and withheldest not thy [*]manna from their mouth, and gavest them water for their thirst. 21  Yea, forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness, so that they lacked nothing; their [*]clothes waxed not old, and their feet swelled not. 22  Moreover thou gavest them kingdoms and nations, and didst divide them into corners: so they possessed the land of [*]Sihon, and the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan. 23  Their children also multipliedst thou as the stars of heaven, and broughtest them into the land, concerning which thou hadst promised to their fathers, that they should go in to possess it. 24  So the children went in and possessed the land, and thou subduedst before them the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, and gavest them into their hands, with their kings, and the people of the land, that they might do with them [†]as they would. 25  And they took strong cities, and a fat land, and possessed houses full of all goods, [∥]wells digged, vineyards, and oliveyards, and [†]fruit trees in abundance: so they did eat, and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in thy great goodness. 26  Nevertheless they were disobedient, and rebelled against thee, and cast thy law behind their backs, and slew thy [*]prophets which testified against them to turn them to thee, and they wrought great provocations. 27  Therefore thou deliveredst them into the hand of their enemies, who vexed them: and in the time of their trouble, when they cried unto thee, thou heardest them from heaven; and according to thy manifold mercies thou gavest them saviours, who saved them out of the hand of their enemies. 28  But after they had rest, [†]they did evil again before thee: therefore leftest thou them in the hand of their enemies, so that they had the dominion over them: yet when they returned, and cried unto thee, thou heardest them from heaven; and many times didst thou deliver them according to thy mercies; 29  And testifiedst against them, that thou mightest bring them again unto thy law: yet they dealt proudly, and hearkened not unto thy commandments, but sinned against thy judgments, (which if a man do, he shall live in them;) and [†]withdrew the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear. 30  Yet many years didst thou [†]forbear them, and testifiedst [*]against them by thy spirit [†]in thy prophets: yet would they not give ear: therefore gavest thou them into the hand of the people of the lands. 31  Nevertheless for thy great mercies’ sake thou didst not utterly consume them, nor forsake them; for thou art a gracious and merciful God. 32  Now therefore, our God, the great, the [*]mighty, and the terrible God, who keepest covenant and mercy, let not all the [†]trouble seem little before thee, [†]that hath come upon us, on our kings, on our princes, and on our priests, and on our prophets, and on our fathers, and on all thy people, since the time of the kings of Assyria unto this day. 33 Howbeit thou art just in all that is brought upon us; for thou hast done right, but we have done wickedly: 34  Neither have our kings, our princes, our priests, nor our fathers, kept thy law, nor hearkened unto thy commandments and thy testimonies, wherewith thou didst testify against them. 35  For they have not served thee in their kingdom, and in thy great goodness that thou gavest them, and in the large and fat land which thou gavest before them, neither turned they from their wicked works. 36 Behold, we are servants this day, and for the land that thou gavest unto our fathers to eat the fruit thereof and the good thereof, behold, we are servants in it: 37  And it yieldeth much increase unto the kings whom thou hast set over us because of our sins: also they have dominion over our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure, and we are in great distress. 38  And because of all this we make a sure covenant, and write it; and our princes, Levites, and priests, [†]seal unto it.

10

1  Now [†]those that sealed were, Nehemiah, [∥]the Tirshatha, the son of Hachaliah, and Zidkijah, 2  Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah, 3  Pashur, Amariah, Malchijah, 4  Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch, 5  Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah, 6  Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch, 7  Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin, 8  Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah: these were the priests. 9  And the Levites: both Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel; 10  And their brethren, Shebaniah, Hodijah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan, 11  Micha, Rehob, Hashabiah, 12  Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah, 13  Hodijah, Bani, Beninu. 14  The chief of the people; Parosh, Pahath-moab, Elam, Zatthu, Bani, 15  Bunni, Azgad, Bebai, 16  Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin, 17  Ater, Hizkijah, Azzur, 18  Hodijah, Hashum, Bezai, 19  Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai, 20  Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir, 21  Meshezabeel, Zadok, Jaddua, 22  Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah, 23  Hoshea, Hananiah, Hashub, 24  Hallohesh, Pileha, Shobek, 25  Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah, 26  And Ahijah, Hanan, Anan, 27  Malluch, Harim, Baanah.

28 ¶ [*]And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the porters, the singers, the Nethinims, and all they that had separated themselves from the people of the lands unto the law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, every one having knowledge, and having understanding; 29  They clave to their brethren, their nobles, and entered into a curse, and into an oath, to walk in God’s law, which was given [†]by Moses the servant of God, and to observe and do all the commandments of the LORD our Lord, and his judgments and his statutes; 30  And that we would not give [*]our daughters unto the people of the land, nor take their daughters for our sons: 31 [*]And if the people of the land bring ware or any victuals on the sabbath day to sell, that we would not buy it of them on the sabbath, or on the holy day: and that we would leave the seventh year, and the [*]exaction of [†]every debt.

32  Also we made ordinances for us, to charge ourselves yearly with the third part of a shekel for the service of the house of our God; 33  For the shewbread, and for the continual meat offering, and for the continual burnt offering, of the sabbaths, of the new moons, for the set feasts, and for the holy things, and for the sin offerings to make an atonement for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God. 34  And we cast the lots among the priests, the Levites, and the people, for the wood offering, to bring it into the house of our God, after the houses of our fathers, at times appointed year by year, to burn upon the altar of the LORD our God, as it is written in the [*]law: 35  And to bring the firstfruits of our ground, and the firstfruits of all fruit of all trees, year by year, unto the house of the LORD: 36  Also the firstborn of our sons, and of our cattle, as it is written [*]in the law, and the firstlings of our herds and of our flocks, to bring to the house of our God, unto the priests that minister in the house of our God: 37 And that we should bring the firstfruits of our dough, and our offerings, and the fruit of all manner of trees, of wine and of oil, unto the priests, to the chambers of the house of our God; and the tithes of our ground unto the Levites, that the same Levites might have the tithes in all the cities of our tillage. 38  And the priest the son of Aaron shall be with the Levites, [*]when the Levites take tithes: and the Levites shall bring up the tithe of the tithes unto the house of our God, to the chambers, into the treasure house. 39  For the children of Israel and the children of Levi shall bring the offering of the corn, of the new wine, and the oil, unto the chambers, where are the vessels of the sanctuary, and the priests that minister, and the porters, and the singers: and we will not forsake the house of our God.

11

1  And the rulers of the people dwelt at Jerusalem: the rest of the people also cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts to dwell in other cities. 2  And the people blessed all the men, that willingly offered themselves to dwell at Jerusalem.

3 ¶ Now these are the chief of the province that dwelt in Jerusalem: but in the cities of Judah dwelt every one in his possession in their cities, to wit, Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants. 4  And at Jerusalem dwelt certain of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin. Of the children of Judah; Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalaleel, of the children of Perez; 5  And Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Col-hozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of Shiloni. 6  All the sons of Perez that dwelt at Jerusalem were four hundred threescore and eight valiant men. 7 And these are the sons of Benjamin; Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jesaiah. 8  And after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty and eight. 9  And Joel the son of Zichri was their overseer: and Judah the son of Senuah was second over the city. 10  Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin. 11  Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, was the ruler of the house of God. 12  And their brethren that did the work of the house were eight hundred twenty and two: and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchiah, 13  And his brethren, chief of the fathers, two hundred forty and two: and Amashai the son of Azareel, the son of Ahasai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer, 14  And their brethren, mighty men of valour, an hundred twenty and eight: and their overseer was Zabdiel, [∥]the son of one of the great men. 15  Also of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hashub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni; 16  And Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chief of the Levites, [†]had the oversight of the outward business of the house of God. 17  And Mattaniah the son of Micha, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, was the principal to begin the thanksgiving in prayer: and Bakbukiah the second among his brethren, and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun. 18  All the Levites in the holy city were two hundred fourscore and four. 19  Moreover the porters, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren that kept [†]the gates, were an hundred seventy and two.

20 ¶ And the residue of Israel, of the priests, and the Levites, were in all the cities of Judah, every one in his inheritance. 21 [*] But the Nethinims dwelt in [∥]Ophel: and Ziha and Gispa were over the Nethinims. 22  The overseer also of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micha. Of the sons of Asaph, the singers were over the business of the house of God. 23 For it was the king’s commandment concerning them, that [∥]a certain portion should be for the singers, due for every day. 24  And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabeel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king’s hand in all matters concerning the people. 25  And for the villages, with their fields, some of the children of Judah dwelt at Kirjath-arba, and in the villages thereof, and at Dibon, and in the villages thereof, and at Jekabzeel, and in the villages thereof, 26  And at Jeshua, and at Moladah, and at Beth-phelet, 27  And at Hazar-shual, and at Beer-sheba, and in the villages thereof, 28  And at Ziklag, and at Mekonah, and in the villages thereof, 29  And at En-rimmon, and at Zareah, and at Jarmuth, 30  Zanoah, Adullam, and in their villages, at Lachish, and the fields thereof, at Azekah, and in the villages thereof. And they dwelt from Beer-sheba unto the valley of Hinnom. 31  The children also of Benjamin [∥]from Geba dwelt [∥]at Michmash, and Aija, and Beth-el, and in their villages, 32  And at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah, 33  Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim, 34  Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat, 35  Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen. 36  And of the Levites were divisions in Judah, and in Benjamin.

12

1 Now these are the [*]priests and the Levites that went up with Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua: Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra, 2  Amariah, [∥]Malluch, Hattush, 3 [∥] Shechaniah, [∥]Rehum, [∥]Meremoth, 4  Iddo, [∥]Ginnetho, Abijah, 5 [∥] Miamin, [∥]Maadiah, Bilgah, 6  Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah, 7 [∥] Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These were the chief of the priests and of their brethren in the days of Jeshua. 8  Moreover the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, and Mattaniah, which was over [∥]the thanksgiving, he and his brethren. 9  Also Bakbukiah and Unni, their brethren, were over against them in the watches.

10 ¶ And Jeshua begat Joiakim, Joiakim also begat Eliashib, and Eliashib begat Joiada, 11  And Joiada begat Jonathan, and Jonathan begat Jaddua. 12  And in the days of Joiakim were priests, the chief of the fathers: of Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah; 13  Of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan; 14  Of Melicu, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph; 15  Of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai; 16  Of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam; 17  Of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai; 18  Of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan; 19  And of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi; 20  Of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber; 21  Of Hilkiah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethaneel.

22 ¶ The Levites in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, were recorded chief of the fathers: also the priests, to the reign of Darius the Persian. 23  The sons of Levi, the chief of the fathers, were written in the book of the [*]chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib. 24  And the chief of the Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brethren over against them, to praise and to give thanks, according to the commandment of David the man of God, ward over against ward. 25  Mattaniah, and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub, were porters keeping the ward at the [∥]thresholds of the gates. 26 These were in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and of Ezra the priest, the scribe.

27 ¶ And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought the Levites out of all their places, to bring them to Jerusalem, to keep the dedication with gladness, both with thanksgivings, and with singing, with cymbals, psalteries, and with harps. 28  And the sons of the singers gathered themselves together, both out of the plain country round about Jerusalem, and from the villages of Netophathi; 29  Also from the house of Gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and Azmaveth: for the singers had builded them villages round about Jerusalem. 30  And the priests and the Levites purified themselves, and purified the people, and the gates, and the wall. 31  Then I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall, and appointed two great companies of them that gave thanks, whereof one went on the right hand upon the wall toward the dung gate: 32  And after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the princes of Judah, 33  And Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam, 34  Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah, 35 And certain of the priests’ sons with trumpets; namely, Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Michaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph: 36  And his brethren, Shemaiah, and Azarael, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethaneel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the man of God, and Ezra the scribe before them. 37  And at the fountain gate, which was over against them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the going up of the wall, above the house of David, even unto the water gate eastward. 38  And the other company of them that gave thanks went over against them, and I after them, and the half of the people upon the wall, from beyond the tower of the furnaces even unto the broad wall; 39  And from above the gate of Ephraim, and above the old gate, and above the fish gate, and the tower of Hananeel, and the tower of Meah, even unto the sheep gate: and they stood still in the prison gate. 40  So stood the two companies of them that gave thanks in the house of God, and I, and the half of the rulers with me: 41  And the priests; Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Michaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, and Hananiah, with trumpets; 42  And Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers [†]sang loud, with Jezrahiah their overseer. 43  Also that day they offered great sacrifices, and rejoiced: for God had made them rejoice with great joy: the wives also and the children rejoiced: so that the joy of Jerusalem was heard even afar off.

44 ¶ And at that time were some appointed over the chambers for the treasures, for the offerings, for the firstfruits, and for the tithes, to gather into them out of the fields of the cities the portions [∥]of the law for the priests and Levites: [†]for Judah rejoiced for the priests and for the Levites [†]that waited. 45  And both the singers and the porters kept the ward of their God, and the ward of the purification, [*]according to the commandment of David, and of Solomon his son. 46  For in the days of David [*]and Asaph of old there were chief of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgiving unto God. 47  And all Israel in the days of Zerubbabel, and in the days of Nehemiah, gave the portions of the singers and the porters, every day his portion: and they [∥]sanctified holy things unto the Levites; [*]and the Levites sanctified them unto the children of Aaron.

13

1  On that day [†]they read in the [*]book of Moses in the [†]audience of the people; and therein was found written, that the Ammonite and the Moabite should not come into the congregation of God for ever; 2 [*] Because they met not the children of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them, that he should curse them: howbeit our God turned the curse into a blessing. 3  Now it came to pass, when they had heard the law, that they separated from Israel all the mixed multitude.

4 ¶ And before this, Eliashib the priest, [†]having the oversight of the chamber of the house of our God, was allied unto Tobiah: 5  And he had prepared for him a great chamber, where aforetime they laid the meat offerings, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithes of the corn, the new wine, and the oil, [†]which was commanded to be given to the Levites, and the singers, and the porters; and the offerings of the priests. 6 But in all this time was not I at Jerusalem: for in the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon came I unto the king, and [†]after certain days [∥]obtained I leave of the king: 7  And I came to Jerusalem, and understood of the evil that Eliashib did for Tobiah, in preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of God. 8  And it grieved me sore: therefore I cast forth all the household stuff of Tobiah out of the chamber. 9  Then I commanded, and they cleansed the chambers: and thither brought I again the vessels of the house of God, with the meat offering and the frankincense.

10 ¶ And I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not been given them: for the Levites and the singers, that did the work, were fled every one to his field. 11  Then contended I with the rulers, and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together, and set them in their [†]place. 12  Then brought all Judah the tithe of the corn and the new wine and the oil unto the [∥]treasuries. 13  And I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah: and [†]next to them was Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah: for they were counted faithful, and [†]their office was to distribute unto their brethren. 14 [*] Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my [†]good deeds that I have done for the house of my God, and for the [∥]offices thereof.

15 ¶ In those days saw I in Judah some treading wine presses on the sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and lading asses; as also wine, grapes, and figs, and all manner of burdens, which they brought into Jerusalem on the sabbath day: and I testified against them in the day wherein they sold victuals. 16  There dwelt men of Tyre also therein, which brought fish, and all manner of ware, and sold on the sabbath unto the children of Judah, and in Jerusalem. 17  Then I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said unto them, What evil thing is this that ye do, and profane the sabbath day? 18  Did not your fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us, and upon this city? yet ye bring more wrath upon Israel by profaning the sabbath. 19  And it came to pass, that when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the sabbath, I commanded that the gates should be shut, and charged that they should not be opened till after the sabbath: and some of my servants set I at the gates, that there should no burden be brought in on the sabbath day. 20  So the merchants and sellers of all kind of ware lodged without Jerusalem once or twice. 21  Then I testified against them, and said unto them, Why lodge ye [†]about the wall? if ye do so again, I will lay hands on you. From that time forth came they no more on the sabbath. 22  And I commanded the Levites that they should cleanse themselves, and that they should come and keep the gates, to sanctify the sabbath day. Remember me, O my God, concerning this also, and spare me according to the [∥]greatness of thy mercy.

23 ¶ In those days also saw I Jews that [†]had married wives of Ashdod, of Ammon, and of Moab: 24  And their children spake half in the speech of Ashdod, and [†]could not speak in the Jews’ language, but according to the language [†]of each people. 25  And I contended with them, and [∥]cursed them, and smote certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them swear by God, saying, Ye shall not give your daughters unto their sons, nor take their daughters unto your sons, or for yourselves. 26  Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? yet among many nations was there no king like him, who was beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel: [*]nevertheless even him did outlandish women cause to sin. 27  Shall we then hearken unto you to do all this great evil, to transgress against our God in marrying strange wives? 28 And one of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, was son in law to Sanballat the Horonite: therefore I chased him from me. 29  Remember them, O my God, [†]because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood, and of the Levites. 30  Thus cleansed I them from all strangers, and appointed the wards of the priests and the Levites, every one in his business; 31  And for the wood offering, at times appointed, and for the firstfruits. Remember me, O my God, for good.

* 1.3 2 Kings 25. 10.

* 1.5 Dan. 9. 4.

* 1.8 Deut. 4. 25, &c.

* 1.9 Deut. 30. 4.

‡ 1.11 [1611 Lord]

† 2.6 Heb. wife.

‡ 2.12 [1611 omits my]

* 3.1 Jer 31. 38.

† 3.2 Heb. at his hand.

‡ 3.5 [1611 Lord]

∥ 3.8 Or, left Jerusalem unto the broad wall.

† 3.11 Heb. second measure.

* 3.15 John 9. 7.

* 3.16 2 Kings 20. 20.

∥ 3.20 Or, Zaccal.

* 3.25 Jer. 32. 2

* 3.26 2 Chr. 27. 3.

∥ 3.26 Or, the tower.

∥ 3.31 Or, corner chamber.

† 4.2 Heb. leave to themselves.

† 4.4 Heb. despite.

† 4.7 Heb. ascended.

† 4.8 Heb. to make an error to it.

∥ 4.12 Or, That from all places ye must return to us.

† 4.13 Heb. from the lower parts of the place, &c.

† 4.18 Heb. on his loins.

∥ 4.23 Or, every one went with his weapon for water.

† 5.7 Heb. my heart consulted in me.

* 5.8 Lev. 25. 48.

† 5.13 Heb. empty, or, void.

* 5.19 ch. 13. 22.

∥ 6.6 ver. 2.

† 6.17 Heb. multiplied [their] letters passing to Tobiah.

∥ 6.19 Or, matters.

† 7.4 Heb. broad in spaces.

* 7.6 Ezra 2. 1. &c.

∥ 7.7 Or, Seraiah.

∥ 7.15 Or, Bam.

∥ 7.24 Or, Jora.

∥ 7.25 Or, Gibbar.

∥ 7.28 Or, Azmaveth.

∥ 7.29 Or, Kirjatharim.

* 7.34 ver. 12.

* 7.39 1 Chr. 24. 7.

∥ 7.43 Ezra 2. 40. or, Judah, Ezra 3. 9.

∥ 7.59 Or, Ami.

* 7.61 Ezra 2. 59.

∥ 7.61 Or, pedigree.

∥ 7.65 Or, the governor.

† 7.70 Heb. part.

* 8.1 Ezra 3. 1. &c 7. 6.

† 8.2 Heb. that understood in hearing.

† 8.3 Heb. from the light.

† 8.4 Heb. tower of wood.

† 8.5 Heb. eyes.

∥ 8.9 Or, the governor.

‡ 8.10 [1611 Lord]

∥ 8.13 Or, that they might instruct in the words of the law.

† 8.14 Heb. by the hand of.

* 8.14 Lev. 23. 34. Deut. 16. 13.

† 8.18 Heb. a restraint.

* 9.1 ch. 8. 2.

† 9.2 Heb. strange children.

∥ 9.4 Or, scaffold

* 9.6 Gen. 1. 1.

* 9.7 Gen. 11. 31. &c 12. 1. &c 17. 5.

* 9.8 Gen. 15. 6.

* 9.8 Gen. 12. 7. &c 15. 18. &c 17. 7, 8.

* 9.9 Ex. 3. 7. &c 14. 10.

* 9.10 Ex. 7, 8, 9, 10, 12, &c 14, chapters.

* 9.11 Ex. 14. 22.

* 9.11 Ex. 15. 10.

* 9.12 Ex. 13. 21.

* 9.13 Ex. 19. 20. &c 20. 1.

† 9.13 Heb. laws of truth.

* 9.15 Ex. 16. 15. &c 17. 6. Num. 20. 9.

* 9.15 Deut. 1. 8.

† 9.15 Heb. which thou hadst lift up thine hand to give them.

‡ 9.17 [1611 the]

* 9.17 Num. 14. 4.

† 9.17 Heb a God of pardons.

* 9.18 Ex. 32. 4.

* 9.19 Ex. 13. 22. Num. 14. 14. 1 Cor. 10. 1.

* 9.20 Num. 11. 17.

* 9.20 Ex. 16. 15. &c 17. 6. Josh. 5. 12.

* 9.21 Deut. 8. 4.

* 9.22 Num. 21. 21, &c.

† 9.24 Heb. according to their will.

∥ 9.25 Or, cisterns.

† 9.25 Heb. tree of food.

* 9.26 1 Kings 19. 10.

† 9.28 Heb. they returned to do evil.

† 9.29 Heb. they gave a withdrawing shoulder.

† 9.30 Heb. protract over them.

* 9.30 2 Kings 17 13. 2 Chr. 36. 15.

† 9.30 Heb. in the hand of thy prophets.

* 9.32 Ex. 34. 6.

† 9.32 Heb. weariness.

† 9.32 Heb. that hath found us.

† 9.38 Heb. are at the sealing, or, sealed.

† 10.1 Heb. at the sealings.

∥ 10.1 Or, the governor.

* 10.28 Ezra 2. 43.

† 10.29 Heb. by the hand of.

* 10.30 Ex. 34. 16. Deut. 7. 3.

* 10.31 Ex. 20. 10. Lev. 23. 3. Deut. 5. 12. ch. 13. 15, &c.

* 10.31 Lev. 25. 4. Deut. 15. 2.

† 10.31 Heb. every hand.

* 10.34 Num. 28, &c 29. Ex. 23. 19. Lev. 19. 23.

* 10.36 Ex. 13. 2 Lev. 23. 17. Num. 15. 19. &c 18. 12, &c.

* 10.38 Num. 18. 26.

∥ 11.14 Or, the son of Haggedolim.

† 11.16 Heb. were over.

† 11.19 Heb. at the gates.

* 11.21 ch. 3. 26.

∥ 11.21 Or, the tower.

∥ 11.23 Or, a sure ordinance.

∥ 11.31 Or, of Geba.

∥ 11.31 Or, to Michmash.

* 12.1 Ezra 2. 1.

∥ 12.2 ver. 14.

∥ 12.3 ver. 14.

∥ 12.3 ver. 15.

∥ 12.3 ver. 15.

∥ 12.4 ver. 16.

∥ 12.5 ver. 17.

∥ 12.5 ver. 17.

∥ 12.7 ver. 20.

∥ 12.8 That is, the psalms of thanksgiving.

* 12.23 1 Chr. 9. 14, &c.

∥ 12.25 Or, treasuries, or, assemblies.

† 12.42 Heb. made their voice to be heard.

∥ 12.44 That is, appointed by the law.

† 12.44 Heb. for the joy of Judah.

† 12.44 Heb. that stood.

* 12.45 1 Chr. 25. &c 26.

* 12.46 1 Chr. 25. 1, &c.

∥ 12.47 That is, set apart.

* 12.47 Num. 18. 26.

† 13.1 Heb. there was read.

* 13.1 Num. 22. 5. Deut. 23. 3.

† 13.1 Heb. ears.

* 13.2 Num. 22. 5. Josh. 24. 9.

† 13.4 Heb. being set over.

† 13.5 Heb. the commandment of the Levites.

† 13.6 Heb. at the end of days.

∥ 13.6 Or, I earnestly requested.

† 13.11 Heb. standing.

∥ 13.12 Or, storehouses.

† 13.13 Heb. at their hand.

† 13.13 Heb. it was upon them.

* 13.14 ver. 22.

† 13.14 Heb. kindnesses.

∥ 13.14 Or, observations.

† 13.21 Heb. before the wall?

∥ 13.22 Or, multitude.

† 13.23 Heb. had made to dwell with them.

† 13.24 Heb. they discerned not to speak.

† 13.24 Heb. of people and people.

∥ 13.25 Or, reviled them.

* 13.26 1 Kings 11. 1, &c.

† 13.29 Heb. for the defilings.

Numbers

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36

The Fourth Book of Moses, called Numbers

1

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, in the tabernacle of the congregation, on the first day of the second month, in the second year after they were come out of the land of Egypt, saying, 2 [*] Take ye the sum of all the congregation of the children of Israel, after their families, by the house of their fathers, with the number of their names, every male by their [‡]polls; 3  From twenty years old and upward, all that are able to go forth to war in Israel: thou and Aaron shall number them by their armies. 4  And with you there shall be a man of every tribe; every one head of the house of his fathers.

5 ¶ And these are the names of the men that shall stand with you: of the tribe of Reuben; Elizur the son of Shedeur. 6  Of Simeon; Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai. 7  Of Judah; Nahshon the son of Amminadab. 8  Of Issachar; Nethaneel the son of Zuar. 9  Of Zebulun; Eliab the son of Helon. 10  Of the children of Joseph: of Ephraim; Elishama the son of Ammihud: of Manasseh; Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur. 11  Of Benjamin; Abidan the son of Gideoni. 12  Of Dan; Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai. 13  Of Asher; Pagiel the son of Ocran. 14  Of Gad; Eliasaph the son of Deuel. 15  Of Naphtali; Ahira the son of Enan. 16 These were the renowned of the congregation, princes of the tribes of their fathers, heads of thousands in Israel.

17 ¶ And Moses and Aaron took these men which are expressed by their names: 18  And they assembled all the congregation together on the first day of the second month, and they declared their pedigrees after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, by their [‡]polls. 19  As the LORD commanded Moses, so he numbered them in the wilderness of Sinai. 20  And the children of Reuben, Israel’s eldest son, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, by their [‡]polls, every male from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 21  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Reuben, were forty and six thousand and five hundred.

22 ¶ Of the children of Simeon, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, those that were numbered of them, according to the number of the names, by their polls, every male from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 23  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Simeon, were fifty and nine thousand and three hundred.

24 ¶ Of the children of Gad, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 25  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Gad, were forty and five thousand six hundred and fifty.

26 ¶ Of the children of Judah, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 27  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Judah, were threescore and fourteen thousand and six hundred.

28 ¶ Of the children of Issachar, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 29  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Issachar, were fifty and four thousand and four hundred.

30 ¶ Of the children of Zebulun, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 31  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Zebulun, were fifty and seven thousand and four hundred.

32 ¶ Of the children of Joseph, namely, of the children of Ephraim, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 33  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Ephraim, were forty thousand and five hundred.

34 ¶ Of the children of Manasseh, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 35  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Manasseh, were thirty and two thousand and two hundred.

36 ¶ Of the children of Benjamin, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 37  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Benjamin, were thirty and five thousand and four hundred.

38 ¶ Of the children of Dan, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 39  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Dan, were threescore and two thousand and seven hundred.

40 ¶ Of the children of Asher, by their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 41  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Asher, were forty and one thousand and five hundred.

42 ¶ Of the children of Naphtali, throughout their generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war; 43  Those that were numbered of them, even of the tribe of Naphtali, were fifty and three thousand and four hundred.

44 These are those that were numbered, which Moses and Aaron numbered, and the princes of Israel, being twelve men: each one was for the house of his fathers. 45  So were all those that were numbered of the children of Israel, by the house of their fathers, from twenty years old and upward, all that were able to go forth to war in Israel; 46  Even all they that were numbered were six hundred thousand and three thousand and five hundred and fifty.

47 ¶ But the Levites after the tribe of their fathers were not numbered among them. 48  For the LORD had spoken unto Moses, saying, 49  Only thou shalt not number the tribe of Levi, neither take the sum of them among the children of Israel: 50  But thou shalt appoint the Levites over the tabernacle of testimony, and over all the vessels thereof, and over all things that belong to it: they shall bear the tabernacle, and all the vessels thereof; and they shall minister unto it, and shall encamp round about the tabernacle. 51  And when the tabernacle setteth forward, the Levites shall take it down: and when the tabernacle is to be pitched, the Levites shall set it up: and the stranger that cometh nigh shall be put to death. 52  And the children of Israel shall pitch their tents, every man by his own camp, and every man by his own standard, throughout their hosts. 53  But the Levites shall pitch round about the tabernacle of testimony, that there be no wrath upon the congregation of the children of Israel: and the Levites shall keep the charge of the tabernacle of testimony. 54  And the children of Israel did according to all that the LORD commanded Moses, so did they.

2

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, 2  Every man of the children of Israel shall pitch by his own standard, with the ensign of their father’s house: [†]far off about the tabernacle of the congregation shall they pitch.

3  And on the east side toward the rising of the sun shall they of the standard of the camp of Judah pitch throughout their armies: and Nahshon the son of Amminadab shall be captain of the children of Judah. 4  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were threescore and fourteen thousand and six hundred. 5  And those that do pitch next unto him shall be the tribe of Issachar: and Nethaneel the son of Zuar shall be captain of the children of Issachar. 6  And his host, and those that were numbered thereof, were fifty and four thousand and four hundred. 7  Then the tribe of Zebulun: and Eliab the son of Helon shall be captain of the children of Zebulun. 8  And his host, and those that were numbered thereof, were fifty and seven thousand and four hundred. 9  All that were numbered in the camp of Judah were an hundred thousand and fourscore thousand and six thousand and four hundred, throughout their armies. These shall first set forth.

10 ¶ On the south side shall be the standard of the camp of Reuben according to their armies: and the captain of the children of Reuben shall be Elizur the son of Shedeur. 11  And his host, and those that were numbered thereof, were forty and six thousand and five hundred. 12  And those which pitch by him shall be the tribe of Simeon: and the captain of the children of Simeon shall be Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai. 13  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were fifty and nine thousand and three hundred. 14  Then the tribe of Gad: and the captain of the sons of Gad shall be Eliasaph the son of Reuel. 15  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were forty and five thousand and six hundred and fifty. 16  All that were numbered in the camp of Reuben were an hundred thousand and fifty and one thousand and four hundred and fifty, throughout their armies. And they shall set forth in the second rank.

17 ¶ Then the tabernacle of the congregation shall set forward with the camp of the Levites in the midst of the camp: as they encamp, so shall they set forward, every man in his place by their standards.

18 ¶ On the west side shall be the standard of the camp of Ephraim according to their armies: and the captain of the sons of Ephraim shall be Elishama the son of Ammihud. 19  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were forty thousand and five hundred. 20 And by him shall be the tribe of Manasseh: and the captain of the children of Manasseh shall be Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur. 21  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were thirty and two thousand and two hundred. 22  Then the tribe of Benjamin: and the captain of the sons of Benjamin shall be Abidan the son of Gideoni. 23  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were thirty and five thousand and four hundred. 24  All that were numbered of the camp of Ephraim were an hundred thousand and eight thousand and an hundred, throughout their armies. And they shall go forward in the third rank.

25 ¶ The standard of the camp of Dan shall be on the north side by their armies: and the captain of the children of Dan shall be Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai. 26  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were threescore and two thousand and seven hundred. 27  And those that encamp by him shall be the tribe of Asher: and the captain of the children of Asher shall be Pagiel the son of Ocran. 28  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were forty and one thousand and five hundred.

29 ¶ Then the tribe of Naphtali: and the captain of the children of Naphtali shall be Ahira the son of Enan. 30  And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were fifty and three thousand and four hundred. 31  All they that were numbered in the camp of Dan were an hundred thousand and fifty and seven thousand and six hundred. They shall go hindmost with their standards.

32 ¶ These are those which were numbered of the children of Israel by the house of their fathers: all those that were numbered of the camps throughout their hosts were six hundred thousand and three thousand and five hundred and fifty. 33  But the Levites were not numbered among the children of Israel; as the LORD commanded Moses. 34  And the children of Israel did according to all that the LORD commanded Moses: so they pitched by their standards, and so they set forward, every one after their families, according to the house of their fathers.

3

1 These also are the generations of Aaron and Moses in the day that the LORD spake with Moses in mount Sinai. 2 And these are the names of the sons of Aaron; Nadab the [*]firstborn, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. 3 These are the names of the sons of Aaron, the priests which were anointed, [†]whom he consecrated to minister in the priest’s office. 4 [*] And Nadab and Abihu died before the LORD, when they offered strange fire before the LORD, in the wilderness of Sinai, and they had no children: and Eleazar and Ithamar ministered in the priest’s office in the sight of Aaron their father.

5 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 6  Bring the tribe of Levi near, and present them before Aaron the priest, that they may minister unto him. 7  And they shall keep his charge, and the charge of the whole congregation before the tabernacle of the congregation, to do the service of the tabernacle. 8  And they shall keep all the instruments of the tabernacle of the congregation, and the charge of the children of Israel, to do the service of the tabernacle. 9  And thou shalt give the Levites unto Aaron and to his sons: they are wholly given unto him out of the children of Israel. 10  And thou shalt appoint Aaron and his sons, and they shall wait on their priest’s office: and the stranger that cometh nigh shall be put to death. 11  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 12  And I, behold, I have taken the Levites from among the children of Israel instead of all the firstborn that openeth the matrix among the children of Israel: therefore the Levites shall be mine; 13  Because all the firstborn are mine; [*]for on the day that I smote all the firstborn in the land of Egypt I hallowed unto me all the firstborn in Israel, both man and beast: mine [‡]shall they be: I am the LORD.

14 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, saying, 15  Number the children of Levi after the house of their fathers, by their families: every male from a month old and upward shalt thou number them. 16  And Moses numbered them according to the [†]word of the LORD, as he was commanded. 17 [*] And these were the sons of Levi by their names; Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari. 18 And these are the names of the sons of Gershon by their families; Libni, and Shimei. 19  And the sons of Kohath by their families; Amram, and Izehar, Hebron, and Uzziel. 20  And the sons of Merari by their families; Mahli, and Mushi. These are the families of the Levites according to the house of their fathers. 21  Of Gershon was the family of the Libnites, and the family of the Shimites: these are the families of the Gershonites. 22  Those that were numbered of them, according to the number of all the males, from a month old and upward, even those that were numbered of them were seven thousand and five hundred. 23  The families of the Gershonites shall pitch behind the tabernacle westward. 24  And the chief of the house of the father of the Gershonites shall be Eliasaph the son of Lael. 25  And the charge of the sons of Gershon in the tabernacle of the congregation shall be the tabernacle, and the tent, the covering thereof, and the hanging for the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, 26  And the hangings of the court, and the curtain for the door of the court, which is by the tabernacle, and by the altar round about, and the cords of it for all the service thereof.

27 ¶ And of Kohath was the family of the Amramites, and the family of the Izeharites, and the family of the Hebronites, and the family of the Uzzielites: these are the families of the Kohathites. 28  In the number of all the males, from a month old and upward, were eight thousand and six hundred, keeping the charge of the sanctuary. 29  The families of the sons of Kohath shall pitch on the side of the tabernacle southward. 30  And the chief of the house of the father of the families of the Kohathites shall be Elizaphan the son of Uzziel. 31  And their charge shall be the ark, and the table, and the candlestick, and the altars, and the vessels of the sanctuary wherewith they minister, and the hanging, and all the service thereof. 32  And Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest shall be chief over the chief of the Levites, and have the oversight of them that keep the charge of the sanctuary.

33 ¶ Of Merari was the family of the Mahlites, and the family of the Mushites: these are the families of Merari. 34  And those that were numbered of them, according to the number of all the males, from a month old and upward, were six thousand and two hundred. 35  And the chief of the house of the father of the families of Merari was Zuriel the son of Abihail: these shall pitch on the side of the tabernacle [‡]northward. 36 And [†]under the custody and charge of the sons of Merari shall be the boards of the tabernacle, and the bars thereof, and the pillars thereof, and the sockets thereof, and all the vessels thereof, and all that serveth thereto, 37  And the pillars of the court round about, and their sockets, and their pins, and their cords.

38 ¶ But those that encamp before the tabernacle toward the east, even before the tabernacle of the congregation eastward, shall be Moses, and Aaron and his sons, keeping the charge of the sanctuary for the charge of the children of Israel; and the stranger that cometh nigh shall be put to death. 39  All that were numbered of the Levites, which Moses and Aaron numbered at the commandment of the LORD, throughout their families, all the males from a month old and upward, were twenty and two thousand.

40 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Number all the firstborn of the males of the children of Israel from a month old and upward, and take the number of their names. 41  And thou shalt take the Levites for me (I am the LORD) instead of all the firstborn among the children of Israel; and the cattle of the Levites instead of all the firstlings among the cattle of the children of Israel. 42  And Moses numbered, as the LORD commanded him, all the firstborn among the children of Israel. 43  And all the firstborn males by the number of names, from a month old and upward, of those that were numbered of them, were twenty and two thousand two hundred and threescore and thirteen.

44 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 45  Take the Levites instead of all the firstborn among the children of Israel, and the cattle of the Levites instead of their cattle; and the Levites shall be mine: I am the LORD. 46  And for those that are to be redeemed of the two hundred and threescore and thirteen of the firstborn of the children of Israel, which are more than the Levites; 47  Thou shalt even take five shekels apiece by the poll, after the shekel of the sanctuary shalt thou take them: ([*]the shekel is twenty gerahs:) 48  And thou shalt give the money, wherewith the odd number of them is to be redeemed, unto Aaron and to his sons. 49  And Moses took the redemption money of them that were over and above them that were redeemed by the Levites: 50  Of the firstborn of the children of Israel took he the money; a thousand three hundred and threescore and five shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary: 51  And Moses gave the money of them that were redeemed unto Aaron and to his sons, according to the word of the LORD, as the LORD commanded Moses.

4

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, 2  Take the sum of the sons of Kohath from among the sons of Levi, after their families, by the house of their fathers, 3  From thirty years old and upward even until fifty years old, all that enter into the host, to do the work in the tabernacle of the congregation. 4 This shall be the service of the sons of Kohath in the tabernacle of the congregation, about the most holy things:

5 ¶ And when the camp setteth forward, Aaron shall come, and his sons, and they shall take down the covering vail, and cover the ark of testimony with it: 6  And shall put thereon the covering of badgers’ skins, and shall spread over it a cloth wholly of blue, and shall put in the staves thereof. 7  And upon the [*]table of shewbread they shall spread a cloth of blue, and put thereon the dishes, and the spoons, and the bowls, and covers to [∥]cover withal: and the continual bread shall be thereon: 8  And they shall spread upon them a cloth of scarlet, and cover the same with a covering of badgers’ skins, and shall put in the staves thereof. 9  And they shall take a cloth of blue, and cover the [*]candlestick of the light, and his lamps, and his tongs, [*]and his snuffdishes, and all the oil vessels thereof, wherewith they minister unto it: 10  And they shall put it and all the vessels thereof within a covering of badgers’ skins, and shall put it upon a bar. 11  And upon the golden altar they shall spread a cloth of blue, and cover it with a covering of badgers’ skins, and shall put to the staves thereof: 12  And they shall take all the instruments of ministry, wherewith they minister in the sanctuary, and put them in a cloth of blue, and cover them with a covering of badgers’ skins, and shall put them on a bar: 13  And they shall take away the ashes from the altar, and spread a purple cloth thereon: 14  And they shall put upon it all the vessels thereof, wherewith they minister about it, even the censers, the fleshhooks, and the shovels, and the [∥]basons, all the vessels of the altar; and they shall spread upon it a covering of badgers’ skins, and put to the staves of it. 15  And when Aaron and his sons have made an end of covering the sanctuary, and all the vessels of the sanctuary, as the camp is to set forward; after that, the sons of Kohath shall come to bear it: but they shall not touch any holy thing, lest they die. These things are the burden of the sons of Kohath in the tabernacle of the congregation.

16 ¶ And to the office of Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest pertaineth the oil for the light, and the [*]sweet incense, and the daily meat offering, and the [*]anointing oil, and the oversight of all the tabernacle, and of all that therein is, in the sanctuary, and in the vessels thereof.

17 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, 18  Cut ye not off the tribe of the families of the Kohathites from among the Levites: 19  But thus do unto them, that they may live, and not die, when they approach unto the most holy things: Aaron and his sons shall go in, and appoint them every one to his service and to his burden: 20  But they shall not go in to see when the holy things are covered, lest they die.

21 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 22  Take also the sum of the sons of Gershon, throughout the houses of their fathers, by their families; 23  From thirty years old and upward until fifty years old shalt thou number them; all that enter in [†]to perform the service, to do the work in the tabernacle of the congregation. 24 This is the service of the families of the Gershonites, to serve, and for [∥]burdens: 25  And they shall bear the curtains of the tabernacle, and the tabernacle of the congregation, his covering, and the covering of the badgers’ skins that is above upon it, and the hanging for the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, 26  And the hangings of the court, and the hanging for the door of the gate of the court, which is by the tabernacle and by the altar round about, and their cords, and all the instruments of their service, and all that is made for them: so shall they serve. 27  At the [†]appointment of Aaron and his sons shall be all the service of the sons of the Gershonites, in all their burdens, and in all their service: and ye shall appoint unto them in charge all their burdens. 28 This is the service of the families of the sons of Gershon in the tabernacle of the congregation: and their charge shall be under the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest.

29 ¶ As for the sons of Merari, thou shalt number them after their families, by the house of their fathers; 30  From thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old shalt thou number them, every one that entereth into the [†]service, to do the work of the tabernacle of the congregation. 31 And this is the charge of their burden, according to all their service in the tabernacle of the congregation; [*]the boards of the tabernacle, and the bars thereof, and the pillars thereof, and sockets thereof, 32  And the pillars of the court round about, and their sockets, and their pins, and their cords, with all their instruments, and with all their service: and by name ye shall reckon the instruments of the charge of their burden. 33 This is the service of the families of the sons of Merari, according to all their service, in the tabernacle of the congregation, under the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest.

34 ¶ And Moses and Aaron and the chief of the congregation numbered the sons of the Kohathites after their families, and after the house of their fathers, 35  From thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that entereth into the service, for the work in the tabernacle of the congregation: 36  And those that were numbered of them by their families were two thousand seven hundred and fifty. 37 These were they that were numbered of the families of the Kohathites, all that might do service in the tabernacle of the congregation, which Moses and Aaron did number according to the commandment of the LORD by the hand of Moses. 38  And those that were numbered of the sons of Gershon, throughout their families, and by the house of their fathers, 39  From thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that entereth into the service, for the work in the tabernacle of the congregation, 40  Even those that were numbered of them, throughout their families, by the [‡]house of their fathers, were two thousand and six hundred and thirty. 41 These are they that were numbered of the families of the sons of Gershon, of all that might do service in the tabernacle of the congregation, whom Moses and Aaron did number according to the commandment of the LORD.

42 ¶ And those that were numbered of the families of the sons of Merari, throughout their families, by the house of their fathers, 43  From thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that entereth into the service, for the work in the tabernacle of the congregation, 44  Even those that were numbered of them after their families, were three thousand and two hundred. 45 These be those that were numbered of the families of the sons of Merari, whom Moses and Aaron numbered according to the word of the LORD by the hand of Moses. 46  All those that were numbered of the Levites, whom Moses and Aaron and the chief of Israel numbered, after their families, and after the house of their fathers, 47  From thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that came to do the service of the ministry, and the service of the burden in the tabernacle of the congregation, 48  Even those that were numbered of them, were eight thousand and five hundred and fourscore. 49  According to the commandment of the LORD they were numbered by the hand of Moses, every one according to his service, and according to his burden: thus were they numbered of him, as the LORD commanded Moses.

5

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Command the children of Israel, that they put out of the camp every [*]leper, and every one that hath an [*]issue, and whosoever is defiled by the [*]dead: 3  Both male and female shall ye put out, without the camp shall ye put them; that they defile not their camps, in the midst whereof I dwell. 4  And the children of Israel did so, and put them out without the camp: as the LORD spake unto Moses, so did the children of Israel.

5 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 6  Speak unto the children of Israel, [*]When a man or woman shall commit any sin that men commit, to do a trespass against the LORD, and that person be guilty; 7  Then they shall confess their sin which they have done: and he shall recompense his trespass [*]with the principal thereof, and add unto it the fifth part thereof, and give it unto him against whom he hath trespassed. 8  But if the man have no kinsman to recompense the trespass unto, let the trespass be recompensed unto the LORD, even to the priest; beside the ram of the atonement, whereby an atonement shall be made for him. 9  And every [∥]offering of all the holy things of the children of Israel, which they bring unto the priest, shall be his. 10  And every man’s hallowed things shall be his: whatsoever any man giveth the priest, it shall be [*]his.

11 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 12  Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, If any man’s wife go aside, and commit a trespass against him, 13  And a man lie with her carnally, and it be hid from the eyes of her husband, and be kept close, and she be defiled, and there be no witness against her, neither she be taken with the manner; 14  And the spirit of jealousy come upon him, and he be jealous of his wife, and she be defiled: or if the spirit of jealousy come upon him, and he be jealous of his wife, and she be not defiled: 15  Then shall the man bring his wife unto the priest, and he shall bring her offering for her, the tenth part of an ephah of barley meal; he shall pour no oil upon it, nor put frankincense thereon; for it is an offering of jealousy, an offering of memorial, bringing iniquity to remembrance. 16  And the priest shall bring her near, and set her before the LORD: 17  And the priest shall take holy water in an earthen vessel; and of the dust that is in the floor of the tabernacle the priest shall take, and put it into the water: 18  And the priest shall set the woman before the LORD, and uncover the woman’s head, and put the offering of memorial in her hands, which is the jealousy offering: and the priest shall have in his hand the bitter water that causeth the curse: 19  And the priest shall charge her by an oath, and say unto the woman, If no man have lain with thee, and if thou hast not gone aside to uncleanness [∥][†]with another instead of thy husband, be thou free from this bitter water that causeth the curse: 20  But if thou hast gone aside to another instead of thy husband, and if thou be defiled, and some man [‡]have lain with thee beside thine husband: 21  Then the priest shall charge the woman with an oath of cursing, and the priest shall say unto the woman, The LORD make thee a curse and an oath among thy people, when the LORD doth make thy thigh to [†]rot, and thy belly to swell; 22  And this water that causeth the curse shall go into thy bowels, to make thy belly to swell, and thy thigh to rot: And the woman shall say, Amen, amen. 23  And the priest shall write these curses in a book, and he shall blot them out with the bitter water: 24  And he shall cause the woman to drink the bitter water that causeth the curse: and the water that causeth the curse shall enter into her, and become bitter. 25  Then the priest shall take the jealousy offering out of the woman’s hand, and shall wave the offering before the LORD, and offer it upon the altar: 26  And the priest shall take an handful of the offering, even the memorial thereof, and burn it upon the altar, and afterward shall cause the woman to drink the water. 27  And when he hath made her to drink the water, then it shall come to pass, that, if she be defiled, and have done trespass against her husband, that the water that causeth the curse shall enter into her, and become bitter, and her belly shall swell, and her thigh shall rot: and the woman shall be a curse among her people. 28  And if the woman be not defiled, but be clean; then she shall be free, and shall conceive seed. 29 This is the law of jealousies, when a wife goeth aside to another instead of her husband, and is defiled; 30  Or when the spirit of jealousy cometh upon him, and he be jealous over his wife, and shall set the woman before the LORD, and the priest shall execute upon her all this law. 31  Then shall the man be guiltless from iniquity, and this woman shall bear her iniquity.

6

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When either man or woman shall [∥]separate themselves to vow a vow of a Nazarite, to separate themselves unto the LORD: 3  He shall separate himself from wine and strong drink, and shall drink no vinegar of wine, or vinegar of strong drink, neither shall he drink any liquor of grapes, nor eat moist grapes, or dried. 4  All the days of his [∥]separation shall he eat nothing that is made of the [†]vine tree, from the kernels even to the husk. 5  All the days of the vow of his separation there shall no [*]razor come upon his head: until the days be fulfilled, in the which he separateth himself unto the LORD, he shall be holy, and shall let the locks of the hair of his head grow. 6  All the days that he separateth himself unto the LORD he shall come at no dead body. 7  He shall not make himself unclean for his father, or for his mother, for his brother, or for his sister, when they die: because the [†]consecration of his God is upon his head. 8  All the days of his separation he is holy unto the LORD. 9  And if any man die very suddenly by him, and he hath defiled the head of his consecration; then he shall shave his head in the day of his cleansing, on the seventh day shall he shave it. 10  And on the eighth day he shall bring two turtles, or two young pigeons, to the priest, to the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: 11  And the priest shall offer the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering, and make an atonement for him, for that he sinned by the dead, and shall hallow his head that same day. 12  And he shall consecrate unto the LORD the days of his separation, and shall bring a lamb of the first year for a trespass offering: but the days that were before shall [†]be lost, because his separation was defiled.

13 ¶ And this is the law of the Nazarite, when the days of his separation are fulfilled: he shall be brought unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: 14  And he shall offer his offering unto the LORD, one he lamb of the first year without blemish for a burnt offering, and one ewe lamb of the first year without blemish for a sin offering, and one [‡]ram without blemish for peace offerings, 15  And a basket of unleavened bread, cakes of fine flour mingled with oil, and wafers of unleavened bread anointed with oil, and their meat offering, and their drink offerings. 16  And the priest shall bring them before the LORD, and shall offer his sin offering, and his burnt offering: 17  And he shall offer the ram for a sacrifice of peace offerings unto the LORD, with the basket of unleavened bread: the priest shall offer also his meat offering, and his drink offering. 18 [*] And the Nazarite shall shave the head of his separation at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and shall take the hair of the head of his separation, and put it in the fire which is under the sacrifice of the peace offerings. 19  And the priest shall take the sodden shoulder of the ram, and one unleavened cake out of the basket, and one unleavened wafer, and shall put them upon the hands of the Nazarite, after the hair of his separation is shaven: 20  And the priest shall wave them [*]for a wave offering before the LORD: this is holy for the priest, with the wave breast and heave shoulder: and after that the Nazarite may drink wine. 21 This is the law of the Nazarite who hath vowed, and of his offering unto the LORD for his separation, beside that that his hand shall get: according to the vow which he vowed, so he must do after the law of his separation.

22 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 23  Speak unto Aaron and unto his sons, saying, On this wise ye shall bless the children of Israel, saying unto them, 24  The LORD bless thee, and keep thee: 25  The LORD make his face shine upon thee, and be gracious unto thee: 26  The LORD lift up his countenance upon thee, and give thee peace. 27  And they shall put my name upon the children of Israel; and I will bless them.

7

1  And it came to pass on the day that Moses had fully [*]set up the tabernacle, and had anointed it, and sanctified it, and all the instruments thereof, both the altar and all the vessels thereof, and had anointed them, and sanctified them; 2  That the princes of Israel, heads of the house of their fathers, who were the princes of the tribes, [†]and were over them that were numbered, offered: 3  And they brought their offering before the LORD, six covered wagons, and twelve oxen; a wagon for two of the princes, and for each one an ox: and they brought them before the tabernacle. 4  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 5  Take it of them, that they may be to do the service of the tabernacle of the congregation; and thou shalt give them unto the Levites, to every man according to his service. 6  And Moses took the wagons and the oxen, and gave them unto the Levites. 7  Two wagons and four oxen he gave unto the sons of Gershon, according to their service: 8  And four wagons and eight oxen he gave unto the sons of Merari, according unto their service, under the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest. 9  But unto the sons of Kohath he gave none: because the service of the sanctuary belonging unto them was that they should bear upon their shoulders.

10 ¶ And the princes offered for dedicating of the altar in the day that it was anointed, even the princes offered their offering before the altar. 11  And the LORD said unto Moses, They shall offer their offering, each prince on his day, for the dedicating of the altar.

12 ¶ And he that offered his offering the first day was Nahshon the son of Amminadab, of the tribe of Judah: 13  And his offering was one silver charger, the weight thereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them were full of fine flour mingled with oil for a [*]meat offering: 14  One spoon of ten shekels of gold, full of incense: 15  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 16  One kid of the goats for a [*]sin offering: 17  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Nahshon the son of Amminadab.

18 ¶ On the second day Nethaneel the son of Zuar, prince of Issachar, did offer: 19  He offered for his offering one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 20  One spoon of gold of ten shekels, full of incense: 21  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 22  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 23  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Nethaneel the son of Zuar.

24 ¶ On the third day Eliab the son of Helon, prince of the children of Zebulun, did offer: 25  His offering was one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 26  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 27  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 28  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 29  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Eliab the son of Helon.

30 ¶ On the fourth day Elizur the son of Shedeur, prince of the children of Reuben, did offer: 31  His offering was one silver charger [‡]of the weight of an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 32  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 33  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 34  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 35  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Elizur the son of Shedeur.

36 ¶ On the fifth day Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai, prince of the children of Simeon, did offer: 37  His offering was one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 38  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 39  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 40  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 41  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai.

42 ¶ On the sixth day Eliasaph the son of Deuel, prince of the children of Gad, offered: 43  His offering was one silver charger of the weight of an hundred and thirty shekels, a silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 44  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 45  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 46  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 47  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Eliasaph the son of Deuel.

48 ¶ On the seventh day Elishama the son of Ammihud, prince of the children of Ephraim, offered: 49  His offering was one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 50  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 51  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 52  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 53  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Elishama the son of Ammihud.

54 ¶ On the eighth day offered Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur, prince of the children of Manasseh: 55  His offering was one silver charger [‡]of the weight of an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 56  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 57  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 58  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 59  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur.

60 ¶ On the ninth day Abidan the son of Gideoni, prince of the children of Benjamin, offered: 61  His offering was one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, [‡]one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 62  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 63  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 64  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 65  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Abidan the son of Gideoni.

66 ¶ On the tenth day Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai, prince of the children of Dan, offered: 67  His offering was one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 68  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 69  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 70  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 71  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai.

72 ¶ On the eleventh day Pagiel the son of Ocran, prince of the children of Asher, offered: 73  His offering was one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 74  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 75  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 76  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 77  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Pagiel the son of Ocran.

78 ¶ On the twelfth day Ahira the son of Enan, prince of the children of Naphtali, offered: 79  His offering was one silver charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirty shekels, one silver bowl of seventy shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary; both of them full of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering: 80  One golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense: 81  One young bullock, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a burnt offering: 82  One kid of the goats for a sin offering: 83  And for a sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, five rams, five he goats, five lambs of the first year: this was the offering of Ahira the son of Enan. 84 This was the dedication of the altar, in the day when it was anointed, by the princes of Israel: twelve chargers of silver, twelve silver bowls, twelve spoons of gold: 85  Each charger of silver weighing an hundred and thirty shekels, each bowl seventy: all the silver vessels weighed two thousand and four hundred shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary: 86  The golden spoons were twelve, full of incense, weighing ten shekels apiece, after the shekel of the sanctuary: all the gold of the spoons was an hundred and twenty shekels. 87  All the oxen for the burnt offering were twelve bullocks, the rams twelve, the lambs of the first year twelve, with their meat offering: and the kids of the goats for sin offering twelve. 88  And all the oxen for the sacrifice of the peace offerings were twenty and four bullocks, the rams sixty, the he goats sixty, the lambs of the first year sixty. This was the dedication of the altar, after that it was anointed. 89  And when Moses was gone into the tabernacle of the congregation to speak with [∥]him, then he heard the voice of one speaking unto him from off the mercy seat that was upon the ark of testimony, from between the two cherubims: and he spake unto him.

8

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Speak unto Aaron, and say unto him, When thou [*]lightest the lamps, the seven lamps shall give light over against the candlestick. 3  And Aaron did so; he lighted the lamps thereof over against the candlestick, as the LORD commanded Moses. 4 [*] And this work of the candlestick was of beaten gold, unto the shaft thereof, unto the flowers thereof, was [*]beaten work: according unto the pattern which the LORD had shewed Moses, so he made the candlestick.

5 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 6  Take the Levites from among the children of Israel, and cleanse them. 7  And thus shalt thou do unto them, to cleanse them: Sprinkle water of purifying upon them, and [†]let them shave all their flesh, and let them wash their clothes, and so make themselves clean. 8  Then let them take a young bullock with his meat offering, even fine flour mingled with oil, and another young bullock shalt thou take for a sin offering. 9  And thou shalt bring the Levites before the tabernacle of the congregation: and thou shalt gather the whole assembly of the children of Israel together: 10  And thou shalt bring the Levites before the LORD: and the children of Israel shall put their hands upon the Levites: 11  And Aaron shall [†]offer the Levites before the LORD for an [†]offering of the children of Israel, that [†]they may execute the service of the LORD. 12  And the Levites shall lay their hands upon the heads of the bullocks: and thou shalt offer the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering, unto the LORD, to make an atonement for the Levites. 13  And thou shalt set the Levites before Aaron, and before his sons, and offer them for an offering unto the LORD. 14  Thus shalt thou separate the Levites from among the children of Israel: and the Levites shall be [*]mine. 15  And after that shall the Levites go in to do the service of the tabernacle of the congregation: and thou shalt cleanse them, and offer them for an offering. 16 For they are wholly given unto me from among the children of Israel; instead of such as open every womb, even instead of the firstborn of all the children of Israel, have I taken them unto me. 17 [*] For all the firstborn of the children of Israel are mine, both man and beast: on the day that I smote every firstborn in the land of Egypt I sanctified them for myself. 18  And I have taken the Levites for all the firstborn of the children of Israel. 19  And I have given the Levites as [†]a gift to Aaron and to his sons from among the children of Israel, to do the service of the children of Israel in the tabernacle of the congregation, and to make an atonement for the children of Israel: that there be no plague among the children of Israel, when the children of Israel come nigh unto the sanctuary. 20  And Moses, and Aaron, and all the congregation of the children of Israel, did to the Levites according unto all that the LORD commanded Moses concerning the Levites, so did the children of Israel unto them. 21  And the Levites were purified, and they washed their clothes; and Aaron offered them as an offering before the LORD; and Aaron made an atonement for them to cleanse them. 22  And after that went the Levites in to do their service in the tabernacle of the congregation before Aaron, and before his sons: as the LORD had commanded Moses concerning the Levites, so did they unto them.

23 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 24 This is it that belongeth unto the Levites: from twenty and five years old and upward they shall go in [†]to wait upon the service of the tabernacle of the congregation: 25  And from the age of fifty years they shall [†]cease waiting upon the service thereof, and shall serve no more: 26  But shall minister with their brethren in the tabernacle of the congregation, to keep the charge, and shall do no service. Thus shalt thou do unto the Levites touching their charge.

9

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, in the first month of the second year after they were come out of the land of Egypt, saying, 2  Let the children of Israel also keep [*]the passover at his appointed season. 3  In the fourteenth day of this month, [†]at even, ye shall keep it in his appointed season: according to all the rites of it, and according to all the ceremonies thereof, shall ye keep it. 4  And Moses spake unto the children of Israel, that they should keep the passover. 5  And they kept the passover on the fourteenth day of the first month at even in the wilderness of Sinai: according to all that the LORD commanded Moses, so did the children of Israel.

6 ¶ And there were certain men, who were defiled by the dead body of a man, that they could not keep the passover on that day: and they came before Moses and before Aaron on that day: 7  And those men said unto him, We are defiled by the dead body of a man: wherefore are we kept back, that we may not offer an offering of the LORD in his appointed season among the children of Israel? 8  And Moses said unto them, Stand still, and I will hear what the LORD will command concerning you.

9 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 10  Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If any man of you or of your posterity shall be unclean by reason of a dead body, or be in a journey afar off, yet he shall keep the passover unto the LORD. 11  The fourteenth day of the second month at even they shall keep it, and eat it with unleavened bread and bitter herbs. 12  They shall leave none of it unto the morning, [*]nor break any bone of it: according to all the ordinances of the passover they shall keep it. 13  But the man that is clean, and is not in a journey, and forbeareth to keep the passover, even the same soul shall be cut off from among his people: because he brought not the offering of the LORD in his appointed season, that man shall bear his sin. 14  And if a stranger shall sojourn among you, and will keep the passover unto the LORD; according to the ordinance of the passover, and according to the manner thereof, so shall he do: [*]ye shall have one ordinance, both for the stranger, and for him that was born in the land.

15 ¶ And [*]on the day that the tabernacle was reared up the cloud covered the tabernacle, namely, the tent of the testimony: and at even there was upon the tabernacle as it were the appearance of fire, until the morning. 16  So it was alway: the cloud covered it by day, and the appearance of fire by night. 17  And when the cloud was taken up from the tabernacle, then after that the children of Israel journeyed: and in the place where the cloud abode, there the children of Israel pitched their tents. 18  At the commandment of the LORD the children of Israel journeyed, and at the commandment of the LORD they pitched: [*]as long as the cloud abode upon the tabernacle they rested in [‡]their tents. 19  And when the cloud [†]tarried long upon the tabernacle many days, then the children of Israel kept the charge of the LORD, and journeyed not. 20 And so it was, when the cloud was a few days upon the tabernacle; according to the commandment of the LORD they abode in their tents, and according to the commandment of the LORD they journeyed. 21 And so it was, when the cloud [†]abode from even unto the morning, and that the cloud was taken up in the morning, then they journeyed: whether it was by day or by night that the cloud was taken up, they journeyed. 22 Or whether it were two days, or a month, or a year, that the cloud tarried upon the tabernacle, remaining thereon, the children of Israel [*]abode in their tents, and journeyed not: but when it was taken up, they journeyed. 23  At the commandment of the LORD they rested in the tents, and at the commandment of the LORD they journeyed: they kept the charge of the LORD, at the commandment of the LORD by the hand of Moses.

10

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Make thee two trumpets of silver; of a whole piece shalt thou make them: that thou mayest use them for the calling of the assembly, and for the journeying of the camps. 3  And when they shall blow with them, all the assembly shall assemble themselves to thee at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. 4  And if they blow but with one trumpet, then the princes, which are heads of the thousands of Israel, shall gather themselves unto thee. 5  When ye blow an alarm, then the camps that lie on the east parts shall go forward. 6  When ye blow an alarm the second time, then the camps that lie on the south side shall take their journey: they shall blow an alarm for their journeys. 7  But when the congregation is to be gathered together, ye shall blow, but ye shall not sound an alarm. 8  And the sons of Aaron, the priests, shall blow with the trumpets; and they shall be to you for an ordinance for ever throughout your generations. 9  And if ye go to war in your land against the enemy that oppresseth you, then ye shall blow an alarm with the trumpets; and ye shall be remembered before the LORD your God, and ye shall be saved from your enemies. 10  Also in the day of your gladness, and in your solemn days, and in the beginnings of your months, ye shall blow with the trumpets over your burnt offerings, and over the sacrifices of your peace offerings; that they may be to you for a memorial before your God: I am the LORD your God.

11 ¶ And it came to pass on the twentieth day of the second month, in the second year, that the cloud was taken up from off the tabernacle of the testimony. 12  And the children of Israel took their journeys out of the wilderness of Sinai; and the cloud rested in the wilderness of Paran. 13  And they first took their journey according to the commandment of the LORD by the hand of Moses.

14 ¶ [*]In the first place went the standard of the camp of the children of Judah according to their armies: and over his host was [*]Nahshon the son of Amminadab. 15  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Issachar was Nethaneel the son of Zuar. 16  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Zebulun was Eliab the son of Helon. 17  And the tabernacle was taken down; and the sons of Gershon and the sons of Merari set forward, bearing the tabernacle.

18 ¶ And the standard of the camp of Reuben set forward according to their armies: and over his host was Elizur the son of Shedeur. 19  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Simeon was Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai. 20  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Gad was Eliasaph the son of Deuel. 21  And the Kohathites set forward, bearing the [*]sanctuary: and [∥]the other did set up the tabernacle against they came.

22 ¶ And the standard of the camp of the children of Ephraim set forward according to their armies: and over his host was Elishama the son of Ammihud. 23  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Manasseh was Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur. 24  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Benjamin was Abidan the son of Gideoni.

25 ¶ And the standard of the camp of the children of Dan set forward, which was the rereward of all the camps throughout their hosts: and over his host was Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai. 26  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Asher was Pagiel the son of Ocran. 27  And over the host of the tribe of the children of Naphtali was Ahira the son of Enan. 28 [†]Thus were the journeyings of the children of Israel according to their armies, when they set forward.

29 ¶ And Moses said unto Hobab, the son of Raguel the Midianite, Moses’ father in law, We are journeying unto the place of which the LORD said, I will give it you: come thou with us, and we will do thee good: for the LORD hath spoken good concerning Israel. 30  And he said unto him, I will not go; but I will depart to mine own land, and to my kindred. 31  And he said, Leave us not, I pray thee; forasmuch as thou knowest how we are to encamp in the wilderness, and thou mayest be to us instead of eyes. 32  And it shall be, if thou go with us, yea, it shall be, that what goodness the LORD shall do unto us, the same will we do unto thee.

33 ¶ And they departed from the mount of the LORD three days’ journey: and the ark of the covenant of the LORD went before them in the three days’ journey, to search out a resting place for them. 34  And the cloud of the LORD was upon them by day, when they went out of the camp. 35  And it came to pass, when the ark set forward, that Moses said, [*]Rise up, LORD, and let thine enemies be scattered; and let them that hate thee flee before thee. 36  And when it rested, he said, Return, O LORD, unto the [†]many thousands of Israel.

11

1 And when the people [∥]complained, [†]it displeased the LORD: and the LORD heard it; and his anger was kindled; and the fire of the LORD burnt [*]among them, and consumed them that were in the uttermost parts of the camp. 2  And the people cried unto Moses; and when Moses prayed unto the LORD, the fire [†]was quenched. 3  And he called the name of the place [∥]Taberah: because the fire of the LORD burnt among them.

4 ¶ And the [*]mixt multitude that was among them [†]fell a lusting: and the children of Israel also [†]wept again, and said, [*]Who shall give us flesh to eat? 5  We remember the fish, which we did eat in Egypt freely; the cucumbers, and the melons, and the leeks, and the onions, and the garlick: 6  But now our soul is dried away: there is nothing at all, beside this manna, before our eyes. 7  And [*]the manna was as coriander seed, and the [†]colour thereof as the colour of bdellium. 8  And the people went about, and gathered it, and ground it in mills, or beat it in a mortar, and baked it in pans, and made cakes of it: and the taste of it was as the taste of fresh oil. 9  And when the dew fell upon the camp in the night, the manna fell upon it.

10 ¶ Then Moses heard the people weep throughout their families, every man in the door of his tent: and the anger of the LORD was kindled greatly; Moses also was displeased. 11  And Moses said unto the LORD, Wherefore hast thou afflicted thy servant? and wherefore have I not found favour in thy sight, that thou layest the burden of all this people upon me? 12  Have I conceived all this people? have I begotten them, that thou shouldest say unto me, Carry them in thy bosom, as a nursing father beareth the sucking child, unto the land which thou swarest unto their fathers? 13  Whence should I have flesh to give unto all this people? for they weep unto me, saying, Give us flesh, that we may eat. 14  I am not able to bear all this people alone, because it is too heavy for me. 15  And if thou deal thus with me, kill me, I pray thee, out of hand, if I have found favour in thy sight; and let me not see my wretchedness.

16 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Gather unto me seventy men of the elders of Israel, whom thou knowest to be the elders of the people, and officers over them; and bring them unto the tabernacle of the congregation, that they may stand there with thee. 17  And I will come down and talk with thee there: and I will take of the spirit which is upon thee, and will put it upon them; and they shall bear the burden of the people with thee, that thou bear it not thyself alone. 18  And say thou unto the people, Sanctify yourselves against to morrow, and ye shall eat flesh: for ye have wept in the ears of the LORD, saying, Who shall give us flesh to eat? for it was well with us in Egypt: therefore the LORD will give you flesh, and ye shall eat. 19  Ye shall not eat one day, nor two days, nor five days, neither ten days, nor twenty days; 20  But even a [†]whole month, until it come out at your nostrils, and it be loathsome unto you: because that ye have despised the LORD which is among you, and have wept before him, saying, Why came we forth out of Egypt? 21  And Moses said, The people, among whom I am, are six hundred thousand footmen; and thou hast said, I will give them flesh, that they may eat a whole month. 22  Shall the flocks and the herds be slain for them, to suffice them? or shall all the fish of the sea be gathered together for them, to suffice them? 23  And the LORD said unto Moses, [*]Is the LORD’s hand waxed short? thou shalt see now whether my word shall come to pass unto thee or not.

24 ¶ And Moses went out, and told the people the words of the LORD, and gathered the seventy men of the elders of the people, and set them round about the tabernacle. 25  And the LORD came down in a cloud, and spake unto him, and took of the spirit that was upon him, and gave it unto the seventy elders: and it came to pass, that, when the spirit rested upon them, they prophesied, and did not cease. 26  But there remained two of the men in the camp, the name of the one was Eldad, and the name of the other Medad: and the spirit rested upon them; and they were of them that were written, but went not out unto the tabernacle: and they prophesied in the camp. 27  And there ran a young man, and told Moses, and said, Eldad and Medad do prophesy in the camp. 28  And Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Moses, one of his young men, answered and said, My lord Moses, forbid them. 29  And Moses said unto him, Enviest thou for my sake? would God that all the LORD’s people were prophets, and that the LORD would put his spirit upon them! 30  And Moses gat him into the camp, he and the elders of Israel.

31 ¶ And there went forth a [*]wind from the LORD, and brought quails from the sea, and let them fall by the camp, [†]as it were a day’s journey on this side, and as it were a day’s journey on the other side, round about the camp, and as it were two cubits high upon the face of the earth. 32  And the people stood up all that day, and all that night, and all the next day, and they gathered the quails: he that gathered least gathered ten homers: and they spread them all abroad for themselves round about the camp. 33  And while the [*]flesh was yet between their teeth, ere it was chewed, the wrath of the LORD was kindled against the people, and the LORD smote the people with a very great plague. 34  And he called the name of that place [∥]Kibroth-hattaavah: because there they buried the people that lusted. 35  And the people journeyed from Kibroth-hattaavah unto Hazeroth; and [†]abode at Hazeroth.

12

1  And Miriam and Aaron spake against Moses because of the [∥]Ethiopian woman whom he had married: for he had [†]married an Ethiopian woman. 2  And they said, Hath the LORD indeed spoken only by Moses? hath he not spoken also by us? And the LORD heard it. 3 (Now the man Moses was [*]very meek, above all the men which were upon the face of the earth.)

4  And the LORD spake suddenly unto Moses, and unto Aaron, and unto Miriam, Come out ye three unto the tabernacle of the congregation. And they three came out. 5  And the LORD came down in the pillar of the cloud, and stood in the door of the tabernacle, and called Aaron and Miriam: and they both came forth. 6  And he said, Hear now my words: If there be a prophet among you, I the LORD will make myself known unto him in a vision, and will speak unto him in a dream. 7  My servant Moses is not so, [*]who is faithful in all mine house. 8  With him will I speak [*]mouth to mouth, even apparently, and not in dark speeches; and the similitude of the LORD shall he behold: wherefore then were ye not afraid to speak against my servant Moses? 9  And the anger of the LORD was kindled against them; and he departed.

10  And the cloud departed from off the tabernacle; and, behold, Miriam became leprous, white as snow: and Aaron looked upon Miriam, and, behold, she was leprous. 11  And Aaron said unto Moses, Alas, my lord, I beseech thee, lay not the sin upon us, wherein we have done foolishly, and wherein we have sinned. 12  Let her not be as one dead, of whom the flesh is half consumed when he cometh out of his mother’s womb. 13  And Moses cried unto the LORD, saying, Heal her now, O God, I beseech thee.

14 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, If her father had but spit in her face, should she not be ashamed seven days? let her be [*]shut out from the camp seven days, and after that let her be received in again. 15  And Miriam was shut out from the camp seven days: and the people journeyed not till Miriam was brought in again. 16  And afterward the people removed from Hazeroth, and pitched in the wilderness of Paran.

13

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Send thou men, that they may search the land of Canaan, which I give unto the children of Israel: of every tribe of their fathers shall ye send a man, every one a ruler among them. 3  And Moses by the commandment of the LORD sent them from the wilderness of Paran: all those men were heads of the children of Israel. 4 And these were their names: of the tribe of Reuben, Shammua the son of Zaccur. 5  Of the tribe of Simeon, Shaphat the son of Hori. 6  Of the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh. 7  Of the tribe of Issachar, Igal the son of Joseph. 8  Of the tribe of Ephraim, Oshea the son of Nun. 9  Of the tribe of Benjamin, Palti the son of Raphu. 10  Of the tribe of Zebulun, Gaddiel the son of Sodi. 11  Of the tribe of Joseph, namely, of the tribe of Manasseh, Gaddi the son of Susi. 12  Of the tribe of Dan, Ammiel the son of Gemalli. 13  Of the tribe of Asher, Sethur the son of Michael. 14  Of the tribe of Naphtali, Nahbi the son of Vophsi. 15  Of the tribe of Gad, Geuel the son of Machi. 16 These are the names of the men which Moses sent to spy out the land. And Moses called Oshea the son of Nun Jehoshua.

17 ¶ And Moses sent them to spy out the land of Canaan, and said unto them, Get you up this way southward, and go up into the mountain: 18  And see the land, what it is; and the people that dwelleth therein, whether they be strong or weak, few or many; 19  And what the land is that they dwell in, whether it be good or bad; and what cities they be that they dwell in, whether in tents, or in strong holds; 20  And what the land is, whether it be fat or lean, whether there be wood therein, or not. And be ye of good courage, and bring of the fruit of the land. Now the time was the time of the firstripe grapes.

21 ¶ So they went up, and searched the land from the wilderness of Zin unto Rehob, as men come to Hamath. 22  And they ascended by the south, and came unto Hebron; where Ahiman, Sheshai, and Talmai, the children of Anak, were. (Now Hebron was built seven years before Zoan in Egypt.) 23 [*] And they came unto the [∥]brook of Eshcol, and cut down from thence a branch with one cluster of grapes, and they bare it between two upon a staff; and they brought of the pomegranates, and of the figs. 24  The place was called the [∥]brook [∥]Eshcol, because of the cluster of grapes which the children of Israel cut down from thence. 25  And they returned from searching of the land after forty days.

26 ¶ And they went and came to Moses, and to Aaron, and to all the congregation of the children of Israel, unto the wilderness of Paran, to Kadesh; and brought back word unto them, and unto all the congregation, and shewed them the fruit of the land. 27  And they told him, and said, We came unto the land whither thou sentest us, and surely it floweth with [*]milk and honey; and this is the fruit of it. 28  Nevertheless the people be strong that dwell in the land, and the cities are walled, and very great: and moreover we saw the children of Anak there. 29  The Amalekites dwell in the land of the south: and the Hittites, and the Jebusites, and the Amorites, dwell in the mountains: and the Canaanites dwell by the sea, and by the coast of Jordan. 30  And Caleb stilled the people before Moses, and said, Let us go up at once, and possess it; for we are well able to overcome it. 31  But the men that went up with him said, We be not able to go up against the people; for they are stronger than we. 32  And they brought up an evil report of the land which they had searched unto the children of Israel, saying, The land, through which we have gone to search it, is a land that eateth up the inhabitants thereof; and all the people that we saw in it are [†]men of a great stature. 33  And there we saw the giants, the sons of Anak, which come of the giants: and we were in our own sight as grasshoppers, and so we were in their sight.

14

1  And all the congregation lifted up their voice, and cried; and the people wept that night. 2  And all the children of Israel murmured against Moses and against Aaron: and the whole congregation said unto them, Would God that we had died in the land of Egypt! or would God we had died in this wilderness! 3  And wherefore hath the LORD brought us unto this land, to fall by the sword, that our wives and our children should be a prey? were it not better for us to return into Egypt? 4  And they said one to another, Let us make a captain, and let us return into Egypt.

5  Then Moses and Aaron fell on their faces before all the assembly of the congregation of the children of Israel.

6 ¶ And Joshua the son of Nun, and Caleb the son of Jephunneh, which were of them that searched the land, rent their clothes: 7  And they spake unto all the company of the children of Israel, saying, The land, which we passed through to search it, is an exceeding good land. 8  If the LORD delight in us, then he will bring us into this land, and give it us; a land which floweth with milk and honey. 9  Only rebel not ye against the LORD, neither fear ye the people of the land; for they are bread for us: their [†]defence is departed from them, and the LORD is with us: fear them not. 10  But all the congregation bade stone them with stones. And the glory of the LORD appeared in the tabernacle of the congregation before all the children of Israel.

11 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, How long will this people provoke me? and how long will it be ere they believe me, for all the signs which I have shewed among them? 12  I will smite them with the pestilence, and disinherit them, and will make of thee a greater nation and mightier than they.

13 ¶ And [*]Moses said unto the LORD, Then the Egyptians shall hear it, (for thou broughtest up this people in thy might from among them;) 14  And they will tell it to the inhabitants of this land: for they have heard that thou LORD art among this people, that thou LORD art seen face to face, and that [*]thy cloud standeth over them, and that thou goest before them, by day time in a pillar of a cloud, and in a pillar of fire by night.

15 ¶ Now if thou shalt kill all this people as one man, then the nations which have heard the fame of thee will speak, saying, 16  Because the LORD was not [*]able to bring this people into the land which he sware unto them, therefore he hath slain them in the wilderness. 17  And now, I beseech thee, let the power of my Lord be great, according as thou hast spoken, saying, 18  The LORD is [*]longsuffering, and of great mercy, forgiving iniquity and transgression, and by no means clearing the guilty, [*]visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth generation. 19  Pardon, I beseech thee, the iniquity of this people according unto the greatness of thy mercy, and as thou hast forgiven this people, from Egypt even [∥]until now.

20  And the LORD said, I have pardoned according to thy word: 21 But as truly as I live, all the earth shall be filled with the glory of the LORD. 22  Because all those men which have seen my glory, and my miracles, which I did in Egypt and in the wilderness, and have tempted me now these ten times, and have not hearkened to my voice; 23 [†] Surely they shall not see the land which I sware unto their fathers, neither shall any of them that provoked me see it: 24  But my servant [*]Caleb, because he had another spirit with him, and hath followed me fully, him will I bring into the land whereinto he went; and his seed shall possess it. 25 (Now the Amalekites and the Canaanites dwelt in the valley.) To morrow turn you, and get you into the wilderness by the way of the Red sea.

26 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, 27 How long shall I bear with this evil congregation, which murmur against me? I have heard the murmurings of the children of Israel, which they murmur against me. 28  Say unto them, [*] As truly as I live, saith the LORD, as ye have spoken in mine ears, so will I do to you: 29  Your carcases shall fall in this wilderness; and all that were [*]numbered of you, according to your whole number, from twenty years old and upward, which have murmured against me, 30  Doubtless ye shall not come into the land, concerning which I [†]sware to make you dwell therein, save Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun. 31  But your little ones, which ye said should be a prey, them will I bring in, and they shall know the land which ye have despised. 32 But as for you, your carcases, they shall fall in this wilderness. 33  And your children shall [∥]wander in the wilderness forty years, and bear your whoredoms, until your carcases be wasted in the wilderness. 34  After the number of the days in which ye searched the land, even [*]forty days, each day for a year, shall ye bear your iniquities, even forty years, and ye shall know my [∥]breach of promise. 35  I the LORD have said, I will surely do it unto all this evil congregation, that are gathered together against me: in this wilderness they shall be consumed, and there they shall die.

36  And the men, which Moses sent to search the land, who returned, and made all the congregation to murmur against him, by bringing up a slander upon the land, 37  Even those men that did bring up the evil report upon the land, [*]died by the plague before the LORD. 38  But Joshua the son of Nun, and Caleb the son of Jephunneh, which were of the men that went to search the land, lived still. 39  And Moses told these sayings unto all the children of Israel: and the people mourned greatly.

40 ¶ And they rose up early in the morning, and gat them up into the top of the mountain, saying, Lo, we [*]be here, and will go up unto the place which the LORD hath promised: for we have sinned. 41  And Moses said, Wherefore now do ye transgress the commandment of the LORD? but it shall not prosper. 42  Go not up, for the LORD is not among you; that ye be not smitten before your enemies. 43  For the Amalekites and the Canaanites are there before you, and ye shall fall by the sword: because ye are turned away from the LORD, therefore the LORD will not be with you. 44  But they presumed to go up unto the hill top: nevertheless the ark of the covenant of the LORD, and Moses, departed not out of the camp. 45  Then the Amalekites came down, and the Canaanites which dwelt in that hill, and smote them, and [*]discomfited them, even unto Hormah.

15

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2 [*] Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye be come into the land of your habitations, which I give unto you, 3  And will make an offering by fire unto the LORD, a burnt offering, or a sacrifice [*]in [†]performing a vow, or in a freewill offering, or in your solemn feasts, to make a [*]sweet savour unto the LORD, of the herd, or of the flock: 4  Then [*]shall he that offereth his offering unto the LORD bring a meat offering of a tenth deal of flour mingled with the fourth part of an hin of oil. 5  And the fourth part of an hin of wine for a drink offering shalt thou prepare with the burnt offering or sacrifice, for one lamb. 6  Or for a ram, thou shalt prepare for a meat offering two tenth deals of flour mingled with the third part of an hin of oil. 7  And for a drink offering thou shalt offer the third part of an hin of wine, for a sweet savour unto the LORD. 8  And when thou preparest a bullock for a burnt offering, or for a sacrifice in performing a vow, or peace offerings unto the LORD: 9  Then shall he bring with a bullock a meat offering of three tenth deals of flour mingled with half an hin of oil. 10  And thou shalt bring for a drink offering half an hin of wine, for an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD. 11  Thus shall it be done for one bullock, or for one ram, or for a lamb, or a kid. 12  According to the number that ye shall prepare, so shall ye do to every one according to their number. 13  All that are born of the country shall do these things after this manner, in offering an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD. 14  And if a stranger sojourn with you, or whosoever be among you in your generations, and will offer an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD; as ye do, so he shall do. 15 [*] One ordinance shall be both for you of the congregation, and also for the stranger that sojourneth with you, an ordinance for ever in your generations: as ye are, so shall the stranger be before the LORD. 16  One law and one manner shall be for you, and for the stranger that sojourneth with you.

17 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 18  Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land whither I bring you, 19  Then it shall be, that, when ye eat of the bread of the land, ye shall offer up an heave offering unto the LORD. 20  Ye shall offer up a cake of the first of your dough for an heave offering: as ye do the heave offering of the threshingfloor, so shall ye heave it. 21  Of the first of your dough ye shall give unto the LORD an heave offering in your generations.

22 ¶ And if ye have erred, and not observed all these commandments, which the LORD hath spoken unto Moses, 23  Even all that the LORD hath commanded you by the hand of Moses, from the day that the LORD commanded Moses, and henceforward among your generations; 24 Then it shall be, if ought be committed by ignorance [†]without the knowledge of the congregation, that all the congregation shall offer one young bullock for a burnt offering, for a sweet savour unto the LORD, with his meat offering, and his drink offering, according to the [∥]manner, and one kid of the goats for a sin offering. 25  And the priest shall make an atonement for all the congregation of the children of Israel, and it shall be forgiven them; for it is ignorance: and they shall bring their offering, a sacrifice made by fire unto the LORD, and their sin offering before the LORD, for their ignorance: 26  And it shall be forgiven all the congregation of the children of Israel, and the stranger that sojourneth among them; seeing all the people were in ignorance.

27 ¶ And [*]if any soul sin through ignorance, then he shall bring a she goat of the first year for a sin offering. 28  And the priest shall make an atonement for the soul that sinneth ignorantly, when he sinneth by ignorance before the LORD, to make an atonement for him; and it shall be forgiven him. 29  Ye shall have one law for him that [†]sinneth through ignorance, both for him that is born among the children of Israel, and for the stranger that sojourneth among them.

30 ¶ But the soul that doeth ought [†]presumptuously, whether he be born in the land, or a stranger, the same reproacheth the LORD; and that soul shall be cut off from among his people. 31  Because he hath despised the word of the LORD, and hath broken his commandment, that soul shall utterly be cut off; his iniquity shall be upon him.

32 ¶ And while the children of Israel were in the wilderness, they found a man that gathered sticks upon the sabbath day. 33  And they that found him gathering sticks brought him unto Moses and Aaron, and unto all the congregation. 34  And they put him [*]in ward, because it was not declared what should be done to him. 35  And the LORD said unto Moses, The man shall be surely put to death: all the congregation shall stone him with stones without the camp. 36  And all the congregation brought him without the camp, and stoned him with stones, and he died; as the LORD commanded Moses.

37 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 38  Speak unto the children of Israel, and bid [*]them that they make them fringes in the borders of their garments throughout their generations, and that they put upon the fringe of the borders a ribband of blue: 39  And it shall be unto you for a fringe, that ye may look upon it, and remember all the commandments of the LORD, and do them; and that ye seek not after your own heart and your own eyes, after which ye use to go a whoring: 40  That ye may remember, and do all my commandments, and be holy unto your God. 41 I am the LORD your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am the LORD your God.

16

1  Now [*]Korah, the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, and Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, and On, the son of Peleth, sons of Reuben, took men: 2  And they rose up before Moses, with certain of the children of Israel, two hundred and fifty princes of the assembly, [*]famous in the congregation, men of renown: 3  And they gathered themselves together against Moses and against Aaron, and said unto them, [†]Ye take too much upon you, seeing all the congregation are holy, every one of them, and the LORD is among them: wherefore then lift ye up yourselves above the congregation of the LORD? 4  And when Moses heard it, he fell upon his face: 5  And he spake unto Korah and unto all his company, saying, Even to morrow the LORD will shew who are his, and who is holy; and will cause him to come near unto him: even him whom he hath chosen will he cause to come near unto him. 6  This do; Take you censers, Korah, and all his company; 7  And put fire therein, and put incense in them before the LORD to morrow: and it shall be that the man whom the LORD doth choose, he shall be holy: ye take too much upon you, ye sons of Levi. 8  And Moses said unto Korah, Hear, I pray you, ye sons of Levi: 9  Seemeth it but a small thing unto you, that the God of Israel hath separated you from the congregation of Israel, to bring you near to himself to do the service of the tabernacle of the LORD, and to stand before the congregation to minister unto them? 10  And he hath brought thee near to him, and all thy brethren the sons of Levi with thee: and seek ye the priesthood also? 11  For which cause both thou and all thy company are gathered together against the LORD: and what is Aaron, that ye murmur against him?

12 ¶ And Moses sent to call Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab: which said, We will not come up: 13  Is it a small thing that thou hast brought us up out of a land that floweth with milk and honey, to kill us in the wilderness, except thou make thyself altogether a prince over us? 14  Moreover thou hast not brought us into a land that floweth with milk and honey, or given us inheritance of fields and vineyards: wilt thou [†]put out the eyes of these men? we will not come up. 15  And Moses was very wroth, and said unto the LORD, [*]Respect not thou their offering: I have not taken one ass from them, neither have I hurt one of them. 16  And Moses said unto Korah, Be thou and all thy company before the LORD, thou, and they, and Aaron, to morrow: 17  And take every man his censer, and put incense in them, and bring ye before the LORD every man his censer, two hundred and fifty censers; thou also, and Aaron, each of you his censer. 18  And they took every man his censer, and put fire in them, and laid incense thereon, and stood in the door of the tabernacle of the congregation with Moses and Aaron. 19  And Korah gathered all the congregation against them unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and the glory of the LORD appeared unto all the congregation. 20  And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, 21  Separate yourselves from among this congregation, that I may consume them in a moment. 22  And they fell upon their faces, and said, O God, the God of the spirits of all flesh, shall one man sin, and wilt thou be wroth with all the congregation?

23 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 24  Speak unto the congregation, saying, Get you up from about the tabernacle of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram. 25  And Moses rose up and went unto Dathan and Abiram; and the elders of Israel followed him. 26  And he spake unto the congregation, saying, Depart, I pray you, from the tents of these wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, lest ye be consumed in all their sins. 27  So they gat up from the tabernacle of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram, on every side: and Dathan and Abiram came out, and stood in the door of their tents, and their wives, and their sons, and their little children. 28  And Moses said, Hereby ye shall know that the LORD hath sent me to do all these works; for I have not done them of mine own mind. 29  If these men die [†]the common death of all men, or if they be visited after the visitation of all men; then the LORD hath not sent me. 30  But if the LORD [†]make a new thing, and the earth open her mouth, and swallow them up, with all that appertain unto them, and they go down quick into the pit; then ye shall understand that these men have provoked the LORD.

31 ¶ [*]And it came to pass, as he had made an end of speaking all these words, that the ground clave asunder that was under them: 32  And the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed them up, and their houses, and all the men that appertained unto Korah, and all their goods. 33 They, and all that appertained to them, went down alive into the pit, and the earth closed upon them: and they perished from among the congregation. 34  And all Israel that were round about them fled at the cry of them: for they said, Lest the earth swallow us up also.

35  And there came out a fire from the LORD, and consumed the two hundred and fifty men that offered incense.

36 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 37  Speak unto Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest, that he take up the censers out of the burning, and scatter thou the fire yonder; for they are hallowed. 38  The censers of these sinners against their own souls, let them make them broad plates for a covering of the altar: for they offered them before the LORD, therefore they are hallowed: and they shall be a sign unto the children of Israel. 39  And Eleazar the priest took the brasen censers, wherewith they that were burnt had offered; and they were made broad plates for a covering of the altar: 40  To be a memorial unto the children of Israel, that no stranger, which is not of the seed of Aaron, come near to offer incense before the LORD; that he be not as Korah, and as his company: as the LORD said to him by the hand of Moses.

41 ¶ But on the morrow all the congregation of the children of Israel murmured against Moses and against Aaron, saying, Ye have killed the people of the LORD. 42  And it came to pass, when the congregation was gathered against Moses and against Aaron, that they looked toward the tabernacle of the congregation: and, behold, the cloud covered it, and the glory of the LORD appeared. 43  And Moses and Aaron came before the tabernacle of the congregation.

44 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 45  Get you up from among this congregation, that I may consume them as in a moment. And they fell upon their faces.

46 ¶ And Moses said unto Aaron, Take a censer, and put fire therein from off the altar, and put on incense, and go quickly unto the congregation, and make an atonement for them: for there is wrath gone out from the LORD; the plague is begun. 47  And Aaron took as Moses commanded, and ran into the midst of the congregation; and, behold, the plague was begun among the people: and he put on incense, and made an atonement for the people. 48  And he stood between the dead and the living; and the plague was stayed. 49  Now they that died in the plague were fourteen thousand and seven hundred, beside them that died about the matter of Korah. 50  And Aaron returned unto Moses unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and the plague was stayed.

17

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Speak unto the children of Israel, and take of every one of them a rod according to the house of their fathers, of all their princes according to the house of their fathers twelve rods: write thou every man’s name upon his rod. 3  And thou shalt write Aaron’s name upon the rod of Levi: for one rod shall be for the head of the house of their fathers. 4  And thou shalt lay them up in the tabernacle of the congregation before the testimony, [*]where I will meet with you. 5 And it shall come to pass, that the man’s rod, whom I shall choose, shall blossom: and I will make to cease from me the murmurings of the children of Israel, whereby they murmur against you.

6 ¶ And Moses spake unto the children of Israel, and every one of their princes gave him [†]a rod apiece, for each prince one, according to their fathers’ houses, even twelve rods: and the rod of Aaron was among their rods. 7  And Moses laid up the rods before the LORD in the tabernacle of witness.

8  And it came to pass, that on the morrow Moses went into the tabernacle of witness; and, behold, the rod of Aaron for the house of Levi was budded, and brought forth buds, and bloomed blossoms, and yielded almonds. 9  And Moses brought out all the rods from before the LORD unto all the children of Israel: and they looked, and took every man his rod.

10 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Bring [*]Aaron’s rod again before the testimony, to be kept for a token against the [†]rebels; and thou shalt quite take away their murmurings from me, that they die not. 11  And Moses did so: as the LORD commanded him, so did he. 12  And the children of Israel spake unto Moses, saying, Behold, we die, we perish, we all perish. 13  Whosoever cometh any thing near unto the tabernacle of the LORD shall die: shall we be consumed with dying?

18

1  And the LORD said unto Aaron, Thou and thy sons and thy father’s house with thee shall bear the iniquity of the sanctuary: and thou and thy sons with thee shall bear the iniquity of your priesthood. 2  And thy brethren also of the tribe of Levi, the tribe of thy father, bring thou with thee, that they may be joined unto thee, and minister unto thee: but thou and thy sons with thee shall minister before the tabernacle of witness. 3  And they shall keep thy charge, and the charge of all the tabernacle: only they shall not come nigh the vessels of the sanctuary and the altar, that neither they, nor ye also, die. 4  And they shall be joined unto thee, and keep the charge of the tabernacle of the congregation, for all the service of the tabernacle: and a stranger shall not come nigh unto you. 5  And ye shall keep the charge of the sanctuary, and the charge of the altar: that there be no wrath any more upon the children of Israel. 6  And I, behold, I have [*]taken your brethren the Levites from among the children of Israel: to you they are given as a gift for the LORD, to do the service of the tabernacle of the congregation. 7  Therefore thou and thy sons with thee shall keep your priest’s office for every thing of the altar, and within the vail; and ye shall serve: I have given your priest’s office unto you as a service of gift: and the stranger that cometh nigh shall be put to death.

8 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Aaron, Behold, I also have given thee the charge of mine heave offerings of all the hallowed things of the children of Israel; unto thee have I given them by reason of the anointing, and to thy sons, by an ordinance for ever. 9  This shall be thine of the most holy things, reserved from the fire: every oblation of theirs, every meat offering of theirs, and every sin offering of theirs, and every trespass offering of theirs, which they shall render unto me, shall be most holy for thee and for thy sons. 10  In the most holy place shalt thou eat it; every male shall eat it: it shall be holy unto thee. 11 And this is thine; the heave offering of their gift, with all the wave offerings of the children of Israel: I have given them unto [*]thee, and to thy sons and to thy daughters with thee, by a statute for ever: every one that is clean in thy house shall eat of it. 12  All the [†]best of the oil, and all the best of the wine, and of the wheat, the firstfruits of them which they shall offer unto the LORD, them have I given thee. 13  And whatsoever is first ripe in the land, which they shall bring unto the LORD, shall be thine; every one that is clean in thine house shall eat of it. 14 [*] Every thing devoted in Israel shall be thine. 15  Every thing that openeth [*]the matrix in all flesh, which they bring unto the LORD, whether it be of men or beasts, shall be thine: nevertheless the firstborn of man shalt thou surely redeem, and the firstling of unclean beasts shalt thou redeem. 16  And those that are to be redeemed from a month old shalt thou redeem, according to thine estimation, for the money of five shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary, [*]which is twenty gerahs. 17  But the firstling of a cow, or the firstling of a sheep, or the firstling of a goat, thou shalt not redeem; they are holy: thou shalt sprinkle their blood upon the altar, and shalt burn their fat for an offering made by fire, for a sweet savour unto the LORD. 18  And the flesh of them shall be thine, as the [*]wave breast and as the right shoulder are thine. 19  All the heave offerings of the holy things, which the children of Israel offer unto the LORD, have I given thee, and thy sons and thy daughters with thee, by a statute for ever: it is a covenant of salt for ever before the LORD unto thee and to thy seed with thee.

20 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Aaron, Thou shalt have no inheritance in their land, neither shalt thou have any part among them: [*]I am thy part and thine inheritance among the children of Israel. 21  And, behold, I have given the children of Levi all the tenth in Israel for an inheritance, for their service which they serve, even the service of the tabernacle of the congregation. 22  Neither must the children of Israel henceforth come nigh the tabernacle of the congregation, lest they bear sin, [†]and die. 23  But the Levites shall do the service of the tabernacle of the congregation, and they shall bear their iniquity: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations, that among the children of Israel they have no inheritance. 24  But the tithes of the children of Israel, which they offer as an heave offering unto the LORD, I have given to the Levites to inherit: therefore I have said unto them, Among the children of Israel they shall have no inheritance.

25 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 26  Thus speak unto the Levites, and say unto them, When ye take of the children of Israel the tithes which I have given you from them for your inheritance, then ye shall offer up an heave offering of it for the LORD, even a tenth part of the tithe. 27 And this your heave offering shall be reckoned unto you, as though it were the corn of the threshingfloor, and as the fulness of the winepress. 28  Thus ye also shall offer an heave offering unto the LORD of all your tithes, which ye receive of the children of Israel; and ye shall give thereof the LORD’s heave offering to Aaron the priest. 29  Out of all your gifts ye shall offer every heave offering of the LORD, of all the [†]best thereof, even the hallowed part thereof out of it. 30  Therefore thou shalt say unto them, When ye have heaved the best thereof from it, then it shall be counted unto the Levites as the increase of the threshingfloor, and as the increase of the winepress. 31  And ye shall eat it in every place, ye and your households: for it is your reward for your service in the tabernacle of the congregation. 32  And ye shall bear no sin by reason of it, when ye have heaved from it the best of it: neither shall ye pollute the holy things of the children of Israel, lest ye die.

19

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, 2 This is the ordinance of the law which the LORD hath commanded, saying, Speak unto the children of Israel, that they bring thee a red heifer without spot, wherein is no blemish, and upon which never came yoke: 3  And ye shall give her unto Eleazar the priest, that he may bring her [*]forth without the camp, and one shall slay her before his face: 4  And Eleazar the priest shall take of her blood with his finger, and [*]sprinkle of her blood directly before the tabernacle of the congregation seven times: 5 And one shall burn the heifer in his sight; [*]her skin, and her flesh, and her blood, with her dung, shall he burn: 6  And the priest shall take cedar wood, and hyssop, and scarlet, and cast it into the midst of the burning of the heifer. 7  Then the priest shall wash his clothes, and he shall bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp, and the priest shall be unclean until the even. 8  And he that burneth her shall wash his clothes in water, and bathe his flesh in water, and shall be unclean until the even. 9  And a man that is clean shall gather up the ashes of the heifer, and lay them up without the camp in a clean place, and it shall be kept for the congregation of the children of Israel for a water of separation: it is a purification for sin. 10  And he that gathereth the ashes of the heifer shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: and it shall be unto the children of Israel, and unto the stranger that sojourneth among them, for a statute for ever.

11 ¶ He that toucheth the dead body of any [†]man shall be unclean seven days. 12  He shall purify himself with it on the third day, and on the seventh day he shall be clean: but if he purify not himself the third day, then the seventh day he shall not be clean. 13  Whosoever toucheth the dead body of any man that is dead, and purifieth not himself, defileth the tabernacle of the LORD; and that soul shall be cut off from Israel: because the water of separation was not sprinkled upon him, he shall be unclean; his uncleanness is yet upon him. 14 This is the law, when a man dieth in a tent: all that come into the tent, and all that is in the tent, shall be unclean seven days. 15  And every open vessel, which hath no covering bound upon it, is unclean. 16  And whosoever toucheth one that is slain with a sword in the open fields, or a dead body, or a bone of a man, or a grave, shall be unclean seven days. 17  And for an unclean person they shall take of the [†]ashes of the burnt heifer of purification for sin, and [†]running water shall be put thereto in a vessel: 18  And a clean person shall take hyssop, and dip it in the water, and sprinkle it upon the tent, and upon all the vessels, and upon the persons that were there, and upon him that touched a bone, or one slain, or one dead, or a grave: 19  And the clean person shall sprinkle upon the unclean on the third day, and on the seventh day: and on the seventh day he shall purify himself, and wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and shall be clean at even. 20  But the man that shall be unclean, and shall not purify himself, that soul shall be cut off from among the congregation, because he hath defiled the sanctuary of the LORD: the water of separation hath not been sprinkled upon him; he is unclean. 21  And it shall be a perpetual statute unto them, that he that sprinkleth the water of separation shall wash his clothes; and he that toucheth the water of separation shall be unclean until even. 22  And whatsoever the unclean person toucheth shall be unclean; and the soul that toucheth it shall be unclean until even.

20

1  Then came the children of Israel, even the whole congregation, into the desert of Zin in the first month: and the people abode in Kadesh; and Miriam died there, and was buried there. 2  And there was no water for the congregation: and they gathered themselves together against Moses and against Aaron. 3  And the people chode with Moses, and spake, saying, Would God that we had died [*]when our brethren died before the LORD! 4  And [*]why have ye brought up the congregation of the LORD into this wilderness, that we and our cattle should die there? 5  And wherefore have ye made us to come up out of Egypt, to bring us in unto this evil place? it is no place of seed, or of figs, or [‡]of vines, or of pomegranates; neither is there any water to drink. 6  And Moses and Aaron went from the presence of the assembly unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and they fell upon their faces: and the glory of the LORD appeared unto them.

7 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 8  Take the rod, and gather thou the assembly together, thou, and Aaron thy brother, and speak ye unto the rock before their eyes; and it shall give forth his water, and thou shalt bring forth to them water out of the rock: so thou shalt give the congregation and their beasts drink. 9  And Moses took the rod from before the LORD, as he commanded him. 10  And Moses and Aaron gathered the congregation together before the rock, and he said unto them, Hear now, ye rebels; must we fetch you water out of this rock? 11  And Moses lifted up his hand, and with his rod he smote the rock twice: and the water came out abundantly, and the congregation drank, and their beasts also.

12 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses and Aaron, Because ye believed me not, to sanctify me in the eyes of the children of Israel, therefore ye shall not bring this congregation into the land which I have given them. 13 [*]This is the water of [∥]Meribah; because the children of Israel strove with the LORD, and he was sanctified in them.

14 ¶ And Moses sent messengers from Kadesh unto the king of Edom, Thus saith thy brother Israel, Thou knowest all the travail that hath [†]befallen us: 15  How our fathers went down into Egypt, and we have dwelt in Egypt a long time; and the Egyptians vexed us, and our fathers: 16  And when we cried unto the LORD, he heard our voice, and sent an angel, and hath brought us forth out of Egypt: and, behold, we are in Kadesh, a city in the uttermost of thy border: 17  Let us pass, I pray thee, through thy country: we will not pass through the fields, or through the vineyards, neither will we drink of the water of the wells: we will go by the king’s high way, we will not turn to the right hand nor to the left, until we have passed thy borders. 18  And Edom said unto him, Thou shalt not pass by me, lest I come out against thee with the sword. 19  And the children of Israel said unto him, We will go by the high way: and if I and my cattle drink of thy water, then I will pay for it: I will only, without doing any thing else, go through on my feet. 20  And he said, Thou shalt not go through. And Edom came out against him with much people, and with a strong hand. 21  Thus Edom refused to give Israel passage through his border: wherefore Israel turned away from him.

22 ¶ And the children of Israel, even the whole congregation, journeyed from [*]Kadesh, and came unto mount Hor. 23  And the LORD spake unto Moses and Aaron in mount Hor, by the coast of the land of Edom, saying, 24  Aaron shall be gathered unto his people: for he shall not enter into the land which I have given unto the children of Israel, because ye rebelled against my [†]word at the water of Meribah. 25 [*] Take Aaron and Eleazar his son, and bring them up unto mount Hor: 26  And strip Aaron of his garments, and put them upon Eleazar his son: and Aaron shall be gathered unto his people, and shall die there. 27  And Moses did as the LORD commanded: and they went up into mount Hor in the sight of all the congregation. 28  And Moses stripped Aaron of his garments, and put them upon Eleazar his son; and [*]Aaron died there in the top of the mount: and Moses and Eleazar came down from the mount. 29  And when all the congregation saw that Aaron was dead, they mourned for Aaron thirty days, even all the house of Israel.

21

1 And when [*]king Arad the Canaanite, which dwelt in the south, heard tell that Israel came by the way of the spies; then he fought against Israel, and took some of them prisoners. 2  And Israel vowed a vow unto the LORD, and said, If thou wilt indeed deliver this people into my hand, then I will utterly destroy their cities. 3  And the LORD hearkened to the voice of Israel, and delivered up the Canaanites; and they utterly destroyed them and their cities: and he called the name of the place [∥]Hormah.

4 ¶ And they journeyed from mount Hor by the way of the Red sea, to compass the land of Edom: and the soul of the people was much [∥][†]discouraged because of the way. 5  And the people spake against God, and against Moses, Wherefore have ye brought us up out of Egypt to die in the wilderness? for there is no bread, neither is there any water; and [*]our soul loatheth this light bread. 6  And [*]the LORD sent fiery serpents among the people, and they bit the people; and much people of Israel died.

7 ¶ Therefore the people came to Moses, and said, We have sinned, for we have spoken against the LORD, and against thee; pray unto the LORD, that he take away the serpents from us. And Moses prayed for the people. 8  And the LORD said unto Moses, Make thee a fiery serpent, and set it upon a pole: and it shall come to pass, that every one that is bitten, when he looketh upon it, shall live. 9  And [*]Moses made a serpent of brass, and put it upon a pole, and it came to pass, that if a serpent had bitten any man, when he beheld the serpent of brass, he lived.

10 ¶ And the children of Israel set forward, and [*]pitched in Oboth. 11  And they journeyed from Oboth, and pitched at [∥]Ije-abarim, in the wilderness which is before Moab, toward the sunrising.

12 ¶ From thence they removed, and pitched in the valley of Zared. 13  From thence they removed, and pitched on the other side of Arnon, which is in the wilderness that cometh out of the coasts of the Amorites: for Arnon is the border of Moab, between Moab and the Amorites. 14  Wherefore it is said in the book of the wars of the LORD, [∥]What he did in the Red sea, and in the brooks of Arnon, 15  And at the stream of the brooks that goeth down to the dwelling of Ar, and [†]lieth upon the border of Moab. 16 And from thence they went to Beer: that is the well whereof the LORD spake unto Moses, Gather the people together, and I will give them water.

17 ¶ Then Israel sang this song, [†]Spring up, O well; [∥]sing ye unto it: 18  The princes digged the well, the nobles of the people digged it, by the direction of the lawgiver, with their staves. And from the wilderness they went to Mattanah: 19  And from Mattanah to Nahaliel: and from Nahaliel to Bamoth: 20  And from Bamoth in the valley, that is in the [†]country of Moab, to the top of [∥]Pisgah, which looketh toward [†]Jeshimon.

21 ¶ And Israel sent messengers unto Sihon king of the Amorites, saying, 22 [*] Let me pass through thy land: we will not turn into the fields, or into the vineyards; we will not drink of the waters of the well: but we will go along by the king’s high way, until we be past thy borders. 23 [*] And Sihon would not suffer Israel to pass through his border: but Sihon gathered all his people together, and went out against Israel into the wilderness: and he came to Jahaz, and fought against Israel. 24  And [*]Israel smote him with the edge of the sword, and possessed his land from Arnon unto Jabbok, even unto the children of Ammon: for the border of the children of Ammon was strong. 25  And Israel took all these cities: and Israel dwelt in all the cities of the Amorites, in Heshbon, and in all the [†]villages thereof. 26  For Heshbon was the city of Sihon the king of the Amorites, who had fought against the former king of Moab, and taken all his land out of his hand, even unto Arnon. 27  Wherefore they that speak in proverbs say, Come into Heshbon, let the city of Sihon be built and prepared: 28  For there is a fire gone out of Heshbon, a flame from the city of Sihon: it hath consumed Ar of Moab, and the lords of the high places of Arnon. 29  Woe to thee, Moab! thou art undone, O people of [*]Chemosh: he hath given his sons that escaped, and his daughters, into captivity unto Sihon king of the Amorites. 30  We have shot at them; Heshbon is perished even unto Dibon, and we have laid them waste even unto Nophah, which reacheth unto Medeba.

31 ¶ Thus Israel dwelt in the land of the Amorites. 32  And Moses sent to spy out Jaazer, and they took the villages thereof, and drove out the Amorites that were there.

33 ¶ [*]And they turned and went up by the way of Bashan: and Og the king of Bashan went out against them, he, and all his people, to the battle at Edrei. 34  And the LORD said unto Moses, Fear him not: for I have delivered him into thy hand, and all his people, and his land; and [*]thou shalt do to him as thou didst unto Sihon king of the Amorites, which dwelt at Heshbon. 35  So they smote him, and his sons, and all his people, until there was none left him alive: and they possessed his land.

22

1  And the children of Israel set forward, and pitched in the plains of Moab on this side Jordan by Jericho.

2 ¶ And Balak the son of Zippor saw all that Israel had done to the Amorites. 3  And Moab was sore afraid of the people, because they were many: and Moab was distressed because of the children of Israel. 4  And Moab said unto the elders of Midian, Now shall this company lick up all that are round about us, as the ox licketh up the grass of the field. And Balak the son of Zippor was king of the Moabites at that time. 5 [*] He sent messengers therefore unto Balaam the son of Beor to Pethor, which is by the river of the land of the children of his people, to call him, saying, Behold, there is a people come out from Egypt: behold, they cover the [†]face of the earth, and they abide over against me: 6  Come now therefore, I pray thee, curse me this people; for they are too mighty for me: peradventure I shall prevail, that we may smite them, and that I may drive them out of the land: for I wot that he whom thou blessest is blessed, and he whom thou cursest is cursed. 7  And the elders of Moab and the elders of Midian departed with the rewards of divination in their hand; and they came unto Balaam, and spake unto him the words of Balak. 8  And he said unto them, Lodge here this night, and I will bring you word again, as the LORD shall speak unto me: and the princes of Moab abode with Balaam. 9  And God came unto Balaam, and said, What men are these with thee? 10  And Balaam said unto God, Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, hath sent unto me, saying, 11 Behold, there is a people come out of Egypt, which covereth the face of the earth: come now, curse me them; peradventure [†]I shall be able to overcome them, and drive them out. 12  And God said unto Balaam, Thou shalt not go with them; thou shalt not curse the people: for they are blessed. 13  And Balaam rose up in the morning, and said unto the princes of Balak, Get you into your land: for the LORD refuseth to give me leave to go with you. 14  And the princes of Moab rose up, and they went unto Balak, and said, Balaam refuseth to come with us.

15 ¶ And Balak sent yet again princes, more, and more honourable than they. 16  And they came to Balaam, and said to him, Thus saith Balak the son of Zippor, [†]Let nothing, I pray thee, hinder thee from coming unto me: 17  For I will promote thee unto very great honour, and I will do whatsoever thou sayest unto me: come therefore, I pray thee, curse me this people. 18  And Balaam answered and said unto the servants of Balak, [*]If Balak would give me his house full of silver and gold, I cannot go beyond the word of the LORD my God, to do less or more. 19  Now therefore, I pray you, tarry ye also here this night, that I may know what the LORD will say unto me more. 20  And God came unto Balaam at night, and said unto him, If the men come to call thee, rise up, and go with them; but yet the word which I shall say unto thee, that shalt thou do. 21  And Balaam rose up in the morning, and saddled his ass, and went with the princes of Moab.

22 ¶ And God’s anger was kindled because he went: and the angel of the LORD stood in the way for an adversary against him. Now he was riding upon his ass, and his two servants were with him. 23  And [*]the ass saw the angel of the LORD standing in the way, and his sword drawn in his hand: and the ass turned aside out of the way, and went into the field: and Balaam smote the ass, to turn her into the way. 24  But the angel of the LORD stood in a path of the vineyards, a wall being on this side, and a wall on that side. 25  And when the ass saw the angel of the LORD, she thrust herself unto the wall, and crushed Balaam’s foot against the wall: and he smote her again. 26  And the angel of the LORD went further, and stood in a narrow place, where was no way to turn either to the right hand or to the left. 27  And when the ass saw the angel of the LORD, she fell down under Balaam: and Balaam’s anger was kindled, and he smote the ass with a staff. 28  And the LORD opened the mouth of the ass, and she said unto Balaam, What have I done unto thee, that thou hast smitten me these three times? 29  And Balaam said unto the ass, Because thou hast mocked me: I would there were a sword in mine hand, for now would I kill thee. 30  And the ass said unto Balaam, Am not I thine ass, [†]upon which thou hast ridden [∥]ever since I was thine unto this day? was I ever wont to do so unto thee? And he said, Nay. 31  Then the LORD opened the eyes of Balaam, and he saw the angel of the LORD standing in the way, and his sword drawn in his hand: and he bowed down his head, and [∥]fell flat on his face. 32  And the angel of the LORD said unto him, Wherefore hast thou smitten thine ass these three times? behold, I went out [†]to withstand thee, because thy way is perverse before me: 33  And the ass saw me, and turned from me these three times: unless she had turned from me, surely now also I had slain thee, and saved her alive. 34  And Balaam said unto the angel of the LORD, I have sinned; for I knew not that thou stoodest in the way against me: now therefore, if it [†]displease thee, I will get me back again. 35  And the angel of the LORD said unto Balaam, Go with the men: but only the word that I shall speak unto thee, that thou shalt speak. So Balaam went with the princes of Balak.

36 ¶ And when Balak heard that Balaam was come, he went out to meet him unto a city of Moab, which is in the border of Arnon, which is in the utmost coast. 37  And Balak said unto Balaam, Did I not earnestly send unto thee to call thee? wherefore camest thou not unto me? am I not able indeed to promote thee to honour? 38  And Balaam said unto Balak, Lo, I am come unto thee: have I now any power at all to say any thing? the word that God putteth in my mouth, that shall I speak. 39  And Balaam went with Balak, and they came unto [∥]Kirjath-huzoth. 40  And Balak offered oxen and sheep, and sent to Balaam, and to the princes that were with him. 41  And it came to pass on the morrow, that Balak took Balaam, and brought him up into the high places of Baal, that thence he might see the utmost part of the people.

23

1  And Balaam said unto Balak, Build me here seven altars, and prepare me here seven oxen and seven rams. 2  And Balak did as Balaam had spoken; and Balak and Balaam offered on every altar a bullock and a ram. 3  And Balaam said unto Balak, Stand by thy burnt offering, and I will go: peradventure the LORD will come to meet me: and whatsoever he sheweth me I will tell thee. And [∥]he went to an high place. 4  And God met Balaam: and he said unto him, I have prepared seven altars, and I have offered upon every altar a bullock and a ram. 5  And the LORD put a word in Balaam’s mouth, and said, Return unto Balak, and thus thou shalt speak. 6  And he returned unto him, and, lo, he stood by his burnt sacrifice, he, and all the princes of Moab. 7  And he took up his parable, and said, Balak the king of Moab hath brought me from Aram, out of the mountains of the east, saying, Come, curse me Jacob, and come, defy Israel. 8  How shall I curse, whom God hath not cursed? or how shall I defy, whom the LORD hath not defied? 9  For from the top of the rocks I see him, and from the hills I behold him: lo, the people shall dwell alone, and shall not be reckoned among the nations. 10  Who can count the dust of Jacob, and the number of the fourth part of Israel? Let [†]me die the death of the righteous, and let my last end be like his! 11  And Balak said unto Balaam, What hast thou done unto me? I took thee to curse mine enemies, and, behold, thou hast blessed them altogether. 12  And he answered and said, Must I not take heed to speak that which the LORD hath put in my mouth?

13  And Balak said unto him, Come, I pray thee, with me unto another place, from whence thou mayest see them: thou shalt see but the utmost part of them, and shalt not see them all: and curse me them from thence.

14 ¶ And he brought him into the field of Zophim, to the top of [∥]Pisgah, and built seven altars, and offered a bullock and a ram on every altar. 15  And he said unto Balak, Stand here by thy burnt offering, while I meet the Lord yonder. 16  And the LORD met Balaam, and [*]put a word in his mouth, and said, Go again unto Balak, and say thus. 17  And when he came to him, behold, he stood by his burnt offering, and the princes of Moab with him. And Balak said unto him, What hath the LORD spoken? 18  And he took up his parable, and said, Rise up, Balak, and hear; hearken unto me, thou son of Zippor: 19  God is not a man, that he should lie; neither the son of man, that he should repent: hath he said, and shall he not do it? or hath he spoken, and shall he not make it good? 20  Behold, I have received commandment to bless: and he hath blessed; and I cannot reverse it. 21  He hath not beheld iniquity in Jacob, neither hath he seen perverseness in Israel: the LORD his God is with him, and the shout of a king is among them. 22 [*] God brought them out of Egypt; he hath as it were the strength of an unicorn. 23 Surely there is no enchantment [∥]against Jacob, neither is there any divination against Israel: according to this time it shall be said of Jacob and of Israel, What hath God wrought! 24  Behold, the people shall rise up as a great lion, and lift up himself as a young lion: he shall not lie down until he eat of the prey, and drink the blood of the slain.

25 ¶ And Balak said unto Balaam, Neither curse them at all, nor bless them at all. 26  But Balaam answered and said unto Balak, Told not I thee, saying, All that the LORD speaketh, that I must do?

27 ¶ And Balak said unto Balaam, Come, I pray thee, I will bring thee unto another place; peradventure it will please God that thou mayest curse me them from thence. 28  And Balak brought Balaam unto the top of Peor, that looketh toward Jeshimon. 29  And Balaam said unto Balak, Build me here seven altars, and prepare me here seven bullocks and seven rams. 30  And Balak did as Balaam had said, and offered a bullock and a ram on every altar.

24

1  And when Balaam saw that it pleased the LORD to bless Israel, he went not, as at [*]other times, [†]to seek for enchantments, but he set his face toward the wilderness. 2  And Balaam lifted up his eyes, and he saw Israel abiding in his tents according to their tribes; and the spirit of God came upon him. 3 [*] And he took up his parable, and said, Balaam the son of Beor hath said, and the man [†]whose eyes are open hath said: 4  He hath said, which heard the words of God, which saw the vision of the Almighty, falling into a trance, but having his eyes open: 5  How goodly are thy tents, O Jacob, and thy tabernacles, O Israel! 6  As the valleys are they spread forth, as gardens by the [‡]river’s side, as the trees of lign aloes which the LORD hath planted, and as cedar trees beside the waters. 7  He shall pour the water out of his buckets, and his seed shall be in many waters, and his king shall be higher than Agag, and his kingdom shall be exalted. 8 [*] God brought him forth out of Egypt; he hath as it were the strength of an unicorn: he shall eat up the nations his enemies, and shall break their bones, and pierce them through with his arrows. 9 [*] He couched, he lay down as a lion, and as a great lion: who shall stir him up? Blessed is he that blesseth thee, and cursed is he that curseth thee.

10 ¶ And Balak’s anger was kindled against Balaam, and he smote his hands together: and Balak said unto Balaam, I called thee to curse mine enemies, and, behold, thou hast altogether blessed them these three times. 11  Therefore now flee thou to thy place: I thought to promote thee unto great honour; but, lo, the LORD hath kept thee back from honour. 12  And Balaam said unto Balak, Spake I not also to thy messengers which thou sentest unto me, saying, 13  If Balak would give me his house full of silver and gold, I cannot go beyond the commandment of the LORD, to do either good or bad of mine own mind; but what the LORD saith, that will I speak? 14  And now, behold, I go unto my people: come therefore, and I will advertise thee what this people shall do to thy people in the latter days.

15 ¶ And he took up his parable, and said, Balaam the son of Beor hath said, and the man whose eyes are open hath said: 16  He hath said, which heard the words of God, and knew the knowledge of the most High, which saw the vision of the Almighty, falling into a trance, but having his eyes open: 17  I shall see him, but not now: I shall behold him, but not nigh: there shall come a Star out of Jacob, and a Sceptre shall rise out of Israel, and shall [∥]smite the corners of Moab, and destroy all the children of Sheth. 18  And Edom shall be a possession, Seir also shall be a possession for his enemies; and Israel shall do valiantly. 19  Out of Jacob shall come he that shall have dominion, and shall destroy him that remaineth of the city.

20 ¶ [∥]And when he looked on Amalek, he took up his parable, and said, Amalek was the first of the nations; but his latter end shall be that he perish for ever. 21 [∥] And he looked on the Kenites, and took up his parable, and said, Strong is thy dwellingplace, and thou puttest thy nest in a rock. 22  Nevertheless [†]the Kenite shall be wasted, [∥]until Asshur shall carry thee away captive. 23  And he took up his parable, and said, Alas, who shall live when God doeth this! 24  And ships shall come from the coast of Chittim, and shall afflict Asshur, and shall afflict Eber, and he also shall perish for ever. 25  And Balaam rose up, and went and returned to his place: and Balak also went his way.

25

1  And Israel abode in [*]Shittim, and the people began to commit whoredom with the daughters of Moab. 2  And they called the people unto the sacrifices of their gods: and the people did eat, and bowed down to their gods. 3  And Israel joined himself unto Baal-peor: and the anger of the LORD was kindled against Israel. 4  And the LORD said unto Moses, [*]Take all the heads of the people, and hang them up before the LORD against the sun, that the fierce anger of the LORD may be turned away from Israel. 5  And Moses said unto the judges of Israel, Slay ye every one his men that were joined unto Baal-peor.

6 ¶ And, behold, one of the children of Israel came and brought unto his brethren a Midianitish woman in the sight of Moses, and in the sight of all the congregation of the children of Israel, who were weeping before the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. 7  And [*]when Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, saw it, he rose up from among the congregation, and took a javelin in his hand; 8  And he went after the man of Israel into the tent, and thrust both of them through, the man of Israel, and the woman through her belly. So the plague was stayed from the children of Israel. 9  And [*]those that died in the plague were twenty and four thousand.

10 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 11 [*] Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, hath turned my wrath away from the children of Israel, while he was zealous for my sake among them, that I consumed not the children of Israel in my jealousy. 12  Wherefore say, [*]Behold, I give unto him my covenant of peace: 13  And he shall have it, and his seed after him, even the covenant of an everlasting priesthood; because he was zealous for his God, and made an atonement for the children of Israel. 14  Now the name of the Israelite that was slain, even that was slain with the Midianitish woman, was Zimri, the son of Salu, a prince of a [†]chief house among the Simeonites. 15  And the name of the Midianitish woman that was slain was Cozbi, the daughter of Zur; he was head over a people, and of a chief house in Midian.

16 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 17 [*] Vex the Midianites, and smite them: 18  For they vex you with their wiles, wherewith they have beguiled you in the matter of Peor, and in the matter of Cozbi, the daughter of a prince of Midian, their sister, which was slain in the day of the plague for Peor’s sake.

26

1  And it came to pass after the plague, that the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest, saying, 2  Take the sum of all the congregation of the children of Israel, [*]from twenty years old and upward, throughout their fathers’ house, all that are able to go to war in Israel. 3  And Moses and Eleazar the priest spake with them in the plains of Moab by Jordan near Jericho, saying, 4  Take the sum of the people, from twenty years old and upward; as the LORD [*]commanded Moses and the children of Israel, which went forth out of the land of Egypt.

5 ¶ [*]Reuben, the eldest son of Israel: the children of Reuben; Hanoch, of whom cometh the family of the Hanochites: of Pallu, the family of the Palluites: 6  Of Hezron, the family of the Hezronites: of Carmi, the family of the Carmites. 7 These are the families of the Reubenites: and they that were numbered of them were forty and three thousand and seven hundred and thirty. 8  And the sons of Pallu; Eliab. 9  And the sons of Eliab; Nemuel, and Dathan, and Abiram. This is that Dathan and Abiram, which were famous in the congregation, who [*]strove against Moses and against Aaron in the company of Korah, when they strove against the LORD: 10  And the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed them up together with Korah, when that company died, what time the fire devoured two hundred and fifty men: and they became a sign. 11  Notwithstanding the children of Korah died not.

12 ¶ The sons of Simeon after their families: of Nemuel, the family of the Nemuelites: of Jamin, the family of the Jaminites: of Jachin, the family of the Jachinites: 13  Of Zerah, the family of the Zarhites: of Shaul, the family of the Shaulites. 14 These are the families of the Simeonites, twenty and two thousand and two hundred.

15 ¶ The children of Gad after their families: of Zephon, the family of the Zephonites: of Haggi, the family of the Haggites: of Shuni, the family of the Shunites: 16  Of Ozni, the family of the Oznites: of Eri, the family of the Erites: 17  Of Arod, the family of the Arodites: of Areli, the family of the Arelites. 18 These are the families of the children of Gad according to those that were numbered of them, forty thousand and five hundred.

19 ¶ [*]The sons of Judah were Er and Onan: and Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. 20  And the sons of Judah after their families were; of Shelah, the family of the Shelanites: of Pharez, the family of the Pharzites: of Zerah, the family of the Zarhites. 21  And the sons of Pharez were; of Hezron, the family of the Hezronites: of Hamul, the family of the Hamulites. 22 These are the families of Judah according to those that were numbered of them, threescore and sixteen thousand and five hundred.

23 ¶ Of the sons of Issachar after their families: of Tola, the family of the Tolaites: of Pua, the family of the Punites: 24  Of Jashub, the family of the Jashubites: of Shimron, the family of the Shimronites. 25 These are the families of Issachar according to those that were numbered of them, threescore and four thousand and three hundred.

26 ¶ Of the sons of Zebulun after their families: of Sered, the family of the Sardites: of Elon, the family of the Elonites: of Jahleel, the family of the Jahleelites. 27 These are the families of the Zebulunites according to those that were numbered of them, threescore thousand and five hundred.

28 ¶ The sons of Joseph after their families were Manasseh and Ephraim. 29  Of the sons of Manasseh: of [*]Machir, the family of the Machirites: and Machir begat Gilead: of Gilead come the family of the Gileadites. 30 These are the sons of Gilead: of Jeezer, the family of the Jeezerites: of Helek, the family of the Helekites: 31 And of Asriel, the family of the Asrielites: and of Shechem, the family of the Shechemites: 32 And of Shemida, the family of the Shemidaites: and of Hepher, the family of the Hepherites.

33 ¶ And [*]Zelophehad the son of Hepher had no sons, but daughters: and the names of the daughters of Zelophehad were Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. 34 These are the families of Manasseh, and those that were numbered of them, fifty and two thousand and seven hundred.

35 ¶ These are the sons of Ephraim after their families: of Shuthelah, the family of the Shuthalhites: of Becher, the family of the Bachrites: of Tahan, the family of the Tahanites. 36 And these are the sons of Shuthelah: of Eran, the family of the Eranites. 37 These are the families of the sons of Ephraim according to those that were numbered of them, thirty and two thousand and five hundred. These are the sons of Joseph after their families.

38 ¶ The sons of Benjamin after their families: of Bela, the family of the Belaites: of Ashbel, the family of the Ashbelites: of Ahiram, the family of the Ahiramites: 39  Of Shupham, the family of the Shuphamites: of Hupham, the family of the Huphamites. 40  And the sons of Bela were Ard and Naaman: of Ard, the family of the Ardites: and of Naaman, the family of the Naamites. 41 These are the sons of Benjamin after their families: and they that were numbered of them were forty and five thousand and six hundred.

42 ¶ These are the sons of Dan after their families: of Shuham, the family of the Shuhamites. These are the families of Dan after their families. 43  All the families of the Shuhamites, according to those that were numbered of them, were threescore and four thousand and four hundred.

44 ¶ Of the children of Asher after their families: of Jimna, the family of the Jimnites: of Jesui, the family of the Jesuites: of Beriah, the family of the Beriites. 45  Of the sons of Beriah: of Heber, the family of the Heberites: of Malchiel, the family of the Malchielites. 46  And the name of the daughter of Asher was Sarah. 47 These are the families of the sons of Asher according to those that were numbered of them; who were fifty and three thousand and four hundred.

48 ¶ Of the sons of Naphtali after their families: of Jahzeel, the family of the Jahzeelites: of Guni, the family of the Gunites: 49  Of Jezer, the family of the Jezerites: of Shillem, the family of the Shillemites. 50 These are the families of Naphtali according to their families: and they that were numbered of them were forty and five thousand and four hundred. 51 These were the numbered of the children of Israel, six hundred thousand and a thousand seven hundred and thirty.

52 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 53  Unto these the land shall be divided for an inheritance according to the number of names. 54 [*] To many thou shalt [†]give the more inheritance, and to few thou shalt [†]give the less inheritance: to every one shall his inheritance be given according to those that were numbered of him. 55  Notwithstanding the land shall be [*]divided by lot: according to the names of the tribes of their fathers they shall inherit. 56  According to the lot shall the possession thereof be divided between many and few.

57 ¶ [*]And these are they that were numbered of the Levites after their families: of Gershon, the family of the Gershonites: of Kohath, the family of the Kohathites: of Merari, the family of the Merarites. 58 These are the families of the Levites: the family of the Libnites, the family of the Hebronites, the family of the Mahlites, the family of the Mushites, the family of the Korathites. And Kohath begat Amram. 59  And the name of Amram’s wife was [*]Jochebed, the daughter of Levi, whom her mother bare to Levi in Egypt: and she bare unto Amram Aaron and Moses, and Miriam their sister. 60  And unto Aaron was born Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. 61  And [*]Nadab and Abihu died, when they offered strange fire before the LORD. 62  And those that were numbered of them were twenty and three thousand, all males from a month old and upward: for they were not numbered among the children of Israel, because there was no inheritance given them among the children of Israel.

63 ¶ These are they that were numbered by Moses and Eleazar the priest, who numbered the children of Israel in the plains of Moab by Jordan near Jericho. 64  But among these there was not a man of them whom Moses and Aaron the priest numbered, when they numbered the children of Israel in the wilderness of Sinai. 65  For the LORD had said of them, They [*]shall surely die in the wilderness. And there was not left a man of them, save Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun.

27

1  Then came the daughters of [*]Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, of the families of Manasseh the son of Joseph: and these are the names of his daughters; Mahlah, Noah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Tirzah. 2  And they stood before Moses, and before Eleazar the priest, and before the princes and all the congregation, by the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, saying, 3  Our father [*]died in the wilderness, and he was not in the company of them that gathered themselves together against the LORD in the company of Korah; but died in his own sin, and had no sons. 4  Why should the name of our father be [†]done away from among his family, because he hath no son? Give unto us therefore a possession among the brethren of our father. 5  And Moses brought their cause before the LORD.

6 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 7  The daughters of Zelophehad speak right: thou shalt surely give them a possession of an inheritance among their father’s brethren; and thou shalt cause the inheritance of their father to pass unto them. 8  And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a man die, and have no son, then ye shall cause his inheritance to pass unto his daughter. 9  And if he have no daughter, then ye shall give his inheritance unto his brethren. 10  And if he have no brethren, then ye shall give his inheritance unto his father’s brethren. 11  And if his father have no brethren, then ye shall give his inheritance unto his kinsman that is next to him of his family, and he shall possess it: and it shall be unto the children of Israel a statute of judgment, as the LORD commanded Moses.

12 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, [*]Get thee up into this mount Abarim, and see the land which I have given unto the children of Israel. 13  And when thou hast seen it, thou also shalt be gathered unto thy people, as [*]Aaron thy brother was gathered. 14  For ye [*]rebelled against my commandment in the desert of Zin, in the strife of the congregation, to sanctify me at the water before their eyes: that is the [*]water of Meribah in Kadesh in the wilderness of Zin.

15 ¶ And Moses spake unto the LORD, saying, 16  Let the LORD, the God of the spirits of all flesh, set a man over the congregation, 17  Which may go out before them, and which may go in before them, and which may lead them out, and which may bring them in; that the congregation of the LORD be not as sheep which have no shepherd.

18 ¶ And the LORD said unto Moses, Take thee Joshua the son of Nun, a man in whom is the spirit, and lay thine hand upon him; 19  And set him before Eleazar the priest, and before all the congregation; and give him a charge in their sight. 20  And thou shalt put some of thine honour upon him, that all the congregation of the children of Israel may be obedient. 21  And he shall stand before Eleazar the priest, who shall ask counsel for him [*]after the judgment of Urim before the LORD: at his word shall they go out, and at his word they shall come in, both he, and all the children of Israel with him, even all the congregation. 22  And Moses did as the LORD commanded him: and he took Joshua, and set him before Eleazar the priest, and before all the congregation: 23  And he laid his hands upon him, and gave him a charge, as the LORD commanded by the hand of Moses.

28

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Command the children of Israel, and say unto them, My offering, and my bread for my sacrifices made by fire, for [†]a sweet savour unto me, shall ye observe to offer unto me in their due season. 3  And thou shalt say unto them, [*]This is the offering made by fire which ye shall offer unto the LORD; two lambs of the first year without spot [†]day by day, for a continual burnt offering. 4  The one lamb shalt thou offer in the morning, and the other lamb shalt thou offer [†]at even; 5  And a tenth part of an ephah of flour for a [*]meat offering, mingled with the fourth part of an [*]hin of beaten oil. 6  It is a continual burnt offering, which was ordained in mount Sinai for a sweet savour, a sacrifice made by fire unto the LORD. 7  And the drink offering thereof shall be the fourth part of an hin for the one lamb: in the holy place shalt thou cause the strong wine to be poured unto the LORD for a drink offering. 8  And the other lamb shalt thou offer at even: as the meat offering of the morning, and as the drink offering thereof, thou shalt offer it, a sacrifice made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD.

9 ¶ And on the sabbath day two lambs of the first year without spot, and two tenth deals of flour for a meat offering, mingled with oil, and the drink offering thereof: 10  This is the burnt offering of every sabbath, beside the continual burnt offering, and his drink offering.

11 ¶ And in the beginnings of your months ye shall offer a burnt offering unto the LORD; two young bullocks, and one ram, seven lambs of the first year without spot; 12  And three tenth deals of flour for a meat offering, mingled with oil, for one bullock; and two tenth deals of flour for a meat offering, mingled with oil, for one ram; 13  And a several tenth deal of flour mingled with oil for a meat offering unto one lamb; for a burnt offering of a sweet savour, a sacrifice made by fire unto the LORD. 14  And their drink offerings shall be half an hin of wine unto a bullock, and the third part of an hin unto a ram, and a fourth part of an hin unto a lamb: this is the burnt offering of every month throughout the months of the year. 15  And one kid of the goats for a sin offering unto the LORD shall be offered, beside the continual burnt offering, and his drink offering.

16 [*] And in the fourteenth day of the first month is the passover of the LORD. 17  And in the fifteenth day of this month is the feast: seven days shall unleavened bread be eaten. 18  In the [*]first day shall be an holy convocation; ye shall do no manner of servile work therein: 19  But ye shall offer a sacrifice made by fire for a burnt offering unto the LORD; two young bullocks, and one ram, and seven lambs of the first year: they shall be unto you without blemish: 20  And their meat offering shall be of flour mingled with oil: three tenth deals shall ye offer for a bullock, and two tenth deals for a ram; 21  A several tenth deal shalt thou offer for every lamb, throughout the seven lambs: 22  And one goat for a sin offering, to make an atonement for you. 23  Ye shall offer these beside the burnt offering in the morning, which is for a continual burnt offering. 24  After this manner ye shall offer daily, throughout the seven days, the meat of the sacrifice made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD: it shall be offered beside the continual burnt offering, and his drink offering. 25  And on the seventh day ye shall have an holy convocation; ye shall do no servile work.

26 ¶ Also in the day of the firstfruits, when ye bring a new meat offering unto the LORD, after your weeks be out, ye shall have an holy convocation; ye shall do no servile work: 27  But ye shall offer the burnt offering for a sweet savour unto the LORD; two young bullocks, one ram, seven lambs of the first year; 28  And their meat offering of flour mingled with oil, three tenth deals unto one bullock, two tenth deals unto one ram, 29  A several tenth deal unto one lamb, throughout the seven lambs; 30  And one kid of the goats, to make an atonement for you. 31  Ye shall offer them beside the continual burnt offering, and his meat offering, (they shall be unto you without blemish) and their drink offerings.

29

1  And in the seventh month, on the first day of the month, ye shall have an holy convocation; ye shall do no servile work: [*]it is a day of blowing the trumpets unto you. 2  And ye shall offer a burnt offering for a sweet savour unto the LORD; one young bullock, one ram, and seven lambs of the first year without blemish: 3  And their meat offering shall be of flour mingled with oil, three tenth deals for a bullock, and two tenth deals for a ram, 4  And one tenth deal for one lamb, throughout the seven lambs: 5  And one kid of the goats for a sin offering, to make an atonement for you: 6  Beside the burnt offering of the month, and his meat offering, and the daily burnt offering, and his meat offering, and their drink offerings, according unto their manner, for a sweet savour, a sacrifice made by fire unto the LORD.

7 ¶ And [*]ye shall have on the tenth day of this seventh month an holy convocation; and ye shall afflict your souls: ye shall not do any work therein: 8  But ye shall offer a burnt offering unto the LORD for a sweet savour; one young bullock, one ram, and seven lambs of the first year; they shall be unto you without blemish: 9  And their meat offering shall be of flour mingled with oil, three tenth deals to a bullock, and two tenth deals to one ram, 10  A several tenth deal for one lamb, throughout the seven lambs: 11  One kid of the goats for a sin offering; beside the sin offering of atonement, and the continual burnt offering, and the meat offering of it, and their drink offerings.

12 ¶ And on the fifteenth day of the seventh month ye shall have an holy convocation; ye shall do no servile work, and ye shall keep a feast unto the LORD seven days: 13  And ye shall offer a burnt offering, a sacrifice made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD; thirteen young bullocks, two rams, and fourteen lambs of the first year; they shall be without blemish: 14  And their meat offering shall be of flour mingled with oil, three tenth deals unto every bullock of the thirteen bullocks, two tenth deals to each ram of the two rams, 15  And a several tenth deal to each lamb of the fourteen lambs: 16  And one kid of the goats for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, his meat offering, and his drink offering.

17 ¶ And on the second day ye shall offer twelve young bullocks, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year without spot: 18  And their meat offering and their drink offerings for the bullocks, for the rams, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the manner: 19  And one kid of the goats for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, and the meat offering thereof, and their drink offerings.

20 ¶ And on the third day eleven bullocks, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year without blemish; 21  And their meat offering and their drink offerings for the bullocks, for the rams, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the manner: 22  And one goat for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, and his meat offering, and his drink offering.

23 ¶ And on the fourth day ten bullocks, two rams, and fourteen lambs of the first year without blemish: 24  Their meat offering and their drink offerings for the bullocks, for the rams, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the manner: 25  And one kid of the goats for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, his meat offering, and his drink offering.

26 ¶ And on the fifth day nine bullocks, two rams, and fourteen lambs of the first year without spot: 27  And their meat offering and their drink offerings for the bullocks, for the rams, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the manner: 28  And one goat for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, and his meat offering, and his drink offering.

29 ¶ And on the sixth day eight bullocks, two rams, and fourteen lambs of the first year without blemish: 30  And their meat offering and their drink offerings for the bullocks, for the rams, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the manner: 31  And one goat for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, his meat offering, and his drink offering.

32 ¶ And on the seventh day seven bullocks, two rams, and fourteen lambs of the first year without blemish: 33  And their meat offering and their drink offerings for the bullocks, for the rams, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the manner: 34  And one goat for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, his meat offering, and his drink offering.

35 ¶ On the eighth day ye shall have a [*]solemn assembly: ye shall do no servile work therein: 36  But ye shall offer a burnt offering, a sacrifice made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD: one bullock, one ram, seven lambs of the first year without blemish: 37  Their meat offering and their drink offerings for the bullock, for the ram, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the manner: 38  And one goat for a sin offering; beside the continual burnt offering, and his meat offering, and his drink offering. 39 These things ye shall [∥]do unto the LORD in your set feasts, beside your vows, and your freewill offerings, for your burnt offerings, and for your meat offerings, and for your drink offerings, and for your peace offerings. 40  And Moses told the children of Israel according to all that the LORD commanded Moses.

30

1  And Moses spake unto the heads of the tribes concerning the children of Israel, saying, This is the thing which the LORD hath commanded. 2  If a man vow a vow unto the LORD, or swear an oath to bind his soul with a bond; he shall not [†]break his word, he shall do according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth.

3  If a woman also vow a vow unto the LORD, and bind herself by a bond, being in her father’s house in her youth; 4  And her father hear her vow, and her bond wherewith she hath bound her soul, and her father shall hold his peace at her: then all her vows shall stand, and every bond wherewith she hath bound her soul shall stand. 5  But if her father disallow her in the day that he heareth; not any of her vows, or of her bonds wherewith she hath bound her soul, shall stand: and the LORD shall forgive her, because her father disallowed her. 6  And if she had at all an husband, when [†]she vowed, or uttered ought out of her lips, wherewith she bound her soul; 7  And her husband heard it, and held his peace at her in the day that he heard it: then her vows shall stand, and her bonds wherewith she bound her soul shall stand. 8  But if her husband [‡]disallowed her on the day that he heard it; then he shall make her vow which she vowed, and that which she uttered with her lips, wherewith she bound her soul, of none effect: and the LORD shall forgive her. 9  But every vow of a widow, and of her that is divorced, wherewith they have bound their souls, shall stand against her. 10  And if she vowed in her husband’s house, or bound her soul by a bond with an oath; 11  And her husband heard it, and held his peace at her, and disallowed her not: then all her vows shall stand, and every bond wherewith she bound her soul shall stand. 12  But if her husband hath utterly made them void on the day he heard them; then whatsoever proceeded out of her lips concerning her vows, or concerning the bond of her soul, shall not stand: her husband hath made them void; and the LORD shall forgive her. 13  Every vow, and every binding oath to afflict the soul, her husband may establish it, or her husband may make it void. 14  But if her husband altogether hold his peace at her from day to day; then he establisheth all her vows, or all her bonds, which are upon her: he confirmeth them, because he held his peace at her in the day that he heard them. 15  But if he shall any ways make them void after that he hath heard them; then he shall bear her iniquity. 16 These are the statutes, which the LORD commanded Moses, between a man and his wife, between the father and his daughter, being yet in her youth in her father’s house.

31

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2 [*] Avenge the children of Israel of the Midianites: afterward shalt thou [*]be gathered unto thy people. 3  And Moses spake unto the people, saying, Arm some of yourselves unto the war, and let them go against the Midianites, and avenge the LORD of Midian. 4 [†] Of every tribe a thousand, throughout all the tribes of Israel, shall ye send to the war. 5  So there were delivered out of the thousands of Israel, a thousand of every tribe, twelve thousand armed for war. 6  And Moses sent them to the war, a thousand of every tribe, them and Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, to the war, with the holy instruments, and the trumpets to blow in his hand.

7  And they warred against the Midianites, as the LORD commanded Moses; and they slew all the males. 8  And they slew the kings of Midian, beside the rest of them that were slain; namely, [*]Evi, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, five kings of Midian: Balaam also the son of Beor they slew with the sword. 9  And the children of Israel took all the women of Midian captives, and their little ones, and took the spoil of all their cattle, and all their flocks, and all their goods. 10  And they burnt all their cities wherein they dwelt, and all their goodly castles, with fire. 11  And they took all the spoil, and all the prey, both of men and of beasts. 12  And they brought the captives, and the prey, and the spoil, unto Moses, and Eleazar the priest, and unto the congregation of the children of Israel, unto the camp at the plains of Moab, which are by Jordan near Jericho.

13 ¶ And Moses, and Eleazar the priest, and all the princes of the congregation, went forth to meet them without the camp. 14  And Moses was wroth with the officers of the host, with the captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, which came from the [†]battle. 15  And Moses said unto them, Have ye saved all the women alive? 16  Behold, [*]these caused the children of Israel, through the [*]counsel of Balaam, to commit trespass against the LORD in the matter of Peor, and there was a plague among the congregation of the LORD. 17  Now therefore [*]kill every male among the little ones, and kill every woman that hath known man by lying with [†]him. 18  But all the women children, that have not known a man by lying with him, keep alive for yourselves. 19  And do ye abide without the camp seven days: whosoever hath killed any person, and [*]whosoever hath touched any slain, purify both yourselves and your captives on the third day, and on the seventh day. 20  And purify all your raiment, and all [†]that is made of skins, and all work of goats’ hair, and all things made of wood.

21 ¶ And Eleazar the priest said unto the men of war which went to the battle, This is the ordinance of the law which the LORD commanded Moses; 22  Only the gold, and the silver, the brass, the iron, the tin, and the lead, 23  Every thing that may abide the fire, ye shall make it go through the fire, and it shall be clean: nevertheless it shall be purified with the water of separation: and all that abideth not the fire ye shall make go through the water. 24  And ye shall wash your clothes on the seventh day, and ye shall be clean, and afterward ye shall come into the camp.

25 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 26  Take the sum of the prey [†]that was taken, both of man and of beast, thou, and Eleazar the priest, and the chief fathers of the congregation: 27  And divide the prey into two parts; between them that took the war upon them, who went out to battle, and between all the congregation: 28  And levy a tribute unto the LORD of the men of war which went out to battle: one soul of five hundred, both of the persons, and of the beeves, and of the asses, and of the sheep: 29  Take it of their half, and give it unto Eleazar the priest, for an heave offering of the LORD. 30  And of the children of Israel’s half, thou shalt take one portion of fifty, of the persons, of the beeves, of the asses, and of the [∥]flocks, of all manner of beasts, and give them unto the Levites, which keep the charge of the tabernacle of the LORD. 31  And Moses and Eleazar the priest did as the LORD commanded Moses. 32  And the booty, being the rest of the prey which the men of war had caught, was six hundred thousand and seventy thousand and five thousand sheep, 33  And threescore and twelve thousand beeves, 34  And threescore and one thousand asses, 35  And thirty and two thousand persons in all, of women that had not known man by lying with him. 36  And the half, which was the portion of them that went out to war, was in number three hundred thousand and seven and thirty thousand and five hundred sheep: 37  And the LORD’s tribute of the sheep was six hundred and threescore and fifteen. 38  And the beeves were thirty and six thousand; of which the LORD’s tribute was threescore and twelve. 39  And the asses were thirty thousand and five hundred; of which the LORD’s tribute was threescore and one. 40  And the persons were sixteen thousand; of which the LORD’s tribute was thirty and two persons. 41  And Moses gave the tribute, which was the LORD’s heave offering, unto Eleazar the priest, as the LORD commanded Moses. 42  And of the children of Israel’s half, which Moses divided from the men that warred, 43 (Now the half that pertained unto the congregation was three hundred thousand and thirty thousand and seven thousand and five hundred sheep, 44  And thirty and six thousand beeves, 45  And thirty thousand asses and five hundred, 46  And sixteen thousand persons;) 47  Even of the children of Israel’s half, Moses took one portion of fifty, both of man and of beast, and gave them unto the Levites, which kept the charge of the tabernacle of the LORD; as the LORD commanded Moses.

48 ¶ And the officers which were over thousands of the host, the captains of thousands, and captains of hundreds, came near unto Moses: 49  And they said unto Moses, Thy servants have taken the sum of the men of war which are under our [†]charge, and there lacketh not one man of us. 50  We have therefore brought an oblation for the LORD, what every man hath [†]gotten, of jewels of gold, chains, and bracelets, rings, earrings, and tablets, to make an atonement for our souls before the LORD. 51  And Moses and Eleazar the priest took the gold of them, even all wrought jewels. 52  And all the gold of the [†]offering that they offered up to the LORD, of the captains of thousands, and of the captains of hundreds, was sixteen thousand seven hundred and fifty shekels. 53 (For the men of war had taken spoil, every man for himself.) 54  And Moses and Eleazar the priest took the gold of the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and brought it into the tabernacle of the congregation, for a memorial for the children of Israel before the LORD.

32

1  Now the children of Reuben and the children of Gad had a very great multitude of cattle: and when they saw the land of Jazer, and the land of Gilead, that, behold, the place was a place for cattle; 2  The children of Gad and the children of Reuben came and spake unto Moses, and to Eleazar the priest, and unto the princes of the congregation, saying, 3  Ataroth, and Dibon, and Jazer, and Nimrah, and Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Shebam, and Nebo, and Beon, 4  Even the country which the LORD smote before the congregation of Israel, is a land for cattle, and thy servants have cattle: 5  Wherefore, said they, if we have found grace in thy sight, let this land be given unto thy servants for a possession, and bring us not over Jordan.

6 ¶ And Moses said unto the children of Gad and to the children of Reuben, Shall your brethren go to war, and shall ye sit here? 7  And wherefore [†]discourage ye the heart of the children of Israel from going over into the land which the LORD hath given them? 8  Thus did your fathers, when I sent them from Kadesh-barnea to see the land. 9  For [*]when they went up unto the valley of Eshcol, and saw the land, they discouraged the heart of the children of Israel, that they should not go into the land which the LORD had given them. 10  And the LORD’s anger was kindled the same time, and he sware, saying, 11  Surely none of the men that came up out of Egypt, [*]from twenty years old and upward, shall see the land which I sware unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob; because they have not [†]wholly followed me: 12  Save Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenezite, and Joshua the son of Nun: for they have wholly followed the LORD. 13  And the LORD’s anger was kindled against Israel, and he made them wander in the wilderness forty years, until all the generation, that had done evil in the sight of the LORD, was consumed. 14  And, behold, ye are risen up in your fathers’ stead, an increase of sinful men, to augment yet the fierce anger of the LORD toward Israel. 15  For if ye turn away from after him, he will yet again leave them in the wilderness; and ye shall destroy all this people.

16 ¶ And they came near unto him, and said, We will build sheepfolds here for our cattle, and cities for our little ones: 17  But we ourselves will go ready armed before the children of Israel, until we have brought them unto their place: and our little ones shall dwell in the fenced cities because of the inhabitants of the land. 18  We will not return unto our houses, until the children of Israel have inherited every man his inheritance. 19  For we will not inherit with them on yonder side Jordan, or forward; because our inheritance is fallen to us on this side Jordan eastward.

20 ¶ And [*]Moses said unto them, If ye will do this thing, if ye will go armed before the LORD to war, 21  And will go all of you armed over Jordan before the LORD, until he hath driven out his enemies from before him, 22  And the land be subdued before the LORD: then afterward ye shall return, and be guiltless before the LORD, and before Israel; and this land shall be your possession before the LORD. 23  But if ye will not do so, behold, ye have sinned against the LORD: and be sure your sin will find you out. 24  Build you cities for your little ones, and folds for your sheep; and do that which hath proceeded out of your mouth. 25  And the children of Gad and the children of Reuben spake unto Moses, saying, Thy servants will do as my lord commandeth. 26  Our little ones, our wives, our flocks, and all our cattle, shall be there in the cities of Gilead: 27 [*] But thy servants will pass over, every man armed for war, before the LORD to battle, as my lord saith.

28  So concerning them Moses commanded Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun, and the chief fathers of the tribes of the children of Israel: 29  And Moses said unto them, If the children of Gad and the children of Reuben will pass with you over Jordan, every man armed to battle, before the LORD, and the land shall be subdued before you; then ye shall give them the land of Gilead for a possession: 30  But if they will not pass over with you armed, they shall have possessions among you in the land of Canaan. 31  And the children of Gad and the children of Reuben answered, saying, As the LORD hath said unto thy servants, so will we do. 32  We will pass over armed before the LORD into the land of Canaan, that the possession of our inheritance on this side Jordan may be ours. 33  And [*]Moses gave unto them, even to the children of Gad, and to the children of Reuben, and unto half the tribe of Manasseh the son of Joseph, the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, and the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, the land, with the cities thereof in the coasts, even the cities of the country round about.

34 ¶ And the children of Gad built Dibon, and Ataroth, and Aroer, 35  And Atroth, Shophan, and Jaazer, and Jogbehah, 36  And Beth-nimrah, and Beth-haran, fenced cities: and folds for sheep. 37  And the children of Reuben built Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Kirjathaim, 38  And Nebo, and Baal-meon, (their names being changed,) and Shibmah: and [†]gave other names unto the cities which they builded. 39  And the children of [*]Machir the son of Manasseh went to Gilead, and took it, and dispossessed the Amorite which was in it. 40  And Moses gave Gilead unto Machir the son of Manasseh; and he dwelt therein. 41  And [*]Jair the son of Manasseh went and took the small towns thereof, and called them Havoth-jair. 42  And Nobah went and took Kenath, and the villages thereof, and called it Nobah, after his own name.

33

1 These are the journeys of the children of Israel, which went forth out of the land of Egypt with their armies under the hand of Moses and Aaron. 2  And Moses wrote their goings out according to their journeys by the commandment of the LORD: and these are their journeys according to their goings out. 3  And they [*]departed from Rameses in the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month; on the morrow after the passover the children of Israel went out with an high hand in the sight of all the Egyptians. 4  For the Egyptians buried all their firstborn, which the LORD had smitten among them: upon their gods also the LORD executed judgments. 5  And the children of Israel removed from Rameses, and pitched in Succoth. 6  And they departed from [*]Succoth, and pitched in Etham, which is in the edge of the wilderness. 7  And they removed from Etham, and turned again unto Pi-hahiroth, which is before Baal-zephon: and they pitched before Migdol. 8  And they departed from before Pi-hahiroth, and [*]passed through the midst of the sea into the wilderness, and went three days’ journey in the wilderness of Etham, and pitched in Marah. 9  And they removed from Marah, and [*]came unto Elim: and in Elim were twelve fountains of water, and threescore and ten palm trees; and they pitched there. 10  And they removed from Elim, and encamped by the Red sea. 11  And they removed from the Red sea, and encamped in the [*]wilderness of Sin. 12  And they took their journey out of the wilderness of Sin, and encamped in Dophkah. 13  And they departed from Dophkah, and encamped in Alush. 14  And they removed from Alush, and encamped at [*]Rephidim, where was no water for the people to drink. 15  And they departed from Rephidim, and pitched in the [*]wilderness of Sinai. 16  And they removed from the desert of Sinai, and pitched [*]at [∥]Kibroth-hattaavah. 17  And they departed from Kibroth-hattaavah, and [*]encamped at Hazeroth. 18  And they departed from Hazeroth, and pitched in Rithmah. 19  And they departed from Rithmah, and pitched at Rimmon-parez. 20  And they departed from Rimmon-parez, and pitched in Libnah. 21  And they removed from Libnah, and pitched at Rissah. 22  And they journeyed from Rissah, and pitched in Kehelathah. 23  And they went from Kehelathah, and pitched in mount Shapher. 24  And they removed from mount Shapher, and encamped in Haradah. 25  And they removed from Haradah, and pitched in Makheloth. 26  And they removed from Makheloth, and encamped at Tahath. 27  And they departed from Tahath, and pitched at Tarah. 28  And they removed from Tarah, and pitched in Mithcah. 29  And they went from Mithcah, and pitched in Hashmonah. 30  And they departed from Hashmonah, and [*]encamped at Moseroth. 31  And they departed from Moseroth, and pitched in Bene-jaakan. 32  And they removed from Bene-jaakan, and encamped at Hor-hagidgad. 33  And they went from Hor-hagidgad, and pitched in Jotbathah. 34  And they removed from Jotbathah, and encamped at Ebronah. 35  And they departed from Ebronah, and encamped at Ezion-gaber. 36  And they removed from Ezion-gaber, and pitched in the [*]wilderness of Zin, which is Kadesh. 37  And they removed from [*]Kadesh, and pitched in mount Hor, in the edge of the land of Edom. 38  And [*]Aaron the priest went up into mount Hor at the commandment of the LORD, and died there, in the fortieth year after the children of Israel were come out of the land of Egypt, in the first day of the fifth month. 39  And Aaron was an hundred and twenty and three years old when he died in mount Hor. 40  And [*]king Arad the Canaanite, which dwelt in the south in the land of Canaan, heard of the coming of the children of Israel. 41  And they departed from mount [*]Hor, and pitched in Zalmonah. 42  And they departed from Zalmonah, and pitched in Punon. 43  And they departed from Punon, and pitched in Oboth. 44  And they departed from Oboth, and pitched in [∥]Ije-abarim, in the border of Moab. 45  And they departed from Iim, and pitched in Dibon-gad. 46  And they removed from Dibon-gad, and encamped in Almon-diblathaim. 47  And they removed from Almon-diblathaim, and pitched in the mountains of Abarim, before Nebo. 48  And they departed from the mountains of Abarim, and pitched in the plains of Moab by Jordan near Jericho. 49  And they pitched by Jordan, from Beth-jesimoth even unto [∥][*]Abel-shittim in the plains of Moab.

50 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses in the plains of Moab by Jordan near Jericho, saying, 51  Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, [*]When ye are passed over Jordan into the land of Canaan; 52  Then ye shall drive out all the inhabitants of the land from before you, and destroy all their pictures, and destroy all their molten images, and quite pluck down all their high places: 53  And ye shall dispossess the inhabitants of the land, and dwell therein: for I have given you the land to possess it. 54  And [*]ye shall divide the land by lot for an inheritance among your families: and to the more ye shall [†]give the more inheritance, and to the fewer ye shall [†]give the less inheritance: every man’s inheritance shall be in the place where his lot falleth; according to the tribes of your fathers ye shall inherit. 55  But if ye will not drive out the inhabitants of the land from before you; then it shall come to pass, that those which ye let remain of them shall be [*]pricks in your eyes, and thorns in your sides, and shall vex you in the land wherein ye dwell. 56 Moreover it shall come to pass, that I shall do unto you, as I thought to do unto them.

34

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 2  Command the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land of Canaan; (this is the land that shall fall unto you for an inheritance, even the land of Canaan with the coasts thereof:) 3  Then [*]your south quarter shall be from the wilderness of Zin along by the coast of Edom, and your south border shall be the outmost coast of the salt sea eastward: 4  And your border shall turn from the south to the ascent of Akrabbim, and pass on to Zin: and the going forth thereof shall be from the south to Kadesh-barnea, and shall go on to Hazar-addar, and pass on to Azmon: 5  And the border shall fetch a compass from Azmon unto the river of Egypt, and the goings out of it shall be at the sea. 6 And as for the western border, ye shall even have the great sea for a border: this shall be your west border. 7  And this shall be your north border: from the great sea ye shall point out for you mount Hor: 8  From mount Hor ye shall point out your border unto the entrance of Hamath; and the goings forth of the border shall be to Zedad:

9 ¶ And the border shall go on to Ziphron, and the goings out of it shall be at Hazar-enan: this shall be your north border. 10  And ye shall point out your east border from Hazar-enan to Shepham: 11  And the coast shall go down from Shepham to Riblah, on the east side of Ain; and the border shall descend, and shall reach unto the [†]side of the sea of Chinnereth eastward: 12  And the border shall go down to Jordan, and the goings out of it shall be at the salt sea: this shall be your land with the coasts thereof round about. 13  And Moses commanded the children of Israel, saying, This is the land which ye shall inherit by lot, which the LORD commanded to give unto the nine tribes, and to the half tribe: 14 [*] For the tribe of the children of Reuben according to the house of their fathers, and the tribe of the children of Gad according to the house of their fathers, have received their inheritance; and half the tribe of Manasseh have received their inheritance: 15  The two tribes and the half tribe have received their inheritance on this side Jordan near Jericho eastward, toward the sunrising.

16  And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 17 These are the names of the men which shall divide the land unto you: [*]Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun. 18  And ye shall take one prince of every tribe, to divide the land by inheritance. 19  And the names of the men are these: Of the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh. 20  And of the tribe of the children of Simeon, Shemuel the son of Ammihud. 21  Of the tribe of Benjamin, Elidad the son of Chislon. 22  And the prince of the tribe of the children of Dan, Bukki the son of Jogli. 23  The prince of the children of Joseph, for the tribe of the children of Manasseh, Hanniel the son of Ephod. 24  And the prince of the tribe of the children of Ephraim, Kemuel the son of Shiphtan. 25  And the prince of the tribe of the children of Zebulun, Elizaphan the son of Parnach. 26  And the prince of the tribe of the children of Issachar, Paltiel the son of Azzan. 27  And the prince of the tribe of the children of Asher, Ahihud the son of Shelomi. 28  And the prince of the tribe of the children of Naphtali, Pedahel the son of Ammihud. 29 These are they whom the LORD commanded to divide the inheritance unto the children of Israel in the land of Canaan.

35

1  And the LORD spake unto Moses in the plains of Moab by Jordan near Jericho, saying, 2 [*] Command the children of Israel, that they give unto the Levites of the inheritance of their possession cities to dwell in; and ye shall give also unto the Levites suburbs for the cities round about them. 3  And the cities shall they have to dwell in; and the suburbs of them shall be for their cattle, and for their goods, and for all their beasts. 4  And the suburbs of the cities, which ye shall give unto the Levites, shall reach from the wall of the city and outward a thousand cubits round about. 5  And ye shall measure from without the city on the east side two thousand cubits, and on the south side two thousand cubits, and on the west side two thousand cubits, and on the north side two thousand cubits; and the city shall be in the midst: this shall be to them the suburbs of the cities. 6  And among the cities which ye shall give unto the Levites there shall be [*]six cities for refuge, which ye shall appoint for the manslayer, that he may flee thither: and [†]to them ye shall add forty and two cities. 7  So all the cities which ye shall give to the Levites shall be forty and eight cities: them shall ye give with their suburbs. 8  And the cities which ye shall give shall be of the possession of the children of Israel: from them that have many ye shall give many; but from them that have few ye shall give few: every one shall give of his cities unto the Levites according to his inheritance which [†]he inheriteth.

9 ¶ And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying, 10  Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, [*]When ye be come over Jordan into the land of Canaan; 11  Then ye shall appoint you cities to be cities of refuge for you; that the slayer may flee thither, which killeth any person [†]at unawares. 12  And they shall be unto you cities for refuge from the avenger; that the manslayer die not, until he stand before the congregation in judgment. 13  And of these cities which ye shall give six cities shall ye have for refuge. 14  Ye shall give three cities on this side Jordan, and three cities shall ye give in the land of Canaan, which shall be cities of refuge. 15  These six cities shall be a refuge, both for the children of Israel, and for the stranger, and for the sojourner among them: that every one that killeth any person unawares may flee thither. 16 [*] And if he smite him with an instrument of iron, so that he die, he is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to death. 17  And if he smite him [†]with throwing a stone, wherewith he may die, and he die, he is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to death. 18 Or if he smite him with an hand weapon of wood, wherewith he may die, and he die, he is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to death. 19  The revenger of blood himself shall slay the murderer: when he meeteth him, he shall slay him. 20  But if [*]he thrust him of hatred, or hurl at him by laying of wait, that he die; 21  Or in enmity smite him with his hand, that he die: he that smote him shall surely be put to death; for he is a murderer: the revenger of blood shall slay the murderer, when he meeteth him. 22  But if he thrust him suddenly [*]without enmity, or have cast upon him any thing without laying of wait, 23  Or with any stone, wherewith a man may die, seeing him not, and cast it upon him, that he die, and was not his enemy, neither sought his harm: 24  Then the congregation shall judge between the slayer and the revenger of blood according to these judgments: 25  And the congregation shall deliver the slayer out of the hand of the revenger of blood, and the congregation shall restore him to the city of his refuge, whither he was fled: and he shall abide in it unto the death of the high priest, which was anointed with the holy oil. 26  But if the slayer shall at any time come without the border of the city of his refuge, whither he was fled; 27  And the revenger of blood find him without the borders of the city of his refuge, and the revenger of blood kill the slayer; [†]he shall not be guilty of blood: 28  Because he should have remained in the city of his refuge until the death of the high priest: but after the death of the high priest the slayer shall return into the land of his possession. 29 So these things shall be for a statute of judgment unto you throughout your generations in all your dwellings. 30  Whoso killeth any person, the murderer shall be put to death by the [*]mouth of witnesses: but one witness shall not testify against any person to cause him to die. 31  Moreover ye shall take no satisfaction for the life of a murderer, which is [†]guilty of death: but he shall be surely put to death. 32  And ye shall take no satisfaction for him that is fled to the city of his refuge, that he should come again to dwell in the land, until the death of the priest. 33  So ye shall not pollute the land wherein ye are: for blood it defileth the land: and [†]the land cannot be cleansed of the blood that is shed therein, but by the blood of him that shed it. 34  Defile not therefore the land which ye shall inhabit, wherein I dwell: for I the LORD dwell among the children of Israel.

36

1  And the chief fathers of the families of the children of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, of the families of the sons of Joseph, came near, and spake before Moses, and before the princes, the chief fathers of the children of Israel: 2  And they said, [*]The LORD commanded my lord to give the land for an inheritance by lot to the children of Israel: and my lord was commanded by the LORD to give the inheritance of Zelophehad our brother unto his daughters. 3  And if they be married to any of the sons of the other tribes of the children of Israel, then shall their inheritance be taken from the inheritance of our fathers, and shall be put to the inheritance of the tribe [†][‡]whereunto they are received: so shall it be taken from the lot of our inheritance. 4  And when the jubile of the children of Israel shall be, then shall their inheritance be put unto the inheritance of the tribe whereunto they are received: so shall their inheritance be taken away from the inheritance of the tribe of our fathers.

5  And Moses commanded the children of Israel according to the word of the LORD, saying, The tribe of the sons of Joseph hath said well. 6 This is the thing which the LORD doth command concerning the daughters of Zelophehad, saying, Let them [†]marry to whom they think best; [*]only to the family of the tribe of their father shall they marry. 7  So shall not the inheritance of the children of Israel remove from tribe to tribe: for every one of the children of Israel shall [†]keep himself to the inheritance of the tribe of his fathers. 8  And every daughter, that possesseth an inheritance in any tribe of the children of Israel, shall be wife unto one of the family of the tribe of her father, that the children of Israel may enjoy every man the inheritance of his fathers. 9  Neither shall the inheritance remove from one tribe to another tribe; but every one of the tribes of the children of Israel shall keep himself to his own inheritance. 10  Even as the LORD commanded Moses, so did the daughters of Zelophehad: 11 [*] For Mahlah, Tirzah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Noah, the daughters of Zelophehad, were married unto their father’s brothers’ sons: 12  And they were married [†]into the families of the sons of Manasseh the son of Joseph, and their inheritance remained in the tribe of the family of their father. 13 These are the commandments and the judgments, which the LORD commanded by the hand of Moses unto the children of Israel in the plains of Moab by Jordan near Jericho.

* 1.2 Ex. 30. 12.

‡ 1.2 [1611 poll]

‡ 1.18 [1611 poll]

‡ 1.20 [1611 poll]

† 2.2 Heb. over against.

* 3.2 Ex. 6. 23.

† 3.3 Heb. whose hand he filled.

* 3.4 Lev. 10. 1. ch. 26. 61. 1 Chr. 24. 2.

* 3.13 Ex. 13. 1. Lev. 27. 26. ch. 8. 16. Luke 2. 23.

‡ 3.13 [1611 they shall be]

† 3.16 Heb. mouth.

* 3.17 Gen. 46. 11. Ex. 6. 16. ch. 26. 57. 1 Chr. 6. 1.

‡ 3.35 [1611 northwards]

† 3.36 Heb. the office of the charge.

* 3.47 Ex. 30. 13. Lev. 27. 25. ch 18. 16. Ezek. 45. 12.

* 4.7 Ex. 25. 30.

∥ 4.7 Or, pour out withal.

* 4.9 Ex. 25. 31.

* 4.9 Ex. 25. 38.

∥ 4.14 Or, bowls.

* 4.16 Ex. 30. 34.

* 4.16 Ex. 30. 23.

† 4.23 Heb. to war the warfare.

∥ 4.24 Or, carriage.

† 4.27 Heb mouth.

† 4.30 Heb. warfare.

* 4.31 Ex. 26. 15.

‡ 4.40 [1611 houses]

* 5.2 Lev. 13. 3.

* 5.2 Lev. 15. 2.

* 5.2 Lev. 21. 1.

* 5.6 Lev. 6. 3.

* 5.7 Lev. 6. 5.

∥ 5.9 Or, heave offering.

* 5.10 Lev. 10. 12.

∥ 5.19 Or, being in the power of thy husband.

† 5.19 Heb. under thy husband.

‡ 5.20 [1611 hath ben]

† 5.21 Heb. fall.

∥ 6.2 Or, make themselves Nazarites.

∥ 6.4 Or, Nazariteship.

† 6.4 Heb. vine of the wine.

* 6.5 Judg. 13 5. 1 Sam. 1. 11.

† 6.7 Heb. separation.

† 6.12 Heb. fall.

‡ 6.14 [1611 lamb]

* 6.18 Acts 21. 24.

* 6.20 Ex. 29. 27.

* 7.1 Ex. 40. 18.

† 7.2 Heb. who stood.

* 7.13 Lev. 2. 1.

* 7.16 Lev. 4. 23.

‡ 7.31 [1611 omits of the weight]

‡ 7.55 [1611 omits of the weight]

‡ 7.61 [1611 a]

∥ 7.89 That is, God.

* 8.2 Ex. 25. 37. &c 40. 25.

* 8.4 Ex. 25. 31.

* 8.4 Ex. 25. 18.

† 8.7 Heb. let them cause a rasor to pass over, &c.

† 8.11 Heb. wave.

† 8.11 Heb. wave offering

† 8.11 Heb. they may be to execute, &c.

* 8.14 ch 3. 45.

* 8.17 Ex 13. 2. ch 3 13. Luke 2. 23.

† 8.19 Heb. given.

† 8.24 Heb. to war the warfare of, &c

† 8.25 Heb. return from the warfare of the service.

* 9.2 Ex. 12. 1, &c. Lev. 23. 5. ch. 28. 16. Deut. 16. 2.

† 9.3 Heb. between the two evenings.

* 9.12 Ex. 12. 46. John 19. 36.

* 9.14 Ex. 12. 49.

* 9.15 Ex. 40. 34.

* 9.18 1 Cor. 10. 1.

‡ 9.18 [1611 the]

† 9.19 Heb. prolonged.

† 9.21 Heb. was.

* 9.22 Ex. 40. 36, 37.

* 10.14 ch. 2. 3.

* 10.14 ch. 1. 7.

* 10.21 ch 4. 4.

∥ 10.21 ver. 17.

† 10.28 Heb. These.

* 10.35 Ps. 68 1, 2.

† 10.36 Heb. ten thousand thousands.

∥ 11.1 Or, were as it were complainers.

† 11.1 Heb. it was evil in the ears of, &c.

* 11.1 Ps. 78. 21

† 11.2 Heb. sunk.

∥ 11.3 That is, A burning.

* 11.4 Ex. 12. 38.

† 11.4 Heb. lusted a lust.

† 11.4 Heb. returned and wept.

* 11.4 1 Cor. 10. 6.

* 11.7 Ex. 16. 14, 31.

† 11.7 Heb eye of it as the eye of.

† 11.20 Heb. month of days.

* 11.23 Is. 50. 2. &c 59. 1.

* 11.31 Ex. 16. 13 Ps. 78. 26.

† 11.31 Heb. as it were the way of a day.

* 11.33 Ps 78. 31.

∥ 11.34 That is, The graves of lust.

† 11.35 Heb. they were in, &c.

∥ 12.1 Or, Cushite.

† 12.1 Heb. taken.

* 12.3 Ecclus. 45. 4.

* 12.7 Heb. 3. 2.

* 12.8 Ex. 33. 11.

* 12.14 Lev. 13. 46.

* 13.23 Deut. 1 24.

∥ 13.23 Or, valley.

∥ 13.24 Or, valley.

∥ 13.24 That is, a cluster of grapes.

* 13.27 Ex. 33. 3.

† 13.32 Heb. men of statures.

† 14.9 Heb shadow.

* 14.13 Ex. 32. 12.

* 14.14 Ex. 13. 21.

* 14.16 Deut 9. 28.

* 14.18 Ex. 34. 6 Ps. 103. 8.

* 14.18 Ex. 20. 5. &c 34. 7.

∥ 14.19 Or, hitherto

† 14.23 Heb. If they see the land.

* 14.24 Josh. 14. 6.

* 14.28 ch 26. 65. &c 32. 10.

* 14.29 Deut. 1. 35.

† 14.30 Heb. lifted up my hand.

∥ 14.33 Or, feed.

* 14.34 Ps. 95. 10. Ezek. 4. 6.

∥ 14.34 Or, altering of my purpose.

* 14.37 1 Cor. 10. 10. Heb. 3. 17. Jude 5.

* 14.40 Deut. 1. 41.

* 14.45 Deut. 1. 44.

* 15.2 Lev. 23 10.

* 15.3 Lev. 22. 21.

† 15.3 Heb. separating.

* 15.3 Ex. 29. 18.

* 15.4 Lev. 2. 1

* 15.15 Ex. 12. 49. ch. 9. 14.

† 15.24 Heb. from the eyes.

∥ 15.24 Or, ordinance.

* 15.27 Lev. 4. 27.

† 15.29 Heb. doeth.

† 15.30 Heb. with an high hand.

* 15.34 Lev. 24 12.

* 15.38 Deut. 22. 12. Matt. 23. 5.

* 16.1 ch. 27. 3. Ecclus. 45 21. Judo 11.

* 16.2 ch. 26. 9.

† 16.3 Heb. It is much for you.

† 16.14 Heb. bore out

* 16.15 Gen. 4. 4.

† 16.29 Heb. as every man dieth.

† 16.30 Heb. create a creature.

* 16.31 ch. 27. 3. Deut. 11. 6. Ps. 106. 17.

* 17.4 Ex 25 22.

† 17.6 Heb. a rod for one prince, a rod for one prince.

* 17.10 Heb 9. 4

† 17.10 Heb children of rebellion.

* 18.6 ch. 3. 45.

* 18.11 Lev. 10. 14.

† 18.12 Heb. fat.

* 18.14 Lev. 27. 28.

* 18.15 Ex. 13. 2. &c 22. 29. Lev. 27. 26. ch. 3. 13.

* 18.16 Ex. 30. 13. Lev. 27. 25. ch 3. 47. Ezek. 45. 12.

* 18.18 Ex. 29. 26.

* 18.20 Deut. 10. 9. &c 18 2. Josh 13. 14, 33. Ezek. 44. 28.

† 18.22 Heb. to die.

† 18.29 Heb. fat.

* 19.3 Heb. 13 11.

* 19.4 Heb. 9. 13.

* 19.5 Ex. 29. 14 Lev 4 11, 12.

† 19.11 Heb soul.

† 19.17 Heb. dust.

† 19.17 Heb. living waters shall be given.

* 20.3 ch. 11 33.

* 20.4 Ex. 17. 3.

‡ 20.5 [1611 omits of]

* 20.13 Ps. 106. 82, &c.

∥ 20.13 That is, Strife.

† 20.14 Heb. found us.

* 20.22 ch. 33. 37.

† 20.24 Heb. mouth.

* 20.25 ch. 33. 38. Deut. 32 50.

* 20.28 Deut. 10. 6. &c 32. 50.

* 21.1 ch. 33. 40.

∥ 21.3 That is, Utter destruction.

∥ 21.4 Or, grieved.

† 21.4 Heb. shortened.

* 21.5 ch. 11. 6.

* 21.6 Wisd. 16 1, 5. 1 Cor. 10. 9.

* 21.9 2 Kings 18. 4. John 3. 14.

* 21.10 ch. 33. 43.

∥ 21.11 Or, Heaps of Abarim.

∥ 21.14 Or, Vaheb in Suphah

† 21.15 Heb. leaneth.

† 21.17 Heb. Ascend.

∥ 21.17 Or, answer.

† 21.20 Heb. field.

∥ 21.20 Or, The hill.

† 21.20 Or, The tenderness.

* 21.22 Deut. 2 27. Judg. 11. 19.

* 21.23 Deut. 29. 7.

* 21.24 Josh. 12. 2 Ps. 135. 11. Amos 2. 9.

† 21.25 Heb daughters.

* 21.29 1 Kings 11. 7, 33.

* 21.33 Deut. 3. 1. &c 29. 7.

* 21.34 Ps. 135. 11.

* 22.5 Josh. 24. 9.

† 22.5 Heb. eye.

† 22.11 Heb. I shall prevail in fighting against him.

† 22.16 Heb. Be not thou letted from, &c.

* 22.18 ch. 24. 13.

* 22.23 2 Pet. 2. 16. Jude 11.

† 22.30 Heb. who hast ridden upon me.

∥ 22.30 Or, ever since thou wast, &c.

∥ 22.31 Or, bowed himself.

† 22.32 Heb. to be an adversary unto thee.

† 22.34 Heb be evil in thine eyes.

∥ 22.39 Or, A city of streets.

∥ 23.3 Or, he went solitary.

† 23.10 Heb. my soul, or, my life.

∥ 23.14 Or, The hill.

* 23.16 ch. 22. 35.

* 23.22 ch. 24. 8.

∥ 23.23 Or, in.

* 24.1 ch 23. 3, 15.

† 24.1 Heb. to the meeting of enchantments

* 24.3 ch. 23 7, 18

† 24.3 Heb. who had his eyes shut, but now open.

‡ 24.6 [1611 river side]

* 24.8 ch. 23 22.

* 24.9 Gen. 49 9

∥ 24.17 Or, smile through the princes of Moab.

∥ 24.20 Israel, Ex. 17. 8.

∥ 24.21 Or, shall be even to destruction.

† 24.22 Heb. Kain.

∥ 24.22 Or, how long shall it be ere Asshur carry thee away captive?

* 25.1 ch. 33. 49.

* 25.4 Deut. 4 3. Josh. 22 17.

* 25.7 Ps. 106. 30 1 Mac. 2. 54.

* 25.9 1 Cor. 10 8.

* 25.11 Ps. 106 30.

* 25.12 Ecclus. 45 24. 1 Mac. 2. 54

† 25.14 Heb. house of a father.

* 25.17 ch 31. 2.

* 26.2 ch. 1. 3.

* 26.4 ch. 1. 1

* 26.5 Gen. 46 8 Ex b 14. 1 Chr. 5. 1.

* 26.9 ch 16. 2.

* 26.19 Gen. 38 2, &c. &c 46. 12.

* 26.29 Josh. 17. 1.

* 26.33 ch. 27. 1.

* 26.54 ch. 33. 54.

† 26.54 Heb. multiply his inheritance.

† 26.54 Heb. diminish his inheritance.

* 26.55 ch. 33. 54. Josh. 11. 23. &c 14. 2.

* 26.57 Ex. 6. 16, 17, 18, 19.

* 26.59 Ex. 2. 2. &c 6. 20.

* 26.61 Lev. 10. 2. ch. 3. 4. 1 Chr. 24. 2.

* 26.65 ch. 14. 28. 1 Cor. 10. 5, 6.

* 27.1 ch. 26. 83. Josh. 17. 3.

* 27.3 ch. 14. 35. &c 26. 64, 65.

† 27.4 Heb. diminished.

* 27.12 Deut. 32. 49.

* 27.13 ch. 20. 24.

* 27.14 ch. 20. 24.

* 27.14 Ex. 17. 7.

* 27.21 Ex. 23. 30.

† 28.2 Heb. a savour of my rest.

* 28.3 Ex. 29. 38.

† 28.3 Heb. in a day.

† 28.4 Heb. between the two evenings.

* 28.5 Lev. 2. 1.

* 28.5 Ex. 29. 40.

* 28.16 Ex. 12. 18. Lev. 23. 5.

* 28.18 Lev. 23. 7.

* 29.1 Lev. 23. 24.

* 29.7 Lev. 16. 29. &c 23. 27.

* 29.35 Lev. 23. 36.

∥ 29.39 Or, offer.

† 30.2 Heb. profane.

† 30.6 Heb. her vows were upon her.

‡ 30.8 [1611 disallow]

* 31.2 ch. 25. 17.

* 31.2 ch. 27. 13.

† 31.4 Heb. A thousand of a tribe, a thousand of a tribe.

* 31.8 Josh. 13 21.

† 31.14 Heb. host of war.

* 31.16 ch. 25. 2.

* 31.16 2 Pet. 2. 15.

* 31.17 Judg. 21. 11.

† 31.17 Heb. a male.

* 31.19 ch. 19. 11, &c.

† 31.20 Heb. instrument, or, vessel of skins.

† 31.26 Heb of the captivity.

∥ 31.30 Or, goats.

† 31.49 Heb. hand.

† 31.50 Heb. found.

† 31.52 Heb. heave offering.

† 32.7 Heb. break.

* 32.9 ch. 13. 24.

* 32.11 ch. 14. 28, 29.

† 32.11 Heb. ful filled after me.

* 32.20 Josh. 1. 13.

* 32.27 Josh. 4. 12.

* 32.33 Deut. 3. 12. Josh. 13. 8. &c 22. 4

† 32.38 Heb. they called by names the names of the cities.

* 32.39 Gen. 50. 23.

* 32.41 Deut. 3. 14.

* 33.3 Ex. 12. 37.

* 33.6 Ex. 13. 20.

* 33.8 Ex. 15. 22.

* 33.9 Ex. 15. 27.

* 33.11 Ex. 16. 1.

* 33.14 Ex. 17. 1.

* 33.15 Ex. 19. 1.

* 33.16 ch. 11. 34.

∥ 33.16 That is, The graves of lust.

* 33.17 ch. 11. 35.

* 33.30 Deut. 10. 6.

* 33.36 ch. 20. 1.

* 33.37 ch. 20. 22.

* 33.38 ch. 20. 25 Deut. 32. 50.

* 33.40 ch. 21. 1, &c.

* 33.41 ch. 21. 4.

∥ 33.44 Or, Heaps of Abarim.

∥ 33.49 Or, The plains of Shittim.

* 33.49 ch. 25. 1.

* 33.51 Deut. 7. 2. Josh. 11. 12.

* 33.54 ch. 26. 53.

† 33.54 Heb. multiply his inheritance.

† 33.54 Heb. diminish his inheritance.

* 33.55 Josh. 28. 13. Judg. 2. 3.

* 34.3 Josh. 15. 1.

† 34.11 Heb. shoulder.

* 34.14 ch. 32. 33. Josh. 14. 2, 3.

* 34.17 Josh. 19. 51.

* 35.2 Josh. 21. 2.

* 35.6 Deut. 4. 41. Josh. 20. 2. &c 21. 3.

† 35.6 Heb. above them ye shall give.

† 35.8 Heb. they inherit.

* 35.10 Deut. 19. 2 Josh. 20. 2.

† 35.11 Heb. by error.

* 35.16 Ex. 21. 14.

† 35.17 Heb. with a stone of the hand.

* 35.20 Deut. 19. 11.

* 35.22 Ex. 21. 18.

† 35.27 Heb. no blood shall be to him.

* 35.30 Deut. 17 6. &c 19. 15. Matt. 18. 16. 2 Cor. 13. 1. Heb. 10. 28.

† 35.31 Heb. faulty to die.

† 35.33 Heb. there can be no expiation for the land.

* 36.2 ch. 27. 1. Josh. 17. 3.

† 36.3 Heb. unto whom they shall be.

‡ 36.3 [1611 whereinto]

† 36.6 Heb. be wives.

* 36.6 Tob. 1. 9.

† 36.7 Heb. cleave to the, &c.

* 36.11 ch. 27. 1.

† 36.12 Heb. to some that were of the families.

Philemon

THE EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO PHILEMON

1

1  Paul, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, and Timothy our brother, unto Philemon our dearly beloved, and fellowlabourer, 2  And to our beloved Apphia, and Archippus our fellowsoldier, and to the church in thy house: 3  Grace to you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

4  I thank my God, making mention of thee always in my prayers, 5  Hearing of thy love and faith, which thou hast toward the Lord Jesus, and toward all saints; 6  That the communication of thy faith may become effectual by the acknowledging of every good thing which is in you in Christ Jesus. 7  For we have great joy and consolation in thy love, because the bowels of the saints are refreshed by thee, brother. 8  Wherefore, though I might be much bold in Christ to enjoin thee that which is convenient, 9 Yet for love’s sake I rather beseech thee, being such an one as Paul the aged, and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ. 10  I beseech thee for my son Onesimus, whom I have begotten in my bonds: 11  Which in time past was to thee unprofitable, but now profitable to thee and to me: 12  Whom I have sent again: thou therefore receive him, that is, mine own bowels: 13  Whom I would have retained with me, that in thy stead he might have ministered unto me in the bonds of the gospel: 14  But without thy mind would I do nothing; that thy benefit should not be as it were of necessity, but willingly. 15  For perhaps he therefore departed for a season, that thou shouldest receive him for ever; 16  Not now as a servant, but above a servant, a brother beloved, specially to me, but how much more unto thee, both in the flesh, and in the Lord? 17  If thou count me therefore a partner, receive him as myself. 18  If he hath wronged thee, or oweth thee ought, put that on mine account; 19  I Paul have written it with mine own hand, I will repay it: albeit I do not say to thee how thou owest unto me even thine own self besides. 20  Yea, brother, let me have joy of thee in the Lord: refresh my bowels in the Lord.

21  Having confidence in thy obedience I wrote unto thee, knowing that thou wilt also do more than I say. 22  But withal prepare me also a lodging: for I trust that through your prayers I shall be given unto you.

23  There salute thee Epaphras, my fellowprisoner in Christ Jesus; 24  Marcus, Aristarchus, Demas, Lucas, my fellowlabourers. 25  The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.

Written from Rome to Philemon, by Onesimus, a servant.

Philippians

1
2
3
4

THE EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO THE PHILIPPIANS

1

1  Paul and Timotheus, the servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus which are at Philippi, with the bishops and deacons: 2  Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ. 3  I thank my God upon every [∥]remembrance of you, 4  Always in every prayer of mine for you all making request with joy, 5  For your fellowship in the gospel from the first day until now; 6  Being confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work in you [∥]will perform it until the day of Jesus Christ: 7  Even as it is meet for me to think this of you all, because [∥]I have you in my heart; inasmuch as both in my bonds, and in the defence and confirmation of the gospel, ye all are [∥]partakers of my grace. 8  For God is my record, how greatly I long after you all in the bowels of Jesus Christ. 9  And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in knowledge and in all [∥]judgment; 10  That ye may [∥]approve things that [∥]are excellent; that ye may be sincere and without offence till the day of Christ; 11  Being filled with the fruits of righteousness, which are by Jesus Christ, unto the glory and praise of God.

12  But I would ye should understand, brethren, that the things which happened unto me have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the gospel; 13  So that my bonds [∥]in Christ are manifest in all [∥]the palace, and [∥]in all other places; 14  And many of the brethren in the Lord, waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to speak the word without fear. 15  Some indeed preach Christ even of envy and strife; and some also of good will: 16  The one preach Christ of contention, not sincerely, supposing to add affliction to my bonds: 17  But the other of love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the gospel. 18  What then? notwithstanding, every way, whether in pretence, or in truth, Christ is preached; and I therein do rejoice, yea, and will rejoice. 19  For I know that this shall turn to my salvation through your prayer, and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ, 20  According to my earnest expectation and my hope, that in nothing I shall be ashamed, but that with all boldness, as always, so now also Christ shall be magnified in my body, whether it be by life, or by death. 21  For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain. 22  But if I live in the flesh, this is the fruit of my labour: yet what I shall choose I wot not. 23  For I am in a strait betwixt two, having a desire to depart, and to be with Christ; which is far better: 24  Nevertheless to abide in the flesh is more needful for you. 25  And having this confidence, I know that I shall abide and continue with you all for your furtherance and joy of faith; 26  That your rejoicing may be more abundant in Jesus Christ for me by my coming to you again. 27  Only let your conversation be as it becometh the gospel of Christ: that whether I come and see you, or else be absent, I may hear of your affairs, that ye stand fast in one spirit, with one mind striving together for the faith of the gospel; 28  And in nothing terrified by your adversaries: which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of salvation, and that of God. 29  For unto you it is given in the behalf of Christ, not only to believe on him, but also to suffer for his sake; 30  Having the same conflict which ye saw in me, and now hear to be in me.

2

1  If there be therefore any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies, 2  Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be likeminded, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind. 3  Let nothing be done through strife or vainglory; but in lowliness of mind let each esteem other better than themselves. 4  Look not every man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others. 5  Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus: 6  Who, being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God: 7  But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the [∥]likeness of men: 8  And being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross. 9  Wherefore God also hath highly exalted him, and given him a name which is above every name: 10  That at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven, and things in earth, and things under the earth; 11  And that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.

12  Wherefore, my beloved, as ye have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling. 13  For it is God which worketh in you both to will and to do of his good pleasure. 14  Do all things without murmurings and disputings: 15  That ye may be blameless and [∥]harmless, the sons of God, without rebuke, in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation, among whom [∥]ye shine as lights in the world; 16  Holding forth the word of life; that I may rejoice in the day of Christ, that I have not run in vain, neither laboured in vain. 17  Yea, and if I be [†]offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy, and rejoice with you all. 18  For the same cause also do ye joy, and rejoice with me.

19 [∥] But I trust in the Lord Jesus to send Timotheus shortly unto you, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know your state. 20  For I have no man [∥]likeminded, who will naturally care for your state. 21  For all seek their own, not the things which are Jesus Christ’s. 22  But ye know the proof of him, that, as a son with the father, he hath served with me in the gospel. 23  Him therefore I hope to send presently, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me. 24  But I trust in the Lord that I also myself shall come shortly. 25  Yet I supposed it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother, and companion in labour, and fellowsoldier, but your messenger, and he that ministered to my wants. 26  For he longed after you all, and was full of heaviness, because that ye had heard that he had been sick. 27  For indeed he was sick nigh unto death: but God had mercy on him; and not on him only, but on me also, lest I should have sorrow upon sorrow. 28  I sent him therefore the more carefully, that, when ye see him again, ye may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful. 29  Receive him therefore in the Lord with all gladness; and [∥]hold such in reputation: 30  Because for the work of Christ he was nigh unto death, not regarding his life, to supply your lack of service toward me.

3

1  Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not grievous, but for you it is safe.

2  Beware of dogs, beware of evil workers, beware of the concision. 3  For we are the circumcision, which worship God in the spirit, and rejoice in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh. 4  Though I might also have confidence in the flesh. If any other man thinketh that he hath whereof he might trust in the flesh, I more: 5  Circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrews; as touching the law, a Pharisee; 6  Concerning zeal, persecuting the church; touching the righteousness which is in the law, blameless. 7  But what things were gain to me, those I counted loss for Christ. 8  Yea doubtless, and I count all things but loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord: for whom I have suffered the loss of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Christ, 9  And be found in him, not having mine own righteousness, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteousness which is of God by faith: 10  That I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being made conformable unto his death; 11  If by any means I might attain unto the resurrection of the dead. 12  Not as though I had already attained, either were already perfect: but I follow after, if that I may apprehend that for which also I am apprehended of Christ Jesus. 13  Brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended: but this one thing I do, forgetting those things which are behind, and reaching forth unto those things which are before, 14  I press toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus. 15  Let us therefore, as many as be perfect, be thus minded: and if in any thing ye be otherwise minded, God shall reveal even this unto you. 16  Nevertheless, whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the same rule, let us mind the same thing. 17  Brethren, be followers together of me, and mark them which walk so as ye have us for an ensample. 18 (For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the cross of Christ: 19  Whose end is destruction, whose God is their belly, and whose glory is in their shame, who mind earthly things.) 20  For our conversation is in heaven; from whence also we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ: 21  Who shall change our vile body, that it may be fashioned like unto his glorious body, according to the working whereby he is able even to subdue all things unto himself.

4

1  Therefore, my brethren dearly beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, my dearly beloved. 2  I beseech Euodias, and beseech Syntyche, that they be of the same mind in the Lord. 3  And I intreat thee also, true yokefellow, help those women which laboured with me in the gospel, with Clement also, and with other my fellowlabourers, whose names are in the book of life. 4  Rejoice in the Lord alway: and again I say, Rejoice. 5  Let your moderation be known unto all men. The Lord is at hand. 6  Be careful for nothing; but in every thing by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your [‡]requests be made known unto God. 7  And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus. 8  Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are [∥]honest, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are lovely, whatsoever things are of good report; if there be any virtue, and if there be any praise, think on these things. 9  Those things, which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me, do: and the God of peace shall be with you.

10  But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly, that now at the last your care of me [∥]hath flourished again; wherein ye were also careful, but ye lacked opportunity. 11  Not that I speak in respect of want: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, therewith to be content. 12  I know both how to be abased, and I know how to abound: every where and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need. 13  I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me. 14  Notwithstanding ye have well done, that ye did communicate with my affliction. 15  Now ye Philippians know also, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving, but ye only. 16  For even in Thessalonica ye sent once and again unto my necessity. 17  Not because I desire a gift: but I desire fruit that may abound to your account. 18  But [∥]I have all, and abound: I am full, having received of Epaphroditus the things which were sent from you, an odour of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, wellpleasing to God. 19  But my God shall supply all your need according to his riches in glory by Christ Jesus. 20  Now unto God and our Father be glory for ever and ever. Amen.

21  Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren which are with me greet you. 22  All the saints salute you, chiefly they that are of Caesar’s household. 23  The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

It was written to the Philippians from Rome by Epaphroditus.

∥ 1.3 Or, mention.

∥ 1.6 Or, will finish it.

∥ 1.7 Or, you have me in your heart.

∥ 1.7 Or, partakers with me of grace.

∥ 1.9 Or, sense.

∥ 1.10 Or, try.

∥ 1.10 Or, differ.

∥ 1.13 Or, for Christ.

∥ 1.13 Or, Cæsar’s court.

∥ 1.13 Or, to all others.

∥ 2.7 Or, habit.

∥ 2.15 Or, sincere.

∥ 2.15 Or, shine ye.

† 2.17 Gr. poured forth.

∥ 2.19 Or, Moreover.

∥ 2.20 Or, so dear unto me.

∥ 2.29 Or, honour such.

‡ 4.6 [1611 request]

∥ 4.8 Or, venerable.

∥ 4.10 Or, is revived.

∥ 4.18 Or, I have received all.

Proverbs

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31

The Proverbs

1

1  The proverbs of Solomon the son of David, king of Israel; 2  To know wisdom and instruction; to perceive the words of understanding; 3  To receive the instruction of wisdom, justice, and judgment, and [†]equity; 4  To give subtilty to the simple, to the young man knowledge and [∥]discretion. 5  A wise man will hear, and will increase learning; and a man of understanding shall attain unto wise counsels: 6  To understand a proverb, and [∥]the interpretation; the words of the wise, and their dark sayings.

7 ¶ [*]The fear of the LORD is [∥]the beginning of knowledge: but fools despise wisdom and instruction. 8  My son, hear the instruction of thy father, and forsake not the law of thy mother: 9 For they shall be [†]an ornament of grace unto thy head, and chains about thy neck.

10 ¶ My son, if sinners entice thee, consent thou not. 11  If they say, Come with us, let us lay wait for blood, let us lurk privily for the innocent without cause: 12  Let us swallow them up alive as the grave; and whole, as those that go down into the pit: 13  We shall find all precious substance, we shall fill our houses with spoil: 14  Cast in thy lot among us; let us all have one purse: 15  My son, walk not thou in the way with them; refrain thy foot from their path: 16 [*] For their feet run to evil, and make haste to shed blood. 17  Surely in vain the net is spread [†]in the sight of any bird. 18  And they lay wait for their own blood; they lurk privily for their own lives. 19 So are the ways of every one that is greedy of gain; which taketh away the life of the owners thereof.

20 ¶ [†][*]Wisdom crieth without; she uttereth her voice in the streets: 21  She crieth in the chief place of concourse, in the openings of the gates: in the city she uttereth her words, saying, 22  How long, ye simple ones, will ye love simplicity? and the scorners delight in their scorning, and fools hate knowledge? 23  Turn you at my reproof: behold, I will pour out my spirit unto you, I will make known my words unto you.

24 ¶ [*]Because I have called, and ye refused; I have stretched out my hand, and no man regarded; 25  But ye have set at nought all my counsel, and would none of my reproof: 26  I also will laugh at your calamity; I will mock when your fear cometh; 27  When your fear cometh as desolation, and your destruction cometh as a whirlwind; when distress and anguish cometh upon you. 28 [*] Then shall they call upon me, but I will not answer; they shall seek me early, but they shall not find me: 29  For that they hated knowledge, and did not choose the fear of the LORD: 30  They would none of my counsel: they despised all my reproof. 31  Therefore shall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices. 32  For the [∥]turning away of the simple shall slay them, and the prosperity of fools shall destroy them. 33  But whoso hearkeneth unto me shall dwell safely, and shall be quiet from fear of evil.

2

1  My son, if thou wilt receive my words, and hide my commandments with thee; 2  So that thou incline thine ear unto wisdom, and apply thine heart to understanding; 3  Yea, if thou criest after knowledge, and [†]liftest up thy voice for understanding; 4 [*] If thou seekest her as silver, and searchest for her as for hid treasures; 5  Then shalt thou understand the fear of the LORD, and find the knowledge of God. 6 [*] For the LORD giveth wisdom: out of his mouth cometh knowledge and understanding. 7  He layeth up sound wisdom for the righteous: he is a buckler to them that walk uprightly. 8  He keepeth the paths of judgment, and preserveth the way of his saints. 9  Then shalt thou understand righteousness, and judgment, and equity; yea, every good path.

10 ¶ When wisdom entereth into thine heart, and knowledge is pleasant unto thy soul; 11  Discretion shall preserve thee, understanding shall keep thee: 12  To deliver thee from the way of the evil man, from the man that speaketh froward things; 13  Who leave the paths of uprightness, to walk in the ways of darkness; 14  Who rejoice to do evil, and delight in the frowardness of the wicked; 15  Whose ways are crooked, and they froward in their paths: 16  To deliver thee from the strange woman, [*]even from the stranger which flattereth with her words; 17  Which forsaketh the guide of her youth, and forgetteth the covenant of her God. 18  For her house inclineth unto death, and her paths unto the dead. 19  None that go unto her return again, neither take they hold of the paths of life. 20  That thou mayest walk in the way of good men, and keep the paths of the righteous. 21 [*] For the upright shall dwell in the land, and the perfect shall remain in it. 22 [*] But the wicked shall be cut off from the earth, and the transgressors shall be [∥]rooted out of it.

3

1  My son, forget not my law; [*]but let thine heart keep my commandments: 2  For length of days, and [†]long life, and peace, shall they add to thee. 3  Let not mercy and truth forsake thee: [*]bind them about thy neck; write them upon the table of thine heart: 4 [*] So shalt thou find favour and [∥]good understanding in the sight of God and man.

5 ¶ Trust in the LORD with all thine heart; and lean not unto thine own understanding. 6 [*] In all thy ways acknowledge him, and he shall direct thy paths.

7 ¶ [*]Be not wise in thine own eyes: fear the LORD, and depart from evil. 8  It shall be [†]health to thy navel, and [†]marrow to thy bones. 9 [*] Honour the LORD with thy substance, and with the firstfruits of all thine increase: 10 [*] So shall thy barns be filled with plenty, and thy presses shall burst out with new wine.

11 ¶ [*]My son, despise not the chastening of the LORD; neither be weary of his correction: 12  For whom the LORD loveth he correcteth; even as a father the son in whom he delighteth.

13 ¶ Happy is the man that findeth wisdom, and [†]the man that getteth understanding. 14 [*] For the merchandise of it is better than the merchandise of silver, and the gain thereof than fine gold. 15 She is more precious than rubies: and all the things thou canst desire are not to be compared unto her. 16  Length of days is in her right hand; and in her left hand riches and honour. 17  Her ways are ways of pleasantness, and all her paths are peace. 18 She is a tree of life to them that lay hold upon her: and happy is every one that retaineth her. 19  The LORD by wisdom hath founded the earth; by understanding hath he [∥]established the heavens. 20  By his knowledge the depths are broken up, and the clouds drop down the dew.

21 ¶ My son, let not them depart from thine eyes: keep sound wisdom and discretion: 22  So shall they be life unto thy soul, and grace to thy neck. 23 [*] Then shalt thou walk in thy way safely, and thy foot shall not stumble. 24  When thou liest down, thou shalt not be afraid: yea, thou shalt lie down, and thy sleep shall be sweet. 25  Be not afraid of sudden fear, neither of the desolation of the wicked, when it cometh. 26  For the LORD shall be thy confidence, and shall keep thy foot from being taken.

27 ¶ Withhold not good from [†]them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to do it. 28  Say not unto thy neighbour, Go, and come again, and to morrow I will give; when thou hast it by thee. 29 [∥] Devise not evil against thy neighbour, seeing he dwelleth securely by thee.

30 ¶ Strive not with a man without cause, if he have done thee no harm.

31 ¶ [*]Envy thou not [†]the oppressor, and choose none of his ways. 32  For the froward is abomination to the LORD: [*]but his secret is with the righteous.

33 ¶ [*]The curse of the LORD is in the house of the wicked: but he blesseth the habitation of the just. 34 [*] Surely he scorneth the scorners: but he giveth grace unto the lowly. 35  The wise shall inherit glory: but shame [†]shall be the promotion of fools.

4

1  Hear, ye children, the instruction of a father, and attend to know understanding. 2  For I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law. 3  For I was my father’s son, [*]tender and only beloved in the sight of my mother. 4 [*] He taught me also, and said unto me, Let thine heart retain my words: keep my commandments, and live. 5  Get wisdom, get understanding: forget it not; neither decline from the words of my mouth. 6  Forsake her not, and she shall preserve thee: love her, and she shall keep thee. 7  Wisdom is the principal thing; therefore get wisdom: and with all thy getting get understanding. 8  Exalt her, and she shall promote thee: she shall bring thee to honour, when thou dost embrace her. 9  She shall give to thine head [*]an ornament of grace: [∥]a crown of glory shall she deliver to thee. 10  Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings; and the years of thy life shall be many. 11  I have taught thee in the way of wisdom; I have led thee in right paths. 12  When thou goest, thy steps shall not be straitened; [*]and when thou runnest, thou shalt not stumble. 13  Take fast hold of instruction; let her not go: keep her; for she is thy life.

14 ¶ [*]Enter not into the path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men. 15  Avoid it, pass not by it, turn from it, and pass away. 16  For they sleep not, except they have done mischief; and their sleep is taken away, unless they cause some to fall. 17  For they eat the bread of wickedness, and drink the wine of violence. 18  But the path of the just is as the shining light, that shineth more and more unto the perfect day. 19  The way of the wicked is as darkness: they know not at what they stumble.

20 ¶ My son, attend to my words; incline thine ear unto my sayings. 21  Let them not depart from thine eyes; keep them in the midst of thine heart. 22 For they are life unto those that find them, and [†]health to all their flesh.

23 ¶ Keep thy heart [†]with all diligence; for out of it are the issues of life. 24  Put away from thee [†]a froward mouth, and perverse lips put far from thee. 25  Let thine eyes look right on, and let thine eyelids look straight before thee. 26  Ponder the path of thy feet, and [∥]let all thy ways be established. 27 [*] Turn not to the right hand nor to the left: remove thy foot from evil.

5

1  My son, attend unto my wisdom, and bow thine ear to my understanding: 2  That thou mayest regard discretion, and that thy lips may keep knowledge.

3 ¶ [*]For the lips of a strange woman drop as an honeycomb, and her [†]mouth is smoother than oil: 4  But her end is bitter as wormwood, sharp as a twoedged sword. 5 [*] Her feet go down to death; her steps take hold on hell. 6  Lest thou shouldest ponder the path of life, her ways are moveable, that thou canst not know them. 7  Hear me now therefore, O ye children, and depart not from the words of my mouth. 8  Remove thy way far from her, and come not nigh the door of her house: 9  Lest thou give thine honour unto others, and thy years unto the cruel: 10  Lest strangers be filled with [†]thy wealth; and thy labours be in the house of a stranger; 11  And thou mourn at the last, when thy flesh and thy body are consumed, 12  And say, How have I hated instruction, and my heart despised reproof; 13  And have not obeyed the voice of my teachers, nor inclined mine ear to them that instructed me! 14  I was almost in all evil in the midst of the congregation and assembly.

15 ¶ Drink waters out of thine own cistern, and running waters out of thine own well. 16  Let thy fountains be dispersed abroad, and rivers of waters in the streets. 17  Let them be only thine own, and not strangers’ with thee. 18  Let thy fountain be blessed: and rejoice with the wife of thy youth. 19  Let her be as the loving hind and pleasant roe; let her breasts [†]satisfy thee at all times; and [†]be thou ravished always with her love. 20  And why wilt thou, my son, be ravished with a strange woman, and embrace the bosom of a stranger? 21 [*] For the ways of man are before the eyes of the LORD, and he pondereth all his goings.

22 ¶ His own iniquities shall take the wicked himself, and he shall be holden with the cords of his [†]sins. 23  He shall die without instruction; and in the greatness of his folly he shall go astray.

6

1  My son, if thou be surety for thy friend, if thou hast stricken thy hand with a stranger, 2  Thou art snared with the words of thy mouth, thou art taken with the words of thy mouth. 3  Do this now, my son, and deliver thyself, when thou art come into the hand of thy friend; go, humble thyself, [∥]and make sure thy friend. 4  Give not sleep to thine eyes, nor slumber to thine eyelids. 5  Deliver thyself as a roe from the hand of the hunter, and as a bird from the hand of the fowler.

6 ¶ Go to the ant, thou sluggard; consider her ways, and be wise: 7  Which having no guide, overseer, or ruler, 8  Provideth her meat in the summer, and gathereth her food in the harvest. 9 [*] How long wilt thou sleep, O sluggard? when wilt thou arise out of thy sleep? 10  Yet a little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep: 11 [*] So shall thy poverty come as one that travelleth, and thy want as an armed man.

12 ¶ A naughty person, a wicked man, walketh with a froward mouth. 13  He winketh with his eyes, he speaketh with his feet, he teacheth with his fingers; 14  Frowardness is in his heart, he deviseth mischief continually; he [†]soweth discord. 15  Therefore shall his calamity come suddenly; suddenly shall he be broken without remedy.

16 ¶ These six things doth the LORD hate: yea, seven are an abomination [†]unto him: 17 [†] A proud look, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood, 18  An heart that deviseth wicked imaginations, [*]feet that be swift in running to mischief, 19  A false witness that speaketh lies, and [‡]he that soweth discord among brethren.

20 ¶ [*]My son, keep thy father’s commandment, and forsake not the law of thy mother: 21  Bind them continually upon thine heart, and tie them about thy neck. 22  When thou goest, it shall lead thee; when thou sleepest, it shall keep thee; and when thou awakest, it shall talk with thee. 23 [*] For the commandment is a [∥]lamp; and the law is light; and reproofs of instruction are the way of life: 24 [*] To keep thee from the evil woman, from the flattery [∥]of the tongue of a strange woman. 25 [*] Lust not after her beauty in thine heart; neither let her take thee with her eyelids. 26  For by means of a whorish woman a man is brought to a piece of bread: and [†]the adulteress will hunt for the precious life. 27  Can a man take fire in his bosom, and his clothes not be burned? 28  Can one go upon hot coals, and his feet not be burned? 29  So he that goeth in to his neighbour’s wife; whosoever toucheth her shall not be innocent. 30  Men do not despise a thief, if he steal to satisfy his soul when he is hungry; 31 But if he be found, he shall restore sevenfold; he shall give all the substance of his house. 32  But whoso committeth adultery with a woman lacketh [†]understanding: he that doeth it destroyeth his own soul. 33  A wound and dishonour shall he get; and his reproach shall not be wiped away. 34  For jealousy is the rage of a man: therefore he will not spare in the day of vengeance. 35 [†] He will not regard any ransom; neither will he rest content, though thou givest many gifts.

7

1  My son, keep my words, and lay up my commandments with thee. 2  Keep my commandments, and live; and my law as the apple of thine eye. 3 [*] Bind them upon thy fingers, write them upon the table of thine heart. 4  Say unto wisdom, Thou art my sister; and call understanding thy kinswoman: 5 [*] That they may keep thee from the strange woman, from the stranger which flattereth with her words.

6 ¶ For at the window of my house I looked through my casement, 7  And beheld among the simple ones, I discerned among [†]the youths, a young man void of understanding, 8  Passing through the street near her corner; and he went the way to her house, 9  In the twilight, [†]in the evening, in the black and dark night: 10  And, behold, there met him a woman with the attire of an harlot, and subtil of heart. 11 [*](She is loud and stubborn; her feet abide not in her house: 12  Now is she without, now in the streets, and lieth in wait at every corner.) 13  So she caught him, and kissed him, and [†]with an impudent face said unto him, 14 [†] I have peace offerings with me; this day have I payed my vows. 15  Therefore came I forth to meet thee, diligently to seek thy face, and I have found thee. 16  I have decked my bed with coverings of tapestry, with carved works, with fine linen of Egypt. 17  I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon. 18  Come, let us take our fill of love until the morning: let us solace ourselves with loves. 19  For the goodman is not at home, he is gone a long journey: 20  He hath taken a bag of money [†]with him, and will come home at [∥]the day appointed. 21  With [‡]her much fair speech she caused him to yield, with the flattering of her lips she forced him. 22  He goeth after her [†]straightway, as an ox goeth to the slaughter, or as a fool to the correction of the stocks; 23  Till a dart strike through his liver; as a bird hasteth to the snare, and knoweth not that it is for his life.

24 ¶ Hearken unto me now therefore, O ye children, and attend to the words of my mouth. 25  Let not thine heart decline to her ways, go not astray in her paths. 26  For she hath cast down many wounded: yea, many strong men have been slain by her. 27 [*] Her house is the way to hell, going down to the chambers of death.

8

1  Doth not [*]wisdom cry? and understanding put forth her voice? 2  She standeth in the top of high places, by the way in the places of the paths. 3  She crieth at the gates, at the entry of the city, at the coming in at the doors. 4  Unto you, O men, I call; and my voice is to the sons of man. 5  O ye simple, understand wisdom: and, ye fools, be ye of an understanding heart. 6  Hear; for I will speak of excellent things; and the opening of my lips shall be right things. 7  For my mouth shall speak truth; and wickedness is [†]an abomination to my lips. 8  All the words of my mouth are in righteousness; there is nothing [†]froward or perverse in them. 9 They are all plain to him that understandeth, and right to them that find knowledge. 10  Receive my instruction, and not silver; and knowledge rather than choice gold. 11 [*] For wisdom is better than rubies; and all the things that may be desired are not to be compared to it.

12  I wisdom dwell with [∥]prudence, and find out knowledge of witty inventions. 13  The fear of the LORD is to hate evil: pride, and arrogancy, and the evil way, and the froward mouth, do I hate. 14  Counsel is mine, and sound wisdom: I am understanding; I have strength. 15  By me kings reign, and princes decree justice. 16  By me princes rule, and nobles, even all the judges of the earth. 17  I love them that love me; and those that seek me early shall find me. 18 [*] Riches and honour are with me; yea, durable riches and righteousness. 19 [*] My fruit is better than gold, yea, than fine gold; and my revenue than choice silver. 20  I [∥]lead in the way of righteousness, in the midst of the paths of judgment: 21  That I may cause those that love me to inherit substance; and I will fill their treasures.

22  The LORD possessed me in the beginning of his way, before his works of old. 23  I was set up from everlasting, from the beginning, or ever the earth was. 24 When there were no depths, I was brought forth; when there were no fountains abounding with water. 25  Before the mountains were settled, before the hills was I brought forth: 26  While as yet he had not made the earth, nor the [∥]fields, nor [∥]the highest part of the dust of the world. 27  When he prepared the heavens, I was there: when he set [∥]a compass upon the face of the depth: 28  When he established the clouds above: when he strengthened the fountains of the deep: 29 [*] When he gave to the sea his decree, that the waters should not pass his commandment: when he appointed the foundations of the earth: 30  Then I was by him, as one brought up with him: and I was daily his delight, rejoicing always before him; 31  Rejoicing in the habitable part of his earth; and my delights were with the sons of men.

32  Now therefore hearken unto me, O ye children: for [*]blessed are they that keep my ways. 33  Hear instruction, and be wise, and refuse it not. 34  Blessed is the man that heareth me, watching daily at my gates, waiting at the posts of my doors. 35  For whoso findeth me findeth life, and shall [†]obtain favour of the LORD. 36  But he that sinneth against me wrongeth his own soul: all they that hate me love death.

9

1  Wisdom hath builded her house, she hath hewn out her seven pillars: 2  She hath killed [†]her beasts; she hath mingled her wine; she hath also furnished her table. 3  She hath sent forth her maidens: she crieth upon the highest places of the city, 4 Whoso is simple, let him turn in hither: as for him that wanteth understanding, she saith to him, 5  Come, eat of my bread, and drink of the wine which I have mingled. 6  Forsake the foolish, and live; and go in the way of understanding. 7  He that reproveth a scorner getteth to himself shame: and he that rebuketh a wicked man getteth himself a blot. 8 [*] Reprove not a scorner, lest he hate thee: rebuke a wise man, and he will love thee. 9  Give instruction to a wise man, and he will be yet wiser: teach a just man, and he will increase in learning. 10 [*] The fear of the LORD is the beginning of wisdom: and the knowledge of the holy is understanding. 11 [*] For by me thy days shall be multiplied, and the years of thy life shall be increased. 12  If thou be wise, thou shalt be wise for thyself: but if thou scornest, thou alone shalt bear it.

13 ¶ [*]A foolish woman is clamorous: she is simple, and knoweth nothing. 14  For she sitteth at the door of her house, on a seat in the high places of the city, 15  To call passengers who go right on their ways: 16 Whoso is simple, let him turn in hither: and as for him that wanteth understanding, she saith to him, 17  Stolen waters are sweet, and bread [†]eaten in secret is pleasant. 18  But he knoweth not that the dead are there; and that her guests are in the depths of hell.

10

1  The proverbs of Solomon. [*]A wise son maketh a glad father: but a foolish son is the heaviness of his mother.

2 [*] Treasures of wickedness profit nothing: but righteousness delivereth from death. 3 [*] The LORD will not suffer the soul of the righteous to famish: but he casteth away [∥]the substance of the wicked. 4 [*] He becometh poor that dealeth with a slack hand: but the hand of the diligent maketh rich. 5  He that gathereth in summer is a wise son: but he that sleepeth in harvest is a son that causeth shame. 6  Blessings are upon the head of the just: but [*]violence covereth the mouth of the wicked. 7 [*] The memory of the just is blessed: but the name of the wicked shall rot. 8  The wise in heart will receive commandments: but [†]a prating fool [∥]shall fall. 9 [*] He that walketh uprightly walketh surely: but he that perverteth his ways shall be known. 10 [*] He that winketh with the eye causeth sorrow: but a prating fool [∥]shall fall. 11 [*] The mouth of a righteous man is a well of life: but violence covereth the mouth of the wicked. 12  Hatred stirreth up strifes: but [*]love covereth all sins. 13  In the lips of him that hath understanding wisdom is found: but a rod is for the back of him that is void of [†]understanding. 14  Wise men lay up knowledge: but the mouth of the foolish is near destruction. 15 [*] The rich man’s wealth is his strong city: the destruction of the poor is their poverty. 16  The labour of the righteous tendeth to life: the fruit of the wicked to sin. 17 He is in the way of life that keepeth instruction: but he that refuseth reproof [∥]erreth. 18  He that hideth hatred with lying lips, and he that uttereth a slander, is a fool. 19  In the multitude of words there wanteth not sin: but he that refraineth his lips is wise.

20  The tongue of the just is as choice silver: the heart of the wicked is little worth. 21  The lips of the righteous feed many: but fools die for want [†]of wisdom. 22  The blessing of the LORD, it maketh rich, and he addeth no sorrow with it. 23 [*] It is as [‡]sport to a fool to do mischief: but a man of understanding hath wisdom.

24  The fear of the wicked, it shall come upon him: but the desire of the righteous shall be granted. 25  As the whirlwind passeth, so is the wicked no more: but the righteous is an everlasting foundation. 26  As vinegar to the teeth, and as smoke to the eyes, so is the sluggard to them that send him.

27 [*] The fear of the LORD [†]prolongeth days: but the years of the wicked shall be shortened. 28  The hope of the righteous shall be gladness: but the [*]expectation of the wicked shall perish.

29  The way of the LORD is strength to the upright: but destruction shall be to the workers of iniquity. 30 [*] The righteous shall never be removed: but the wicked shall not inhabit the earth.

31  The mouth of the just bringeth forth wisdom: but the froward tongue shall be cut out. 32  The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable: but the mouth of the wicked speaketh [†]frowardness.

11

1  A [*][†]false balance is abomination to the LORD: but [†]a just weight is his delight. 2 [*] When pride cometh, then cometh shame: but with the lowly is wisdom. 3 [*] The integrity of the upright shall guide them: but the perverseness of transgressors shall destroy them. 4 [*] Riches profit not in the day of wrath: but righteousness delivereth from death.

5  The righteousness of the perfect shall [†]direct his way: but the wicked shall fall by his own wickedness. 6  The righteousness of the upright shall deliver them: but [*]transgressors shall be taken in their own naughtiness. 7  When a wicked man dieth, his expectation shall perish: and the hope of unjust men perisheth. 8 [*] The righteous is delivered out of trouble, and the wicked cometh in his stead. 9  An [*]hypocrite with his mouth destroyeth his neighbour: but through knowledge shall the just be delivered.

10  When it goeth well with the righteous, the city rejoiceth: and when the wicked perish, there is shouting. 11  By the blessing of the upright the city is exalted: but it is overthrown by the mouth of the wicked.

12  He that is [†]void of wisdom despiseth his neighbour: but a man of understanding holdeth his peace. 13 [†] A talebearer revealeth secrets: but he that is of a faithful spirit concealeth the matter. 14 [*] Where no counsel is, the people fall: but in the multitude of counsellors there is safety. 15  He that is surety for a stranger [†]shall smart for it: and he that hateth [†]suretiship is sure. 16  A gracious woman retaineth honour: and strong men retain riches. 17  The merciful man doeth good to his own soul: but he that is cruel troubleth his own flesh. 18  The wicked worketh a deceitful work: but to him that soweth righteousness shall be a sure reward. 19  As righteousness tendeth to life: so he that pursueth evil pursueth it to his own death. 20  They that are of a froward heart are abomination to the LORD: but such as are upright in their way are his delight. 21  Though hand join in hand, the wicked shall not be unpunished: but the seed of the righteous shall be delivered. 22  As a jewel of gold in a swine’s snout, so is a fair woman which [†]is without discretion. 23  The desire of the righteous is only good: but the expectation of the wicked is wrath. 24  There is that scattereth, and yet increaseth; and there is that withholdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth to poverty. 25 [*][†] The liberal soul shall be made fat: and he that watereth shall be watered also himself. 26  He that withholdeth corn, the people shall curse him: but blessing shall be upon the head of him that selleth it. 27  He that diligently seeketh good procureth favour: [*]but he that seeketh mischief, it shall come unto him. 28  He that trusteth in his riches shall fall: but [*]the righteous shall flourish as a branch. 29  He that troubleth his own house shall inherit the wind: and the fool shall be servant to the wise of heart. 30  The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life; and he that [†]winneth souls is wise. 31 [*] Behold, the righteous shall be recompensed in the earth: much more the wicked and the sinner.

12

1  Whoso loveth instruction loveth knowledge: but he that hateth reproof is brutish. 2  A good man obtaineth favour of the LORD: but a man of wicked devices will he condemn. 3  A man shall not be established by wickedness: but the [*]root of the righteous shall not be moved. 4 [*] A virtuous woman is a crown to her husband: but she that maketh ashamed is as rottenness in his bones. 5  The thoughts of the righteous are right: but the counsels of the wicked are deceit. 6 [*] The words of the wicked are to lie in wait for blood: but the mouth of the upright shall deliver them. 7 [*] The wicked are overthrown, and are not: but the house of the righteous shall stand. 8  A man shall be commended according to his wisdom: but he that is [†]of a perverse heart shall be despised. 9  He that is despised, and hath a servant, is better than he that honoureth himself, and lacketh bread. 10  A righteous man regardeth the life of his beast: but the [∥]tender mercies of the wicked are cruel. 11 [*] He that tilleth his land shall be satisfied with bread: but he that followeth vain persons is void of understanding. 12  The wicked desireth [∥]the net of evil men: but the root of the righteous yieldeth fruit. 13 [†][*] The wicked is snared by the transgression of his lips: but the just shall come out of trouble. 14 [*] A man shall be satisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth: and the recompence of a man’s hands shall be rendered unto him. 15 [*] The way of a fool is right in his own eyes: but he that hearkeneth unto counsel is wise. 16  A fool’s wrath is [†]presently known: but a prudent man covereth shame. 17 [*] He that speaketh truth sheweth forth righteousness: but a false witness deceit. 18 [*] There is that speaketh like the piercings of a sword: but the tongue of the wise is health. 19  The lip of truth shall be established for ever: but a lying tongue is but for a moment. 20  Deceit is in the heart of them that imagine evil: but to the counsellors of peace is joy. 21  There shall no evil happen to the just: but the wicked shall be filled with mischief. 22  Lying lips are abomination to the LORD: but they that deal truly are his delight. 23 [*] A prudent man concealeth knowledge: but the heart of fools proclaimeth foolishness. 24 [*] The hand of the diligent shall bear rule: but the [∥]slothful shall be under tribute. 25 [*] Heaviness in the heart of man maketh it stoop: but a good word maketh it glad. 26  The righteous is more [∥]excellent than his neighbour: but the way of the wicked seduceth them. 27  The slothful man roasteth not that which he took in hunting: but the substance of a diligent man is precious. 28  In the way of righteousness is life; and in the pathway thereof there is no death.

13

1  A wise son heareth his father’s instruction: but a scorner heareth not rebuke. 2 [*] A man shall eat good by the fruit of his mouth: but the soul of the transgressors shall eat violence. 3  He that keepeth his mouth keepeth his life: but he that openeth wide his lips shall have destruction. 4  The soul of the sluggard desireth, and hath nothing: but the soul of the diligent shall be made fat. 5  A righteous man hateth lying: but a wicked man is loathsome, and cometh to shame. 6 [*] Righteousness keepeth him that is upright in the way: but wickedness overthroweth [†]the sinner. 7  There is that maketh himself rich, yet hath nothing: there is that maketh himself poor, yet hath great riches. 8  The ransom of a man’s life are his riches: but the poor heareth not rebuke. 9  The light of the righteous rejoiceth: [*]but the [∥]lamp of the wicked shall be put out. 10  Only by pride cometh contention: but with the well advised is wisdom. 11 [*] Wealth gotten by vanity shall be diminished: but he that gathereth [†]by labour shall increase. 12  Hope deferred maketh the heart sick: but when the desire cometh, it is a tree of life. 13  Whoso despiseth the word shall be destroyed: but he that feareth the commandment [∥]shall be rewarded. 14 [*] The law of the wise is a fountain of life, to depart from the snares of death. 15  Good understanding giveth favour: but the way of transgressors is hard. 16 [*] Every prudent man dealeth with knowledge: but a fool [†]layeth open his folly. 17  A wicked messenger falleth into mischief: but a faithful ambassador is health. 18  Poverty and shame shall be to him that refuseth instruction: but he that regardeth reproof shall be honoured. 19  The desire accomplished is sweet to the soul: but it is abomination to fools to depart from evil. 20  He that walketh with wise men shall be wise: but a companion of fools [†]shall be destroyed. 21  Evil pursueth sinners: but to the righteous good shall be repayed. 22  A good man leaveth an inheritance to his children’s children: and the [*]wealth of the sinner is laid up for the just. 23 [*] Much food is in the tillage of the poor: but there is that is destroyed for want of judgment. 24 [*] He that spareth his rod hateth his son: but he that loveth him chasteneth him betimes. 25 [*] The righteous eateth to the satisfying of his soul: but the belly of the wicked shall want.

14

1  Every wise woman buildeth her house: but the foolish plucketh it down with her hands. 2  He that walketh in his uprightness feareth the LORD: [*]but he that is perverse in his ways despiseth him. 3  In the mouth of the foolish is a rod of pride: but the lips of the wise shall preserve them. 4  Where no oxen are, the crib is clean: but much increase is by the strength of the ox. 5 [*] A faithful witness will not lie: but a false witness will utter lies. 6  A scorner seeketh wisdom, and findeth it not: but [*]knowledge is easy unto him that understandeth. 7  Go from the presence of a foolish man, when thou perceivest not in him the lips of knowledge. 8  The wisdom of the prudent is to understand his way: but the folly of fools is deceit. 9 [*] Fools make a mock at sin: but among the righteous there is favour. 10  The heart knoweth [†]his own bitterness; and a stranger doth not intermeddle with his joy. 11  The house of the wicked shall be overthrown: but the tabernacle of the upright shall flourish. 12 [*] There is a way which seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof are the ways of death. 13  Even in laughter the heart is sorrowful; and the end of that mirth is heaviness. 14  The backslider in heart shall be [*]filled with his own ways: and a good man shall be satisfied from himself. 15  The simple believeth every word: but the prudent man looketh well to his going. 16  A wise man feareth, and departeth from evil: but the fool rageth, and is confident. 17  He that is soon angry dealeth foolishly: and a man of wicked devices is hated. 18  The simple inherit folly: but the prudent are crowned with knowledge. 19  The evil bow before the good; and the wicked at the gates of the righteous. 20 [*] The poor is hated even of his own neighbour: but [†]the rich hath many friends. 21  He that despiseth his neighbour sinneth: [*]but he that hath mercy on the poor, happy is he. 22  Do they not err that devise evil? but mercy and truth shall be to them that devise good. 23  In all labour there is profit: but the talk of the lips tendeth only to penury. 24  The crown of the wise is their riches: but the foolishness of fools is folly. 25 [*] A true witness delivereth souls: but a deceitful witness speaketh lies.

26  In the fear of the LORD is strong confidence: and his children shall have a place of refuge. 27 [*] The fear of the LORD is a fountain of life, to depart from the snares of death. 28  In the multitude of people is the king’s honour: but in the want of people is the destruction of the prince. 29  He that is slow to wrath is of great understanding: but he that is [†]hasty of spirit exalteth folly. 30  A sound heart is the life of the flesh: but envy the rottenness of the bones. 31 [*] He that oppresseth the poor reproacheth his Maker: but he that honoureth him hath mercy on the poor. 32  The wicked is driven away in his wickedness: but the righteous hath hope in his death. 33  Wisdom resteth in the heart of him that hath understanding: but that which is in the midst of fools is made known. 34  Righteousness exalteth a nation: but sin is a reproach [†]to any people. 35  The king’s favour is toward a wise servant: but his wrath is against him that causeth shame.

15

1  A [*]soft answer turneth away wrath: but grievous words stir up anger. 2  The tongue of the wise useth knowledge aright: [*]but the mouth of fools [†]poureth out foolishness. 3 [*] The eyes of the LORD are in every place, beholding the evil and the good. 4 [†] A wholesome tongue is a tree of life: but perverseness therein is a breach in the spirit. 5 [*] A fool despiseth his father’s instruction: but he that regardeth reproof is prudent. 6  In the house of the righteous is much treasure: but in the revenues of the wicked is trouble. 7  The lips of the wise disperse knowledge: but the heart of the foolish doeth not so. 8 [*] The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the LORD: but the prayer of the upright is his delight. 9  The way of the wicked is an abomination unto the LORD: but he loveth him that followeth after righteousness. 10 [∥] Correction is grievous unto him that forsaketh the way: and he that hateth reproof shall die. 11 [*] Hell and destruction are before the LORD: how much more then the hearts of the children of men? 12  A scorner loveth not one that reproveth him: neither will he go unto the wise. 13 [*] A merry heart maketh a cheerful countenance: but by sorrow of the heart the spirit is broken. 14  The heart of him that hath understanding seeketh knowledge: but the mouth of fools feedeth on foolishness. 15  All the days of the afflicted are evil: but he that is of a merry heart hath a continual feast.

16 [*] Better is little with the fear of the LORD than great treasure and trouble therewith. 17 [*] Better is a dinner of herbs where love is, than a stalled ox and hatred therewith. 18 [*] A wrathful man stirreth up strife: but he that is slow to anger appeaseth strife. 19  The way of the slothful man is as an hedge of thorns: but the way of the righteous [†]is made plain. 20 [*] A wise son maketh a glad father: but a foolish man despiseth his mother. 21 [*] Folly is joy to him that is [†]destitute of wisdom: but a man of understanding walketh uprightly. 22 [*] Without counsel purposes are disappointed: but in the multitude of counsellors they are established. 23  A man hath joy by the answer of his mouth: and a word spoken [†]in due season, how good is it! 24 [*] The way of life is above to the wise, that he may depart from hell beneath. 25 [*] The LORD will destroy the house of the proud: but he will establish the border of the widow. 26 [*] The thoughts of the wicked are an abomination to the LORD: but the words of the pure are [†]pleasant words. 27  He that is greedy of gain troubleth his own house; but he that hateth gifts shall live. 28  The heart of the righteous studieth to answer: but the mouth of the wicked poureth out evil things. 29 [*] The LORD is far from the wicked: but he heareth the prayer of the righteous. 30  The light of the eyes rejoiceth the heart: and a good report maketh the bones fat. 31  The ear that heareth the reproof of life abideth among the wise. 32  He that refuseth [∥]instruction despiseth his own soul: but he that [∥]heareth reproof [†]getteth understanding. 33  The fear of the LORD is the instruction of wisdom; and [*]before honour is humility.

16

1  The [*][∥]preparations of the heart in man, and the answer of the tongue, is from the LORD. 2 [*] All the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes; but the LORD weigheth the spirits. 3 [*][†] Commit thy works unto the LORD, and thy thoughts shall be established. 4  The LORD hath made all things for himself: [*]yea, even the wicked for the day of evil. 5 [*]Every one that is proud in heart is an abomination to the LORD: though hand join in hand, he shall not be [†]unpunished. 6  By mercy and truth iniquity is purged: and by the fear of the LORD men depart from evil. 7  When a man’s ways please the LORD, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him. 8 [*] Better is a little with righteousness than great revenues without right. 9 [*] A man’s heart deviseth his way: but the LORD directeth his steps. 10 [†] A divine sentence is in the lips of the king: his mouth transgresseth not in judgment. 11 [*] A just weight and balance are the LORD’s: [†]all the weights of the bag are his work. 12  It is an abomination to kings to commit wickedness: for the throne is established by righteousness. 13  Righteous lips are the delight of kings; and they love him that speaketh right.

14  The wrath of a king is as messengers of death: but a wise man will pacify it. 15  In the light of the king’s countenance is life; and [*]his favour is as a cloud of the latter rain. 16 [*] How much better is it to get wisdom than gold! and to get understanding rather to be chosen than silver! 17  The highway of the upright is to depart from evil: he that keepeth his way preserveth his soul. 18 [*] Pride goeth before destruction, and an haughty spirit before a fall. 19  Better it is to be of an humble spirit with the lowly, than to divide the spoil with the proud. 20 [∥] He that handleth a matter wisely shall find good: and whoso [*]trusteth in the LORD, happy is he. 21  The wise in heart shall be called prudent: and the sweetness of the lips increaseth learning. 22 [*] Understanding is a wellspring of life unto him that hath it: but the instruction of fools is folly. 23  The heart of the wise [†]teacheth his mouth, and addeth learning to his lips. 24  Pleasant words are as an honeycomb, sweet to the soul, and health to the bones. 25 [*] There is a way that seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof are the ways of death. 26 [†] He that laboureth laboureth for himself; for his mouth [†]craveth it of him.

27 [†] An ungodly man diggeth up evil: and in his lips there is as a burning fire. 28 [*] A froward man [†]soweth strife: and a whisperer separateth chief friends.

29  A violent man enticeth his neighbour, and leadeth him into the way that is not good. 30  He shutteth his eyes to devise froward things: moving his lips he bringeth evil to pass. 31  The hoary head is a crown of glory, if it be found in the way of righteousness. 32  He that is slow to anger is better than the mighty; and he that ruleth his spirit than he that taketh a city. 33  The lot is cast into the lap; but the whole disposing thereof is of the LORD.

17

1  Better is [*]a dry morsel, and quietness therewith, than an house full of [∥]sacrifices with strife. 2  A wise servant shall have rule over a son that causeth shame, and shall have part of the inheritance among the brethren. 3 [*] The fining pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold: but the LORD trieth the hearts. 4  A wicked doer giveth heed to false lips; and a liar giveth ear to a naughty tongue. 5 [*] Whoso mocketh the poor reproacheth his Maker: and he that is glad at calamities shall not be [†]unpunished. 6 [*] Children’s children are the crown of old men; and the glory of children are their fathers. 7 [†] Excellent speech becometh not a fool: much less do [†]lying lips a prince. 8 [*] A gift is as a [†]precious stone in the eyes of him that hath it: whithersoever it turneth, it prospereth. 9 [*] He that covereth a transgression [∥]seeketh love; but he that repeateth a matter separateth very friends. 10 [∥] A reproof entereth more into a wise man than an hundred stripes into a fool. 11  An evil man seeketh only rebellion: therefore a cruel messenger shall be sent against him. 12  Let a bear robbed of her whelps meet a man, rather than a fool in his folly. 13  Whoso [*]rewardeth evil for good, evil shall not depart from his house. 14  The beginning of strife is as when one letteth out water: therefore leave off contention, before it be meddled with. 15 [*] He that justifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the just, even they both are abomination to the LORD. 16 Wherefore is there a price in the hand of a fool to get wisdom, seeing he hath no heart to it? 17 [*] A friend loveth at all times, and a brother is born for adversity. 18 [*] A man void of [†]understanding striketh hands, and becometh surety in the presence of his friend. 19  He loveth transgression that loveth strife: and he that exalteth his gate seeketh destruction. 20 [†] He that hath a froward heart findeth no good: and he that hath a perverse tongue falleth into mischief. 21 [*] He that begetteth a fool doeth it to his sorrow: and the father of a fool hath no joy. 22 [*] A merry heart doeth good [∥]like a medicine: but a broken spirit drieth the bones. 23  A wicked man taketh a gift out of the bosom to pervert the ways of judgment. 24 [*] Wisdom is before him that hath understanding; but the eyes of a fool are in the ends of the earth. 25 [*] A foolish son is a grief to his father, and bitterness to her that bare him. 26  Also to punish the just is not good, nor to strike princes for equity.

27 [*] He that hath knowledge spareth his words: and a man of understanding is of [∥]an excellent spirit. 28 [*] Even a fool, when he holdeth his peace, is counted wise: and he that shutteth his lips is esteemed a man of understanding.

18

1 [∥] Through desire a man, having separated himself, seeketh and intermeddleth with all wisdom. 2  A fool hath no delight in understanding, but that his heart may discover itself. 3  When the wicked cometh, then cometh also contempt, and with ignominy reproach. 4 [*] The words of a man’s mouth are as deep waters, and the wellspring of wisdom as a flowing brook. 5 [*] It is not good to accept the person of the wicked, to overthrow the righteous in judgment.

6  A fool’s lips enter into contention, and his mouth calleth for strokes. 7 [*] A fool’s mouth is his destruction, and his lips are the snare of his soul. 8 [*] The words of a [∥]talebearer are [∥]as wounds, and they go down into the [†]innermost parts of the belly. 9  He also that is slothful in his work is brother to him that is a great waster. 10 [*] The name of the LORD is a strong tower: the righteous runneth into it, and [†]is safe. 11 [*] The rich man’s wealth is his strong city, and as an high wall in his own conceit. 12 [*] Before destruction the heart of man is haughty, and before honour is humility. 13  He that [†]answereth a matter before he heareth it, it is folly and shame unto him. 14  The spirit of a man will sustain his infirmity; but a wounded spirit who can bear? 15  The heart of the prudent getteth knowledge; and the ear of the wise seeketh knowledge. 16 [*] A man’s gift maketh room for him, and bringeth him before great men. 17  He that is first in his own cause seemeth just; but his neighbour cometh and searcheth him. 18  The lot causeth contentions to cease, and parteth between the mighty. 19  A brother offended is harder to be won than a strong city: and their contentions are like the bars of a castle. 20 [*] A man’s belly shall be satisfied with the fruit of his mouth; and with the increase of his lips shall he be filled. 21  Death and life are in the power of the tongue: and they that love it shall eat the fruit thereof. 22 [*] Whoso findeth a wife findeth a good thing, and obtaineth favour of the LORD. 23  The poor useth intreaties; but the rich answereth [*]roughly. 24  A man that hath friends must shew himself friendly: [*]and there is a friend that sticketh closer than a brother.

19

1 [*] Better is the poor that walketh in his integrity, than he that is perverse in his lips, and is a fool. 2 Also, that the soul be without knowledge, it is not good; and he that hasteth with his feet sinneth. 3  The foolishness of man perverteth his way: and his heart fretteth against the LORD. 4 [*] Wealth maketh many friends; but the poor is separated from his neighbour. 5 [*] A false witness shall not be [†]unpunished, and he that speaketh lies shall not escape.

6  Many will intreat the favour of the prince: and every man is a friend to [†]him that giveth gifts. 7 [*] All the brethren of the poor do hate him: how much more do his friends go far from him? he pursueth them with words, yet they are wanting to him. 8  He that getteth [†]wisdom loveth his own soul: he that keepeth understanding shall find good. 9 [*] A false witness shall not be unpunished, and he that speaketh lies shall perish. 10  Delight is not seemly for a fool; much less [*]for a servant to have rule over princes. 11 [*] The [∥]discretion of a man deferreth his anger; and it is his glory to pass over a transgression. 12 [*] The king’s wrath is as the roaring of a lion; but his favour is as dew upon the grass. 13 [*] A foolish son is the calamity of his father: [*]and the contentions of a wife are a continual dropping. 14  House and riches are the inheritance of fathers: and [*]a prudent wife is from the LORD. 15  Slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep; and an idle soul [*]shall suffer hunger. 16 [*] He that keepeth the commandment keepeth his own soul; but he that despiseth his ways shall die. 17 [*] He that hath pity upon the poor lendeth unto the LORD; and [∥]that which he hath given will he pay him again. 18 [*] Chasten thy son while there is hope, and let not thy soul spare [∥]for his crying. 19  A man of great wrath shall suffer punishment: for if thou deliver him, yet thou must [†]do it again. 20  Hear counsel, and receive instruction, that thou mayest be wise in thy latter end. 21 [*] There are many devices in a man’s heart; nevertheless the counsel of the LORD, that shall stand. 22  The desire of a man is his kindness: and a poor man is better than a liar. 23  The fear of the LORD tendeth to life: and he that hath it shall abide satisfied; he shall not be visited with evil. 24 [*] A slothful man hideth his hand in his bosom, and will not so much as bring it to his mouth again. 25 [*] Smite a scorner, and the simple [†]will beware: and reprove one that hath understanding, and he will understand knowledge. 26  He that wasteth his father, and chaseth away his mother, is a son that causeth shame, and bringeth reproach. 27  Cease, my son, to hear the instruction that causeth to err from the words of knowledge. 28 [†] An ungodly witness scorneth judgment: and the mouth of the wicked devoureth iniquity. 29  Judgments are prepared for scorners, and stripes for the back of fools.

20

1  Wine is a mocker, strong drink is raging: and whosoever is deceived thereby is not wise. 2 [*] The fear of a king is as the roaring of a lion: whoso provoketh him to anger sinneth against his own soul. 3  It is an honour for a man to cease from strife: but every fool will be meddling. 4 [*] The sluggard will not plow by reason of the [∥]cold; therefore shall he beg in harvest, and have nothing. 5 [*] Counsel in the heart of man is like deep water; but a man of understanding will draw it out. 6  Most men will proclaim every one his own [∥]goodness: but a faithful man who can find? 7  The just man walketh in his integrity: [*]his children are blessed after him. 8  A king that sitteth in the throne of judgment scattereth away all evil with his eyes. 9 [*] Who can say, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my sin? 10 [*][†] Divers weights, and [†]divers measures, both of them are alike abomination to the LORD. 11  Even a child is known by his doings, whether his work be pure, and whether it be right. 12 [*] The hearing ear, and the seeing eye, the LORD hath made even both of them. 13 [*] Love not sleep, lest thou come to poverty; open thine eyes, and thou shalt be satisfied with bread. 14  It is naught, it is naught, saith the buyer: but when he is gone his way, then he boasteth. 15  There is gold, and a multitude of rubies: but the lips of knowledge are a precious jewel. 16 [*] Take his garment that is surety for a stranger: and take a pledge of him for a strange woman. 17 [*][†] Bread of deceit is sweet to a man; but afterwards his mouth shall be filled with gravel. 18 [*] Every purpose is established by counsel: and with good advice make war. 19 [*] He that goeth about as a talebearer revealeth secrets: therefore meddle not with him that [∥]flattereth with his lips. 20 [*] Whoso curseth his father or his mother, his [∥]lamp shall be put out in obscure darkness. 21  An inheritance may be gotten hastily at the beginning; but the end thereof shall not be blessed. 22 [*] Say not thou, I will recompense evil; but wait on the LORD, and he shall save thee. 23 [*] Divers weights are an abomination unto the LORD; and [†]a false balance is not good. 24 [*] Man’s goings are of the LORD; how can a man then understand his own way? 25  It is a snare to the man who devoureth that which is holy, and after vows to make enquiry. 26 [*] A wise king scattereth the wicked, and bringeth the wheel over them. 27  The spirit of man is the [∥]candle of the LORD, searching all the inward parts of the belly. 28 [*] Mercy and truth preserve the king: and his throne is upholden by mercy. 29  The glory of young men is their strength: and [*]the beauty of old men is the gray head. 30  The blueness of a wound [†]cleanseth away evil: so do stripes the inward parts of the belly.

21

1  The king’s heart is in the hand of the LORD, as the rivers of water: he turneth it whithersoever he will. 2 [*] Every way of a man is right in his own eyes: but the LORD pondereth the hearts. 3 [*] To do justice and judgment is more acceptable to the LORD than sacrifice. 4 [*][†] An high look, and a proud heart, and [∥]the plowing of the wicked, is sin. 5  The thoughts of the diligent tend only to plenteousness; but of every one that is hasty only to want. 6 [*] The getting of treasures by a lying tongue is a vanity tossed to and fro of them that seek death. 7  The robbery of the wicked shall [†]destroy them; because they refuse to do judgment. 8  The way of man is froward and strange: but as for the pure, his work is right. 9 [*] It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop, than with [†]a brawling woman in [†]a wide house. 10 [*] The soul of the wicked desireth evil: his neighbour [†]findeth no favour in his eyes. 11 [*] When the scorner is punished, the simple is made wise: and when the wise is instructed, he receiveth knowledge. 12  The righteous man wisely considereth the house of the wicked: but God overthroweth the wicked for their wickedness. 13 [*] Whoso stoppeth his ears at the cry of the poor, he also shall cry himself, but shall not be heard. 14 [*] A gift in secret pacifieth anger: and a reward in the bosom strong wrath. 15  It is joy to the just to do judgment: but destruction shall be to the workers of iniquity. 16  The man that wandereth out of the way of understanding shall remain in the congregation of the dead. 17  He that loveth [∥]pleasure shall be a poor man: he that loveth wine and oil shall not be rich. 18 [*] The wicked shall be a ransom for the righteous, and the transgressor for the upright. 19 [*] It is better to dwell [†]in the wilderness, than with a contentious and an angry woman. 20  There is treasure to be desired and oil in the dwelling of the wise; but a foolish man spendeth it up. 21  He that followeth after righteousness and mercy findeth life, righteousness, and honour. 22 [*] A wise man scaleth the city of the mighty, and casteth down the strength of the confidence thereof. 23 [*] Whoso keepeth his mouth and his tongue keepeth his soul from troubles. 24  Proud and haughty scorner is his name, who dealeth [†]in proud wrath.

25 [*] The desire of the slothful killeth him; for his hands refuse to labour. 26  He coveteth greedily all the day long: but the [*]righteous giveth and spareth not. 27 [*] The sacrifice of the wicked is abomination: how much more, when he bringeth it [†]with a wicked mind? 28 [*][†] A false witness shall perish: but the man that heareth speaketh constantly. 29  A wicked man hardeneth his face: but as for the upright, he [∥]directeth his way.

30 [*] There is no wisdom nor understanding nor counsel against the LORD. 31 [*] The horse is prepared against the day of battle: but [*][∥]safety is of the LORD.

22

1 [*]A good name is rather to be chosen than great riches, and [∥]loving favour rather than silver and gold. 2 [*] The rich and poor meet together: the LORD is the maker of them all. 3 [*] A prudent man foreseeth the evil, and hideth himself: but the simple pass on, and are punished. 4 [*][∥] By humility and the fear of the LORD are riches, and honour, and life. 5  Thorns and snares are in the way of the froward: he that doth keep his soul shall be far from them. 6 [∥] Train up a child [†]in the way he should go: and when he is old, he will not depart from it. 7  The rich ruleth over the poor, and the borrower is servant [†]to the lender. 8 [*] He that soweth iniquity shall reap vanity: [∥]and the rod of his anger shall fail. 9 [*][†] He that hath a bountiful eye shall be blessed; for he giveth of his bread to the poor. 10 [*] Cast out the scorner, and contention shall go out; yea, strife and reproach shall cease. 11  He that loveth pureness of heart, [∥]for the grace of his lips the king shall be his friend. 12  The eyes of the LORD preserve knowledge, and he overthroweth [∥]the words of the transgressor. 13 [*] The slothful man saith, There is a lion without, I shall be slain in the streets. 14 [*] The mouth of strange women is a deep pit: he that is abhorred of the LORD shall fall therein. 15  Foolishness is bound in the heart of a child; but [*]the rod of correction shall drive it far from him. 16  He that oppresseth the poor to increase his riches, and he that giveth to the rich, shall surely come to want.

17  Bow down thine ear, and hear the words of the wise, and apply thine heart unto my knowledge. 18 For it is a pleasant thing if thou keep them [†]within thee; they shall withal be fitted in thy lips. 19  That thy trust may be in the LORD, I have made known to thee this day, [∥]even to thee. 20  Have not I written to thee excellent things in counsels and knowledge, 21  That I might make thee know the certainty of the words of truth; that thou mightest answer the words of truth [∥]to them that send unto thee?

22  Rob not the poor, because he is poor: [*]neither oppress the afflicted in the gate: 23 [*] For the LORD will plead their cause, and spoil the soul of those that spoiled them.

24  Make no friendship with an angry man; and with a furious man thou shalt not go: 25  Lest thou learn his ways, and get a snare to thy soul.

26 [*]Be not thou one of them that strike hands, or of them that are sureties for debts. 27  If thou hast nothing to pay, why should he take away thy bed from under thee? 28 [*] Remove not the ancient [∥]landmark, which thy fathers have set. 29  Seest thou a man diligent in his business? he shall stand before kings; he shall not stand before [†]mean men.

23

1  When thou sittest to eat with a ruler, consider diligently what is before thee: 2  And put a knife to thy throat, if thou be a man given to appetite. 3  Be not desirous of his dainties: for they are deceitful meat.

4 [*] Labour not to be rich: cease from thine own wisdom. 5 [†] Wilt thou set thine eyes upon that which is not? for riches certainly make themselves wings; they fly away as an eagle toward heaven.

6  Eat thou not the bread of him that hath an evil eye, neither desire thou his dainty meats: 7  For as he thinketh in his heart, so is he: Eat and drink, saith he to thee; but his heart is not with thee. 8  The morsel which thou hast eaten shalt thou vomit up, and lose thy sweet words. 9  Speak not in the ears of a fool: for he will despise the wisdom of thy words.

10 [*] Remove not the old [∥]landmark; and enter not into the fields of the fatherless: 11 [*] For their redeemer is mighty; he shall plead their cause with thee.

12  Apply thine heart unto instruction, and thine ears to the words of knowledge. 13 [*] Withhold not correction from the child: for if thou beatest him with the rod, he shall not die. 14  Thou shalt beat him with the rod, and shalt deliver his soul from hell. 15  My son, if thine heart be wise, my heart shall rejoice, [∥]even mine. 16  Yea, my reins shall rejoice, when thy lips speak right things.

17 [*] Let not thine heart envy sinners: but be thou in the fear of the LORD all the day long. 18 [*] For surely there is an [∥]end; and thine expectation shall not be cut off.

19  Hear thou, my son, and be wise, and guide thine heart in the way. 20 [*] Be not among winebibbers; among riotous eaters [†]of flesh: 21  For the drunkard and the glutton shall come to poverty: and drowsiness shall clothe a man with rags. 22 [*] Hearken unto thy father that begat thee, and despise not thy mother when she is old. 23  Buy the truth, and sell it not; also wisdom, and instruction, and understanding. 24 [*] The father of the righteous shall greatly rejoice: and he that begetteth a wise child shall have joy of him. 25  Thy father and thy mother shall be glad, and she that bare thee shall rejoice. 26  My son, give me thine heart, and let thine eyes observe my ways. 27 [*] For a whore is a deep ditch; and a strange woman is a narrow pit. 28 [*] She also lieth in wait [∥]as for a prey, and increaseth the transgressors among men.

29 [*] Who hath woe? who hath sorrow? who hath contentions? who hath babbling? who hath wounds without cause? who hath redness of eyes? 30  They that tarry long at the wine; they that go to seek mixed wine. 31  Look not thou upon the wine when it is red, when it giveth his colour in the cup, when it moveth itself aright. 32  At the last it biteth like a serpent, and stingeth like [∥]an adder. 33  Thine eyes shall behold strange women, and thine heart shall utter perverse things. 34  Yea, thou shalt be as he that lieth down [†]in the midst of the sea, or as he that lieth upon the top of a mast. 35  They have stricken me, shalt thou say, and I was not sick; they have beaten me, and [†]I felt it not: when shall I awake? I will seek it yet again.

24

1  Be not thou [*]envious against evil men, neither desire to be with them. 2 [*] For their heart studieth destruction, and their lips talk of mischief.

3  Through wisdom is an house builded; and by understanding it is established: 4  And by knowledge shall the chambers be filled with all precious and pleasant riches. 5  A wise man [†]is strong; yea, a man of knowledge [†]increaseth strength. 6 [*] For by wise counsel thou shalt make thy war: and in multitude of counsellors there is safety.

7  Wisdom is too high for a fool: he openeth not his mouth in the gate. 8  He that deviseth to do evil shall be called a mischievous person. 9  The thought of foolishness is sin: and the scorner is an abomination to men. 10  If thou faint in the day of adversity, thy strength is [†]small.

11 [*] If thou forbear to deliver them that are drawn unto death, and those that are ready to be slain; 12  If thou sayest, Behold, we knew it not; doth not he that pondereth the heart consider it? and he that keepeth thy soul, doth not he know it? and shall not he render to every man [*]according to his works?

13  My son, eat thou honey, because it is good; and the honeycomb, which is sweet [†]to thy taste: 14 [*]So shall the knowledge of wisdom be unto thy soul: when thou hast found it, [*]then there shall be a reward, and thy expectation shall not be cut off.

15  Lay not wait, O wicked man, against the dwelling of the righteous; spoil not his resting place: 16 [*] For a just man falleth seven times, and riseth up again: but the wicked shall fall into mischief.

17 [*] Rejoice not when thine enemy falleth, and let not thine heart be glad when he stumbleth: 18  Lest the LORD see it, and [†]it displease him, and he turn away his wrath from him.

19 [*][∥] Fret not thyself because of evil men, neither be thou envious at the wicked; 20  For there shall be no reward to the evil man; [*]the [∥]candle of the wicked shall be put out.

21  My son, fear thou the LORD and the king: and meddle not with [†]them that are given to change: 22  For their calamity shall rise suddenly; and who knoweth the ruin of them both?

23 These things also belong to the wise. [*]It is not good to have respect of persons in judgment. 24 [*] He that saith unto the wicked, Thou art righteous; him shall the people curse, nations shall abhor him: 25  But to them that rebuke him shall be delight, and [†]a good blessing shall come upon them. 26  Every man shall kiss his lips [†]that giveth a right answer. 27  Prepare thy work without, and make it fit for thyself in the field; and afterwards build thine house.

28  Be not a witness against thy neighbour without cause; and deceive not with thy lips. 29 [*] Say not, I will do so to him as he hath done to me: I will render to the man according to his work.

30  I went by the field of the slothful, and by the vineyard of the man void of understanding; 31  And, lo, it was all grown over with thorns, and nettles had covered the face thereof, and the stone wall thereof was broken down. 32  Then I saw, and [†]considered it well: I looked upon it, and received instruction. 33 [*] Yet a little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep: 34  So shall thy poverty come as one that travelleth; and thy want as [†]an armed man.

25

1 These are also proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah copied out.

2  It is the glory of God to conceal a thing: but the honour of kings is to search out a matter. 3  The heaven for height, and the earth for depth, and the heart of kings [†]is unsearchable.

4  Take away the dross from the silver, and there shall come forth a vessel for the finer. 5 [*] Take away the wicked from before the king, and his throne shall be established in righteousness.

6 [†] Put not forth thyself in the presence of the king, and stand not in the place of great men: 7 [*] For better it is that it be said unto thee, Come up hither; than that thou shouldest be put lower in the presence of the prince whom thine eyes have seen.

8  Go not forth hastily to strive, lest thou know not what to do in the end thereof, when thy neighbour hath put thee to shame. 9 [*] Debate thy cause with thy neighbour himself; and [∥]discover not a secret to another: 10  Lest he that heareth it put thee to shame, and thine infamy turn not away.

11  A word [†]fitly spoken is like apples of gold in pictures of silver. 12  As an earring of gold, and an ornament of fine gold, so is a wise reprover upon an obedient ear. 13 [*] As the cold of snow in the time of harvest, so is a faithful messenger to them that send him: for he refresheth the soul of his masters. 14  Whoso boasteth himself [†]of a false gift is like clouds and wind without rain. 15 [*] By long forbearing is a prince persuaded, and a soft tongue breaketh the bone. 16  Hast thou found honey? eat so much as is sufficient for thee, lest thou be filled therewith, and vomit it. 17 [∥] Withdraw thy foot from thy neighbour’s house; lest he be [†]weary of thee, and so hate thee. 18 [*] A man that beareth false witness against his neighbour is a maul, and a sword, and a sharp arrow. 19  Confidence in an unfaithful man in time of trouble is like a broken tooth, and a foot out of joint. 20  As he that taketh away a garment in cold weather, and as vinegar upon nitre, so is he that singeth songs to an heavy heart.

21 [*] If thine enemy be hungry, give him bread to eat; and if he be thirsty, give him water to drink: 22  For thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head, and the LORD shall reward thee. 23 [∥] The north wind driveth away rain: so doth an angry countenance a backbiting tongue. 24 [*] It is better to dwell in the corner of the housetop, than with a brawling woman and in a wide house. 25  As cold waters to a thirsty soul, so is good news from a far country. 26  A righteous man falling down before the wicked is as a troubled fountain, and a corrupt spring. 27  It is not good to eat much honey: so for men to search their own glory is not glory. 28 [*] He that hath no rule over his own spirit is like a city that is broken down, and without walls.

26

1  As snow in summer, and as rain in harvest, so honour is not seemly for a fool. 2  As the bird by wandering, as the swallow by flying, so the curse causeless shall not come. 3  A [*]whip for the horse, a bridle for the ass, and a rod for the fool’s back.

4  Answer not a fool according to his folly, lest thou also be like unto him. 5  Answer a fool according to his folly, lest he be wise in [†]his own conceit.

6  He that sendeth a message by the hand of a fool cutteth off the feet, and drinketh [∥]damage. 7  The legs of the lame [†]are not equal: so is a parable in the mouth of fools. 8 [∥] As he that bindeth a stone in a sling, so is he that giveth honour to a fool. 9  As a thorn goeth up into the hand of a drunkard, so is a parable in the mouth of fools. 10 [∥] The great God that formed all things both rewardeth the fool, and rewardeth transgressors. 11 [*] As a dog returneth to his vomit, so a fool [†]returneth to his folly. 12  Seest thou a man wise in his own conceit? there is more hope of a fool than of him. 13 [*] The slothful man saith, There is a lion in the way; a lion is in the streets. 14  As the door turneth upon his hinges, so doth the slothful upon his bed. 15 [*] The slothful hideth his hand in his bosom; [∥]it grieveth him to bring it again to his mouth. 16  The sluggard is wiser in his own conceit than seven men that can render a reason. 17  He that passeth by, and [∥]meddleth with strife belonging not to him, is like one that taketh a dog by the ears.

18  As a mad man who casteth [†]firebrands, arrows, and death, 19 So is the man that deceiveth his neighbour, and saith, Am not I in sport?

20 [†] Where no wood is, there the fire goeth out: so [*]where there is no [∥]talebearer, the strife [†]ceaseth. 21 [*] As coals are to burning coals, and wood to fire; so is a contentious man to kindle strife. 22 [*] The words of a talebearer are as wounds, and they go down into the [†]innermost parts of the belly. 23  Burning lips and a wicked heart are like a potsherd covered with silver dross.

24  He that hateth [∥]dissembleth with his lips, and layeth up deceit within him; 25  When he [†]speaketh fair, believe him not: for there are seven abominations in his heart. 26  Whose [∥]hatred is covered by deceit, his wickedness shall be shewed before the whole congregation. 27 [*] Whoso diggeth a pit shall fall therein: and he that rolleth a stone, it will return upon him. 28  A lying tongue hateth those that are afflicted by it; and a flattering mouth worketh ruin.

27

1 [*] Boast not thyself of [†]to morrow; for thou knowest not what a day may bring forth. 2  Let another man praise thee, and not thine own mouth; a stranger, and not thine own lips.

3  A stone is [†]heavy, and the sand weighty; but a fool’s wrath is heavier than them both. 4 [†] Wrath is cruel, and anger is outrageous; but who is able to stand before [∥]envy?

5  Open rebuke is better than secret love. 6 [*] Faithful are the wounds of a friend; but the kisses of an enemy are [∥]deceitful. 7  The full soul [†]loatheth an honeycomb; but [*]to the hungry soul every bitter thing is sweet. 8  As a bird that wandereth from her nest, so is a man that wandereth from his place.

9  Ointment and perfume rejoice the heart: so doth the sweetness of a man’s friend [†]by hearty counsel. 10  Thine own friend, and thy father’s friend, forsake not; neither go into thy brother’s house in the day of thy calamity: for [*]better is a neighbour that is near than a brother far off. 11 [*] My son, be wise, and make my heart glad, that I may answer him that reproacheth me. 12 [*] A prudent man foreseeth the evil, and hideth himself; but the simple pass on, and are punished. 13 [*] Take his garment that is surety for a stranger, and take a pledge of him for a strange woman. 14  He that blesseth his friend with a loud voice, rising early in the morning, it shall be counted a curse to him.

15 [*] A continual dropping in a very rainy day and a contentious woman are alike. 16  Whosoever hideth her hideth the wind, and the ointment of his right hand, which bewrayeth itself. 17  Iron sharpeneth iron; so a man sharpeneth the countenance of his friend. 18  Whoso keepeth the fig tree shall eat the fruit thereof: so he that waiteth on his master shall be honoured. 19  As in water face answereth to face, so the heart of man to man. 20  Hell and destruction are [†]never full; so [*]the eyes of man are never satisfied. 21 [*] As the fining pot for silver, and the furnace for gold; so is a man to his praise. 22  Though thou shouldest bray a fool in a mortar among wheat with a pestle, yet will not his foolishness depart from him.

23  Be thou diligent to know the state of thy flocks, and [†]look well to thy herds. 24  For [†]riches are not for ever: and doth the crown endure [†]to every generation? 25  The hay appeareth, and the tender grass sheweth itself, and herbs of the mountains are gathered. 26  The lambs are for thy clothing, and the goats are the price of [‡]the field. 27 And thou shalt have goats’ milk enough for thy food, for the food of thy household, and for the [†]maintenance for thy maidens.

28

1  The [*]wicked flee when no man pursueth: but the righteous are bold as a lion. 2  For the transgression of a land many are the princes thereof: but [∥]by a man of understanding and knowledge the state thereof shall be prolonged. 3  A poor man that oppresseth the poor is like a sweeping rain [†]which leaveth no food. 4  They that forsake the law praise the wicked: but such as keep the law contend with them. 5  Evil men understand not judgment: but they that seek the LORD understand all things. 6 [*] Better is the poor that walketh in his uprightness, than he that is perverse in his ways, though he be rich. 7 [*] Whoso keepeth the law is a wise son: but he that [∥]is a companion of riotous men shameth his father. 8 [*] He that by usury and [†]unjust gain increaseth his substance, he shall gather it for him that will pity the poor. 9  He that turneth away his ear from hearing the law, even his prayer shall be abomination. 10 [*] Whoso causeth the righteous to go astray in an evil way, he shall fall himself into his own pit: but the upright shall have good things in possession. 11  The rich man is wise [†]in his own conceit; but the poor that hath understanding searcheth him out. 12 [*] When righteous men do rejoice, there is great glory: but when the wicked rise, a man is [∥]hidden. 13 [*] He that covereth his sins shall not prosper: but whoso confesseth and forsaketh them shall have mercy. 14  Happy is the man that feareth alway: [*]but he that hardeneth his heart shall fall into mischief. 15  As a roaring lion, and a ranging bear; so is a wicked ruler over the poor people. 16  The prince that wanteth understanding is also a great oppressor: but he that hateth covetousness shall prolong his days. 17 [*] A man that doeth violence to the blood of any person shall [‡]flee to the pit; let no man stay him. 18 [*] Whoso walketh uprightly shall be saved: but he that is perverse in his ways shall fall at once. 19 [*] He that tilleth his land shall have plenty of bread: but he that followeth after vain persons shall have poverty enough. 20  A faithful man shall abound with blessings: [*]but he that maketh haste to be rich shall not be [∥]innocent. 21 [*] To have respect of persons is not good: for for a piece of bread that man will transgress. 22 [∥] He that hasteth to be rich hath an evil eye, and considereth not that poverty shall come upon him. 23 [*] He that rebuketh a man afterwards shall find more favour than he that flattereth with the tongue. 24  Whoso robbeth his father or his mother, and saith, It is no transgression; the same is the companion of [†]a destroyer. 25 [*] He that is of a proud heart stirreth up strife: but he that putteth his trust in the LORD shall be made fat. 26  He that trusteth in his own heart is a fool: but whoso walketh wisely, he shall be delivered. 27 [*] He that giveth unto the poor shall not lack: but he that hideth his eyes shall have many a curse. 28 [*] When the wicked rise, men hide themselves: but when they perish, the righteous increase.

29

1 [†] He, that being often reproved hardeneth his neck, shall suddenly be destroyed, and that without remedy. 2 [*] When the righteous are [∥]in authority, the people rejoice: but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn. 3 [*] Whoso loveth wisdom rejoiceth his father: [*]but he that keepeth company with harlots spendeth his substance. 4  The king by judgment establisheth the land: but [†]he that receiveth gifts overthroweth it. 5  A man that flattereth his neighbour spreadeth a net for his feet. 6  In the transgression of an evil man there is a snare: but the righteous doth sing and rejoice. 7 [*] The righteous considereth the cause of the poor: but the wicked regardeth not to know it. 8  Scornful men [∥]bring a city into a snare: but wise men turn away wrath. 9  If a wise man contendeth with a foolish man, whether he rage or laugh, there is no rest. 10 [†] The bloodthirsty hate the upright: but the just seek his soul. 11  A fool uttereth all his mind: but a wise man keepeth it in till afterwards. 12  If a ruler hearken to lies, all his servants are wicked. 13 [*] The poor and [∥]the deceitful man meet together: the LORD lighteneth both their eyes. 14 [*] The king that faithfully judgeth the poor, his throne shall be established for ever. 15 [*] The rod and reproof give wisdom: but [*]a child left to himself bringeth his mother to shame. 16  When the wicked are multiplied, transgression increaseth: [*]but the righteous shall see their fall. 17 [*] Correct thy son, and he shall give thee rest; yea, he shall give delight unto thy soul. 18 Where there is no vision, the people [∥]perish: but he that keepeth the law, happy is he. 19  A servant will not be corrected by words: for though he understand he will not answer. 20  Seest thou a man that is hasty [∥]in his words? there is more hope of a fool than of him. 21  He that delicately bringeth up his servant from a child shall have him become his son at the length. 22 [*] An angry man stirreth up strife, and a furious man aboundeth in transgression. 23 [*] A man’s pride shall bring him low: but honour shall uphold the humble in spirit. 24  Whoso is partner with a thief hateth his own soul: he heareth cursing, and bewrayeth it not. 25  The fear of man bringeth a snare: but whoso putteth his trust in the LORD [†]shall be safe. 26 [*] Many seek [†]the ruler’s favour; but every man’s judgment cometh from the LORD. 27  An unjust man is an abomination to the just: and he that is upright in the way is abomination to the wicked.

30

1  The words of Agur the son of Jakeh, even the prophecy: the man spake unto Ithiel, even unto Ithiel and Ucal, 2 Surely I am more brutish than any man, and have not the understanding of a man. 3  I neither learned wisdom, nor [†]have the knowledge of the holy. 4 [*] Who hath ascended up into heaven, or descended? [*]who hath gathered the wind in his fists? who hath bound the waters in a garment? who hath established all the ends of the earth? what is his name, and what is his son’s name, if thou canst tell? 5 [*] Every word of God is [†]pure: he is a shield unto them that put their trust in him. 6 [*] Add thou not unto his words, lest he reprove thee, and thou be found a liar.

7  Two things have I required of thee; [†]deny me them not before I die: 8  Remove far from me vanity and lies: give me neither poverty nor riches; [*]feed me with food [†]convenient for me: 9 [*] Lest I be full, and [†]deny thee, and say, Who is the LORD? or lest I be poor, and steal, and take the name of my God in vain.

10 [†] Accuse not a servant unto his master, lest he curse thee, and thou be found guilty. 11  There is a generation that curseth their father, and doth not bless their mother. 12  There is a generation that are pure in their own eyes, and yet is not washed from their filthiness. 13  There is a generation, O how [*]lofty are their eyes! and their eyelids are lifted up. 14 [*] There is a generation, whose teeth are as swords, and their jaw teeth as knives, to devour the poor from off the earth, and the needy from among men.

15  The horseleach hath two daughters, crying, Give, give. There are three things that are never satisfied, yea, four things say not, [†]It is enough: 16  The grave; and the barren womb; the earth that is not filled with water; and the fire that saith not, It is enough. 17  The eye that mocketh at his father, and despiseth to obey his mother, the ravens of [∥]the valley shall pick it out, and the young eagles shall eat it.

18  There be three things which are too wonderful for me, yea, four which I know not: 19  The way of an eagle in the air; the way of a serpent upon a rock; the way of a ship in the [†]midst of the sea; and the way of a man with a maid. 20 Such is the way of an adulterous woman; she eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and saith, I have done no wickedness. 21  For three things the earth is disquieted, and for four which it cannot bear: 22 [*] For a servant when he reigneth; and a fool when he is filled with meat; 23  For an odious woman when she is married; and an handmaid that is heir to her mistress.

24  There be four things which are little upon the earth, but they are [†]exceeding wise: 25 [*] The ants are a people not strong, yet they prepare their meat in the summer; 26  The conies are but a feeble folk, yet make they their houses in the rocks; 27  The locusts have no king, yet go they forth all of them [†]by bands; 28  The spider taketh hold with her hands, and is in kings’ palaces.

29  There be three things which go well, yea, four are comely in going: 30  A lion which is strongest among beasts, and turneth not away for any; 31  A [∥][†]greyhound; an he goat also; and a king, against whom there is no rising up. 32  If thou hast done foolishly in lifting up thyself, or if thou hast thought evil, [*]lay thine hand upon thy mouth. 33  Surely the churning of milk bringeth forth butter, and the wringing of the nose bringeth forth blood: so the forcing of wrath bringeth forth strife.

31

1  The words of king Lemuel, the prophecy that his mother taught him. 2  What, my son? and what, the son of my womb? and what, the son of my vows? 3  Give not thy strength unto women, nor thy ways to that which destroyeth kings. 4  It is not for kings, O Lemuel, it is not for kings to drink wine; nor for princes strong drink: 5  Lest they drink, and forget the law, and [†]pervert the judgment [†]of any of the afflicted. 6 [*] Give strong drink unto him that is ready to perish, and wine unto those that be [†]of heavy hearts. 7  Let him drink, and forget his poverty, and remember his misery no more. 8  Open thy mouth for the dumb in the cause of all [†]such as are appointed to destruction. 9  Open thy mouth, [*]judge righteously, and plead the cause of the poor and needy.

10 ¶ [*]Who can find a virtuous woman? for her price is far above rubies. 11  The heart of her husband doth safely trust in her, so that he shall have no need of spoil. 12  She will do him good and not evil all the days of her life. 13  She seeketh wool, and flax, and worketh willingly with her hands. 14  She is like the merchants’ ships; she bringeth her food from afar. 15  She riseth also while it is yet night, and giveth meat to her household, and a portion to her maidens. 16  She considereth a field, and [†]buyeth it: with the fruit of her hands she planteth a vineyard. 17  She girdeth her loins with strength, and strengtheneth her arms. 18 [†] She perceiveth that her merchandise is good: her candle goeth not out by night. 19  She layeth her hands to the spindle, and her hands hold the distaff. 20 [†] She stretcheth out her hand to the poor; yea, she reacheth forth her hands to the needy. 21  She is not afraid of the snow for her household: for all her household are clothed with [∥]scarlet. 22  She maketh herself coverings of tapestry; her clothing is silk and purple. 23  Her husband is known in the gates, when he sitteth among the elders of the land. 24  She maketh fine linen, and selleth it; and delivereth girdles unto the merchant. 25  Strength and honour are her clothing; and she shall rejoice in time to come. 26  She openeth her mouth with wisdom; and in her tongue is the law of kindness. 27  She looketh well to the ways of her household, and eateth not the bread of idleness. 28  Her children arise up, and call her blessed; her husband also, and he praiseth her. 29  Many daughters [∥]have done virtuously, but thou excellest them all. 30  Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vain: but a woman that feareth the LORD, she shall be praised. 31  Give her of the fruit of her hands; and let her own works praise her in the gates.

† 1.3 Heb. equities.

∥ 1.4 Or, advisement.

∥ 1.6 Or, an eloquent speech.

* 1.7 Job 28. 28. Ps. 111. 10. ch. 9. 10.

∥ 1.7 Or, the principal part.

† 1.9 Heb. an adding

* 1.16 Is. 59. 7. Rom. 8. 15.

† 1.17 Heb. in the eyes of every thing that hath a wing.

† 1.20 Heb. Wisdoms, that is, excellent wisdom.

* 1.20 ch. 8. 1.

* 1.24 Is. 65. 12. &c 66. 4. Jer. 7. 13. Ezek. 8. 18.

* 1.28 Job 27. 9. Is. 1. 15. Jer. 11. 11. &c 14. 12. Mic. 3. 4.

∥ 1.32 Or, ease of the simple.

† 2.3 Heb. givest thy voice.

* 2.4 Matt. 13. 44.

* 2.6 James 1. 5. 1 Kin. 3. 9.

* 2.16 ch. 5. 3. &c 7. 5.

* 2.21 Ps. 37. 29.

* 2.22 Job 18. 17. Ps. 104. 35.

∥ 2.22 Or, plucked up.

* 3.1 Deut. 8. 1. &c 30. 16.

† 3.2 Heb. years of life.

* 3.3 Ex. 13. 9. Deut. 6. 8.

* 3.4 Ps. 111. 10.

∥ 3.4 Or, good success.

* 3.6 1 Chr. 28 9.

* 3.7 Rom, 12. 16.

† 3.8 Heb. medicine.

† 3.8 Heb watering, or, moistening.

* 3.9 Ex. 23 19. &c 34 26 Deut. 26. 2, &c. Mal. 3. 10, &c. Luke 14. 13.

* 3.10 Deut. 28. 8

* 3.11 Job 5. 17. Heb. 12. 5. Rev. 3. 19.

† 3.13 Heb. the man that draweth out understanding

* 3.14 Job 28 15, &c. Ps. 19 10. ch. 8 11, 19. &c 16. 16.

∥ 3.19 Or, prepared.

* 3.23 Ps 37. 24 &c 91. 11.

† 3.27 Heb. the owners thereof.

∥ 3.29 Or, Practise no evil.

* 3.31 Ps. 37. 1.

† 3.31 Heb. a man of violence.

* 3.32 Ps. 25. 14.

* 3.33 Mal. 2. 2.

* 3.34 James 4. 6. 1 Pet. 5. 5.

† 3.35 Heb. exalteth the fools.

* 4.3 1 Chr. 29 1

* 4.4 1 Chr. 28 9.

* 4.9 ch. 1. 9.

∥ 4.9 Or, she shall compass thee with a crown of glory.

* 4.12 Ps. 91. 11.

* 4.14 Ps. 1. 1. ch. 1. 10, 15.

† 4.22 Heb. medicine.

† 4.23 Heb. above all keeping.

† 4.24 Heb. frowardness of mouth, and perverseness of lips.

∥ 4.26 Or, all thy ways shall be ordered aright.

* 4.27 Deut. 5. 32.

* 5.3 ch. 2 16. &c 6 24.

† 5.3 Heb. palate.

* 5.5 ch.7.27.

† 5.10 Heb. thy strength.

† 5.19 Heb. water thee.

† 5.19 Heb. err thou always in her love.

* 5.21 Job 31. 4. &c 34. 21. ch. 15. 3. Jer. 16. 17. &c 32. 19.

† 5.22 Heb. sin.

∥ 6.3 Or, so shalt thou prevail with thy friend.

* 6.9 ch. 24. 33.

* 6.11 ch. 13. 4. &c 20. 4.

† 6.14 Heb. casteth forth.

† 6.16 Heb. of his soul.

† 6.17 Heb. Haughty eyes.

* 6.18 Rom. 3. 15.

‡ 6.19 [1611 him]

* 6.20 ch. 1. 8.

* 6.23 Ps. 19. 8. &c 119. 105.

∥ 6.23 Or, candle.

* 6.24 ch. 2. 16. &c 5. 3. &c 7. 5.

∥ 6.24 Or, of the strange tongue.

* 6.25 Matt. 5. 28.

† 6.26 Heb. the woman of a man, or, a man's wife.

† 6.32 Heb. heart.

† 6.35 Heb. He will not accept the face of any ransom.

* 7.3 Deut. 6. 8. &c 11. 18. ch. 8. 3.

* 7.5 ch. 5. 3.

† 7.7 Heb. the sons.

† 7.9 Heb. in the evening of the day.

* 7.11 ch. 9. 13.

† 7.13 Heb. she strengthened her face, and said.

† 7.14 Heb. Peace offerings are upon me.

† 7.20 Heb. in his hand.

∥ 7.20 Or, the new moon.

‡ 7.21 [1611 omits her]

† 7.22 Heb. suddenly.

* 7.27 ch 2. 18. &c 5 5.

* 8.1 ch. 1. 20.

† 8.7 Heb. the abomination of my lips.

† 8.8 Heb. wreathed.

* 8.11 Job 28. 15. Ps 19 10. ch. 3. 15. &c 16. 16.

∥ 8.12 Or, subtilty.

* 8.18 ch. 3. 16.

* 8.19 ch. 3. 14.

∥ 8.20 Or, walk.

∥ 8.26 Or, open places.

∥ 8.26 Or, the chief part.

∥ 8.27 Or, a circle.

* 8.29 Gen. 1. 9, 10. Job 38. 10, 11. Ps. 104. 9.

* 8.32 Ps. 119. 1, 2. &c 128 1 Luke 11. 28.

† 8.35 Heb. bring forth.

† 9.2 Heb her killing.

* 9.8 Matt. 7. 6.

* 9.10 Job 28. 28. Ps. 111. 10. ch 1. 7.

* 9.11 ch. 10. 27.

* 9.13 ch. 7. 11.

† 9.17 Heb. of secrecies.

* 10.1 ch. 15. 20.

* 10.2 ch. 11. 4.

* 10.3 Ps. 37. 25.

∥ 10.3 Or, the wicked for their wickedness.

* 10.4 ch. 12. 24.

* 10.6 ver. 11.

* 10.7 Ps. 112. 6.

† 10.8 Heb. a fool of lips.

∥ 10.8 Or, shall be beaten.

* 10.9 Ps. 23. 4.

* 10.10 ch. 6. 13.

∥ 10.10 Or, shall be beaten.

* 10.11 ch. 13. 14

* 10.12 1 Cor. 13. 4. 1 Pet. 4. 8.

† 10.13 Heb. heart

* 10.15 ch. 18. 11.

∥ 10.17 Or, causeth to err.

† 10.21 Heb. of heart.

* 10.23 ch. 14 9.

‡ 10.23 [1611 a sport]

* 10.27 ch. 9. 11.

† 10.27 Heb. addeth.

* 10.28 Job 8. 13 &c 11. 20. Ps. 112. 10.

* 10.30 Ps. 37. 22. &c 125. 1.

† 10.32 Heb. frowardnesses.

* 11.1 Lev. 19. 36. Deut. 25. 15. ch 16. 11. &c 20. 10, 23.

† 11.1 Heb. Balances of deceit.

† 11.1 Heb. a perfect stone.

* 11.2 ch. 15. 33 &c 16 18. &c 18. 12.

* 11.3 ch. 13. 6.

* 11.4 ch 10. 2. Ezek. 7. 19. Zeph. 1. 18

† 11.5 Heb. rectify.

* 11.6 ch. 5 22.

* 11.8 ch 21. 18.

* 11.9 Job 8. 13.

† 11.12 Heb. destitute of heart.

† 11.13 Heb. He that walketh, being a talebearer.

* 11.14 1 Kin. 12 1.

† 11.15 Heb. shall be sore broken.

† 11.15 Heb. those that strike hands.

† 11.22 Heb. departeth from.

* 11.25 2 Cor. 9. 9.

† 11.25 Heb. The soul of blessing.

* 11.27 Ps. 7. 15, 16. &c 9. 15, 16. &c 10. 2. &c 57. 6.

* 11.28 Ps. 1. 3. &c 92. 12, &c. Jer. 17. 8.

† 11.30 Heb. taketh.

* 11.31 1 Pet. 4. 18.

* 12.3 ch. 10. 25.

* 12.4 1 Cor. 11. 7.

* 12.6 ch. 1. 11, 18.

* 12.7 Ps 37. 37 ch. 11. 21.

† 12.8 Heb. perverse of heart.

∥ 12.10 Or, bowels.

* 12.11 ch. 28. 19.

∥ 12.12 Or, the fortress.

† 12.13 Heb. The snare of the wicked is in the transgression of lips.

* 12.13 ch. 18. 7.

* 12.14 ch. 13. 2.

* 12.15 ch. 3. 7.

† 12.16 Heb. in that day.

* 12.17 ch. 14. 5.

* 12.18 Ps. 57. 4 &c 59. 7.

* 12.23 ch. 13. 16. &c 15 2.

* 12.24 ch. 10. 4.

∥ 12.24 Or, deceitful.

* 12.25 ch. 15. 13.

∥ 12.26 Or, abundant.

* 13.2 ch. 12. 14.

* 13.6 ch. 11. 3, 5, 6.

† 13.6 Heb. sin.

* 13.9 Job 18. 6. &c 21. 17.

∥ 13.9 Or, candle.

* 13.11 ch. 10.2. &c 20. 21.

† 13.11 Heb. with the hand.

∥ 13.13 Or, shall be in peace.

* 13.14 ch. 14. 27.

* 13.16 ch. 12. 23 &c 15. 2.

† 13.16 Heb. spreadeth.

† 13.20 Heb. shall be broken.

* 13.22 Job 27. 17.

* 13.23 ch. 12. 11.

* 13.24 ch 23. 13.

* 13.25 Ps. 34. 10. &c 37. 3.

* 14.2 Job 12. 4.

* 14.5 Ex. 20. 16. &c 23. 1. ch. 6. 19. &c 12. 17.

* 14.6 ch. 8. 9.

* 14.9 ch. 10. 23.

† 14.10 Heb. the bitterness of his soul.

* 14.12 ch. 16. 25.

* 14.14 ch. 1. 31.

* 14.20 ch. 19. 7.

† 14.20 Heb. many are the lovers of the rich.

* 14.21 Ps. 112. 9.

* 14.25 ver. 5.

* 14.27 ch. 13. 14.

† 14.29 Heb. short of spirit.

* 14.31 ch. 17. 5. Matt. 25. 40.

† 14.34 Heb to nations.

* 15.1 ch. 25. 15.

* 15.2 ch. 12. 23. &c 13. 16. ver. 28.

† 15.2 Heb. belcheth, or, bubbleth.

* 15.3 Job 34. 21. ch. 5. 21. Jer. 16. 17 &c 32. 19. Heb. 4. 13.

† 15.4 Heb. The healing of the tongue.

* 15.5 ch. 10.1.

* 15.8 ch. 21. 27. Is. 1. 11. &c 66. 3 Jer. 6. 20. &c 7. 22. Amos 5. 22.

∥ 15.10 Or, Instruction.

* 15.11 Job 26. 6

* 15.13 ch. 17 22.

* 15.16 Ps. 37. 16. ch. 16 8 1 Tim. 6 6

* 15.17 ch 17 1

* 15.18 ch. 26. 21. &c 29. 22.

† 15.19 Heb. is raised up as a causey

* 15.20 ch. 10 1.

* 15.21 ch. 10. 23.

† 15.21 Heb. void of heart.

* 15.22 ch. 11. 14.

† 15.23 Heb. in his season.

* 15.24 Phil. 3. 20. Col 3. 1, 2

* 15.25 ch. 12 7. &c 14. 11.

* 15.26 ch. 6. 18

† 15.26 Heb. words of pleasantness.

* 15.29 Ps. 34. 16. &c 145 18.

∥ 15.32 Or, correction.

∥ 15.32 Or, obeyeth.

† 15.32 Heb. possesseth an heart.

* 15.33 ch. 18. 12.

* 16.1 ver. 9. 19. 21. &c 20 24. Jer. 10. 23.

∥ 16.1 Or, disposings.

* 16.2 ch. 21. 2.

* 16.3 Ps 37. 5. &c 55. 23. Matt. 6. 25. Luke 12. 22. 1 Pet. 5. 7.

† 16.3 Heb. Roll.

* 16.4 Job 21. 30.

* 16.5 ch 6 17. &c 8. 13.

† 16.5 Heb. held innocent.

* 16.8 Ps. 37. 16. ch. 15 16.

* 16.9 ver. 1.

† 16.10 Heb. Divination

* 16.11 Lev. 19. 36. ch 11. 1.

† 16.11 Heb. all the stones.

* 16.15 ch. 19. 12.

* 16.16 ch. 8. 11.

* 16.18 ch 11 2. &c 18. 12.

∥ 16.20 Or, He that understandeth a matter.

* 16.20 Ps. 2 12. &c 34 8. &c 125 1. Is 30 18 Jer. 17. 7.

* 16.22 ch 13. 14.

† 16.23 Heb maketh wise

* 16.25 ch. 14. 12.

† 16.26 Heb. The soul of him that laboureth.

† 16.26 Heb boweth unto him.

† 16.27 Heb. A man of Belial

* 16.28 ch 6. 14, 19. &c 15. 18. &c 26 21. &c 29. 22.

† 16.28 Heb. sendeth forth.

* 17.1 ch. 15. 17.

∥ 17.1 Or, good cheer

* 17.3 Ps 26. 2 ch 27 21 Jer. 17. 10. Mal. 3. 3.

* 17.5 ch. 14. 31.

† 17.5 Heb. held innocent.

* 17.6 Ps. 127. 3. &c 128. 3.

† 17.7 Heb. A lip of excellency.

† 17.7 Heb. a lip of lying.

* 17.8 ch. 18. 16.

† 17.8 Heb. stone of grace.

* 17.9 ch. 10. 12.

∥ 17.9 Or, procureth.

∥ 17.10 Or, A reproof aweth more a wise man, than to strike a fool an hundred times

* 17.13 Rom. 12 17. 1 Thess. 5 15. 1 Pet. 3. 9.

* 17.15 Ex. 23. 7. ch. 24. 24. Is 5. 23.

* 17.17 ch. 18. 24.

* 17.18 ch. 6. 1. &c 11. 15.

† 17.18 Heb. heart.

† 17.20 Heb. The froward of heart.

* 17.21 ch. 10. 1

* 17.22 ch. 12. 25. &c 15. 13.

∥ 17.22 Or, to a medicine.

* 17.24 Eccles. 2. 14. &c 8. 1.

* 17.25 ch 10. 1. &c 15. 20 &c 19. 13.

* 17.27 James 1. 19.

∥ 17.27 Or, a cool spirit.

* 17.28 Job 13. 5.

∥ 18.1 Or, He that separateth himself seeketh according to his desire, and intermeddleth in every business.

* 18.4 ch. 20.5.

* 18.5 Lev. 19. 15. Deut. 1. 17. &c 16. 19. ch. 24.23.

* 18.7 ch. 10. 14. &c 12. 13. &c 13. 3.

* 18.8 ch. 12. 18. &c 26. 22.

∥ 18.8 Or, whisperer.

∥ 18.8 Or, like as when men are wounded

† 18.8 Heb. chambers.

* 18.10 Ps. 18. 2. &c 27. 1. &c 144. 2.

† 18.10 Heb. is set aloft.

* 18.11 ch. 10. 15.

* 18.12 ch.11.2. &c 15 33 &c 16 18.

† 18.13 Heb returneth a word.

* 18.16 ch.17.8.

* 18.20 ch 12. 14. &c 13. 2.

* 18.22 ch. 19. 14.

* 18.23 James 2. 3.

* 18.24 ch. 17. 17.

* 19.1 ch.28.6.

* 19.4 ch 14. 20.

* 19.5 Ex.23.1 Deut. 19. 16. ch 6 19. &c 21. 28.

† 19.5 Heb. held innocent.

† 19.6 Heb. a man of gifts

* 19.7 ch. 14. 20

† 19.8 Heb. an heart.

* 19.9 ver. 5.

* 19.10 ch. 30. 22 Eccles. 10 6.

* 19.11 ch. 14. 29.

∥ 19.11 Or, prudence.

* 19.12 ch. 16. 15 &c 20 2 &c 28. 15.

* 19.13 ch 10 1 &c 15. 20 &c 17. 21, 25.

* 19.13 ch 21 9 &c 27 15.

* 19.14 ch. 18. 22.

* 19.15 ch 10.4. &c 20. 13

* 19.16 Luke 11 28.

* 19.17 Matt. 10. 42. &c 25. 40. 2 Cor. 9. 6. 7.

∥ 19.17 Or, his deed.

* 19.18 ch 13. 24 &c 23. 13.

∥ 19.18 Or, to his destruction or, to cause him to die.

† 19.19 Heb. add.

* 19.21 Job 23. 13 Ps. 33. 10, 11. ch. 16. 1, 9. Is. 46 10.

* 19.24 ch. 15. 19 &c 26. 13, 15.

* 19.25 ch. 21. 11.

† 19.25 Heb. will be cunning.

† 19.28 Heb. A witness of Belial.

* 20.2 ch. 16. 14. &c 19. 12.

* 20.4 ch 10.4

∥ 20.4 Or, winter.

* 20.5 ch 18.4.

∥ 20.6 Or, bounty.

* 20.7 Ps. 112. 2.

* 20.9 1 Kin. 8 46. 2 Chr. 6. 36. Job 14. 4. Ps. 51. 5 Eccles. 7. 20. 1 John 1. 8.

* 20.10 Deut. 25, 13,&c. ch 11. 1. &c 16. 11.

† 20.10 Heb. A stone and a stone.

† 20.10 Heb. an ephah and an ephah.

* 20.12 Ex. 4. 11. Ps. 94. 9.

* 20.13 ch. 12. 11. &c 19. 15.

* 20.16 ch. 27. 13.

* 20.17 ch 9 17.

† 20.17 Heb. Bread of lying. or, falsehood.

* 20.18 ch. 15. 22.

* 20.19 ch. 11. 13.

∥ 20.19 Or, enticeth

* 20.20 Ex. 21 17. Lev. 20 9. Matt. 15 4.

∥ 20.20 Or, candle.

* 20.22 Deut. 32. 35. ch. 17. 13. &c 24 29 Rom. 12. 17. 1 Thess. 5. 15. 1 Pet. 3. 9.

* 20.23 ver. 10.

† 20.23 Heb. balances of deceit.

* 20.24 Ps. 37. 23 ch. 16. 9. Jer. 10. 23.

* 20.26 Ps. 101. 5, &c. ver. 8.

∥ 20.27 Or, lamp.

* 20.28 Ps. 101. 1. ch. 29 14.

* 20.29 ch. 16. 31.

† 20.30 Heb. is a purging medicine against evil.

* 21.2 ch. 16. 2.

* 21.3 1 Sam. 15. 22. ch. 15. 8. Is. 1. 11. Hos. 6. 6. Mic. 6. 7, 8.

* 21.4 ch. 6. 17.

† 21.4 Heb. Haughtiness of eyes.

∥ 21.4 Or, the light of the wicked.

* 21.6 ch. 10. 2. &c 13. 11.

† 21.7 Heb. saw them, or, dwell with them.

* 21.9 ch. 19. 13. &c 25. 24. &c 27. 15.

† 21.9 Heb. a woman of contentions.

† 21.9 Heb. an house of society.

* 21.10 James 4. 5.

† 21.10 Heb. is not favoured.

* 21.11 ch. 19. 25.

* 21.13 Matt. 18. 30.

* 21.14 ch. 17. 8 &c 18. 16.

∥ 21.17 Or, sport.

* 21.18 ch. 11 8.

* 21.19 ver. 9.

† 21.19 Heb. in the land of the desert.

* 21.22 Eccles 9. 14.

* 21.23 ch. 12. 13 &c 18 21.

† 21.24 Heb. in the wrath of pride.

* 21.25 ch. 13. 4

* 21.26 Ps. 112. 9.

* 21.27 Ps. 50 9. ch. 15 8. Is 66. 3. Jer. 6 20. Amos 5. 22.

† 21.27 Heb. in wickedness.

* 21.28 ch. 19. 5, 9.

† 21.28 Heb. A witness of lies.

∥ 21.29 Or, considereth.

* 21.30 Jer. 9. 23.

* 21.31 Ps. 33. 17.

* 21.31 Ps 3 8

∥ 21.31 Or, victory

* 22.1 Eccles. 7. 1.

∥ 22.1 Or, favour is better than, &c.

* 22.2 ch. 29. 13.

* 22.3 ch 27. 12.

* 22.4 Ps. 112 3.

∥ 22.4 Or, The reward of humility, &c.

∥ 22.6 Or, Catechise.

† 22.6 Heb. in his way.

† 22.7 Heb. to the man that lendeth.

* 22.8 Job 4. 8. Hos. 10. 13.

∥ 22.8 Or, and with the rod of his anger he shall be consumed.

* 22.9 2 Cor. 9. 6.

† 22.9 Heb. Good of eye.

* 22.10 Ps. 101. 5.

∥ 22.11 Or, and hath grace in his lips.

∥ 22.12 Or, the matters.

* 22.13 ch. 26. 13.

* 22.14 ch 2 16 &c 5 3. &c 7. 5 &c 23 27.

* 22.15 ch 13. 24. &c 19. 18. &c 23 13. &c 29. 15, 17

† 22.18 Heb. in thy belly

∥ 22.19 Or, trust thou also.

∥ 22.21 Or, to those that send thee.

* 22.22 Zech 7. 10

* 22.23 Job 31. 14 ch. 23. 11.

* 22.26 ch. 6 1. &c 11 15

* 22.28 Deut. 19. 14. &c 27. 17. ch 23. 10.

∥ 22.28 Or, bound.

† 22.29 Heb. obscure men.

* 23.4 1 Tim. 6. 9, 10.

† 23.5 Heb. Wilt thou cause thine eyes to fly upon.

* 23.10 Deut. 19. 14. &c 27. 17. ch. 22. 28.

∥ 23.10 Or, bound.

* 23.11 Job 31. 21. ch. 22 23.

* 23.13 ch. 13. 24. &c 19. 18. &c 23. 15.

∥ 23.15 Or, even I will rejoice.

* 23.17 Ps. 37 1. &c 73. 3. ch. 3. 31. &c 24. 1.

* 23.18 ch. 24. 14.

∥ 23.18 Or, reward.

* 23.20 Rom. 13 13. Eph. 5. 18.

† 23.20 Heb of their flesh.

* 23.22 ch. 1. 8.

* 23.24 ch 10. 1. &c 15 20.

* 23.27 ch. 22. 14.

* 23.28 ch. 7. 12.

∥ 23.28 Or, as a robber.

* 23.29 Is. 5. 11.

∥ 23.32 Or, a cockatrice.

† 23.34 Heb. in the heart of the sea.

† 23.35 Heb. I knew it not.

* 24.1 Ps. 37 1, &c. &c 73. 3. ch. 23. 17. ver. 19.

* 24.2 Ps. 10. 7.

† 24.5 Heb. is in strength.

† 24.5 Heb. strengtheneth might.

* 24.6 ch. 11. 14. &c 15. 22. &c 20. 18.

† 24.10 Heb. narrow.

* 24.11 Ps. 82. 4

* 24.12 Job 34. 11. Ps. 62 12. Jer. 32. 19. Rom. 2. 6. Rev. 22. 12.

† 24.13 Heb uponthy palate.

* 24.14 Ps. 19. 10. &c 119. 103.

* 24.14 ch. 23. 18.

* 24.16 Job 5. 19. Ps. 34. 19. &c 37. 24.

* 24.17 Job 31. 29. Ps. 35 15. ch. 17. 5.

† 24.18 Heb. it be evil in his eyes.

* 24.19 Ps. 37 1. ch. 23. 17.

∥ 24.19 Or, Keep not company with the wicked.

* 24.20 Job 21. 17. ch. 13. 9.

∥ 24.20 Or, lamp.

† 24.21 Heb. changers.

* 24.23 Lev. 19. 15. Deut. 1. 17. &c 16 19. ch 18. 5. &c 28. 21. John 7. 24.

* 24.24 ch. 17. 15. Is. 5. 23.

† 24.25 Heb. a blessing of good.

† 24.26 Heb. that answereth right words.

* 24.29 ch. 20. 22.

† 24.32 Heb. set my heart.

* 24.33 ch. 6. 9, &c.

† 24.34 Heb. a man of shield.

† 25.3 Heb. there is no searching.

* 25.5 ch 20. 8.

† 25.6 Heb. Set not out thy glory

* 25.7 Luke 14. 10.

* 25.9 Matt. 5 25. &c 18. 15.

∥ 25.9 Or, discover not the secret of another.

† 25.11 Heb. spoken upon his wheels.

* 25.13 ch. 13. 17.

† 25.14 Heb. in a gift of falsehood.

* 25.15 Gen. 32. 4, &c. 1 Sam. 25 24, &c. ch. 15. 1. &c 16. 14.

∥ 25.17 Or, Let thy foot be seldom in thy neighbour's house.

† 25.17 Heb. full of thee.

* 25.18 Ps. 120. 4 ch. 12. 18.

* 25.21 Ex. 23. 4. Rom. 12. 20.

∥ 25.23 Or, The north wind bringeth forth rain so doth a backbiting tongue an angry countenance.

* 25.24 ch. 19. 13 &c 21. 9.

* 25.28 ch. 16. 32.

* 26.3 Ps. 32. 9. ch. 10 13.

† 26.5 Heb. his own eyes.

∥ 26.6 Or, violence.

† 26.7 Heb. are lifted up.

∥ 26.8 Or, As he that putteth a precious stone in an heap of stones.

∥ 26.10 Or, A great man grieveth all, and he hireth the fool, he hireth also transgressors.

* 26.11 2 Pet. 2. 22.

† 26.11 Heb. iterateth his folly.

* 26.13 ch. 22. 13.

* 26.15 ch. 19. 24

∥ 26.15 Or, he is weary.

∥ 26.17 Or, is enraged.

† 26.18 Heb. flames, or, sparks.

† 26.20 Heb. Without wood.

* 26.20 ch. 22. 10.

∥ 26.20 Or, whisperor.

† 26.20 Heb. is silent.

* 26.21 ch 15. 18 &c 29 22.

* 26.22 ch. 18. 8.

† 26.22 Heb. chambers.

∥ 26.24 Or, is known.

† 26.25 Heb. maketh his voice gracious.

∥ 26.26 Or, hatred is covered in secret.

* 26.27 Ps. 7. 15, 16 &c 9. 15. Eccles. 10 8.

* 27.1 James 4. 13, &c.

† 27.1 Heb. to morrow day.

† 27.3 Heb. heaviness.

† 27.4 Heb. Wrath is cruelty, and anger an overflowing.

∥ 27.4 Or, jealousy?

* 27.6 Ps. 141. 5.

∥ 27.6 Or, earnest, or, frequent.

† 27.7 Heb. treadeth under foot.

* 27.7 Job 6. 7.

† 27.9 Heb. from the counsel of the soul.

* 27.10 ch. 17. 17. &c 18. 24.

* 27.11 ch. 10. 1 &c 23. 24.

* 27.12 ch. 22. 3.

* 27.13 ch. 20. 16.

* 27.15 ch. 19. 13.

† 27.20 Heb. not.

* 27.20 Eccles. 1. 8.

* 27.21 ch 17. 3.

† 27.23 Heb. set thy heart

† 27.24 Heb strength.

† 27.24 Heb to generation and generation?

‡ 27.26 [1611 thy]

† 27.27 Heb. life.

* 28.1 Lev. 26. 36.

∥ 28.2 Or, by men of understanding and wisdom shall they likewise be prolonged.

† 28.3 Heb. without food.

* 28.6 ch. 19. 1.

* 28.7 ch. 29. 3.

∥ 28.7 Or, feedeth gluttons.

* 28.8 ch. 13. 22. Eccles. 2. 26.

† 28.8 Heb. by increase.

* 28.10 ch. 26. 27.

† 28.11 Heb. in his eyes.

* 28.12 ch. 11. 10. ver. 28. 10. 6.

∥ 28.12 Or, sought for.

* 28.13 Ps. 32. 5. 1 John 1. 9, 10.

* 28.14 Rom. 11. 20.

* 28.17 Gen. 9. 6. Ex. 21. 14.

‡ 28.17 [1611 fly]

* 28.18 ch. 10. 25.

* 28.19 ch. 12. 11.

* 28.20 ch. 13. 11. &c 23. 4. 1 Tim. 6. 9.

∥ 28.20 Or, unpunished.

* 28.21 ch 18. 5. &c 24. 23.

∥ 28.22 ver. 20.

* 28.23 ch 27. 6.

† 28.24 Heb. a man destroying.

* 28.25 ch. 13. 10.

* 28.27 Deut. 15 7, &c. ch. 22. 9.

* 28.28 ver. 12. 29. 2.

† 29.1 Heb. A man of reproofs.

* 29.2 ch 11. 10. &c 28. 28. Eccles. 10. 5.

∥ 29.2 Or, increased.

* 29.3 ch. 10. 1. &c 15. 20. &c 27. 11.

* 29.3 ch. 5. 9. &c 28. 7. Luke 15. 13.

† 29.4 Heb. a man of oblations.

* 29.7 Job 29. 16.

∥ 29.8 Or, set a city on fire.

† 29.10 Heb. Men of blood.

* 29.13 ch. 22 2.

∥ 29.13 Or, the usurer.

* 29.14 ch. 20. 28

* 29.15 ver. 17.

* 29.15 ch 10 1. &c 17. 21, 25.

* 29.16 Ps. 37. 36. &c 58. 10. &c 91 8.

* 29.17 ch. 13. 24. &c 22 15. &c 23. 13, 14.

∥ 29.18 Or, is made naked.

∥ 29.20 Or, in his matters?

* 29.22 ch. 15 18 &c 26. 21.

* 29.23 Job 22 29 ch 15 33. &c 18 12. Matt 23. 12 Luke 14. 11.

† 29.25 Heb. shall be set on high

* 29.26 ch. 19 6.

† 29.26 Heb. the face of a ruler.

† 30.3 Heb. know.

* 30.4 John 3. 13.

* 30.4 Job 38. 4. Ps. 104. 3. Is. 40. 12.

* 30.5 Ps 12 6. &c 18 30. &c 19. 8. &c 119 140.

† 30.5 Heb. purified.

* 30.6 Deut. 4. 2. &c 12 32. Rev. 22. 18, 19.

† 30.7 Heb. withhold not from me

* 30.8 Matt. 6. 11.

† 30.8 Heb. of my allowance.

* 30.9 Deut. 32 15

† 30.9 Heb. belie thee.

† 30.10 Heb. Hurt not with thy tongue.

* 30.13 ch. 6. 17.

* 30.14 Job 29. 17. Ps 52. 2. &c 57. 4.

† 30.15 Heb. Wealth.

∥ 30.17 Or, the brook.

† 30.19 Heb. heart.

* 30.22 ch. 19. 10.

† 30.24 Heb. wise, made wise.

* 30.25 ch. 6. 6.

† 30.27 Heb. gathered together.

∥ 30.31 Or, horse.

† 30.31 Heb. girt in the loins

* 30.32 Job 21. 5 &c 40. 4.

† 31.5 Heb. alter.

† 31.5 Heb. of all the sons of affliction.

* 31.6 Ps. 104. 15.

† 31.6 Heb. bitter of soul.

† 31.8 Heb. the sons of destruction.

* 31.9 Lev. 19. 15. Deut. 1. 16.

* 31.10 ch. 12. 4.

† 31.16 Heb. taketh.

† 31.18 Heb. She tasteth.

† 31.20 Heb. She spreadeth.

∥ 31.21 Or, double garments.

∥ 31.29 Or, have gotten riches.

Romans

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16

THE EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO THE ROMANS

1

1  Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle, [*]separated unto the gospel of God, 2 (Which he had promised afore by his prophets in the holy scriptures,) 3  Concerning his Son Jesus Christ our Lord, which was made of the seed of David according to the flesh; 4  And [†]declared to be the Son of God with power, according to the spirit of holiness, by the resurrection from the dead: 5  By whom we have received grace and apostleship, [∥]for obedience to the faith among all nations, for his name: 6  Among whom are ye also the called of Jesus Christ: 7  To all that be in Rome, beloved of God, called to be saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.

8  First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that your faith is spoken of throughout the whole world. 9  For God is my witness, whom I serve [∥]with my spirit in the gospel of his Son, that without ceasing I make mention of you always in my prayers; 10  Making request, if by any means now at length I might have a prosperous journey by the will of God to come unto you. 11  For I long to see you, that I may impart unto you some spiritual gift, to the end ye may be established; 12  That is, that I may be comforted together [∥]with you by the mutual faith both of you and me. 13  Now I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that oftentimes I purposed to come unto you, (but was let hitherto,) that I might have some fruit [∥]among you also, even as among other Gentiles. 14  I am debtor both to the Greeks, and to the Barbarians; both to the wise, and to the unwise. 15  So, as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the gospel to you that are at Rome also. 16  For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto salvation to every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek. 17  For therein is the righteousness of God revealed from faith to faith: as it is written, [*]The just shall live by faith.

18  For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who hold the truth in unrighteousness; 19  Because that which may be known of God is manifest [∥]in them; for God hath shewed it unto them. 20  For the invisible things of him from the creation of the world are clearly seen, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and Godhead; [∥]so that they are without excuse: 21  Because that, when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful; but became vain in their imaginations, and their foolish heart was darkened. 22  Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools, 23  And changed the glory of the uncorruptible [*]God into an image made like to corruptible man, and to birds, and fourfooted beasts, and creeping things.

24  Wherefore God also gave them up to uncleanness through the lusts of their own hearts, to dishonour their own bodies between themselves: 25  Who changed the truth of God into a lie, and worshipped and served the creature more than the Creator, who is blessed for ever. Amen. 26  For this cause God gave them up unto vile affections: for even their women did change the natural use into that which is against nature: 27  And likewise also the men, leaving the natural use of the woman, burned in their lust one toward another; men with men working that which is unseemly, and receiving in themselves that recompence of their error which was meet. 28  And even as they did not like [∥]to retain God in their knowledge, God gave them over to [∥]a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not convenient; 29  Being filled with all unrighteousness, fornication, wickedness, covetousness, maliciousness; full of envy, murder, debate, deceit, malignity; whisperers, 30  Backbiters, haters of God, despiteful, proud, boasters, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents, 31  Without understanding, covenantbreakers, [∥]without natural affection, implacable, unmerciful: 32  Who knowing the judgment of God, that they which commit such things are worthy of death, not only do the same, but [∥]have pleasure in them that do them.

2

1  Therefore thou art inexcusable, O man, whosoever thou art that judgest: for wherein thou judgest another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest doest the same things. 2  But we are sure that the judgment of God is according to truth against them which commit such things. 3  And thinkest thou this, O man, that judgest them which do such things, and doest the same, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God? 4  Or despisest thou the riches of his goodness and forbearance and longsuffering; not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance? 5  But after thy hardness and impenitent heart [*]treasurest up unto thyself wrath against the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God; 6 [*] Who will render to every man according to his deeds: 7  To them who by patient continuance in well doing seek for glory and honour and immortality, eternal life: 8  But unto them that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey unrighteousness, indignation and wrath, 9  Tribulation and anguish, upon every soul of man that doeth evil, of the Jew first, and also of the [†]Gentile; 10  But glory, honour, and peace, to every man that worketh good, to the Jew first, and also to the [†]Gentile: 11  For there is no respect of persons with God. 12  For as many as have sinned without law shall also perish without law: and as many as have sinned in the law shall be judged by the law; 13 (For not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified. 14  For when the Gentiles, which have not the law, do by nature the things contained in the law, these, having not the law, are a law unto themselves: 15  Which shew the work of the law written in their hearts, [∥]their conscience also bearing witness, and their thoughts [∥]the mean while accusing or else excusing one another;) 16  In the day when God shall judge the secrets of men by Jesus Christ according to my gospel.

17  Behold, thou art called a Jew, and restest in the law, and makest thy boast of God, 18  And knowest his will, and [∥]approvest the things that are more excellent, being instructed out of the law; 19  And art confident that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light of them which are in darkness, 20  An instructor of the foolish, a teacher of babes, which hast the form of knowledge and of the truth in the law. 21  Thou therefore which teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal? 22  Thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou commit sacrilege? 23  Thou that makest thy boast of the law, through breaking the law dishonourest thou God? 24  For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles through you, as it is [*]written. 25  For circumcision verily profiteth, if thou keep the law: but if thou be a breaker of the law, thy circumcision is made uncircumcision. 26  Therefore if the uncircumcision keep the righteousness of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be counted for circumcision? 27  And shall not uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfil the law, judge thee, who by the letter and circumcision dost transgress the law? 28  For he is not a Jew, which is one outwardly; neither is that circumcision, which is outward in the flesh: 29  But he is a Jew, which is one inwardly; and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit, and not in the letter; whose praise is not of men, but of God.

3

1  What advantage then hath the Jew? or what profit is there of circumcision? 2  Much every way: chiefly, because that unto them were committed the oracles of God. 3  For what if some did not believe? shall their unbelief make the faith of God without effect? 4  God forbid: yea, let God be true, but every man a liar; as it is written, [*]That thou mightest be justified in thy sayings, and mightest overcome when thou art judged. 5  But if our unrighteousness commend the righteousness of God, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who taketh vengeance? (I speak as a man) 6  God forbid: for then how shall God judge the world? 7  For if the truth of God hath more abounded through my lie unto his glory; why yet am I also judged as a sinner? 8  And not rather, (as we be slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say,) Let us do evil, that good may come? whose damnation is just.

9  What then? are we better than they? No, in no wise: for we have before [†]proved both Jews and Gentiles, that they are all under sin; 10  As it is written, There is none righteous, no, not one: 11  There is none that understandeth, there is none that seeketh after God. 12  They are all gone out of the way, they are together become unprofitable; there is none that doeth good, no, not one. 13  Their throat is an open sepulchre; with their tongues they have used deceit; the poison of asps is under their lips: 14  Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness: 15  Their feet are swift to shed blood: 16  Destruction and misery are in their ways: 17  And the way of peace have they not known: 18  There is no fear of God before their eyes.

19  Now we know that what things soever the law saith, it saith to them who are under the law: that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may become [∥]guilty before God. 20  Therefore by the deeds of the law there shall no flesh be justified in his sight: for by the law is the knowledge of sin.

21  But now the righteousness of God without the law is manifested, being witnessed by the law and the prophets; 22  Even the righteousness of God which is by faith of Jesus Christ unto all and upon all them that believe: for there is no difference: 23  For all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God; 24  Being justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in [‡]Christ Jesus: 25  Whom God hath [∥]set forth to be a propitiation through faith in his blood, to declare his righteousness for the [∥]remission of sins that are past, through the forbearance of God; 26  To declare, I say, at this time his righteousness: that he might be just, and the justifier of him which believeth in Jesus. 27  Where is boasting then? It is excluded. By what law? of works? Nay: but by the law of faith. 28  Therefore we conclude that a man is justified by faith without the deeds of the law. 29  Is he the God of the Jews only? is he not also of the Gentiles? Yes, of the Gentiles also: 30  Seeing it is one God, which shall justify the circumcision by faith, and uncircumcision through faith. 31  Do we then make void the law through faith? God forbid: yea, we establish the law.

4

1  What shall we say then that Abraham our father, as pertaining to the flesh, hath found? 2  For if Abraham were justified by works, he hath whereof to glory; but not before God. 3  For what saith the scripture? Abraham believed God, and it was counted unto him for righteousness. 4  Now to him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt. 5  But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteousness. 6  Even as David also describeth the blessedness of the man, unto whom God imputeth righteousness without works, 7  Saying, Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered. 8  Blessed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute sin. 9  Cometh this blessedness then upon the circumcision only, or upon the uncircumcision also? for we say that faith was reckoned to Abraham for righteousness. 10  How was it then reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision. 11  And he received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had yet being uncircumcised: that he might be the father of all them that believe, though they be not circumcised; that righteousness might be imputed unto them also: 12  And the father of circumcision to them who are not of the circumcision only, but [‡]who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham, which he had being yet uncircumcised. 13  For the promise, that he should be the heir of the world, was not to Abraham, or to his seed, through the law, but through the righteousness of faith. 14  For if they which are of the law be heirs, faith is made void, and the promise made of none effect: 15  Because the law worketh wrath: for where no law is, there is no transgression. 16  Therefore it is of faith, that it might be by grace; to the end the promise might be sure to all the seed; not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham; who is the father of us all, 17 (As it is written, [*]I have made thee a father of many nations,) [∥]before him whom he believed, even God, who quickeneth the dead, and calleth those things which be not as though they were. 18  Who against hope believed in hope, that he might become the father of many nations; according to that which was spoken, [*]So shall thy seed be. 19  And being not weak in faith, he considered not his own body now dead, when he was about an hundred years old, neither yet the deadness of Sara’s womb: 20  He staggered not at the promise of God through unbelief; but was strong in faith, giving glory to God; 21  And being fully persuaded that, what he had promised, he was able also to perform. 22  And therefore it was imputed to him for righteousness. 23  Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was imputed to him; 24  But for us also, to whom it shall be imputed, if we believe on him that raised up Jesus our Lord from the dead; 25  Who was delivered for our offences, and was raised again for our justification.

5

1  Therefore being justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ: 2  By whom also we have access by faith into this grace wherein we stand, and rejoice in hope of the glory of God. 3  And not only so, but we glory in tribulations also: knowing that tribulation worketh patience; 4  And patience, experience; and experience, hope: 5  And hope maketh not ashamed; because the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost which is given unto us. 6  For when we were yet without strength, [∥]in due time Christ died for the ungodly. 7  For scarcely for a righteous man will one die: yet peradventure for a good man some would even dare to die. 8  But God commendeth his love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us. 9  Much more then, being now justified by his blood, we shall be saved from wrath through him. 10  For if, when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, we shall be saved by his life. 11  And not only so, but we also joy in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom we have now received the atonement.

12  Wherefore, as by one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin; and so death passed upon all men, [∥]for that all have sinned: 13 (For until the law sin was in the world: but sin is not imputed when there is no law. 14  Nevertheless death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over them that had not sinned after the similitude of Adam’s transgression, who is the figure of him that was to come. 15  But not as the offence, so also is the free gift. For if through the offence of one many be dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, which is by one man, Jesus Christ, hath abounded unto many. 16  And not as it was by one that sinned, so is the gift: for the judgment was by one to condemnation, but the free gift is of many offences unto justification. 17  For if [∥]by one man’s offence death reigned by one; much more they which receive abundance of grace and of the gift of righteousness shall reign in life by one, Jesus Christ.) 18  Therefore as [∥]by the offence of one judgment came upon all men to condemnation; even so [∥]by the righteousness of one the free gift came upon all men unto justification of life. 19  For as by one man’s disobedience many were made sinners, so by the obedience of one shall many be made righteous. 20  Moreover the law entered, that the offence might abound. But where sin abounded, grace did much more abound: 21  That as sin hath reigned unto death, even so might grace reign through righteousness unto eternal life by Jesus Christ our Lord.

6

1  What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound? 2  God forbid. How shall we, that are dead to sin, live any longer therein? 3  Know ye not, that so many of us as [∥]were baptized into Jesus Christ were baptized into his death? 4  Therefore we are buried with him by baptism into death: that like as Christ was raised up from the dead by the glory of the Father, even so we also should walk in newness of life. 5  For if we have been planted together in the likeness of his death, we shall be also in the likeness of his resurrection: 6  Knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him, that the body of sin might be destroyed, that henceforth we should not serve sin. 7  For he that is dead is [†]freed from sin. 8  Now if we be dead with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him: 9  Knowing that Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; death hath no more dominion over him. 10  For in that he died, he died unto sin once: but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God. 11  Likewise reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed unto sin, but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord. 12  Let not sin [‡]therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey it in the lusts thereof. 13  Neither yield ye your members as [†]instruments of unrighteousness unto sin: but yield yourselves unto God, as those that are alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God. 14  For sin shall not have dominion over you: for ye are not under the law, but under grace. 15  What then? shall we sin, because we are not under the law, but under grace? God forbid. 16  Know ye not, that to whom ye yield yourselves servants to obey, his servants ye are to whom ye obey; whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness? 17  But God be thanked, that ye were the servants of sin, but ye have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine [†]which was delivered you. 18  Being then made free from sin, ye became the servants of righteousness. 19  I speak after the manner of men because of the infirmity of your flesh: for as ye have yielded your members servants to uncleanness and to iniquity unto iniquity; even so now yield your members servants to righteousness unto holiness. 20  For when ye were the servants of sin, ye were free [†]from righteousness. 21  What fruit had ye then in those things whereof ye are now ashamed? for the end of those things is death. 22  But now being made free from sin, and become servants to God, ye have your fruit unto holiness, and the end everlasting life. 23  For the wages of sin is death; but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.

7

1  Know ye not, brethren, (for I speak to them that know the law,) how that the law hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth? 2  For the woman which hath an husband is bound by the law to her husband so long as he liveth; but if the husband be dead, she is loosed from the law of [‡]her husband. 3  So then if, while her husband liveth, she be married to another man, she shall be called an adulteress: but if her husband be dead, she is free from that law; so that she is no adulteress, though she be married to another man. 4  Wherefore, my brethren, ye also are become dead to the law by the body of Christ; that ye should be married to another, even to him who is raised from the dead, that we should bring forth fruit unto God. 5  For when we were in the flesh, the [†]motions of sins, which were by the law, did work in our members to bring forth fruit unto death. 6  But now we are delivered from the law, [∥]that being dead wherein we were held; that we should serve in newness of spirit, and not in the oldness of the letter.

7  What shall we say then? Is the law sin? God forbid. Nay, I had not known sin, but by the law: for I had not known [∥]lust, except the law had said, Thou shalt not covet. 8  But sin, taking occasion by the commandment, wrought in me all manner of concupiscence. For without the law sin was dead. 9  For I was alive without the law once: but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I died. 10  And the commandment, which was ordained to life, I found to be unto death. 11  For sin, taking occasion by the commandment, deceived me, and by it slew me. 12  Wherefore the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and just, and good. 13  Was [‡]then that which is good made death unto me? God forbid. But sin, that it might appear sin, working death in me by that which is good; that sin by the commandment might become exceeding sinful. 14  For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am carnal, sold under sin. 15  For that which I do I [†]allow not: for what I would, that do I not; but what I hate, that do I. 16  If then I do that which I would not, I consent unto the law that it is good. 17  Now then it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me. 18  For I know that in me (that is, in my flesh,) dwelleth no good thing: for to will is present with me; but how to perform that which is good I find not. 19  For the good that I would I do not: but the evil which I would not, that I do. 20  Now if I do that I would not, it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me. 21  I find then a law, that, when I would do good, evil is present with me. 22  For I delight in the law of God after the inward man: 23  But I see another law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of sin which is in my members. 24  O wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me from [∥]the body of this death? 25  I thank God through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then with the mind I myself serve the law of God; but with the flesh the law of sin.

8

1  There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit. 2  For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus hath made me free from the law of sin and death. 3  For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh, and [∥]for sin, condemned sin in the flesh: 4  That the righteousness of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit. 5  For they that are after the flesh do mind the things of the flesh; but they that are after the Spirit the things of the Spirit. 6  For [†]to be carnally minded is death; but [†]to be spiritually minded is life and peace. 7  Because [†]the carnal mind is enmity against God: for it is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can be. 8  So then they that are in the flesh cannot please God. 9  But ye are not in the flesh, but in the Spirit, if so be that the Spirit of God dwell in you. Now if any man have not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his. 10  And if Christ be in you, the body is dead because of sin; but the Spirit is life because of righteousness. 11  But if the Spirit of him that raised up Jesus from the dead dwell in you, he that raised up Christ from the dead shall also quicken your mortal bodies [∥]by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.

12  Therefore, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh. 13  For if ye live after the flesh, ye shall die: but if ye through the Spirit do mortify the deeds of the body, ye shall live. 14  For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the sons of God. 15  For ye have not received the spirit of bondage again to fear; but ye have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father. 16  The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are the children of God: 17  And if children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ; if so be that we suffer with him, that we may be also glorified together.

18  For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed in us. 19  For the earnest expectation of the creature waiteth for the manifestation of the sons of God. 20  For the creature was made subject to vanity, not willingly, but by reason of him who hath subjected the same in hope, 21  Because the creature itself also shall be delivered from the bondage of corruption into the glorious liberty of the children of God. 22  For we know that [∥]the whole creation groaneth and travaileth in pain together until now. 23  And not only they, but ourselves also, which have the firstfruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for the adoption, to wit, the [*]redemption of our body. 24  For we are saved by hope: but hope that is seen is not hope: for what a man seeth, why doth he yet hope for? 25  But if we hope for that we see not, then do we with patience wait for it. 26  Likewise the Spirit also helpeth our infirmities: for we know not what we should pray for as we ought: but the Spirit itself maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered. 27  And he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, [∥]because he maketh intercession for the saints according to the will of God. 28  And we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpose. 29  For whom he did foreknow, he also did predestinate to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brethren. 30  Moreover whom he did predestinate, them he also called: and whom he called, them he also justified: and whom he justified, them he also glorified. 31  What shall we then say to these things? If God be for us, who can be against us? 32  He that spared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not with him also freely give us all things? 33  Who shall lay any thing to the charge of God’s elect? It is God that justifieth. 34  Who is he that condemneth? It is Christ that died, yea rather, that is risen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us. 35  Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword? 36  As it is written, [*]For thy sake we are killed all the day long; we are accounted as sheep for the slaughter. 37  Nay, in all these things we are more than conquerors through him that loved us. 38  For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come, 39  Nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

9

1  I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost, 2  That I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart. 3  For I could wish that myself were [∥]accursed from Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh: 4  Who are Israelites; to whom pertaineth the adoption, and the glory, and the [∥]covenants, and the giving of the law, and the service of God, and the promises; 5  Whose are the fathers, and of whom as concerning the flesh Christ came, who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen.

6  Not as though the word of God hath taken none effect. For they are not all Israel, which are of Israel: 7  Neither, because they are the seed of Abraham, are they all children: but, [*]In Isaac shall thy seed be called. 8  That is, They which are the children of the flesh, these are not the children of God: but the children of the promise are counted for the seed. 9  For this is the word of promise, [*]At this time will I come, and Sara shall have a son. 10  And not only this; but when Rebecca also had conceived by one, even by our father Isaac; 11 (For the children being not yet born, neither having done any good or evil, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth;) 12  It was said unto her, [*]The [∥]elder shall serve the [∥]younger. 13  As it is written, [*]Jacob have I loved, but Esau have I hated.

14  What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? God forbid. 15  For he saith to Moses, [*]I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I will have compassion. 16  So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that sheweth mercy. 17  For the scripture saith unto Pharaoh, [*]Even for this same purpose have I raised thee up, that I might shew my power in thee, and that my name might be declared throughout all the earth. 18  Therefore hath he mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth. 19  Thou wilt say then unto me, Why doth he yet find fault? For who hath resisted his will? 20  Nay but, O man, who art thou that [∥]repliest against God? [*]Shall the thing formed say to him that formed it, Why hast thou made me thus? 21  Hath not the [*]potter power over the clay, of the same lump to make one vessel unto honour, and another unto dishonour? 22  What if God, willing to shew his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much longsuffering the vessels of wrath [∥]fitted to destruction: 23  And that he might make known the riches of his glory on the vessels of mercy, which he had afore prepared unto glory, 24  Even us, whom he hath called, not of the Jews only, but also of the Gentiles? 25  As he saith also in Osee, [*]I will call them my people, which were not my people; and her beloved, which was not beloved. 26 [*] And it shall come to pass, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people; there shall they be called the children of the living God. 27  Esaias also crieth concerning Israel, [*]Though the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, a remnant shall be saved: 28  For he will finish [∥]the work, and cut it short in righteousness: because a short work will the Lord make upon the earth. 29  And as Esaias said before, [*]Except the Lord of Sabaoth had left us a seed, we had been as Sodoma, and been made like unto Gomorrha. 30  What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, which followed not after righteousness, have attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith. 31  But Israel, which followed after the law of righteousness, hath not attained to the law of righteousness. 32  Wherefore? Because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the law. For they stumbled at that stumblingstone; 33  As it is written, [*]Behold, I lay in Sion a stumblingstone and rock of offence: and whosoever believeth on him shall not be [∥]ashamed.

10

1  Brethren, my heart’s desire and prayer to God for Israel is, that they might be saved. 2  For I bear them record that they have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledge. 3  For they being ignorant of God’s righteousness, and going about to establish their own righteousness, have not submitted themselves unto the righteousness of God. 4  For Christ is the end of the law for righteousness to every one that believeth. 5  For Moses describeth the righteousness which is of the law, [*]That the man which doeth those things shall live by them. 6  But the righteousness which is of faith speaketh on this wise, [*]Say not in thine heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring Christ down from above:) 7  Or, Who shall descend into the deep? (that is, to bring up Christ again from the dead.) 8  But what saith it? [*]The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach; 9  That if thou shalt confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thine heart that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved. 10  For with the heart man believeth unto righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation. 11  For the scripture saith, [*]Whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed. 12  For there is no difference between the Jew and the Greek: for the same Lord over all is rich unto all that call upon him. 13 [*] For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. 14  How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a preacher? 15  And how shall they preach, except they be sent? as it is written, [*]How beautiful are the feet of them that preach the gospel of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things! 16  But they have not all obeyed the gospel. For Esaias saith, [*]Lord, who hath believed [†]our [∥]report? 17  So then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God. 18  But I say, Have they not heard? Yes verily, [*]their sound went into all the earth, and their words unto the ends of the world. 19  But I say, Did not Israel know? First Moses saith, [*]I will provoke you to jealousy by them that are no people, and by a foolish nation I will anger you. 20  But Esaias is very bold, and saith, [*]I was found of them that sought me not; I was made manifest unto them that asked not after me. 21  But to Israel he saith, [*]All day long I have stretched forth my hands unto a disobedient and gainsaying people.

11

1  I say then, Hath God cast away his people? God forbid. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin. 2  God hath not cast away his people which he foreknew. Wot ye not what the scripture saith of Elias? how he maketh intercession to God against Israel, saying, 3 [*] Lord, they have killed thy prophets, and digged down thine altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life. 4  But what saith the answer of God unto him? [*]I have reserved to myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to the image of Baal. 5  Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace. 6  And if by grace, then is it no more of works: otherwise grace is no more grace. But if it be of works, then is it no more grace: otherwise work is no more work.

7  What then? Israel hath not obtained that which he seeketh for; but the election hath obtained it, and the rest were [∥]blinded 8 (According as it is written, [*]God hath given them the spirit of [∥]slumber, [*]eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear;) unto this day. 9  And David saith, [*]Let their table be made a snare, and a trap, and a stumblingblock, and a recompence unto them: 10 [*] Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see, and bow down their back alway. 11  I say then, Have they stumbled that they should fall? God forbid: but rather through their fall salvation is come unto the Gentiles, for to provoke them to jealousy. 12  Now if the fall of them be the riches of the world, and the [∥]diminishing of them the riches of the Gentiles; how much more their fulness?

13  For I speak to you Gentiles, inasmuch as I am the apostle of the Gentiles, I magnify mine office: 14  If by any means I may provoke to emulation them which are my flesh, and might save some of them. 15  For if the casting away of them be the reconciling of the world, what shall the receiving of them be, but life from the dead? 16  For if the firstfruit be holy, the lump is also holy: and if the root be holy, so are the branches. 17  And if some of the branches be broken off, and thou, being a wild olive tree, wert graffed in [∥]among them, and with them partakest of the root and fatness of the olive tree; 18  Boast not against the branches. But if thou boast, thou bearest not the root, but the root thee. 19  Thou wilt say then, The branches were broken off, that I might be graffed in. 20  Well; because of unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by faith. Be not highminded, but fear: 21  For if God spared not the natural branches, take heed lest he also spare not thee. 22  Behold therefore the goodness and severity of God: on them which fell, severity; but toward thee, goodness, if thou continue in his goodness: otherwise thou also shalt be cut off. 23  And they also, if they abide not still in unbelief, shall be graffed in: for God is able to graff them in again. 24  For if thou wert cut out of the olive tree which is wild by nature, and wert graffed contrary to nature into a good olive tree: how much more shall these, which be the natural branches, be graffed into their own olive tree?

25  For I would not, brethren, that ye should be ignorant of this mystery, lest ye should be wise in your own conceits; that [∥]blindness in part is happened to Israel, until the fulness of the Gentiles be come in. 26  And so all Israel shall be saved: as it is written, [*]There shall come out of Sion the Deliverer, and shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob: 27  For this is my covenant unto them, when I shall take away their sins. 28  As concerning the gospel, they are enemies for your sakes: but as touching the election, they are beloved for the fathers’ sakes. 29  For the gifts and calling of God are without repentance. 30  For as ye in times past have not [∥]believed God, yet have now obtained mercy through their unbelief: 31  Even so have these also now not [∥]believed, that through your mercy they also may obtain mercy. 32  For God hath [∥]concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all.

33  O the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and knowledge of God! how unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past finding out! 34 [*] For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his counsellor? 35  Or who hath first given to him, and it shall be recompensed unto him again? 36  For of him, and through him, and to him, are all things: to whom be glory for ever. Amen.

12

1  I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, that ye present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reasonable service. 2  And be not conformed to this world: but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is that good, [‡]and acceptable, and perfect, will of God.

3  For I say, through the grace given unto me, to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think; but to think [†]soberly, according as God hath dealt to every man the measure of faith. 4  For as we have many members in one body, and all members have not the same office: 5  So we, being many, are one body in Christ, and every one members one of another. 6  Having then gifts differing according to the grace that is given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of faith; 7  Or ministry, let us wait on our ministering: or he that teacheth, on teaching; 8  Or he that exhorteth, on exhortation: he that [∥]giveth, let him do it [∥]with simplicity; he that ruleth, with diligence; he that sheweth mercy, with cheerfulness.

9  Let love be without dissimulation. Abhor that which is evil; cleave to that which is good. 10  Be kindly affectioned one to another [∥]with brotherly love; in honour preferring one another; 11  Not slothful in business; fervent in spirit; serving the Lord; 12  Rejoicing in hope; patient in tribulation; continuing instant in prayer; 13  Distributing to the necessity of saints; given to hospitality. 14  Bless them which persecute you: bless, and curse not. 15  Rejoice with them that do rejoice, and weep with them that weep. 16  Be of the same mind one toward another. Mind not high things, but [∥]condescend to men of low estate. Be not wise in your own conceits. 17  Recompense to no man evil for evil. Provide things honest in the sight of all men. 18  If it be possible, as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men. 19  Dearly beloved, avenge not yourselves, but rather give place unto wrath: for it is written, [*]Vengeance is mine; I will repay, saith the Lord. 20 [*] Therefore if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst, give him drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire on his head. 21  Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.

13

1  Let every soul be subject unto the higher powers. For there is no power but of God: the powers that be are [∥]ordained of God. 2  Whosoever therefore resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God: and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation. 3  For rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil. Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise of the same: 4  For he is the minister of God to thee for good. But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid; for he beareth not the sword in vain: for he is the minister of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doeth evil. 5  Wherefore ye must needs be subject, not only for wrath, but also for conscience sake. 6  For for this cause pay ye tribute also: for they are God’s ministers, attending continually upon this very thing. 7  Render therefore to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute is due; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honour to whom honour. 8  Owe no man any thing, but to love one another: for he that loveth another hath fulfilled the law. 9  For this, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, Thou shalt not covet; and if there be any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this saying, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. 10  Love worketh no ill to his neighbour: therefore love is the fulfilling of the law. 11  And that, knowing the time, that now it is high time to awake out of sleep: for now is our salvation nearer than when we believed. 12  The night is far spent, the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armour of light. 13  Let us walk [∥]honestly, as in the day; not in rioting and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and envying. 14  But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, to fulfil the lusts thereof.

14

1  Him that is weak in the faith receive ye, but [∥]not to doubtful disputations. 2  For one believeth that he may eat all things: another, who is weak, eateth herbs. 3  Let not him that eateth despise him that eateth not; and let not him which eateth not judge him that eateth: for God hath received him. 4  Who art thou that judgest another man’s servant? to his own master he standeth or falleth. Yea, he shall be holden up: for God is able to make him stand. 5  One man esteemeth one day above another: another esteemeth every day alike. Let every man be [∥]fully persuaded in his own mind. 6  He that [∥]regardeth [‡]the day, regardeth it unto the Lord; and he that regardeth not the day, to the Lord he doth not regard it. He that eateth, eateth to the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks. 7  For none of us liveth to himself, and no man dieth to himself. 8  For whether we live, we live unto the Lord; and whether we die, we die unto the Lord: whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord’s. 9  For to this end Christ both died, and rose, and revived, that he might be Lord both of the dead and living. 10  But why dost thou judge thy brother? or why dost thou set at nought thy brother? [‡]for [*]we shall all stand before the judgment seat of Christ. 11  For it is written, [*]As I live, saith the Lord, every knee shall bow to me, and every tongue shall confess to God. 12  So then every one of us shall give account of himself to God. 13  Let us not therefore judge one another any more: but judge this rather, that no man put a stumblingblock or an occasion to fall in his brother’s way. 14  I know, and am persuaded by the Lord Jesus, that there is nothing [†]unclean of itself: but to him that esteemeth any thing to be [†]unclean, to him it is unclean. 15  But if thy brother be grieved with thy meat, now walkest thou not [†]charitably. [*]Destroy not him with thy meat, for whom Christ died. 16  Let not then your good be evil spoken of: 17  For the kingdom of God is not meat and drink; but righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost. 18  For he that in these things serveth Christ is acceptable to God, and approved of men. 19  Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one may edify another. 20  For meat destroy not the work of God. [*]All things indeed are pure; but it is evil for that man who eateth with offence. 21  It is good neither to eat [*]flesh, nor to drink wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother stumbleth, or is offended, or is made weak. 22  Hast thou faith? have it to thyself before God. Happy is he that condemneth not himself in that thing which he alloweth. 23  And he that [∥]doubteth is damned if he eat, because he eateth not of faith: for whatsoever is not of faith is sin.

15

1  We then that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves. 2  Let every one of us please his neighbour for his good to edification. 3  For even Christ pleased not himself; but, as it is written, [*]The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell on me. 4  For whatsoever things were written aforetime were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the scriptures might have hope. 5 [*] Now the God of patience and consolation grant you to be likeminded one toward another [∥]according to Christ Jesus: 6  That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorify God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.

7  Wherefore receive ye one another, as Christ also received us to the glory of God. 8  Now I say that Jesus Christ was a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, to confirm the promises made unto the fathers: 9  And that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy; as it is written, [*]For this cause I will confess to thee among the Gentiles, and sing unto thy name. 10  And again he saith, [*]Rejoice, ye Gentiles, with his people. 11  And again, [*]Praise the Lord, all ye Gentiles; and laud him, all ye people. 12  And again, Esaias saith, [*]There shall be a root of Jesse, and he that shall rise to reign over the Gentiles; in him shall the Gentiles trust. 13  Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope, through the power of the Holy Ghost. 14  And I myself also am persuaded of you, my brethren, that ye also are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another. 15  Nevertheless, brethren, I have written the more boldly unto you in some sort, as putting you in mind, because of the grace that is given to me of God, 16  That I should be the minister of Jesus Christ to the Gentiles, ministering the gospel of God, that the [∥]offering up of the Gentiles might be acceptable, being sanctified by the Holy Ghost. 17  I have therefore whereof I may glory through Jesus Christ in those things which pertain to God. 18  For I will not dare to speak of any of those things which Christ hath not wrought by me, to make the Gentiles obedient, by word and deed, 19  Through mighty signs and wonders, by the power of the Spirit of God; so that from Jerusalem, and round about unto Illyricum, I have fully preached the gospel of Christ. 20  Yea, so have I strived to preach the gospel, not where Christ was named, lest I should build upon another man’s foundation: 21  But as it is written, [*]To whom he was not spoken of, they shall see: and they that have not heard shall understand. 22  For which cause also I have been [∥]much hindered from coming to you. 23  But now having no more place in these parts, and having a great desire these many years to come unto you; 24  Whensoever I take my journey into Spain, I will come to you: for I trust to see you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you, if first I be somewhat filled [†]with your company. 25  But now I go unto Jerusalem to minister unto the saints. 26  For it hath pleased them of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor saints which are at Jerusalem. 27  It hath pleased them verily; and their debtors they are. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, their duty is also to minister unto them in carnal things. 28  When therefore I have performed this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will come by you into Spain. 29  And I am sure that, when I come unto you, I shall come in the fulness of the blessing of the gospel of Christ.

30  Now I beseech you, brethren, for the Lord Jesus Christ’s sake, and for the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in your prayers to God for me; 31  That I may be delivered from them that [∥]do not believe in Judaea; and that my service which I have for Jerusalem may be accepted of the saints; 32  That I may come unto you with joy by the will of God, and may with you be refreshed. 33  Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.

16

1  I commend unto you Phebe our sister, which is a servant of the church which is at Cenchrea: 2  That ye receive her in the Lord, as becometh saints, and that ye assist her in whatsoever business she hath need of you: for she hath been a succourer of many, and of myself also. 3  Greet Priscilla and Aquila my helpers in Christ Jesus: 4  Who have for my life laid down their own necks: unto whom not only I give thanks, but also all the churches of the Gentiles. 5  Likewise greet the church that is in their house. Salute my wellbeloved Epaenetus, who is the firstfruits of Achaia unto Christ. 6  Greet Mary, who bestowed much labour on us. 7  Salute Andronicus and Junia, my kinsmen, and my fellowprisoners, who are of note among the apostles, who also were in Christ before me. 8  Greet Amplias my beloved in the Lord. 9  Salute Urbane, our helper in Christ, and Stachys my beloved. 10  Salute Apelles approved in Christ. Salute them which are of Aristobulus’ [∥]household. 11  Salute Herodion my kinsman. Greet them that be of the [∥]household of Narcissus, which are in the Lord. 12  Salute Tryphena and Tryphosa, who labour in the Lord. Salute the beloved Persis, which laboured much in the Lord. 13  Salute Rufus chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine. 14  Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermas, Patrobas, Hermes, and the brethren which are with them. 15  Salute Philologus, and Julia, Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints which are with them. 16  Salute one another with an holy kiss. The churches of Christ salute you.

17  Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them which cause divisions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned; and avoid them. 18  For they that are such serve not our Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly; and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the simple. 19  For your obedience is come abroad unto all men. I am glad therefore on your behalf: but yet I would have you wise unto that which is good, and [∥]simple concerning evil. 20  And the God of peace shall [∥]bruise Satan under your feet shortly. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen.

21  Timotheus my workfellow, and Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater, my kinsmen, salute you. 22  I Tertius, who wrote this epistle, salute you in the Lord. 23  Gaius mine host, and of the whole church, saluteth you. Erastus the chamberlain of the city saluteth you, and Quartus a brother. 24  The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

25  Now to him that is of power to stablish you according to my gospel, and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery, which was kept secret since the world began, 26  But now is made manifest, and by the scriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the everlasting God, made known to all nations for the obedience of faith: 27  To God only wise, be glory through Jesus Christ for ever. Amen.

Written to the Romans from Corinthus, and sent by Phebe servant of the church at Cenchrea.

* 1.1 Acts 13. 2.

† 1.4 Gr. determined.

∥ 1.5 Or, to the obedience of faith.

∥ 1.9 Or, in my spirit.

∥ 1.12 Or, in you.

∥ 1.13 Or, in you.

* 1.17 Hab. 2. 4.

∥ 1.19 Or, to them.

∥ 1.20 Or, that they may be.

* 1.23 Ps. 106. 20.

∥ 1.28 Or, to acknowledge.

∥ 1.28 Or, a mind void of judgment.

∥ 1.31 Or, unsociable.

∥ 1.32 Or, consent with them.

* 2.5 Jam. 5. 3.

* 2.6 Ps. 62. 12. Matt. 16. 27. Rev. 22. 12.

† 2.9 Gr. Greek.

† 2.10 Gr. Greek.

∥ 2.15 Or, the conscience witnessing with them.

∥ 2.15 Or, between themselves.

∥ 2.18 Or, triest the things that differ.

* 2.24 Is. 52. 5. Ezek. 36. 20, 23.

* 3.4 Ps. 51. 4.

† 3.9 Gr. charged.

∥ 3.19 Or, subject to the judgment of God.

‡ 3.24 [1611 Jesus Christ]

∥ 3.25 Or, foreordained.

∥ 3.25 Or, passing over.

‡ 4.12 [1611 omits who]

* 4.17 Gen. 17. 5.

∥ 4.17 Or, like unto him.

* 4.18 Gen. 15. 5.

∥ 5.6 Or, according to the time.

∥ 5.12 Or, in whom.

∥ 5.17 Or, by one offence.

∥ 5.18 Or, by one offence.

∥ 5.18 Or, by one righteousness.

∥ 6.3 Or, are.

† 6.7 Gr. justified.

‡ 6.12 [1611 reign therefore]

† 6.13 Gr. arms, or, weapons.

† 6.17 Gr. whereto ye were delivered.

† 6.20 Gr. to righteousness.

‡ 7.2 [1611 the husband]

† 7.5 Gr. passions.

∥ 7.6 Or, being dead to that.

∥ 7.7 Or, concupiscence.

‡ 7.13 [1611 that then]

† 7.15 Gr. know.

∥ 7.24 Or, this body of death.

∥ 8.3 Or, by a sacrifice for sin.

† 8.6 Gr. the minding of the flesh.

† 8.6 Gr. the minding of the Spirit.

† 8.7 Gr. the minding of the flesh.

∥ 8.11 Or, because of his Spirit.

∥ 8.22 Or, every creature.

* 8.23 Luke 21. 28.

∥ 8.27 Or, that.

* 8.36 Ps. 41. 22.

∥ 9.3 Or, separated.

∥ 9.4 Or, testaments.

* 9.7 Gen. 21. 12.

* 9.9 Gen. 18. 10.

* 9.12 Gen. 25. 23.

∥ 9.12 Or, greater.

∥ 9.12 Or, lesser.

* 9.13 Mal. 1. 2, 3.

* 9.15 Ex. 33. 19.

* 9.17 Ex. 9. 16.

∥ 9.20 Or, answerest again, or, disputest with God?

* 9.20 Is. 45. 9.

* 9.21 Jer 18. 6 Wis. 15. 7.

∥ 9.22 Or, made up

* 9.25 Hos. 2. 23 1 Pet. 2. 10.

* 9.26 Hos. 1. 10.

* 9.27 Is. 10. 22, 23.

∥ 9.28 Or, the account.

* 9.29 Is. 1. 9.

* 9.33 Is. 8. 14. & 28. 16 1 Pet. 2. 6.

∥ 9.33 Or, confounded.

* 10.5 Lev. 18. 5. Ezek. 20. 11. Gal. 8. 12.

* 10.6 Deut. 30. 12.

* 10.8 Deut. 30. 14.

* 10.11 Is. 28. 16.

* 10.13 Joel 2. 32 Acts 2. 21.

* 10.15 Is. 52. 7. Nah. 1. 15.

* 10.16 Is. 53. 1. John 12. 38.

† 10.16 Gr. the hearing of us.

∥ 10.16 Or, preaching.

* 10.18 Ps. 19. 4.

* 10.19 Deut. 32. 21.

* 10.20 Is. 65. 1.

* 10.21 Is. 65. 2.

* 11.3 1 Kin. 19. 10, 14.

* 11.4 1 Kin. 19. 18.

∥ 11.7 Or, hardened.

* 11.8 Is. 29. 10.

∥ 11.8 Or, remorse.

* 11.8 Is. 6. 9.

* 11.9 Ps. 69. 22.

* 11.10 Ps. 69. 23.

∥ 11.12 Or, decay, or, loss.

∥ 11.17 Or, for them.

∥ 11.25 Or, hardness.

* 11.26 Is. 59. 20.

∥ 11.30 Or, obeyed.

∥ 11.31 Or, obeyed.

∥ 11.32 Or, shut them all up together.

* 11.34 Is. 40. 13. Wisd. 9. 13 1 Cor. 2. 16.

‡ 12.2 [1611 that acceptable]

† 12.3 Gr to sobriety.

∥ 12.8 Or, imparteth.

∥ 12.8 Or, liberally.

∥ 12.10 Or, in the love of the brethren.

∥ 12.16 Or, be contented with mean things.

* 12.19 Deut. 32. 35.

* 12.20 Prov. 25. 21.

∥ 13.1 Or, ordered.

∥ 13.13 Or, decently.

∥ 14.1 Or, not to judge his doubtful thoughts.

∥ 14.5 Or, fully assured.

∥ 14.6 Or, observeth.

‡ 14.6 [1611 a day]

‡ 14.10 [1611 omits for]

* 14.10 2 Cor. 5. 10.

* 14.11 Is. 45. 23.

† 14.14 Gr. common.

† 14.14 Gr. common.

† 14.15 Gr. according to charity.

* 14.15 1 Cor. 8. 11.

* 14.20 1. 15.

* 14.21 1 Cor. 8. 13.

∥ 14.23 Or, discerneth and putteth a difference between meats.

* 15.3 Ps. 69. 9.

* 15.5 1 Cor. 1. 10.

∥ 15.5 Or, after the example of.

* 15.9 Ps. 18. 49.

* 15.10 Deut. 32 43.

* 15.11 Ps. 117. 1.

* 15.12 Is. 11. 10.

∥ 15.16 Or, sacrificing.

* 15.21 Is. 52. 15.

∥ 15.22 Or, many ways, or, oftentimes,

† 15.24 ver. 32.

∥ 15.31 Or, are disobedient.

∥ 16.10 Or, friends.

∥ 16.11 Or, friends.

∥ 16.19 Or, harmless.

∥ 16.20 Or, tread.

Sirach

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40

41
42
43
44
45
46
47
48
49
50

51

The Wisdom of Jesus the Son of Sirach, or Ecclesiasticus

1

A Prologue made by an uncertain Author. [*]

This Jesus was the son of Sirach, and grandchild to Jesus of the same name with him: this man therefore lived in the latter times, after the people had been led away captive, and called home again, and almost after all the prophets. Now his grandfather Jesus, as he himself witnesseth, was a man of great diligence and wisdom among the Hebrews, who did not only gather the grave and short sentences of wise men, that had been before him, but himself also uttered some of his own, full of much understanding and wisdom. When as therefore the first Jesus died, leaving this book almost [*]perfected, Sirach his son receiving it after him left it to his own son Jesus, who, having gotten it into his hands, compiled it all orderly into one volume, and called it Wisdom, intituling it both by his own name, his father’s name, and his grandfather’s; alluring the hearer by the very name of Wisdom to have a greater love to the study of this book. It containeth therefore wise sayings, [a]dark sentences, and parables, and [b]certain particular ancient godly stories of men [c]that pleased God; also [d]his prayer and [e]song; moreover, what benefits God had vouchsafed his people, and what plagues he had heaped upon their enemies. This Jesus did imitate Solomon, and was no less famous for wisdom and learning, both being indeed a man of great learning, and so reputed also.

The Prologue of the Wisdom of [*]Jesus the Son of Sirach.

Whereas many and great things have been delivered unto us by [a]the law and the prophets, and by others that have followed their steps, for the which things Israel ought to be commended for learning and wisdom; and whereof not only the readers must needs become skilful themselves, but also they that desire to learn be able to profit them which are [*]without, both by speaking and writing: my grandfather Jesus, when he had much given himself to the reading of [a]the law, and the prophets, and other books of our fathers, and had gotten therein good judgment, was drawn on also himself to write something pertaining to learning and wisdom; to the intent that those which are desirous to learn, and are addicted to these things, might profit much more in living according to the law. Wherefore let me intreat you to read it with favour and attention, and to pardon us, wherein we may seem to come short of some words, which we have laboured to interpret. For the same things uttered in [b]Hebrew, and translated into another tongue, have not the same force in them: and not only these things, but [a]the law itself, and the [*]prophets, and the rest of the books, have no small [*]difference, when they are spoken in their own language. [*]For in the eight and thirtieth year coming into Egypt, when Euergetes was king, and continuing there some time, I found a [*]book of no small learning: therefore I thought it most necessary for me to bestow some diligence and travail to interpret it; using great watchfulness and skill in that space to bring the book to an end, and set it forth for them also, which [c]in a strange country are willing to learn, being prepared before in manners to live after the law.

1 [*][a]All wisdom cometh from the Lord, and [c]is with him for ever.

2 [b]Who can number the sand of the sea, and the drops of rain, and the days of eternity?

3 Who can find out the height of heaven, and the breadth of the earth, and the deep, and wisdom?

4 [c]Wisdom hath been created before all things, and the understanding of prudence from everlasting.

5 The word of God most high is [d]the fountain of wisdom; and her ways are everlasting commandments.

6 To whom hath [e]the root of wisdom been revealed? or who hath known her wise counsels?

7  Unto whom hath the knowledge of wisdom been made manifest? and who hath understood her great experience?

8 There is one wise and greatly to be feared, the Lord sitting upon his throne.

9 He created her, and saw her, and [f]numbered her, and poured her out upon all his works.

10 She is with all flesh according to his gift, and he hath given her to them that love him.

11 The fear of the Lord is honour, and glory, and [g]gladness, and a crown of rejoicing.

12 The fear of the Lord maketh a merry heart, and giveth joy, and gladness, and a long life.

13 Whoso feareth the Lord, it shall go well with him [h]at the last, and he [*]shall find favour in the day of his death.

14 [i]To fear the Lord is the beginning of wisdom: and it was created with the faithful in the womb.

15 [j]She hath built an everlasting foundation with men, and she shall [k]continue with their seed.

16 [i]To fear the Lord is fulness of wisdom, and filleth men with her fruits.

17 [l]She filleth all their house with things desirable, and the garners with her increase.

18 The fear of the Lord is a crown of wisdom, making peace and perfect health to flourish; both which are the gifts of God: and it enlargeth their rejoicing that love him.

19 Wisdom [m]raineth down skill and knowledge of understanding standing, and exalteth them to honour that hold her fast.

20 [e]The root of wisdom is to fear the Lord, and the branches thereof are [n]long life.

21 The fear of the Lord driveth away sins: and where it is present, it turneth away wrath.

22 A furious man cannot [*]be justified; for the sway of his fury shall be his destruction.

23 [o]A patient man will tear for a time, and afterward joy shall spring up unto him.

24 He will hide his words for a time, and the lips of [p]many shall declare his wisdom.

25 [q]The parables of knowledge are in the treasures of wisdom: but godliness is an abomination to a sinner.

26 If thou desire wisdom, [r]keep the commandments, and [s]the Lord shall give her unto thee.

27 For the fear of the Lord is wisdom and instruction: and faith and meekness are his delight.

28 [*]Distrust not the fear of the Lord when thou art poor: and come not unto him [t]with a double heart.

29 Be not an hypocrite in the sight of men, and [u]take good heed what thou speakest.

30 [x]Exalt not thyself, lest thou fall, and bring dishonour upon thy soul, and so God discover thy secrets, and cast thee down [y]in the midst of the congregation, because thou camest not in truth to the fear of the Lord, but thy heart is [z]full of deceit.

2

1 My son, [a]if thou come to serve the Lord, prepare thy soul for temptation.

2 Set thy heart aright, and [b]constantly endure, and [*]make not haste in time of [c]trouble.

3 [d]Cleave unto him, and depart not away, that thou mayest be increased [e]at thy last end.

4 Whatsoever [c]is brought upon thee take cheerfully, and be patient when thou art changed to [f]a low estate.

5 For [g]gold is tried in the fire, and [h]acceptable men in the furnace of [f]adversity.

6 [i]Believe in him, and he will help thee; order thy way aright, and trust in him.

7 Ye that fear the Lord, [j]wait for his mercy; and [k]go not aside, lest ye fall.

8 Ye that fear the Lord, believe him; and your reward shall not fail.

9 Ye that fear the Lord, hope for good, and for everlasting joy and mercy.

10 [l]Look at the generations of old, and see; did ever any trust in the Lord, and was confounded? or did any abide in his fear, and was forsaken? or [m]whom did he ever despise, that called upon him?

11 For [n]the Lord is full of compassion and mercy, longsuffering, and very pitiful, and [o]forgiveth sins, and saveth in time of affliction.

12 Woe be to [p]fearful hearts, and [q]faint hands, and the sinner that goeth [r]two ways!

13 Woe unto him that is fainthearted! for he believeth not; therefore shall he not be defended.

14 Woe unto you [s]that have lost patience! and what will ye do when the Lord shall [t]visit you?

15 They that fear the Lord will not disobey his Word; and [u]they that love him will keep his ways.

16 They that fear the Lord will seek that which is well, pleasing unto him; and they that love him shall be filled with the law.

17 They that fear the Lord will [x]prepare their hearts, and humble their souls in his sight,

18 [y]Saying, [z]We will fall into the hands of the Lord, and not into the hands of men: for as his [a]majesty is, so is his mercy.

3

1 Hear me your father, O children, and do thereafter, that ye may be safe.

2 For [a]the Lord hath given the father honour over the children, and hath confirmed the [*]authority of the mother over the sons.

3 Whoso honoureth his father maketh an atonement for his sins:

4 And he that honoureth his mother is as one that [b]layeth up treasure.

5 Whoso honoureth his father shall have joy of his own children; and when he maketh his prayer, he shall be heard.

6 He that honoureth his father [a]shall have a long life; and he that is obedient unto the Lord shall [c]be a comfort to his mother.

7 He that feareth the Lord will honour his father, and will do service unto his parents, as to his masters.

8 [a]Honour thy father and mother both in word and deed, that a blessing may come upon thee from them.

9 For [d]the blessing of the father establisheth the houses of children; but the curse of the mother rooteth out foundations.

10 Glory not in the dishonour of thy father; for thy father’s dishonour is no glory unto thee.

11 For [e]the glory of a man is from the honour of his father; and a mother in dishonour is a reproach to the children.

12 My son, help thy father in his age, and grieve him not as long as he liveth.

13 And if his understanding fail, have patience with him; and despise him not when thou art [*]in thy full strength.

14 For the relieving of thy father shall not be forgotten: and instead of sins it shall be added [g]to build thee up.

15 In the day of thine affliction it shall be remembered; thy sins also shall melt away, as the ice in the [h]fair warm weather.

16 He that forsaketh his father is as a blasphemer; and he that angereth his mother is cursed: of God.

17 My son, go on with thy business in meekness; so shalt thou be beloved of [i]him that is approved.

18 [k]The greater thou art, the more humble thyself, and thou shalt [l]find favour before the Lord.

19 Many are in high place, and of renown: but [m]mysteries are revealed unto the meek.

20 For the power of the Lord is great, and he is honoured of the lowly.

21 [n]Seek not out things that are too hard for thee, neither search the things that are above thy strength.

22 But what is commanded thee, think thereupon with reverence, for it is not needful for thee to see with thine eyes the things that are in secret.

23 Be not [o]curious in unnecessary matters: for more things are shewed unto thee than men understand.

24 For many are deceived by their own vain opinion; and an evil suspicion hath overthrown their judgment.

25 Without eyes thou shalt want light: profess not the knowledge therefore that thou hast not.

26 A stubborn heart shall fare evil [p]at the last; and he that loveth danger shall perish therein.

27 An obstinate heart shall be laden with sorrows; and the wicked man shall [q]heap sin upon sin.

28 [*]In the [r]punishment of the proud there is no remedy; for the plant of wickedness hath taken root in him.

29 The heart of the prudent will understand a parable; and an attentive ear is the desire of a wise man.

30 Water will quench a flaming fire; and [s]alms maketh an atonement for sins.

31 And he that requiteth good turns is mindful of that which may come hereafter; and [t]when he falleth, he shall find a stay.

4

1 My son, [a]defraud not the poor of his living, and [a]make not the needy eyes to wait long.

2 Make not an hungry soul sorrowful; neither provoke a man in his distress.

3 [aa]Add not more trouble to an heart that is vexed; and [b]defer not to give to him that is in need.

4 Reject not the supplication of the afflicted; [c]neither [d]turn away thy face from a poor man.

5 [d]Turn not away thine eye from [*][e]the needy, and give him none occasion [f]to curse thee:

6 For [g]if he curse thee in the bitterness of his soul, [h]his prayer shall be heard of him that made him.

7 Get thyself the love of the congregation, and bow thy head to a great man.

8 Let it not grieve thee to bow down thine ear to the poor, and give him a friendly answer with meekness.

9 [i]Deliver him that suffereth wrong from the hand of the oppressor; and [j]be not fainthearted when thou sittest in judgment.

10 [k]Be as a father unto the fatherless, and instead of an husband unto their mother: so shalt thou be as [l]the son of the most High, and he shall love thee more than thy mother doth.

11 [m]Wisdom exalteth [n]her children, and layeth hold of them that seek her.

12 [o]He that loveth her loveth life; and [p]they that seek to her early shall be filled with [q]joy.

13 He that holdeth her fast [r]shall inherit glory; and wheresoever she entereth, the Lord will bless.

14 They that serve her shall minister [*]to the Holy One: and them that love her the Lord doth love.

15 Whoso giveth ear unto her [s]shall judge the nations: and he that attendeth unto her shall dwell securely.

16 If a man commit himself unto her, he shall inherit her; and his generation shall hold her in possession.

17 For at the first she will walk with him [t]by crooked ways, and bring fear and dread upon him, and torment him with her discipline, until she may trust his soul, and try him by her laws.

18 Then will she return the straight way unto him, and [q]comfort him, and [u]shew him her secrets.

19 But if he go wrong, she will forsake him, and give him over to his own ruin.

20 [w]Observe the opportunity, and beware of evil; and [x]be not ashamed when it concerneth thy soul.

21 For [y]there is a shame that bringeth sin; and [z]there is a shame which is glory and grace.

22 [a]Accept no person against thy soul, and let not the reverence of any man cause thee to fall.

23 And refrain not to speak, [*]when there is occasion to do good, and hide not thy wisdom in her beauty.

24 For by speech wisdom shall be known: and learning by the word of the tongue.

25 In no wise speak against the truth; but be abashed of the error of thine ignorance.

26 [b]Be not ashamed to confess thy sins; [*]and force not the course of the river.

27 Make not thyself an underling to a foolish man; neither [a]accept the person of the mighty.

28 Strive for the truth unto death, and the Lord shall fight for thee.

29 [c]Be not hasty in thy tongue, and in thy deeds slack and remiss.

30 Be not as a lion in thy house, [d]nor frantick among thy servants.

31 [e]Let not thine hand be stretched out to receive, and shut when thou shouldest [*]repay.

5

1 [a]Set thy heart [b]upon thy goods; and say not, [c]I have enough for my life.

2 [d]Follow not thine own mind and thy strength, to walk in the ways of thy heart:

3 And say not, Who shall controul me for my works? for the Lord will surely revenge thy pride.

4 [e]Say not, I have sinned, and what harm hath happened unto me? for [f]the Lord is longsuffering, [g]he will in no wise let thee go.

5 Concerning propitiation, be not without fear [h]to add sin unto sin:

6 And say not His mercy is great; he will be pacified for the multitude of my sins: [i]for mercy and wrath come from him, and his indignation resteth upon sinners.

7 [j]Make no tarrying to turn to the Lord, and put not off from day to day: for [k]suddenly shall the wrath of the Lord come forth, and in thy security thou shalt be destroyed, and perish in the day of vengeance.

8 [a]Set not thine heart upon [l]goods unjustly gotten, for [m]they shall not profit thee in the day of [n]calamity.

9 Winnow not with every wind, and go not into every way: for [o]so doth the sinner [p]that hath a double tongue.

10 [o]Be stedfast in thy understanding; and let thy word be [p]the same.

11 [q]Be swift to hear; and let thy life be sincere; and [r]with patience give answer.

12 If thou hast understanding, [r]answer thy neighbour; if not, [s]lay thy hand upon thy mouth.

13 [t]Honour and shame is in talk: and [u]the tongue of man is his fall.

14 Be not called [x]a whisperer, and [y]lie not in wait with thy tongue: for [z]a foul shame is upon the thief, and an evil condemnation upon [p]the double tongue.

15 Be not ignorant of any thing in a great matter or a small.

6

1 Instead of a friend become not an enemy; for thereby thou shalt inherit an ill name, shame, and reproach: even so shall a sinner [a]that hath a double tongue.

2 [b]Extol not thyself in the counsel of thine own heart; that thy soul be not torn in pieces as a bull straying alone.

3 Thou shalt eat up thy leaves, and lose thy fruit, and leave thyself as [c]a dry tree.

4 A wicked soul shall destroy him that hath it, and shall make him to be laughed to scorn of his enemies.

5 [*][d]Sweet language will multiply friends: and a fairspeaking tongue will increase kind greetings.

6 Be in peace with many: nevertheless have but one counsellor of a thousand.

7 If thou wouldest get a friend, [*]prove him first and be not hasty to credit him.

8 For some man is a friend for his own occasion, and [e]will not abide in the day of thy trouble.

9 And there is a friend, who being turned to enmity, and strife will discover thy reproach.

10 Again, [f]some friend is a companion at the table, and [e]will not continue in the day of thy affliction.

11 But in thy prosperity he will be as thyself, and will be bold over thy servants.

12 If thou be brought low, he will be against thee, and will hide himself from thy face.

13 Separate thyself from thine enemies, and [g]take heed of [h]thy friends.

14 A faithfull friend is a strong defence: and he that hath found such an one hath found a treasure.

15 Nothing doth [i]countervail a faithful friend, and his excellency is invaluable.

16 A faithful friend is the medicine of life; and they that fear the Lord shall find him.

17 Whoso feareth the Lord shall direct his friendship aright: for as he is, so shall his neighbour be also.

18 My son, gather instruction [k]from thy youth up: so shalt thou find wisdom till thine old age.

19 Come unto her as one that ploweth and soweth, and [l]wait for her good fruits: for [m]thou shalt not toil much in labouring about her, but thou shalt eat of her fruits right soon.

20 [n]She is very unpleasant to the unlearned: he that is without [*]understanding will not remain with her.

21 She will lie upon him as [o]a mighty stone of trial; and he will cast her from him ere it be long.

22 For wisdom is [p]according to her name, and she is not manifest unto many.

23 Give ear, my son, receive my advice, and refuse not my counsel,

24 And put thy feet into her fetters, and thy neck into her [*]chain.

25 [q]Bow down thy shoulder, and bear her, and be not grieved with her bonds.

26 Come unto her [r]with thy whole heart, and keep her ways [r]with all thy power.

27 Search, and seek, and she shall be made known unto thee: and when [s]thou hast got hold of her, let her not go.

28 For [t]at the last thou shalt [u]find her rest, and that shall be turned to thy joy.

29 Then shall [w]her fetters be a strong defence for thee, and [w]her chains a robe of glory.

30 For there is a golden ornament upon her, and her bands are [*]purple lace.

31 Thou shalt put her on as a robe of honour, and shalt put her about thee as [x]a crown of joy.

32 My son, if thou wilt, thou shalt be taught: and if thou wilt apply thy mind, thou shalt be [y]prudent.

33 If thou love to hear, thou shalt receive understanding: and if thou bow thine ear, thou shalt be wise,

34 Stand in the multitude of the [z]elders; and cleave unto him that is wise.

35 Be willing to hear every godly discourse; and let not the [a]parables of understanding escape thee.

36 And if thou seest a man of understanding, [b]get thee betimes unto him, and let thy foot wear the steps of his door.

37 Let thy mind be upon the ordinances of the Lord and [c]meditate continually in his commandments: [d]he shall establish thine heart, and give thee wisdom at thine owns desire.

7

1 Do no evil, [a]so shall no harm come unto thee.

2 Depart from the unjust, and iniquity shall turn away from thee.

3 My son, [b]sow not upon the furrows of unrighteousness, and thou shalt not reap them [c]sevenfold.

4 Seek not of the Lord preeminence, neither of the king the seat of honour.

5 [d]justify not thyself before the Lord; and boast not of thy wisdom before the king.

6 Seek not to be judge, being not able to take away iniquity; [e]lest at any time thou fear the person of the mighty, an [f]stumblingblock in the way of thy uprightness.

7 [g]Offend not against the multitude of a city, and then thou shalt not cast thyself down among the people.

8 [h]Bind not one sin upon another; for in one thou shalt not be unpunished.

9 [i]Say not, God will look upon the multitude of my oblations, and when I offer to the most high God, he will accept it.

10 [k]Be not fainthearted when thou makest thy prayer, and [l]neglect not to give alms.

11 [m]Laugh no man to scorn in the bitterness of his soul: for [n]there is one which humbleth and exalteth.

12 [*]Devise not a lie against thy brother; neither do the like to thy friend.

13 Use not to make any manner of lie: for the custom thereof is not good.

14 [o]Use not many words in a multitude of elders, and [p]make not [*]much babbling when thou prayest.

15 Hate not laborious work, neither husbandry, [q]which the most High hath [*]ordained.

16 Number not thyself among the multitude of sinners, but remember that wrath will not tarry long.

17 [qq]Humble thyself greatly: for the vengeance of the ungodly is [r]fire and worms.

18 Change not a friend [rr]for any good by no means; neither a [s]faithful brother for the gold of [t]Ophir.

19 [u]Forego not a wise and good woman: [v]for her grace is above gold.

20 [w]Whereas thy servant worketh truly, entreat him not evil, nor [x]the hireling that bestoweth himself wholly for thee.

21 [w]Let thy soul love a [y]good servant, and [z]defraud him not of liberty.

22 [a]Hast thou cattle? have an eye to them: and if they be for thy profit, keep them with thee.

23 Hast thou children? [b]instruct them, and [c]bow down their neck from their youth.

24 [d]Hast thou daughters? have a care of their body, and shew not thyself cheerful toward them.

25 Marry thy daughter, and so shalt thou have performed a weighty matter: but give her to a man [y]of understanding.

26 Hast thou a wife after thy mind? forsake her not: but give not thyself over to a [*]light woman.

27 [e]Honour thy father with thy whole heart, and [f]forget not the sorrows of thy mother.

28 Remember that thou wast begotten of them; and how canst thou recompense them the things that they have done for thee?

29 Fear the Lord with all thy soul, and [g]reverence his priests.

30 [h]Love him that made thee with all thy strength, and [i]forsake not his ministers.

31 Fear the Lord, and honor the priest; and give him his portion, [i]as it is commanded thee; [k]the firstfruits, and [l]the trespass offering, and [m]the gift of the shoulders, and [n]the sacrifice of sanctification, and [o]the firstfruits of the holy things.

32 And [p]stretch thine hand unto the poor, that [*]thy [q]blessing may be perfected.

33 A gift hath grace in the sight of every man living; and [r]for the dead detain it not.

34 [s]Fail not to be with them that weep, and mourn with them that mourn.

35 [t]Be not slow to visit the sick: for that shall make thee to be beloved.

36 Whatsoever thou takest in hand, [u]remember the end, and thou shalt never do amiss.

8

1 Strive not with a mighty man’ lest thou fall into his hands.

2 [a]Be not at variance with a rich man, lest he overweigh thee: for [b]gold hath destroyed many, and perverted the hearts of kings.

3 Strive not with a man that is [*]full of tongue, and [c]heap not wood upon his fire.

4 Jest not with a rude man, lest thy ancestors be disgraced.

5 [d]Reproach not a man that turneth from sin, but remember that we are all worthy of [e]punishment.

6 [f]Dishonour not a man in his old age: for even some of us wax old.

7 Rejoice not over thy greatest enemy being dead, but remember that we die all.

8 Despise not the discourse of the wise, but acquaint thyself with their proverbs: for of them thou shalt learn instruction, and how to serve great men with ease.

9 [g]Miss not the discourse of the elders: for they also learned of their fathers, and of them thou shalt learn understanding, and [h]to give answer as need requireth.

10 [i]Kindle not the coals of a sinner, lest thou be burnt with the flame of his fire.

11 Rise not up in anger at the presence of an injurious person, lest he lie in wait [j]to entrap thee [*]in thy words

12 [k]Lend not unto him that is mightier than thyself; for if thou lendest him, count it but lost.

13 Be not surety above thy power: for [l]if thou be surety, take care to pay it.

14 Go not to law with a judge; for they will judge for him according to his [*]honour.

15 [m]Travel not by the way with a bold fellow, lest he become grievous unto thee: for he will do according to his own will, and thou shalt perish with him through his folly.

16 [n]Strive not with an angry man, and go not with him into a solitary place: for blood is as nothing in his sight, and where there is no help, he will overthrow thee.

17 [o]Consult not with a fool; for [p]he cannot keep counsel.

18 Do no secret thing before a stranger; for thou knowest not what he will bring forth.

19 Open not thine heart to every man, lest he requite thee with a shrewd turn.

9

1 Be not jealous over [a]the wife of thy bosom, and teach her not an evil lesson against thyself.

2 Give not thy soul unto a woman to set her foot upon thy [b]substance.

3 [c]Meet not with an harlot, lest thou fall into her snares.

4 Use not much the company of a woman that [*]is a singer, lest thou be taken with her attempts.

5 [d]Gaze not on a maid, [e]that thou fall not by [f]those things that are precious in her.

6 Give not thy soul unto harlots, that thou lose not thine inheritance.

7 Look not round about thee in the streets of the city, neither wander thou in the solitary place thereof.

8 Turn away thine eye from a beautiful woman, and look not upon another’s beauty; for [g]many have been [h]deceived by the beauty of a woman; for herewith [i]love is kindled as a fire.

9 Sit not at all with [j]another man’s wife, nor sit down with her in thine arms, and spend not thy money with her at the wine; lest thine heart incline unto her, and so through thy desire thou fall into destruction.

10 Forsake not an old friend; for the new is not comparable to him: a new friend is as new wine; [k]when it is old, thou shalt drink it with pleasure.

11 [l]Envy not the glory of a sinner: for thou knowest not what shall be his [m]end.

12 [n]Delight not in the thing that the ungodly have pleasure in; but remember they shall not go unpunished unto their grave.

13 Keep thee far from the man that hath power to kill; so shalt thou not doubt the fear of death: and if thou come unto him, make no fault, lest he take away thy life presently: remember that thou goest in the midst of snares, and that thou walkest upon the battlements of the city.

14 As near as thou canst, guess at thy neighbour, and [o]consult with the wise.

15 Let thy talk be with the wise, and [p]all thy communication in the law of the most High.

16 And let just men eat and drink with thee; and let thy glorying be in the fear of the Lord.

17 For the hand of the artificer the work shall be commended: and the wise ruler of the people for his speech.

18 A man [q]of an ill tongue is dangerous in his city; and he that is rash in his talk shall be hated.

10

1 A wise judge will instruct his people; and the government of a prudent man is well ordered.

2 [a]As the judge of the people is himself, so are his officers; and what manner of man the ruler of the city is, such are all they that dwell therein.

3 An unwise king destroyeth his people; but through the prudence of them which are in authority the city shall be inhabited.

4 [b]The power of the earth is in the hand of the Lord, and in due time he will set over it one that is profitable.

5 In the hand of God is the [c]prosperity of man: and upon the [*]person of [d]the scribe shall he lay his honour.

6 [e]Bear not hatred to thy neighbour for every wrong; and do nothing at all by injurious practices.

7 Pride is hateful before God and man: and by both doth one commit iniquity.

8 Because of unrighteous dealings, injuries, and riches got by deceit, [b]the kingdom is translated from one people to another.

9 Why is [f]earth and ashes proud? There is not a more wicked thing than a covetous man: for such an one setteth his own soul to sale; because while he liveth [g]he casteth away his bowels.

10 The physician cutteth off a long disease; and [h]he that is to day a king to morrow shall die.

11 For when a man is dead, he shall inherit creeping things, beasts, and [h][i]worms.

12 The beginning of pride is when one departeth from God, and his heart is turned away from his Maker.

13 For pride is the beginning of sin, and he that hath it shall [j]pour out abomination: and therefore the Lord brought upon them strange [k]calamities, and overthrew them utterly.

14 [l]The Lord hath cast down the thrones of proud princes, and set up the meek in their stead.

15 The Lord hath plucked up the roots of the proud nations, and planted the lowly in their place.

16 The Lord overthrew countries of the heathen, and destroyed them to the foundations of the earth.

17 He took some of them away, and destroyed them, and [m]hath made their memorial to cease from the earth.

18 Pride was not [n]made for men, nor furious anger for [o]them that are born of a woman.

19 They that fear the Lord are a sure seed, and they that love him an honourable plant: they that regard not the law are a dishonourable seed; they that transgress the commandments are a [*]deceivable seed.

20 Among brethren he that is chief is honorable; so are they that fear the Lord in his eyes.

21 The fear of the Lord goeth before the obtaining of [*]authority: but roughness and pride is the losing thereof.

22 Whether he be rich, noble, or poor, [p]their glory is the fear of the Lord.

23 It is not meet to despise the poor man [q]that hath understanding; neither [r]is it convenient to magnify a sinful man.

24 Great men, and judges, and potentates, shall be honoured; yet is there none of them greater than he that feareth the Lord.

25 [s]Unto the servant that is wise shall they that are free do service: and [t]he that hath knowledge will not grudge when he is reformed.

26 Be not overwise in doing thy business; and boast not thyself in the time of thy distress.

27 [u]Better is he that laboureth, and aboundeth in all things, than he that boasteth himself, and wanteth bread.

28 My son, [x]glorify thy soul in meekness, and give it honour according to the dignity thereof.

29 Who will justify him that sinneth against his own soul? and who will honour him that dishonoureth his own life?

30 [u]The poor man is honoured for his skill, and the rich man is honoured for his riches.

31 He that is honoured in poverty, how much more in riches? and he that is dishonourable in riches, how much more in poverty?

11

1 Wisdom lifteth up the head [*]of him that is of low degree, and [a]maketh him to sit among great men.

2 Commend not a man for his beauty; neither abhor a man for his outward appearance.

3 The bee is little among such as fly; but her fruit is [b]the chief of sweet things.

4 [c]Boast not of thy clothing and raiment, and exalt not thyself in the day of honour: for [d]the works of the Lord are wonderful, and his works among men are hidden.

5 Many [*]kings have [e]sat down upon the ground; and one that was never thought of hath worn the crown.

6 [f]Many mighty men have been greatly disgraced; and the honourable delivered into other men’s hands.

7 [g]Blame not before thou hast examined the truth: understand first, and then rebuke.

8 [h]Answer not before thou hast heard the cause: neither interrupt men in the midst of their talk.

9 Strive not in a matter that concerneth thee not; and sit not [*]in judgment with sinners.

10 My son, meddle not with many matters: for if thou meddle much, thou shalt not be innocent; and if thou [i]follow after, thou shalt not [i]obtain, neither shalt thou [*]escape by fleeing.

11 [k]There is one that laboureth, and taketh pains, and maketh haste, and is so much the more behind.

12 Again, there is another that is slow, and hath need of help, wanting [l]ability, and full of poverty; [m]yet the eye of the Lord looked upon him for good, and set him up from his low estate,

13 And lifted up his head from misery; so that many that saw it marvelled at him.

14 [n]Prosperity and adversity, life and death, poverty and riches, come of the Lord.

15 [o]Wisdom, knowledge, and understanding of the law, are of the Lord: love, and the way of good works, are from him.

16 Error and darkness [p]had their beginning together with sinners: and evil shall wax old with them that glory therein.

17 The gift of the Lord remaineth with the ungodly, and his favour bringeth prosperity for ever.

18 There is that waxeth rich by his wariness and pinching, and this is the portion of his reward:

19 [q]Whereas he saith, I have found rest, and now will eat [q]continually of my goods; and yet he knoweth not what time shall [*]come upon him, and that [r]he must leave those things to others, and die.

20 [s]Be stedfast in thy covenant, and be conversant therein, and wax old in thy work.

21 [t]Marvel not at the works of sinners; but trust in the Lord, and abide in thy labour: for it is an easy thing in the sight of the Lord on the sudden to make a poor man rich.

22 The blessing of the Lord is [*]in the reward of the godly, and suddenly he maketh his blessing flourish.

23 Say not, [u]What profit is there of my service? and what good things shall I have hereafter?

24 Again, [q]say not, I have enough, and possess many things, and what evil shall I have hereafter?

25 [v]In the day of prosperity there is a forgetfulness of affliction: and in the day of affliction there is no more remembrance of prosperity.

26 For it is an easy thing unto the Lord [w]in the day of death to reward a man according to his ways.

27 The affliction of an hour maketh a man forget pleasure: and in his end his deeds shall be discovered.

28 [x]Judge none blessed before his death: for a man shall be known in his children.

29 Bring not every man into thine house: for the deceitful man hath many trains.

30 Like as a partridge taken and kept in a cage, so is the heart of the proud; and like as a spy, watcheth he for thy fall:

31 For he lieth in wait, and turneth good into evil, and in things worthy praise will lay blame upon thee.

32 Of a spark of fire [y]a heap of coals is kindled: and a sinful man layeth wait for blood.

33 Take heed of a mischievous man, for he worketh wickedness; lest he bring upon thee a perpetual blot.

34 Receive a stranger into thine house, and he will disturb thee, and turn thee out of [z]thine own.

12

1 When thou wilt do good [a]know to whom thou doest it; so shalt thou be thanked for thy benefits.

2 Do good to the godly man, and thou shalt find a recompence; and [b]if not from him, yet from the most High.

3 There can no good come to him that is always occupied in evil, nor [c]to him that giveth no alms.

4 [d]Give to the godly man, [d][e]and help not a sinner.

5 Do well unto him that is lowly, but [e]give not to the ungodly: hold back thy bread, and give it not unto him, lest he overmaster thee thereby: for else [f]thou shalt receive twice as much evil for all the good thou shalt have done unto him.

6 For the most High hateth sinners, and will repay vengeance unto the ungodly, and [g]keepeth them against the mighty day of their punishment.

7 [d]Give unto the good, [d][e]and help not the sinner.

8 A friend cannot be known in prosperity: and an enemy cannot be hidden in adversity.

9 In the prosperity of a man enemies will be grieved: but in his adversity even a friend will depart.

10 Never trust thine enemy: for like as [*]iron rusteth, so is his wickedness.

11 [h]Though he humble himself, and go [i]crouching, yet take good heed and beware of him, and thou shalt be unto him as if thou hadst [j]wiped a [k]lookingglass, and thou shalt know that [j][l]his rust hath not been altogether wiped away.

12 Set him not by thee, lest, when he hath overthrown thee, he stand up in thy place; neither let him sit at thy right hand, lest he seek to take thy seat, and thou [ll]at the last remember my words, and [m]be pricked therewith.

13 Who will pity [n]a charmer that is bitten with a serpent, or any such as come nigh wild beasts?

14 So one that goeth to a sinner, and is [*]defiled with him in his sins, who will pity?

15 For a while he will abide with thee, but if thou begin to fall, he will not [o]tarry.

16 [p]An enemy speaketh sweetly with his lips, but in his heart [q]he imagineth how to throw thee into a pit: [q]he will weep with his eyes, but if he find opportunity, he will not be satisfied with blood.

17 If adversity come upon thee, thou shalt find him there first; and though he pretend to help thee, yet shall he [*]undermine thee.

18 He will [r]shake his head, and [s]clap his hands, and whisper much, and [t]change his countenance.

13

1 He that toucheth pitch shall be defiled therewith; and [a]he that hath fellowship with a proud man shall be like unto him.

2 Burden not thyself above thy power while thou livest; and have no fellowship with one that is mightier and richer than thyself: for how agree the kettle and the earthen pot together? [*]for if the one be smitten against the other, it shall be broken.

3 [b]The rich man hath done wrong, and yet he threateneth withal: the poor is wronged, and he must intreat also.

4 If thou be for his profit, he will use thee: but if thou have nothing, he will forsake thee.

5 If thou have any thing, he will live with thee: yea, he will [c]make thee bare, and will not be sorry for it.

6 If he have need of thee, he will deceive thee, and smile upon thee, and put thee in hope; he will speak thee fair, and say, What wantest thou?

7 And he will shame thee by his meats, until he have [c]drawn thee dry twice or thrice, and at the last he will laugh thee to scorn afterward, when he seeth thee, he will forsake thee, and [d]shake his head at thee.

8 Beware that thou be not deceived and brought down [*]in thy [e]jollity.

9 If thou be invited of a mighty man, withdraw thyself, and so much the more will he invite thee.

10 [f]Press thou not upon him, lest thou be put back; stand not far off, lest thou be forgotten.

11 [*][g]Affect not to be made equal unto him in talk, [*]and believe not his many words: for with much communication will he tempt thee, and smiling upon thee will get out thy secrets:

12 But cruelly he will lay up thy words, and will not spare to do thee hurt, and to put thee in prison.

13 Observe, and take good heed, for thou walkest in peril of thy overthrowing: when thou hearest these things, awake in thy sleep.

14 Love the Lord all thy life, and call upon him for thy salvation.

15 Every beast loveth his like, and every man loveth his neighbor.

16 All flesh consorteth according to kind, and a man will cleave to his like.

17 [h]What fellowship hath the wolf with the lamb? [i]so the sinner with the godly.

18 What agreement is there between the hyena and a dog? and what peace between the rich and the poor?

19 As [k]the wild ass is the lion’s prey in the wilderness: so [l]the rich eat up the poor.

20 As the proud hate humility: so doth the rich abhor the poor.

21 A rich man beginning to fall is held up of his friends: but a poor man being down is thrust away by his friends.

22 When a rich man is fallen, he hath many helpers: he speaketh things not to be spoken, and yet men justify him: the poor man slipped, and yet they rebuked him too; [m]he spake wisely, and [n]could have no place.

23 When a rich man speaketh, [o]every man holdeth his tongue, and, look, what he saith, they extol it to the clouds: but if the poor man speak, they say, What fellow is this? and if he stumble, they will help to overthrow him.

24 Riches are good unto him that hath no sin, and poverty is evil in the mouth of the ungodly.

25 The heart of a man [p]changeth his countenance, whether it be for good or evil: and [q]a merry heart maketh a cheerful countenance.

26 A cheerful countenance is a token of a heart that is in prosperity; and the finding out of parables is [r]a wearisome labour of the mind.

14

1 [a]Blessed is the man that hath not [a][b]slipped with his mouth, and is not [c]pricked with the [*]multitude of sins.

2 [d]Blessed is he whose conscience hath not condemned him, and who is not fallen from his hope in the Lord.

3 Riches are not comely for a niggard: and what should an envious man do with money?

4 He that gathereth by defrauding his own soul [e]gathereth for others, that shall spend his goods riotously.

5 He that is evil to himself, to whom will he be good? he shall not take pleasure in his goods.

6 There is none worse than he that envieth himself; and this is a recompence of his wickedness.

7 And if he doeth good, he doeth it unwillingly; and [f]at the last he will declare his wickedness.

8 The envious man hath a wicked eye; he turneth away his face, and despiseth men.

9 A covetous man’s eye [g]is not satisfied with his [p]portion; and the iniquity of the wicked drieth up his soul.

10 [h]A wicked eye [i]envieth his bread, and he is a niggard at his table.

11 My son, according to thy ability do good to thyself, and [k]give the Lord his due offering.

12 Remember that death will not be long in coming, and that the covenant of the grave is not shewed unto thee.

13 [l]Do good unto thy friend before thou die, and according to thy [m]ability stretch out [n]thy hand and give to him.

14 [o]Defraud not thyself of [*]the good day, and let not the [p]part of a good desire overpass thee.

15 [e]Shalt thou not leave thy travails unto another? and thy labours to be divided by lot?

16 Give, and take, and sanctify thy soul; for there is no seeking of dainties in the grave.

17 All flesh [q]waxeth old as a garment: for the covenant from the beginning is, [r]Thou shalt die the death.

18 As of the green leaves on a thick tree, some fall, and some grow; so is the generation of [s]flesh and blood, [t]one cometh to an end, and another is born.

19 Every work rotteth and consumeth away, and the worker thereof shall go withal.

20 [u]Blessed is the man that doth meditate good things in wisdom, and that reasoneth of holy things by his understanding.

21 [x]He that considereth her ways in his heart shall also have understanding in her secrets.

22 Go after her as one that traceth, and lie in wait in her ways.

23 He that [y]prieth in at her windows [z]shall also hearken at her doors.

24 He that doth lodge near her house shall also fasten a [*][a]pin in her walls.

25 He shall pitch his tent nigh unto her, and [b]shall lodge in a lodging where good things are.

26 He shall set his children under her shelter, and shall lodge under her branches.

27 By her he shall be [c]covered from heat, and in her glory shall he dwell.

15

1 He that feareth the Lord will do good, and he that hath the knowledge of the law shall obtain her.

2 And [a]as a mother shall she meet him, and receive him as a wife married of a virgin.

3 [b]With the bread of understanding shall she feed him, and [b][c]give him the water of wisdom to drink.

4 He shall be stayed upon her, and shall not be moved; and shall rely upon her, and shall not be confounded.

5 She shall exalt him above his neighbours, and in the midst of the congregation shall she open his mouth.

6 He shall find [d]joy and a crown of gladness, and she shall cause him to inherit an everlasting name.

7 But foolish men shall not attain unto her, and sinners shall not see her.

8 For she is far from pride, and men that are liars cannot remember her.

9 [*]Praise is not seemly in the mouth of a sinner, for [*]it was not sent him of the Lord.

10 For [*][e]praise shall be uttered in wisdom, and the Lord will prosper it.

11 [f]Say not thou, It is through the Lord that I fell away: for thou oughtest not to do the things that he hateth.

12 [f]Say not thou, He hath caused me to err: for he hath no need of the sinful man.

13 The Lord hateth all abomination; and they that fear God love it not.

14 [g]He himself made man from the beginning, and [h]left him in the hand of his counsel;

15 [i]If thou wilt, to keep the commandments, and to perform acceptable faithfulness.

16 [k]He hath set fire and water before thee: stretch forth thy hand unto whether thou wilt.

17 [l]Before man is life and death; and whether him liketh shall be given him.

18 For [m]the wisdom of the Lord is great, and he is mighty in power, and beholdeth all things:

19 And [n]his eyes are upon them that fear him, and [o]he knoweth every work of man.

20 [p]He hath commanded no man to do wickedly, neither hath he given any man licence to sin.

16

1 Desire not a multitude of [a]unprofitable children, neither delight in ungodly sons.

2 Though they multiply, rejoice not in them, except the fear of the Lord be with them.

3 Trust not thou in their life, neither respect their multitude: for one that is just is better than a thousand; and better it is to die without children, than to have them that are ungodly.

4 For by one that hath understanding shall the city be replenished: but the [*]kindred of the wicked shall speedily become desolate.

5 Many such things have I seen with mine eyes, and mine ear hath heard greater things than these.

6 [b]In the congregation of the ungodly shall a fire be kindled; and in a rebellious nation wrath [*]is set on fire.

7 [c]He was not pacified toward the old giants, who fell away in the strength of their foolishness.

8 [d]Neither spared he the place where Lot sojourned, but abhorred them for their [e]pride.

9 [e]He pitied not the people of perdition, who were taken away in their sins:

10 [f]Nor [g]the six hundred thousand footmen, who were gathered together in the hardness of their hearts.

11 And if there be one stiffnecked among the people, it is marvel if he escape unpunished: [h]for mercy and wrath are with him; he is mighty to forgive, and to pour out displeasure.

12 As his mercy is great, so is his correction also: [i]he judgeth a man according to his works

13 [k]The sinner shall not escape with his spoils: and the patience of the godly shall not be frustrate.

14 Make way for every work of mercy: for [i]every man shall find according to his works.

15 [l]The Lord hardened Pharaoh, that he should not know him, that his powerful works might be known to the world.

16 His mercy is manifest to every creature; and [m]he hath separated his light from the darkness with an [*][n]adamant.

17 Say not thou, [o]I will hide myself from the Lord: shall any remember me from above? I shall not be remembered among so many people: for what is my soul among such an infinite number of creatures?

18 Behold, [p]the heaven, and the heaven of heavens, the deep, and the earth, and all that therein is, [q]shall be moved [r]when he shall visit.

19 [s]The mountains also and [t]foundations of the earth be shaken with trembling, when the Lord looketh upon them.

20 No heart can think upon these things worthily: and [u]who is able to conceive his ways?

21 It is a tempest which no man can see: for [x]the most part of his works are hid.

22 Who can declare the works of his justice? or who can endure them? for his covenant is afar off, and the trial of all things is in the end.

23 [y]He that wanteth understanding will think upon vain things: and a foolish man erring imagineth follies.

24 [z]My son, hearken unto me, and learn knowledge, and mark my words with thy heart.

25 I will shew forth doctrine [a]in weight, and declare his knowledge [b]exactly.

26 [c]The works of the Lord are done in judgment from the beginning: and from the time he made them he disposed the parts thereof.

27 [d]He garnished his works for ever, and in his hand are the [*]chief of them unto all generations: they neither labour, nor are weary, nor cease from their works.

28 None of them hindereth another, and [e]they shall never disobey his word.

29 [f]After this the Lord looked upon the earth, and filled it with his blessings.

30 [g]With all manner of living things hath he covered the face thereof; and [h]they shall return into it again.

17

1 The Lord [a]created man of the earth, and [b]turned him into it again.

2 [c]He gave them [d]few days, and a short time, and power also over the things therein.

3 He endued them with strength by themselves, and [e]made them according to his image,

4 And [f]put the fear [*]of man upon all flesh, and [g]gave him dominion over beasts and fowls.

5 They received the use of the five [h]operations of the Lord, and in the sixth place he imparted them understanding, and in the seventh speech, an interpreter of the [h]cogitations thereof.

6 Counsel, and a tongue, and eyes, ears, and a heart, gave he them to understand.

7 Withal he filled them with the knowledge of understanding, and shewed them good and evil.

8 He set his eye upon their hearts, that he might shew them [i]the greatness of his works.

9 He gave them to glory in his marvellous acts for ever, that they might declare his works with understanding.

10 And [k]the elect shall praise his holy name.

11 Beside this he gave them knowledge, and the law of life for an heritage.

12 He made an everlasting covenant with them, and shewed them his judgments.

13 Their eyes saw [i]the majesty of his glory, and their ears heard his glorious voice.

14 And he said unto them, Beware of all unrighteousness; and [l]he gave every man commandment concerning his neighbour.

15 [m]Their ways are ever before him, and shall not be hid from his eyes.

16 [n]Every man from his youth is given to evil; neither could they make to themselves [o]fleshy hearts for stony.

17 For [p]in the division of the nations of the whole earth [q]he set a ruler over every people; but [r]Israel is the Lord’s portion:

18 Whom, [s]being his firstborn, he nourisheth with discipline, and giving him the light of his love doth not forsake him.

19 Therefore all their works are as the sun before him, and [m]his eyes are continually upon their ways.

20 None of their unrighteous deeds are hid from him, but all their sins are before the Lord

21 But the Lord being gracious and knowing his workmanship, [t]neither left nor forsook them, but spared them.

22 [u]The alms of a man is as [x]a signet with him, and he will keep the good deeds of man as [y]the apple of the eye, and give repentance to his sons and daughters.

23 [z]Afterwards he will rise up and reward them, and [a]render their recompence upon their heads.

24 But [b]unto them that repent, he granted them return, and comforted those that failed in patience.

25 [c]Return unto the Lord, and forsake thy sins, make thy prayer before his face, and [*][e]offend less.

26 Turn again to the most High, and turn away from iniquity: for he will lead thee out of darkness into the [*]light of health, and hate thou abomination vehemently.

27 [f]Who shall praise the most High in the grave, instead of them which live and give thanks?

28 Thanksgiving perisheth from the dead, as from one that is not: [g]the living and sound in heart shall praise the Lord.

29 How great is the lovingkindness of the Lord our God, and his compassion unto such as turn unto him in holiness!

30 For all things cannot be in men, because the son of man is not immortal.

31 [h]What is brighter than the sun? yet the light thereof faileth; and flesh and blood will imagine evil.

32 He vieweth the power of the height of heaven; and all men are but [i]earth and ashes.

18

1 He that liveth for ever [a]Hath created all things in general.

2 The Lord only is righteous, and [b]there is none other but he,

3 Who governeth the world [c]with the palm of his hand, and [d]all things obey his will: for he is the King of all, by his power [e]dividing holy things among them from profane.

4 [f]To whom hath he given power to declare his works? and [g]who shall find out his [h]noble acts?

5 Who shall number the strength of his [i]majesty? and who shall also tell out his [i]mercies?

6 As for the wondrous works of the Lord, [j]there may nothing be taken from them, neither may any thing be put unto them, neither can the ground of them be found out.

7 When a man hath done, then he beginneth; and when he leaveth off, then he shall be [k]doubtful.

8 What is man, and whereto serveth he? what is his good, and what is his evil?

9 [l]The number of a man’s days at the most are an hundred years.

10 [m]As a drop of water unto the sea, and a gravelstone in comparison of the sand; so are [n]a thousand years to the days of eternity.

11 Therefore is God [o]patient with them, and poureth forth his mercy upon them.

12 He saw and perceived their [p]end to be evil; [q]therefore he multiplied his compassion.

13 The mercy of man is toward his neighbour; but [r]the mercy of the Lord is upon all flesh: he reproveth, and nurtureth, and teacheth and bringeth again, [s]as a shepherd his flock.

14 He hath mercy on them that receive discipline, and that diligently seek after his judgments.

15 [t]My son, blemish not thy good deeds, neither use uncomfortable words when thou givest any thing.

16 Shall not the [u]dew asswage the heat? so is a word better than a gift.

17 Lo, is not a word better than a gift? but both are with a [x]gracious man.

18 A fool will upbraid churlishly, and [t]a gift of the envious consumeth the eyes.

19 Learn before thou speak, and use physick or ever thou be sick.

20 [y]Before judgment examine thyself, and in the day of [z]visitation thou shalt find mercy.

21 [a]Humble thyself before thou be sick, and in the time of sins shew repentance.

22 [b]Let nothing hinder thee to pay thy vow in due time, and defer not until death to be justified.

23 [c]Before thou prayest, prepare thyself; and be not as one that tempteth the Lord.

24 [d]Think upon the wrath [e]that shall be at the end, and the time of vengeance, when he shall turn away his face.

25 [f]When thou hast enough, remember the time of hunger: and when thou art rich, think upon poverty and need.

26 From the morning until the evening the time is changed, and all things are soon done before the Lord.

27 [g]A wise man will fear in every thing, and in the day of sinning he will beware of offence: but a fool will not observe time.

28 Every man of understanding knoweth wisdom, and will give praise unto him that found her.

29 They that were of understanding in sayings became also wise themselves, and [h]poured forth [i]exquisite parables.

30 [j]Go not after thy lusts, but refrain thyself from thine [k]appetites.

31 If thou givest thy soul the desires that please her, she will make thee a laughingstock to thine enemies that malign thee.

32 Take not pleasure in much good cheer, neither be tied to the expence thereof.

33 Be not made a beggar by banqueting upon borrowing, when thou hast nothing in thy purse: for thou shalt lie in wait for thine own life, and be talked on.

19

1 [a]A labouring man that is given to drunkenness shall not be rich: and [aa]he that contemneth small things shall fall by little and little.

2 [b]Wine and [b][c]women will make men of understanding to fall away: and [d]he that cleaveth to harlots will become impudent.

3 [e]Moths and worms shall have him to heritage, and a bold man shall be taken away.

4 [f]He that is hasty to give credit is lightminded; and [g]he that sinneth shall offend against his own soul.

5 Whoso taketh pleasure in wickedness shall be condemned: but he that [h]resisteth pleasures crowneth his life.

6 He that can rule his tongue shall live without strife; and he that hateth babbling shall have less evil.

7 [i]Rehearse not unto another that which is told unto thee, and thou shalt fare never the worse.

8 Whether it be [*]to friend or foe, talk not of other men’s lives; and if thou canst without offence, reveal them not.

9 For he heard and [j]observed thee, and when time cometh he will [*]hate thee.

10 If thou hast heard a word, let it die with thee; and be bold, [k]it will not burst thee.

11 A fool travaileth with a word, as a woman in labour of a child.

12 As an arrow that sticketh in a man’s thigh, so is a word within a fool’s [*]belly.

13 [l]Admonish a friend, it may be he hath not done it: and if he have done it, that he do it no more.

14 [*]Admonish thy friend, it may be he hath not said it: and if he have, that he [i]speak it not again.

15 Admonish a friend: for many times it is a slander, and believe not every tale.

16 [m]There is one that slippeth in his speech, but not [*]from his heart; and who is he that hath not offended with his tongue?

17 [*]Admonish thy neighbour before thou threaten him; and not being angry, [n]give place to the law of the most High.

18 [o]The fear of the Lord is the first step [*][p]to be accepted of him, and wisdom obtaineth his love.

19 The knowledge of the commandments of the Lord is the doctrine of life: and they that do things that please him shall [q]receive the fruit of the tree of immortality.

20 The fear of the Lord is all wisdom; and in all wisdom is the performance of the law, and the knowledge of his omnipotency.

21 [r]If a servant say to his master, I will not do as it pleaseth thee; though afterward he do it, he angereth him that nourisheth him.

22 The knowledge of wickedness is not wisdom, neither at any time the counsel of sinners prudence.

23 There is a wickedness, and the same an abomination; and there is a fool wanting in wisdom.

24 He that hath small understanding, and feareth God, is better than one that hath much wisdom, and transgresseth the law of the most High.

25 There is an exquisite subtilty, and the same is unjust; and there is one that turneth aside to make judgment appear; and there is a wise man that [*]justifieth in judgment.

26 There is a wicked man that [s]hangeth down his head [*]sadly; but inwardly he is full of deceit,

27 [s]Casting down his countenance, and making as if he heard not: where he is not known, he will do thee a mischief before thou be aware.

28 And if for want of power he be hindered from sinning, yet when he findeth opportunity he will do evil.

29 A man may be known by his look, and one that hath understanding by his countenance, when thou meetest him.

30 A man’s attire, and [t]excessive laughter, and gait, shew what he is.

20

1 [a]There is a reproof that is not [*]comely: again, [e]some man holdeth his tongue, and he is wise.

2 It is much better to reprove, than to be angry secretly: and [b]he that confesseth his fault shall be preserved from hurt.

3 How good is it, when thou art reproved, to shew repentance! for so shalt thou escape [c]wilful sin.

4 As is [d]the lust of an eunuch to deflower a virgin; so is he that executeth judgment with violence.

5 [e]There is one that keepeth silence, and is found wise: and another by much babbling becometh hateful.

6 Some man holdeth his tongue, because he hath not to answer: and some keepeth silence, [f]knowing his time.

7 [g]A wise man will hold his tongue [f]till he see opportunity: but a babbler and a fool will regard no time.

8 He that useth many words shall be abhorred; and he that taketh to himself authority therein shall be hated.

9 There is a sinner that hath good success in evil things; and [h]there is a [i]gain that turneth to loss.

10 There is a gift that shall not profit thee; and there is a gift whose recompence is double.

11 [k]There is an abasement because of glory; and there is that lifteth up his head from a low estate.

12 There is that buyeth much for a little, and repayeth it [l]sevenfold.

13 [m]A wise man by his words maketh him beloved: but the [*][n]graces of fools shall be [*]poured out.

14 The gift of a fool shall do thee no good when thou hast it; neither yet of the envious [o]for his necessity: [*]for he looketh to receive many things for one.

15 He giveth little, and [p]upbraideth much; [q]he openeth his mouth like a crier; to day he lendeth, and to morrow will he ask it again: such an one is to be hated of God and man.

16 The fool saith, I have no friends, I have no thank for all my good deeds, and [r]they that eat my bread speak evil of me.

17 How oft, and of how many shall he be laughed to scorn! for he knoweth not aright what it is to have; and it is [rr]all one unto him as if he had it not.

18 To slip upon a pavement is better than [s]to slip with the tongue: so the fall of the wicked shall come speedily.

19 [*][t]An unseasonable tale will always be in the mouth of the unwise.

20 [u]A wise sentence shall be rejected when it cometh out of a fool’s mouth; for [a]he will not speak it in due season.

21 There is that is hindered from sinning through want: and when he taketh rest, he [*]shall not be troubled.

22 [v]There is that destroyeth his own soul through [v]bashfulness, and by [v][w]accepting of persons overthroweth himself.

23 There is that for [v]bashfulness promiseth to his friend, and maketh him his enemy for nothing.

24 [x]A lie is a foul blot in a man, yet it is continually in the mouth of the untaught.

25 [y]A thief is better than a man that is accustomed to lie: but they both shall have destruction to heritage.

26 The disposition of a liar is [*]dishonourable, and his shame is ever with him.

27 [*]A wise man shall promote himself to honour with his words: and he that hath understanding will please great men.

28 [z]He that tilleth his land shall increase his heap: and he that pleaseth great men shall get pardon for iniquity.

29 [a]Presents and gifts blind the eyes of the wise, and [*]stop up his mouth that he cannot reprove.

30 [b]Wisdom that is hid, and [c]treasure that is hoarded up, what profit is in them both?

31 [d]Better is he that hideth his folly [b][d]than a man that hideth his wisdom.

32 Necessary patience in seeking the Lord is better than he that leadeth his life without a guide.

21

1 My son, hast thou sinned? [a]do so no more, but [b]ask pardon for thy former sins.

2 Flee from sin as from the face of [c]a serpent: for if thou comest too near it, it will [c]bite thee: the teeth thereof are as the teeth of a lion, [d]slaying the souls of men.

3 All iniquity is as [e]a two edged sword, the wounds whereof cannot be healed.

4 To terrify and do wrong will waste riches: thus the house of proud men shall be made desolate.

5 [f]A prayer out of a poor man’s mouth reacheth to the ears of God, and his judgment cometh speedily.

6 [g]He that hateth to be reproved is in the way of sinners: but he that feareth the Lord will [*]repent from his heart.

7 An eloquent man is known far and near; but a man of understanding knoweth when he [h]slippeth.

8 [i]He that buildeth his house with other men’s money is like one that gathereth himself stones for the tomb of his burial.

9 [k]The congregation of the wicked is like [l]tow wrapped together: and the end of them is a flame of fire to destroy them.

10 The way of sinners is [m]made plain with stones, [n]but at the end thereof is the pit of hell.

11 [o]He that keepeth the law of the Lord getteth the understanding thereof: and the perfection of the fear of the Lord is wisdom.

12 [p]He that is not [*]wise will not be taught: but [q]there is a [*]wisdom which multiplieth bitterness.

13 The knowledge of a wise man [r]shall abound like a flood: and his counsel is like a pure fountain of life.

14 [s]The inner parts of a fool are like [t]a broken vessel, and he will hold no knowledge as long as he liveth.

15 If a skilful man hear a wise word, he will commend it, and [u]add unto it: but as soon as one of no understanding heareth it, it displeaseth him, and [v]he casteth it behind his back.

16 The talking of a fool is like [w]a burden in the way: but [x]grace shall be found in the lips of the wise.

17 They enquire at the mouth of the wise man in the congregation, and they shall ponder his words in their heart.

18 As is a house that is destroyed, so is wisdom to a fool: and the knowledge of the unwise is as talk [*]without sense.

19 Doctrine unto fools is as fetters on the feet, and like manacles on the right hand.

20 [y]A fool lifteth up his voice with laughter; but a [z]wise man doth scarce smile a little.

21 Learning is unto a wise man as an ornament of gold, and like a [a]bracelet upon his right arm.

22 [b]A foolish man’s foot is soon in his neighbour’s house: but a man of experience is ashamed of him.

23 A fool will [c]peep in at the door into the house: but he that is well nurtured will stand without.

24 It is the rudeness of a man to hearken at the door: but a wise man will be grieved with the disgrace.

25 The lips of talkers will be telling such things as pertain not unto them: but the words of such as have understanding are [d]weighed in the balance.

26 [e]The heart of fools is in their mouth: but the mouth of the wise is in their heart.

27 When the ungodly curseth [f]Satan, [g]he curseth his own soul.

28 [h]A whisperer defileth his own soul, and is hated wheresoever he dwelleth.

22

1 A slothful man is compared to a filthy stone, and every one will hiss him out to his disgrace.

2 A slothful man is compared to the filth of a dunghill: every man that takes it up will shake his hand.

3 [a]An evilnurtured man is the dishonour of his father that begat him: and a foolish daughter is born to his loss.

4 A wise daughter [b][*]shall bring an inheritance to her husband: but she that liveth dishonestly is her father’s heaviness.

5 She that is bold dishonoureth both her father and her husband, but they both shall despise her.

6 [c]A [d]tale out of season is as [e]musick in mourning: but stripes and correction of wisdom are never out of time.

7 Whoso teacheth a fool is as one that glueth a potsherd together, and as he that waketh one from a sound sleep.

8 He that telleth a tale to a fool speaketh to one in a slumber: when he hath told his tale, he will say, What is the matter?

9 If children live honestly, and have [*]wherewithal, they shall cover the baseness of their parents.

10 But children, being haughty, through disdain and want of nurture do stain the nobility of their kindred.

11 [f]Weep for the dead, for he hath lost the light: and weep for the fool, for he wanteth understanding: make little weeping for the dead, for he is at rest: but the life of the fool is worse than death.

12 [g]Seven days do men mourn for him that is dead; but for a fool and an ungodly man all the days of his life.

13 Talk not much with a fool, and go not to him that hath no understanding: [h]beware of him, lest thou have trouble, and thou shalt never be defiled [*]with his fooleries: depart from him, and [i]thou shalt find rest, and never be [*]disquieted with madness.

14 What is heavier than lead? and what is the name thereof, but a fool?

15 [k]Sand, and salt, and a mass of iron, is [l]easier to bear, than a man without understanding.

16 As timber girt and bound together in a building cannot be loosed with shaking: so [m]the heart that is stablished by advised counsel shall fear at no time.

17 A heart settled upon a thought of understanding is as [n]a fair plaistering [*]on the wall of a gallery.

18 Pales set on an high place will never stand against the wind: so [nn]a fearful heart in the imagination of a fool cannot stand against any fear.

19 He that pricketh the eye will make tears to fall: and he that pricketh the heart maketh it to shew her knowledge.

20 Whoso casteth a stone at the birds [o]frayeth them away: and [p]he that upbraideth his friend breaketh friendship.

21 Though thou drewest a sword at thy friend, yet despair not: for there may be a returning to favour.

22 If thou hast opened thy mouth against thy friend, fear not; for there may be a reconciliation: except for upbraiding, or pride, or [q]disclosing of secrets, or a treacherous wound: for for these things every friend will depart.

23 Be faithful to thy neighbour in his poverty, that thou mayest rejoice in his prosperity: abide stedfast unto him in the time of his trouble, that thou mayest be heir with him in his heritage: for a mean estate is not always to be contemned: nor the rich that is foolish to be had in admiration.

24 As the vapour and smoke of a furnace goeth before the fire; so reviling before blood.

25 I will not be ashamed to defend a friend; neither will I hide myself from him.

26 And if any evil happen unto me by him, every one that heareth it will [h]beware of him.

27 Who shall [r]set a watch before my mouth, and a seal of [s]wisdom upon my lips, that I fall not suddenly by them, and that my tongue destroy me not?

23

1 O Lord, Father and Governor of all my whole life, leave me not to their counsels, and let me not fall by them.

2 Who will set scourges over my thoughts, and the discipline of wisdom over mine heart? that they spare me not for mine [a]ignorances, and it pass not by my sins:

3 Lest mine [a]ignorances increase, and my sins abound to my destruction, and I fall before mine adversaries, and mine enemy rejoice over me, whose hope is far from thy mercy.

4 O Lord, Father and God of my life, give me not [b]a proud look, but turn away from thy servants always a [*]haughty mind.

5 Turn away from me vain hopes and concupiscence, and thou shalt hold him up that is desirous always to serve thee.

6 Let not the greediness of the belly nor lust of the flesh take hold of me; and give not over me thy servant into an impudent mind.

7 [*]Hear, O ye children, the discipline of the mouth: he that keepeth it shall never be taken in his lips.

8 The sinner shall be left in his foolishness: both the evil speaker and the proud shall fall thereby.

9 [c]Accustom not thy mouth to swearing; neither use thyself to the naming of the Holy One.

10 For as a servant that is continually beaten shall not be without [d]a blue mark: so he that sweareth and nameth God continually shall not be faultless.

11 A man that useth much swearing shall be filled with iniquity, and [e]the plague shall never depart from his house: if he shall offend, [f]his sin shall be upon him: and if he acknowledge not his sin, he maketh a double offence: and if he swear in vain, he shall not be [*]innocent, but his house shall be full of [g]calamities.

12 [h]There is a word that is clothed about with death: God grant that it be not found in the heritage of Jacob; for all such things shall be far from the godly, and they shall not [i]wallow in their sins.

13 Use not thy mouth to intemperate swearing, for therein is the word of sin.

14 Remember thy father and thy mother, when thou sittest among great men. Be not forgetful before them, and so thou by thy custom become a fool, and [j]wish that thou hadst not been born, and curse they day of thy nativity.

15 [k]The man that is accustomed to opprobrious words will never be reformed all the days of his life.

16 [l]Two sorts of men multiply sin, and the [m]third will bring wrath: a hot mind is as a burning fire, it will never be quenched till it be consumed: a fornicator [n]in the body of his flesh will never cease till he hath kindled a fire.

17 [o]All bread is sweet to a whoremonger, he will not leave off till he die.

18 [m]A man that breaketh wedlock, saying thus in his heart, [p]Who seeth me? I am compassed about with darkness, the walls cover me, and no body seeth me; what need I to fear? the most High will not remember my sins:

19 Such a man only feareth the eyes of men, and knoweth not that the eyes of the Lord are ten thousand times brighter than the sun, [q]beholding all the ways of men, and considering the most secret parts.

20 He knew all things ere ever they were created; so also [r]after they were perfected he looked upon them all.

21 [s]This man shall be punished in the streets of the city, and where he suspecteth not he shall be taken.

22 Thus shall it go also with the wife that leaveth her husband, and bringeth in an heir by [*]another.

23 For first, she hath disobeyed [t]the law of the most High; and secondly, she hath trespassed against her own husband; and thirdly, she hath played the whore in adultery, and brought children by [*]another man.

24 [u]She shall be brought out into the congregation, and [*][x]inquisition shall be made of her children.

25 [y]Her children shall not take root, and her branches shall bring forth no fruit.

26 She shall leave her memory to be cursed, and her reproach shall not be blotted out.

27 And they that remain shall know that there is nothing better than the fear of the Lord, and that there is nothing sweeter than to take heed unto the commandments of the Lord.

28 It is great glory to follow the Lord, and [yy]to be received of him is [z]long life.

24

1 [*]Wisdom shall praise herself, and shall [a]glory in the midst of her people.

2 In the congregation of the most High shall she open her mouth, and [a]triumph before his power.

3 I came out of the mouth of the most High, and covered the earth as [*]a cloud.

4 I dwelt in high places, and [b]my throne is in a cloudy pillar.

5 [c]I alone compassed the circuit of heaven, and walked in the bottom of the deep.

6 In the waves of the sea and in all the earth, and in every people and nation, I got a possession.

7 With all these I sought rest: and in whose inheritance shall I abide?

8 So the Creator of all things gave me a commandment, and he that made me caused my [d]tabernacle to rest, and said, Let thy dwelling be in Jacob, and thine inheritance in Israel.

9 [e]He created me from the beginning before the world, and I shall never fail.

10 [f]In the holy tabernacle I served before him; and so [g]was I established in Sion.

11 Likewise [h]in the [*]beloved city he gave me rest, and in Jerusalem was my power.

12 And I took root in an honourable people, even in the portion of the Lord’s inheritance.

13 I was exalted like [i]a cedar in Libanus, and as [j]a cypress tree upon the mountains of [k]Hermon.

14 I was exalted like [l]a palm tree in [*][m]En-gaddi, and as a [n]rose plant in Jericho, as a fair [j]olive tree in a pleasant field, and grew up as a plane tree [*]by the water.

15 I gave a sweet smell like [o]cinnamon and aspalathus, and I yielded a pleasant odour like the best [p]myrrh, as [q]galbanum, and onyx, and sweet storax, and as the fume of [q][r]frankincense [s]in the tabernacle.

16 As [t]the turpentine tree I stretched out my branches, and my branches are the branches of honour and grace.

17 As [u]the vine brought I forth pleasant savour, and my flowers are the fruit of honour and riches.

18 I am the mother of fair love, and fear, and knowledge, and holy hope: I therefore, being eternal, am given to all my children which are [*]named of him.

19 [x]Come unto me, all ye that be desirous of me, and fill yourselves with my fruits.

20 For my memorial is [y]sweeter than honey, and mine inheritance than the honeycomb.

21 [x][z]They that eat me shall yet be hungry, and they that drink me shall yet be thirsty.

22 He that obeyeth me shall never be confounded, and they that work by me shall not do amiss.

23 All these things are the book of the covenant of the most high God, even [a]the law which Moses commanded for an heritage unto the congregations of Jacob.

24 Faint not to be strong in the Lord; that he may confirm you, [b]cleave unto him: for [c]the Lord [cc]Almighty is God alone, and beside him there is no other Saviour.

25 [d]He filleth all things with his wisdom, as [e]Phison and as [f][g]Tigris in the time of the new fruits.

26 He maketh the understanding to abound like [g]Euphrates, and as [h]Jordan in the time of the harvest.

27 He maketh the doctrine of knowledge appear as the light, and as [i]Geon in the time of vintage.

28 The first man knew her not perfectly: no more shall the last find her out.

29 For her thoughts are more than the sea, and her counsels profounder than the great deep.

30 I also came out as a [*]brook from a river, and [j]as a conduit into a [k]garden.

31 I said, I will water my best garden, and will water abundantly my garden bed: and, lo, my brook became a river, and my river became a sea.

32 I will yet make doctrine to shine as the morning, and will send forth her light afar off.

33 I will yet pour out [l]doctrine as [l]prophecy, and leave it to all ages for ever.

34 Behold [m]that I have not laboured for myself only, but for all them that seek wisdom.

25

1 [a]In three things I [*]was beautified, and stood up [g]beautiful both before God and men: [b]the unity of brethren, [c]the love of neighbours, a man and a wife [d]that agree together.

2 [a]Three sorts of men my soul hateth, and I am greatly offended at their life: a poor man that is proud, a rich man that is a [e]liar, and an old adulterer [f]that doateth.

3 If thou hast gathered nothing in thy youth, how canst thou find any thing in thine age?

4 O how [g]comely a thing is judgment for gray hairs, and for ancient men to know counsel!

5 O how [g]comely is the wisdom of old men, and understanding and counsel to men of honour.

6 Much experience is [h]the crown of old men, and [i]the fear of God is their glory.

7 There be [a]nine things which I have judged in mine heart to be happy, and [m]the tenth I will utter with my tongue: A man that hath joy of his children; and [j]he that liveth to see the fall of his enemy:

8 Well is him that dwelleth with a wife of understanding, and that hath not [k]slipped with his tongue, and that hath not served a man more unworthy than himself:

9 Well is him that hath found [*]prudence, and he that speaketh in the ears of them that will hear:

10 [l]O how great is he that findeth wisdom! yet is there none above him that feareth the Lord.

11 [m]But the love of the Lord passeth all things for [n]illumination: he that holdeth it, [*]whereto shall he be likened?

12 [o]The fear of the Lord is the beginning of his love: and faith is the beginning of cleaving unto him.

13  Give me any plague, [p]but the plague of the heart: and [q]any wickedness, but the wickedness of a woman:

14 And any [r]affliction, but the [r]affliction from them that hate me: and any revenge, but the revenge of enemies.

15 There is no head above the [s]head of a serpent; and there is no wrath above the wrath of an enemy.

16 [t]I had rather dwell with a lion and a dragon, than to keep house with a wicked woman.

17 The [u]wickedness of a woman changeth her face, and darkeneth her countenance [*]like sackcloth.

18 Her husband shall sit among his neighbours; and when he heareth it shall sigh bitterly.

19 [q]All wickedness is but little to the wickedness of a woman: let the portion of a sinner fall upon her.

20 As the climbing up a sandy way is to the feet of the aged, so is a wife [*]full of words to a quiet man.

21 [v]Stumble not at the beauty of a woman, and desire her not for pleasure.

22 A woman, if she maintain her husband, is full of anger, impudence, and much reproach.

23 [t]A wicked woman abateth the courage, maketh an heavy countenance and [p]a wounded heart: a woman that will not comfort her husband in distress maketh [w]weak hands and feeble knees.

24 [x]Of the woman came the beginning of sin, and through her we all die.

25 [y]Give the water no passage; neither a wicked woman liberty [y]to gad abroad.

26 If she go not as thou wouldest have her, cut her off from thy flesh, and [z]give her a bill of divorce, and let her go.

26

1 [a]Blessed is the man that hath [c]a virtuous wife, for the number of his days shall be double.

2 A [b]virtuous woman rejoiceth her husband, and he shall fulfil the years of his life in peace.

3 [c]A good wife is a good portion, which shall be given in the portion of them that fear the Lord.

4 Whether a man be rich or poor, if he have a good heart toward the Lord, he shall at all times rejoice with a cheerful countenance.

5 There be [d]three things that mine heart feareth; and for the fourth I was sore afraid: [*]the slander of a city, the gathering together of an unruly multitude, and a false accusation: all these are worse than death.

6 But a grief of heart and sorrow is [dd]a woman that is jealous over another woman, and a scourge of the tongue which communicateth with all.

7 An evil wife is [*]a yoke shaken to and fro: he that hath hold of her is as though he held [e]a scorpion.

8 A drunken woman and a [f]gadder abroad causeth great anger, and she will not cover her own shame.

9 The whoredom of a woman may be known in her [g]haughty looks and eyelids.

10 [h]If thy daughter be [i]shameless, keep her in straitly, lest she abuse herself through overmuch liberty.

11 Watch over an impudent eye: and marvel not if she trespass against thee.

12 She will open her mouth, as a thirsty traveller when he hath found a fountain, and drink of every water near her: by every [*]hedge will she sit down, and open her quiver against every arrow.

13 The grace of a wife delighteth her husband, and her discretion will [j]fatten his bones.

14 A silent and loving woman is a gift of the Lord; and there is nothing so much worth as a mind well instructed.

15 A shamefaced and faithful woman is a double grace, and her continent mind cannot be valued.

16 As the sun when it ariseth [*]in the high heaven; so is the beauty of [c]a good wife in the [*]ordering of her house.

17 As the clear light is upon [k]the holy candlestick; so is the beauty of the face [*]in ripe age.

18 As the golden pillars are upon the sockets of silver; so are the [*]fair feet with a constant [*]heart.

19 [m]My son, keep the flower of thine [l]age sound; and give not thy strength to strangers.

20 When thou hast gotten a fruitful possession through all the field, sow it with thine own seed, trusting in the goodness of thy stock.

21 So thy race which thou leavest shall be magnified, having the confidence of their good descent.

22 An harlot shall be accounted as [*]spittle; but [n]a married woman is a tower against death [o]to her husband.

23 A wicked woman is given as a portion to a wicked man: but a godly woman is given to him that feareth the Lord.

24 A dishonest woman contemneth shame: but an honest [p]woman will reverence her husband.

25 A [i]shameless woman shall be counted as a dog; but she that is shamefaced will fear the Lord.

26 A woman that honoureth her husband shall be judged wise of all; but she that dishonoureth him in her pride shall be counted ungodly of all.

27 A loud crying woman and a [q]scold shall be sought out to drive away the enemies.

28 There be [d]two things that grieve my heart; and the third maketh me angry: a man of war that suffereth poverty; and [r]men of understanding that are [s]not set by; and [t]one that returneth from righteousness to sin; [u]the Lord prepareth such an one for the sword.

29 A [w]merchant shall hardly keep himself from doing wrong; and an huckster shall not be [x]freed from sin.

27

1 Many [a]have sinned for [*]a small matter; and he that [b]seeketh for abundance will turn his eyes away.

2 As a [c]nail sticketh fast between the joinings of the stones; so [d]doth sin stick close between buying and selling.

3 Unless a man hold himself diligently in the fear of the Lord, his house shall soon be overthrown.

4 As when one sifteth with a sieve, the refuse remaineth; so the [e]filth of man in his [*][i]talk.

5 [f]The furnace proveth the potter’s vessels; so [k]the trial of man is in his [g]reasoning.

6 [h]The fruit declareth if the tree have been dressed; so is the utterance of a conceit in the heart of man.

7 Praise no man before thou hearest him [i]speak; for [k]this is the trial of men.

8 If thou followest [l]righteousness, thou shalt obtain her, and [l]put her on, [m]as a glorious long robe.

9 The birds will [n]resort unto their like; so will truth return unto them that practise in her.

10 As [o]the lion lieth in wait for the prey; so sin for them that work iniquity.

11 The discourse of a godly man is always with wisdom; but a fool changeth as the moon.

12 If thou be among the indiscreet, [p]observe the time; but be continually among men of understanding.

13 The discourse of fools is irksome, and their sport is the [q]wantonness of sin.

14 [r]The talk of him that sweareth much maketh the hair stand upright; and their brawls make one stop his ears.

15 The strife of the proud is bloodshedding, and their revilings are grievous to the ear.

16 [s]Whoso discovereth secrets loseth his credit; and shall never find friend to his mind.

17 Love thy friend, and be faithful unto him: but [s]if thou [t]betrayest his secrets, [u]follow no more after him.

18 For as a man hath destroyed his enemy; so hast thou lost the love of thy neighbor.

19 [x]As one that letteth a bird go out of his hand, so hast thou let thy neighbour go, and shalt not get him again

20 [u]Follow after him no more, for he is too far off; he is as a roe escaped out of the snare.

21 As for a wound, it may be bound up; and after reviling there may be [y]reconcilement: but [s]he that [t]betrayeth secrets is without hope.

22 He that [z]winketh with the eyes worketh evil: and he that knoweth him will depart from him.

23 When thou art present, [a]he will speak sweetly, and will admire thy words: but at the last he will [*]writhe his mouth, and slander thy sayings.

24 I have hated many things, but nothing like him; for the Lord will hate him.

25 Whoso casteth a stone on high [b]casteth it on his own head; and a deceitful stroke shall make wounds.

26 [c]Whoso diggeth a pit shall fall therein: and he that setteth [d]a trap shall be taken therein.

27 He that worketh mischief, it shall fall upon him, and he shall not know whence it cometh.

28 Mockery and reproach are from the proud; but [e]vengeance, as [f]a lion, shall lie in wait for them.

29 They that rejoice at the fall of the righteous shall be [d]taken in the snare; and anguish shall consume them before they die.

30 [g]Malice and wrath, even these are abominations; and the sinful man shall have them both.

28

1 [a]He that revengeth shall find vengeance from the Lord, and he will surely keep his sins in remembrance.

2 [b]Forgive thy neighbour the hurt that he hath done unto thee, so shall thy sins also be forgiven when thou prayest.

3 [c]One man beareth hatred against another, and doth he seek pardon from the Lord?

4 He sheweth no mercy to a man, which is like himself: and doth he ask forgiveness of his own sins?

5 If he that is but flesh nourish [d]hatred, who will intreat for pardon of his sins?

6 [e]Remember thy end, and let enmity cease; remember corruption and death, and abide in the commandments.

7 Remember the commandments, and [d]bear no malice to thy neighbour: remember the covenant of the Highest, and [f]wink at ignorance.

8 [g]Abstain from strife, and thou shalt diminish thy sins: for a furious man will kindle strife,

9 A sinful man disquieteth friends, and maketh [h]debate among them that be at peace.

10 [i]As the [k]matter of the fire is, so it burneth: and as a man’s strength is, so is his wrath; and according to his riches his anger riseth; and the stronger they are which contend, the more they will be inflamed.

11 [l]An hasty contention kindleth a fire: and an hasty fighting sheddeth blood.

12 If thou blow the spark, it shall burn: [m]if thou spit upon it, it shall be quenched: and both these come out of thy mouth.

13 Curse the [n]whisperer and [o]doubletongued: for such have destroyed many that were at peace.

14 A backbiting tongue hath disquieted many, and driven them from nation to nation: strong cities hath it pulled down, and overthrown the houses of great men.

15 A [*]backbiting tongue hath cast out [p]virtuous women, and deprived them of their labours.

16 Whoso hearkeneth unto it shall never find rest, and never dwell quietly.

17 The stroke of the whip maketh [q]marks in the flesh: but the stroke of the tongue breaketh the bones.

18 Many have fallen by [r]the edge of the sword: but not so many as have fallen by the tongue.

19 Well is he that is defended through the venom thereof; who hath not drawn the yoke thereof, nor hath been bound in her bands.

20 [s]For the yoke thereof is a yoke of iron, and the bands thereof are bands of brass.

21 The death thereof is an evil death, [t]the grave were better than it.

22 [u]It shall not have rule over them that fear God, neither shall they be burned with the flame thereof.

23 Such as forsake the Lord shall fall into it; and it shall burn in them, and not be quenched; it shall be sent upon them as a lion, and devour them as a [v]leopard.

24 Look that [w]thou hedge thy possession about with thorns, and [x]bind up thy silver and gold,

25 And [y]weigh thy words in a balance, and [z]make a door and bar for thy mouth.

26 Beware thou slide not by it, lest thou fall before him that lieth in wait.

29

1 [a]He that is merciful will lend unto his neighbour; and he that strengtheneth his hand [b]keepeth the commandments.

2 [a]Lend to thy neighbour in time of his need, and pay thou thy neighbour again in due season.

3 Keep thy word, and deal faithfully with him, and thou shalt always find the thing that is necessary for thee.

4 [c]Many, when a thing was lent them, reckoned it [d]to be found, and [e]put them to trouble that helped them.

5 Till he hath received, he will kiss a man’s hand; and for his neighbour’s money he will speak submissly: but when he should repay, he will prolong the time, and return words of grief, and complain of the time.

6 [*]If he prevail, he shall hardly receive the half, and he will count [d]as if he had found it: if not, he hath deprived him of his money, and he hath gotten him an enemy without cause: he payeth him with cursings and railings; and for honour he will pay him disgrace.

7 Many therefore have refused to lend for other men’s ill dealing, fearing to be defrauded.

8 Yet have thou patience with a man in poor estate, and delay not to shew him mercy.

9 Help the poor [f]for the commandment’s sake, and turn him not away because of his poverty.

10 Lose thy money for thy brother and thy friend, and [g]let it not rust under a stone to be lost.

11 [h]Lay up thy treasure [i]according to the commandments of the most High, and [j]it shall bring thee more profit than gold.

12 [k]Shut up alms in thy [l]storehouses: and it shall deliver thee from all affliction.

13 [m]It shall fight for thee against thine enemies better than a mighty shield and strong spear.

14 An honest man is surety for his neighbour: but he that is impudent will [*][n]forsake him.

15 Forget not the friendship of thy surety, for he hath given [o]his life for thee.

16 A sinner will overthrow the good estate of his surety:

17 And he that is of an unthankful mind will leave him in danger that delivered him.

18 [p]Suretiship hath undone many of good estate, and shaken them as a wave of the sea: mighty men hath it driven from their houses, so that they wandered among strange nations.

19 A wicked man transgressing the commandments of the Lord shall fall into suretiship: and he that undertaketh and followeth other men’s business for gain shall fall into suits.

20 Help thy neighbour according to thy power, and beware that thou thyself fall not into the same.

21 The [q]chief thing for life is water, and [r]bread, and clothing, and an house to cover shame.

22 Better is the life of a poor man in a mean cottage, than delicate fare in another man’s house.

23 [r]Be it little or much, hold thee contented, that thou hear not the reproach of thy house.

24 For it is a miserable life to go from house to house: for where thou art a stranger, thou darest not open thy mouth.

25 Thou shalt entertain, and feast, and have no thanks: moreover thou shalt hear bitter words:

26 [s]Come, thou stranger, and furnish a table, and feed me of that thou hast ready.

27 [t]Give place, thou stranger, to an honourable man; my brother cometh to be lodged, and I have need of mine house.

28 These things are grievous to a man of understanding; [u]the upbraiding of houseroom, and [x]reproaching of the lender.

30

1 [*][a]He that loveth his son causeth him oft to feel the rod, that he may have joy of him [b]in the end.

2 He that chastiseth his son shall have [*]joy in him, and shall rejoice of him among his [*]acquaintance.

3 He that [c]teacheth his son grieveth the enemy: and before his friends he shall rejoice of him.

4 Though his father die, yet he is as though he were not dead: for he hath left one behind him that is like himself.

5 While he lived, he [d]saw and rejoiced in him: and when he died, he was not sorrowful.

6 [e]He left behind him an avenger against his enemies, and one that shall requite kindness to his friends.

7 He that maketh too much of his son shall bind up his wounds; and his bowels will be troubled at every cry.

8 An horse not broken becometh headstrong: and a child left to himself will be wilful.

9 Cocker thy child, and he shall make thee [*]afraid: play with him, and he will bring thee to heaviness.

10 Laugh not with him, lest thou have sorrow with him, and lest thou gnash thy teeth [b]in the end.

11 Give him no liberty in his youth, and [f]wink not at his follies.

12 [g]Bow down his neck while he is young, and beat him on the sides while he is a child, lest he wax stubborn, and be disobedient unto thee, and so bring sorrow to thine heart.

13 Chastise thy son, and [h]hold him to labour, lest his lewd behaviour be an offence unto thee.

14 [*]Better is the poor, being sound and strong of constitution, than a rich man that is afflicted in his body.

15 Health and good estate of body are above all gold, and a strong body above infinite wealth.

16 There is no riches above a sound body, and no joy above the joy of the heart.

17 Death is better than a bitter life or continual sickness.

18 Delicates poured upon a mouth shut up are as [i]messes of meat set upon a grave.

19 [k]What good doeth the [l]offering unto an idol? for neither can it eat [m]nor smell: so is he that is [*]persecuted of the Lord.

20 He seeth with his eyes and groaneth, [n]as an eunuch that embraceth a virgin and sigheth.

21 [o]Give not over thy mind to heaviness, and afflict not thyself in thine own counsel.

22 [p]The gladness of the heart is the life of man, and the [*]joyfulness of a man prolongeth his days.

23 Love thine own soul, and comfort thy heart, remove sorrow far from thee: for [q]sorrow hath killed many, and there is no profit therein.

24 Envy and wrath shorten the life, and carefulness bringeth age before the time.

25 [*]A cheerful and [r]good heart will have a care of his meat and diet.

31

1 [a]Watching for riches consumeth the flesh, and [b]the care thereof driveth away sleep.

2 Watching care will not let a man slumber, as a sore disease breaketh sleep,

3 The rich hath great labour in gathering riches together; and [c]when he resteth, he is filled with his delicates.

4 The poor laboureth in his poor estate; and when he leaveth off, he is still needy.

5 [d]He that loveth gold shall not be justified, and he that followeth corruption shall have enough thereof.

6 [e]Gold hath been the ruin of many, and their destruction was present.

7 It is a stumblingblock unto them [f]that sacrifice unto it, and every fool shall be taken therewith.

8 [g]Blessed is the rich that is found without blemish, and hath not [h]gone after gold.

9 Who is he? and we will call him blessed: for wonderful things hath he done among his people.

10 Who hath been tried thereby, and found perfect? then let him glory. Who might offend, and hath not offended? or done evil, and hath not done it?

11 His goods shall be established, and the congregation shall declare his alms.

12 If thou sit at a bountiful table, [i][n][*]be not greedy upon it, and say not, There is much meat on it.

13 Remember that [j]a wicked eye is an evil thing: and what is created more wicked than an eye? therefore it weepeth [*]upon every occasion.

14 [jj]Stretch not thine hand whithersoever it looketh, and thrust it not with him [k]into the dish.

15 [l]Judge not thy neighbour by thyself: and be discreet in every point.

16 [m]Eat as it becometh a man, those things which are set before thee; and devour not, lest thou be hated.

17 Leave off first for manners’ sake; and [n]be not unsatiable, lest thou offend.

18 When thou sittest among many, [jj]reach not thine hand out first of all.

19 A very little is sufficient for a man well nurtured, [*]and he fetcheth not his wind short upon his bed.

20 Sound sleep cometh of moderate eating: he riseth early, and his wits are with him: but the pain of watching, and [o]choler, and pangs of the belly, are with an unsatiable man.

21 And if thou hast been forced to eat, arise, go forth, [p]vomit, and thou shalt have rest.

22 My son, hear me, and despise me not, and [q]at the last thou shalt find as I told thee: [qq]in all thy works be quick, so shall there no sickness come unto thee.

23 [r]Whoso is [s]liberal of his meat, [t]men shall speak well of him; and the report of his good housekeeping will be believed.

24 But against him that is a niggard of his meat the whole city shall murmur; and the testimonies of his niggardness shall not be doubted of.

25 [u]Shew not thy valiantness in wine; for [v]wine hath destroyed many.

26 The furnace proveth the edge by dipping: so doth wine the hearts of the proud by drunkeness.

27 [w]Wine is as good as life to a man, if it be drunk moderately: what life is then to a man that is without wine? [w]for it was made to make men [y]glad.

28 Wine measurably drunk and in season bringeth gladness of the heart, and [y]cheerfulness of the mind:

29 But [x]wine drunken with excess maketh bitterness of the mind, with brawling and quarrelling.

30 Drunkenness increaseth the rage of a fool till he offend: it diminisheth strength, and maketh wounds.

31 [w]Rebuke not thy neighbour at the wine, and despise him not in his [y]mirth: give him no despiteful words, and [z]press not upon him with urging him to drink.

32

1 If thou be made [a]the master of a feast, lift not thyself up, but be among them as one of the rest; take diligent care for them, and so sit down.

2 And when thou hast done all thy office, [b]take thy place, that thou mayest be merry with them, and receive [c]a crown for thy well ordering of the feast.

3 [d]Speak, thou that art the elder, for it becometh thee, but with sound judgment; and hinder not musick.

4 Pour not out words where there is a musician, and [e]shew not forth wisdom out of time.

5 [f]A concert of musick in a banquet of wine is as a signet of [g]carbuncle set in gold.

6 As a signet of an [h]emerald set in a work of gold, so is the melody of musick with pleasant wine.

7 [d]Speak, young man, if there be need of thee: and yet scarcely when thou art twice asked.

8 Let thy speech be short, comprehending much in few words; be as one that knoweth and yet holdeth his tongue.

9 If thou be among great men, make not thyself equal with them; and [i]when ancient men are in place, use not many words.

10 Before the thunder goeth lightning; and before a shamefaced man shall go favour.

11 Rise up betimes, and be not the last; but get thee home without delay.

12 There take thy pastime, and do what thou wilt: but sin not by proud speech.

13 And [j]for these things bless him that made thee, and hath [k]replenished thee with his good things.

14 Whoso feareth the Lord will receive his discipline; and [l]they that seek him early shall find favour.

15 He that seeketh the law [m]shall be filled therewith: but [n]the hypocrite will be offended thereat.

16 They that fear the Lord shall find judgment, and shall kindle justice [o]as a light.

17 [p]A sinful man will not be reproved, but findeth an excuse according to his will.

18 A man of counsel will be considerate; but a strange and proud man is not daunted with fear, even when of himself he hath done without counsel.

19 [q]Do nothing without advice; and [u]when thou hast once done, repent not.

20 Go not in a way wherein thou mayest fall, and [r]stumble not among the stones.

21 Be not confident in a [s]plain way.

22 And [t]beware of thine own children.

23 [u]In every good work trust thy own soul; for this is [x]the keeping of the commandments.

24 He that believeth in the Lord [y]taketh heed to the commandment; and he that trusteth in him [*]shall fare never the worse.

33

1 [a]There shall no evil happen unto him that feareth the Lord; but [b]in temptation even again he will deliver him.

2 A wise man hateth not the law; but [c]he that is an hypocrite therein is [d]as a ship in a storm.

3 A man of understanding trusteth in the law; and the law is faithful unto him, [*]as an oracle.

4 Prepare what to say, and so thou shalt be heard: and bind up instruction, and then make answer.

5 The [*]heart of the foolish is like [d]a cartwheel; and his thoughts are like [d]a rolling axletree.

6 A stallion horse is as a mocking friend, he neigheth under every one that sitteth upon him.

7 Why doth one day excel another, when as all the light of every day in the year is of the sun?

8 By the knowledge of the Lord they were distinguished: and he [e]altered seasons and feasts.

9 Some of them hath he made high days, and [f]hallowed them, and some of them hath he [*]made ordinary days.

10 And all men are from the ground, and [g]Adam was created of earth:

11 In much knowledge the Lord hath divided them, and [e]made their ways diverse.

12 Some of them hath he blessed and exalted and some of them he sanctified, and set near himself: but some of them hath he cursed and brought low, and turned out of their [*]places.

13 [h]As the clay is in the potter’s hand, to fashion it at his pleasure: so man is in the hand of him that made him, to render to them as liketh him best.

14 Good is set against evil, and life against death: so is the godly against the sinner, and the sinner against the godly.

15 So look upon all the works of the most High; and there are [i]two and two, one against another.

16 I awaked up [k]last of all, [l]as one that [*]gathereth after the grapegatherers: by the blessing of the Lord I profited, and tred my [m]winepress like a gatherer of grapes.

17 Consider [n]that I laboured not for myself only, but for all them that seek learning.

18 Hear me, O ye great men of the people, and hearken with your ears, ye rulers of the congregation.

19 Give not [o]thy son and wife, thy brother and friend, power over thee while thou livest, and give not thy goods to another: lest it repent thee, and thou intreat for the same again.

20 As long as thou livest and hast breath in thee, [*]give not thyself over to any.

21 For better it is that thy children should seek to thee, than that thou shouldest [*]stand to their courtesy.

22 In all thy works keep to thyself the preeminence; leave not a stain in thine honour.

23 At the time when thou shalt end thy days, and finish thy life, distribute thine inheritance.

24 [*]Fodder, a wand, and burdens, are for the ass; and bread, correction, and work, for a servant.

25 If thou [p]set thy servant to labour, thou shalt find rest: but if thou let him go idle, he shall seek liberty.

26 A yoke and a collar do bow the neck: [q]so are tortures and torments for an evil servant.

27 Send him to labour, that he be not idle; for idleness teacheth much evil.

28 Set him to work, as is fit for him: if he be not obedient, put on more heavy fetters.

29 But be not excessive toward any; and [r]without discretion do nothing.

30 [s]If thou have a servant, let him be unto thee as thyself, because thou hast bought him [*]with a price.

31 If thou have a servant, entreat him as a brother: for thou hast need of him, as of thine own soul: [r]if thou entreat him evil, and he run from thee, which way wilt thou go to seek him?

34

1 [*]The hopes of a man void of understanding are vain and false: and dreams lift up fools.

2 Whoso [*]regardeth dreams is like him that catcheth at a shadow, and followeth after the wind.

3 The vision of dreams is the resemblance of one thing to another, even as [a]the likeness of a face to a face.

4 [b]Of an unclean thing what can be cleansed? and from that thing which is false what truth can come?

5 Divinations, and soothsayings, and dreams, are vain: and the heart fancieth, as a woman’s heart in travail.

6 [c]If they be not sent from the most High in thy [d]visitation, [*]set not thy heart upon them.

7 For dreams have deceived many, and they have failed that put their trust in them.

8 The law shall be found perfect [e]without lies: and wisdom is perfection to a faithful mouth.

9 A man that hath travelled knoweth many things; and [f]he that hath much experience will declare wisdom.

10 He that hath no experience knoweth little: but he that hath travelled is full of [g]prudence.

11 When I travelled, I saw many things; and I understand more than I can express.

12 I was ofttimes in danger of death: yet I was delivered because of [h]these things.

13 The spirit of those that fear the Lord shall live; for their hope is in him that saveth them.

14 Whoso feareth the Lord shall not fear nor be afraid; for [i]he is his hope.

15 Blessed is the soul of him that feareth the Lord: to whom doth he [j]look? and who is his strength?

16 For [k]the eyes of the Lord are upon them that love him, he is their [l]mighty protection and strong stay, [m]a defence from heat, and a cover from the sun at noon, a preservation from stumbling, and an help from falling.

17 He raiseth up the soul, and lighteneth the eyes: he giveth health, life, and blessing.

18 He that sacrificeth of a thing [n]wrongfully gotten, his offering is ridiculous; and [*]the gifts of unjust men are not accepted.

19 [o]The most High is not pleased with the offerings of the wicked; [p]neither is he pacified for sin by the multitude of sacrifices.

20 [q]Whoso bringeth an offering of the goods of the poor doeth as one that killeth the son before his father’s eyes.

21 The bread of the needy is their life: he that defraudeth him thereof is a man of blood.

22 He that taketh away his neighbour’s living slayeth him; and [r]he that defraudeth the labourer of his hire is a bloodshedder.

23 When one buildeth, and another pulleth down, what profit have they then but labour?

24 When one prayeth, and another curseth, whose voice will the [s]Lord hear?

25 [t]He that washeth himself after the touching of a dead body, if he touch it again, what availeth his washing?

26 So is it with a man [u]that fasteth for his sins, and [x]goeth again, and doeth the same: who will hear his prayer? or what doth his humbling profit him?

35

1 [a]He that keepeth the law bringeth offerings enough: he that [b]taketh heed to the commandment [c]offereth a peace offering.

2 He that requiteth a goodturn [d]offereth fine flour; and he that giveth alms [e]sacrificeth praise.

3 To depart from wickedness is a thing pleasing to the Lord; and to forsake unrighteousness is a propitiation.

4 [f]Thou shalt not appear empty before the Lord.

5 For all these things are to be done because of the commandment.

6 The offering of the righteous maketh the altar fat, and the [g]sweet savour thereof is before the most High.

7 The sacrifice of a just man is acceptable, and [h]the memorial thereof shall never be forgotten.

8 Give the Lord his honour with a [i]good eye, and diminish not [j]the firstfruits of thine hands.

9 In all thy gifts [k]shew a cheerful countenance, and [*]dedicate thy [l]tithes with gladness.

10 [m]Give unto the most High according as he hath enriched thee; and [m]as thou hast gotten, give with a [i]cheerful eye.

11 [n]For the Lord recompenseth, and will give thee [o]seven times as much.

12 [*]Do not think to corrupt with gifts; for [p]such he will not receive: and [q]trust not to unrighteous sacrifices; for [r]the Lord is judge, and [s]with him is no respect of persons.

13 [s]He will not accept any person against a poor man, but will hear the prayer of the oppressed.

14 He will not despise the supplication of [t]the fatherless; nor [t]the widow, when she poureth out her complaint.

15 Do not the tears run down the widow’s cheeks? and is not [t][u]her cry against him that causeth them to fall?

16 He that serveth the Lord shall be accepted with favour, and his prayer shall reach unto the clouds.

17 The prayer of the humble pierceth the clouds: and till it come nigh, he will not be comforted; and [v]will not depart, till the most High shall behold to judge righteously, and execute judgment.

18 For [w]the Lord will not be slack, neither will the Mighty [x]be patient toward them, till he have smitten in sunder the loins of the unmerciful, and repayed vengeance to the heathen; till he have taken away the multitude of the [*]proud, and broken the sceptre of the unrighteous;

19 Till he have [y]rendered to every man according to his deeds, and to the works of men according to their devices; till he have judged the cause of his people, and made them to rejoice in his mercy.

20 Mercy is [*]seasonable in the time of affliction, as [z]clouds of rain in the time of drought.

36

1 [a]Have mercy upon us, O Lord God of all, and behold us:

2 And send thy fear upon all the nations that seek not after thee.

3 [b]Lift up thy hand [*]against the strange nations, and let them see thy power.

4 As [c][d]thou wast sanctified in us before them: so [d]be thou magnified among them before us.

5 And [d][e]let them know thee, as we have known thee, that there is no God but only thou, O God.

6 Shew new signs, and [f]make other strange wonders: glorify [e]thy hand and thy right arm, that they may set forth thy wondrous works.

7 Raise up indignation, and [b]pour out wrath: take away the adversary, and destroy the enemy.

8 [g]Make the time short, remember the [*]covenant, and let them declare thy wonderful works.

9 Let [h]him that escapeth be consumed by the rage of the fire; and let them perish that oppress the people.

10 [i]Smite in sunder the heads of the rulers of the heathen, that say, There is none other but we.

11 [k]Gather all the tribes of Jacob together, and [l]inherit thou them, as from the beginning.

12 O Lord, have mercy upon [m]the people that [n]is called by thy name, and upon Israel, whom thou hast named [o]thy firstborn.

13 O be merciful unto Jerusalem, thy [p]holy city, [q]the place of thy rest.

14 Fill Sion [*]with thine unspeakable oracles, and thy people with thy glory:

15 Give testimony unto those that thou hast possessed from the beginning, and raise up [*]prophets that have been in thy name.

16 Reward [r]them that wait for thee, and let thy prophets be found faithful.

17 O Lord, hear the prayer of thy [*]servants, according to [s]the blessing of Aaron over thy people, that [e][t]all they which dwell upon the earth may know that thou art the Lord, [u]the eternal God.

18 [v]The belly devoureth all meats, yet is one meat better than another.

19 [w]As the palate tasteth divers kinds of venison: so doth an heart of understanding false speeches.

20 A froward heart causeth heaviness: but [x]a man of experience will recompense him.

21 [v]A woman will receive every man, yet is one daughter better than another.

22 The beauty of a woman cheereth the countenance, and [y]a man loveth nothing better.

23 If there be kindness, meekness, and comfort, in her tongue, then is not her husband [z]like [*]other men.

24 He that getteth a wife beginneth [*]a possession, [a]a help [z]like unto himself, and a pillar of rest.

25 [b]Where no hedge is, there the possession is spoiled: and he that hath no wife will wander up and down mourning.

26 Who will trust [c]a thief well appointed, that skippeth from city to city? so who will believe a man that hath no house, and [d]lodgeth wheresoever the night taketh him?

37

1 Every friend saith, I am his friend also: but there is a friend, which is only a friend in name.

2 Is it not a grief unto death, when a companion and friend is turned to an enemy?

3 O wicked imagination, whence camest thou in to cover the earth with deceit?

4 [a]There is a companion, which rejoiceth in the prosperity of a friend, but in the time of trouble will be against him.

5 There is a companion, which helpeth his friend for the belly, and taketh up the buckler [*]against the enemy.

6 Forget not thy friend in thy mind, and be not unmindful of him [b]in thy riches.

7 Every counsellor extolleth counsel; but there is some that counselleth for himself.

8 Beware of a counsellor, and know before [*]what need he hath; for he will counsel for himself; lest he [c]cast the lot upon thee,

9 And say unto thee, Thy way is good: and afterward he stand on the other side, to see what shall befall thee.

10 Consult not with one that suspecteth thee: and hide thy counsel from such as envy thee.

11 Neither consult with [d]a woman touching her of whom she is jealous; neither with a coward in matters of war; nor [e]with a merchant concerning exchange; nor with a buyer of selling; nor with an envious man of thankfulness; nor with an unmerciful man touching kindness; nor with the slothful for any work; nor with an hireling for a year of finishing work; nor with an idle servant of much business: [f]hearken not unto these in any matter of counsel.

12 But be continually with a godly man, whom thou knowest to keep the commandments of the Lord, whose, mind is [g]according to thy mind, and [h]will sorrow with thee, if thou shalt miscarry.

13 And let the counsel of thine own heart stand: for there is no man more faithful unto thee than it.

14 For a man’s mind is sometime wont to tell him more than [i]seven [k]watchmen, that sit above in an high tower.

15 And above all this pray to the most High, that he will direct thy way in truth.

16 Let reason go before every enterprize, and counsel before every action.

17 The countenance is a sign of changing of the heart.

18 [l]Four manner of things appear: good and evil, life and death: but [m]the tongue ruleth over them continually.

19 There is one that is [n]wise and teacheth many, and [o]yet is [p]unprofitable to himself.

20 There is one that sheweth wisdom in words, and is hated: he shall be destitute of all [*]food.

21 For grace is not given, him from the Lord, because he is deprived of all wisdom.

22 [p]Another is wise to himself; and the fruits of understanding are commendable in his mouth.

23 A wise man instructeth his people; and the fruits of his understanding fail not.

24 A wise man shall be filled with blessing; and all they that see him [q]shall count him happy.

25 The days of the life of man may be numbered: but the days of Israel are innumerable.

26 A wise man [r]shall inherit [*][s]glory among his people, and his name shall be perpetual.

27 My son, prove thy soul in thy life, and see what is evil for it, and give not that unto it.

28 For [t]all things are not profitable for all men, neither hath every soul pleasure in every thing.

29 [u]Be not unsatiable in any dainty thing, nor too greedy upon meats:

30 For [*]excess of meats bringeth [x]sickness, and [x]surfeiting will turn into choler.

31 By surfeiting have many perished; but he that taketh heed prolongeth his life.

38

1 Honour a physician with the [a]honour due unto him for the [l]uses which ye may have of him: [b]for the Lord hath created him.

2 For of the most High cometh healing, and he shall receive [*][c]honour of the king.

3 The skill of the physician shall lift up his head: and in the sight of great men he shall be in admiration.

4 The Lord hath created medicines out of the earth; and he that is wise will not abhor them.

5 [d]Was not the water made sweet with wood, that the virtue thereof might be known?

6 And he hath given men skill, that he might be honoured in his marvellous works.

7 With such doth he heal men, and taketh away their pains.

8 Of such doth the apothecary make a [e]confection; and of his works there is no end; and from him is [f]peace over all the earth,

9 My son, in thy sickness be not negligent: but [g]pray unto the Lord, and he will make thee whole.

10 [h]Leave off from sin, and order thine hands aright, and [i]cleanse thy heart from all wickedness.

11 Give a [j]sweet savour, and a memorial of [j]fine flour; and make a fat offering, [*]as not being.

12 Then [k]give place to the physician, [b]for the Lord hath created him: let him not go from thee, for thou hast [l]need of him.

13 There is a time when in their hands there is [m]good success.

14 For they shall also pray unto the Lord, that he would prosper that, which they give for [f]ease and [*]remedy to prolong life.

15 [n]He that sinneth before his Maker, let him fall into the hand of the physician.

16 My son, [o]let tears fall down over the dead, and begin to lament, as if thou hadst suffered great harm thyself; and then cover his body according to the custom, and neglect not his burial.

17 Weep bitterly, and make great moan, and use lamentation, as he is worthy, and that a day or two, lest thou be evil spoken of: and then comfort thyself for thy heaviness.

18 For [p]of heaviness cometh death, and [q]the heaviness of the heart breaketh strength.

19 In [r]affliction also sorrow remaineth: and the life of the poor is the curse of the heart.

20 Take no heaviness to heart: drive it away, and [s]remember the last end.

21 Forget it not, for there is no turning again: thou shalt not do him good, but hurt thyself.

22 Remember [*]my judgment: for thine also shall be so; yesterday for me, and to day for thee.

23 [t]When the dead is at rest, let his remembrance rest; and be comforted for him, when his Spirit is departed from him.

24 The wisdom of a [u]learned man cometh by opportunity of leisure: and he that hath little business shall become wise.

25 How can he get wisdom that holdeth the plough, and that glorieth in the goad, that driveth oxen, and is occupied in their labours, and whose [v]talk is [*]of bullocks?

26 He giveth his mind to make furrows; and is diligent to give the kine fodder.

27 So every carpenter and [w]workmaster, that laboureth night and day: and they that cut and grave seals, and are diligent to [x]make great variety, and [y]give themselves to counterfeit imagery, and [y]watch to finish a work:

28 [z]The smith also sitting by the anvil, and considering the iron work, the vapour of the fire wasteth his flesh, and he fighteth with the heat of the furnace: the noise of the hammer and the anvil is ever in his ears, and his eyes look still upon the pattern of the thing that he maketh; [y]he setteth his mind to finish his work, and [y]watcheth to polish it [a]perfectly:

29 So doth the potter sitting at his work, and [b]turning the wheel about with his feet, who is alway carefully set at his work, and maketh all his work by number;

30 He fashioneth the clay with his arm, and [*]boweth down his strength before his feet; [y]he applieth himself to lead it over; and [y]he is diligent to make clean the furnace:

31 All these trust to their hands: and every one is wise in his work.

32 Without these cannot a city be inhabited: and they shall not dwell where they will, nor go up and down:

33 They shall not be sought for in publick counsel, nor sit high in the congregation: they shall not sit on the judges’ seat, nor understand the sentence of judgment: they cannot declare justice and judgment; and [c]they shall not be found where parables are spoken.

34 But they will maintain the state of the world, and all their desire is in the work of their craft.

39

1 But he that giveth his mind to the law of the most High, and is occupied in the meditation thereof, will seek out the wisdom of all the ancient, and [a]be occupied in prophecies.

2 He will keep the sayings of the renowned men: and [aa]where subtil parables are, he will be there also.

3 He will seek out the secrets of [b]grave sentences, and be conversant in [c]dark parables.

4 He shall serve among great men, and [d]appear before princes: he will travel through strange countries; for he hath tried the good and the evil among men.

5 He will give his heart [e]to resort early to the Lord that made him, and will pray before the most High, and will open his mouth in prayer, and make supplication for his sins.

6 [f]When the great Lord will, [e]he shall be filled with the spirit of understanding: he shall [g]pour out wise sentences, and give thanks unto the Lord in his prayer.

7 He shall direct his counsel and knowledge, and in his secrets shall he meditate.

8 He shall shew forth that which he hath learned, and shall glory in the law of the covenant of the Lord.

9 [h]Many shall commend his understanding; and so long as the world endureth, [i]it shall not be blotted out; [i]his memorial shall not depart away, and his name shall live from generation to generation.

10 [j]Nations shall shew forth his wisdom, [j]and the congregation shall declare his praise.

11 If he die, he shall leave a greater name than a thousand: and if he live, he shall [*]increase it.

12 Yet have I more to say, which [k]I have thought upon; for I am filled as the moon at the full.

13 Hearken unto me, ye holy children, and bud forth [l]as a rose growing by the [*]brook of the field:

14 And [m]give ye a sweet savour as [n]frankincense, and flourish as a [o]lily, send forth a smell, and sing a song of praise, bless the Lord in all his works.

15 Magnify his name, and shew forth his praise with the songs of your lips, and with [p]harps, and in praising him ye shall say after this manner:

16 [q]All the works of the Lord are exceeding good, and [r]whatsoever he commandeth shall be accomplished in due season.

17 [s]And none may say, What is this? wherefore is that? for at time convenient they shall all be sought out: [t]at his commandment the waters stood as an heap, and at the words of his mouth the receptacles of waters.

18 [u]At his commandment is done whatsoever pleaseth him; and [x]none can hinder, when he will save.

19 [y]The works of all flesh are before him, and nothing can be hid from his eyes.

20 He seeth from everlasting to everlasting; and there is nothing [z]wonderful before him.

21 A man need not to say, What is this? wherefore is that? for he hath made all things for their uses.

22 His blessing covered the dry land as a river, and [a]watered it as a flood.

23 As he hath turned the waters into saltness: so shall the heathen inherit his wrath.

24 As [b]his ways are plain unto the holy; so are they stumblingblocks unto the wicked.

25 For the good are good things created from the beginning: [c]so evil things for sinners.

26 [d]The principal things for the whole use of man’s life are [d]water, fire, iron, and salt, [d]flour of wheat, honey, milk, and [e]the blood of the grape, and oil, and [d]clothing.

27 [f]All these things are for good to the godly: so to the sinners they are turned into evil.

28 There be spirits that are created for vengeance, which in their fury lay on sore strokes; in the time of destruction they pour out their force, and appease the wrath of him that made them.

29 [k]Fire, and [k]hail, and [g]famine, and [g]death, all these were created for vengeance;

30 [h]Teeth of [i]wild beasts, and [i]scorpions, [i][*]serpents, and [g]the sword punishing the wicked to destruction.

31 [k]They shall rejoice in his commandment, and they shall be ready upon earth, when need is; and when their time is come, they shall not transgress his word.

32 Therefore from the beginning I was resolved, and [l]thought upon these things, and have left them in writing.

33 [m]All the works of the Lord are good: and he will give every needful thing in due season.

34 So that a man cannot say, This is worse than that: for in time they shall all be well approved.

35 And therefore praise ye the Lord with the whole heart and mouth, and bless the name of the Lord.

40

1 [a]Great travail is created for every man, and an heavy yoke is upon the sons of Adam, from the day that they go out of their mother’s womb, [b]till the day that they return to the mother of all things.

2 Their imagination of [c]things to come, and the day of death, trouble their thoughts, and cause [c]fear of heart;

3 [d]From him that sitteth on a throne of glory, unto him that is humbled in [e]earth and ashes;

4 [d]From him that weareth [f]purple and a crown, [*]unto him that is clothed with a linen frock.

5 Wrath, and envy, trouble, and unquietness, fear of death, and anger, and strife, and in the time of rest upon his bed his night sleep, do change his knowledge.

6 A little or nothing is his rest, and afterward he is in his sleep, as in a day of keeping watch, [g]troubled in the vision of his heart, as if he were escaped out of a battle.

7 When all is safe, he awaketh, and marvelleth that the fear was nothing.

8  Such things happen unto all flesh, [h]both man and beast, and that is [i]sevenfold more upon sinners.

9 [k]Death, and bloodshed, strife, and [k]sword, [l]calamities, [k]famine, [m]tribulation, and the scourge;

10 [n]These things are created for the wicked, and [o]for their sakes came the flood.

11 [b]All things that are of the earth shall turn to the earth again: and that which is [p]of the waters doth return into the sea.

12 All [*]bribery and injustice shall be blotted out: but true dealing shall endure for ever.

13 The goods of the unjust [q]shall be dried up like a river, and [r]shall vanish with noise, like a great thunder in rain.

14 While [s]he openeth his hand he shall rejoice: so shall transgressors come to nought.

15 The children of the ungodly shall not bring forth many branches: but are as [t]unclean roots upon a hard rock.

16 [u]The [v]weed growing upon every water and bank of a river [w]shall be pulled up before all grass.

17 Bountifulness is as [*]a most fruitful garden, and mercifulness endureth for ever.

18 To labour, and [x]to be content with that a man hath, is a sweet life: but he that findeth [y]a treasure is above them both.

19 Children and the building of a city continue a man’s name: but a blameless wife is counted above them both.

20 [z]Wine and musick rejoice the heart: but the love of wisdom is above them both.

21 The pipe and the [a]psaltery make sweet melody: but a pleasant tongue is above them both.

22 Thine eye desireth favour and beauty: but more than both corn while it is green.

23 A friend and companion never meet amiss: but above both is a wife with her husband.

24 Brethren and help are against time of trouble: but [b]alms shall deliver more than them both.

25 Gold and silver make the foot stand sure: but counsel is esteemed above them both.

26 [c]Riches and strength lift up the heart: but [d]the fear of the Lord is above them both: there is no want in the fear of the Lord, and it needeth not to seek help.

27 The fear of the Lord is [*]a fruitful garden, and [e]covereth him above all glory.

28 My son, lead not a beggar’s life; for [f]better it is to die than to beg.

29 The life of him that dependeth on another man’s table is not to be counted for a life; for he [g]polluteth himself with other men’s meat: but a wise man well nurtured will beware thereof.

30 Begging is sweet in the mouth of the shameless: but in his belly there shall burn a fire.

41

1 O death, how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that liveth at rest in his possessions, unto the man [a]that hath nothing to vex him, and that hath prosperity in all things: yea, unto him that is yet able to receive meat!

2 O death, acceptable is thy sentence unto the needy, and unto him whose strength faileth, [aa]that is now in the last age, and [*]is vexed with all things, and to him that [b]despaireth, and [c]hath lost patience!

3 Fear not the sentence of death, remember them that have been before thee, and that come after; for this is the sentence of the Lord over all flesh.

4 And why art thou against the pleasure of the most High? there is no inquisition in the grave, whether thou have lived ten, or an hundred, or a thousand years.

5 The children of sinners are abominable children, and they that are conversant in the dwelling of the ungodly.

6 [d]The inheritance of sinners’ children shall perish, and their posterity shall have a perpetual reproach.

7 The children will complain of an ungodly father, [e]because they shall be reproached for his sake.

8 Woe be unto you, ungodly men, which have forsaken the law of the most high God! for if ye increase, it shall be to your destruction:

9 And if ye be born, ye shall be born to a curse: and if ye die, a curse shall be your portion.

10 [f]All that are of the earth shall turn to earth again: so the ungodly shall go from a curse to destruction.

11 The mourning of men is about their bodies: but [g]an ill name of sinners shall be blotted out.

12 Have regard to thy name; for [h]that shall continue with thee above a thousand great treasures of gold.

13 A good life hath but [i]few days: but a good name endureth for ever.

14 My children, keep discipline in peace: for [k]wisdom that is hid, and a treasure that is not seen, what profit is in them both?

15 [l]A man that hideth his foolishness is better [l]than a man that hideth his wisdom.

16 Therefore be shamefaced according to my word: [m]for it is not good to retain all shamefacedness; [n]neither is it altogether approved in every thing.

17 Be ashamed of whoredom [o]before father and mother: and of a lie [o]before a prince and a mighty man;

18 Of an offence [o]before a judge and ruler; of iniquity [o]before a congregation and people; of unjust dealing [o]before thy partner and friend;

19 And [p]of theft [o]in regard of the place where thou sojournest, and [o]in regard of [q]the truth of God and his covenant; and [o]to lean with thine elbow upon the meat; and [o]of scorning to give and take;

20 And of silence [o]before them that salute thee; and [o]to look upon an harlot;

21 And [o]to turn away thy face from thy kinsman; or [o]to take away a portion or a gift; or [o]to [r]gaze upon [s]another man’s wife.

22 Or to be overbusy with his maid, and come not near her bed; or [t]of upbraiding speeches [o]before friends; and [u]after thou hast given, upbraid not;

23 Or [o]of [x]iterating and speaking again that which thou hast heard; and [o]of [y]revealing of secrets.

24 So shalt thou be truly shamefaced and [z]find favour before all men.

42

1 [a]Of these things be not thou ashamed, and [b]accept no person to sin thereby:

2 [c]Of the law of the most High, and his covenant; and of judgment to justify the ungodly;

3 [*]Of reckoning with thy partners and [*]travellers; or [*]of the gift of the heritage of friends;

4 [d]Of exactness of balance and weights; or [e]of getting much or little;

5 And of merchants’ [*]indifferent selling; of much [f]correction of children; and [g]to make the side of an evil servant to bleed.

6 Sure keeping is good, where an evil wife is; and shut up, where many hands are.

7 [h]Deliver all things in number and weight; and put all in writing that thou [*]givest out, or receivest in.

8 [i]Be not ashamed to [*]inform the unwise and foolish, and [k]the extreme aged [*]that contendeth with those that are young: thus shalt thou be truly learned, and approved of all men living.

9 [l]The father waketh for the daughter, when no man knoweth; and the care for her taketh away sleep: when she is young, lest she [m]pass away the flower of her age; and being married, lest she should be hated:

10 In her virginity, [n]lest she should be defiled and gotten with child in her father’s house; and having an husband, lest she should misbehave herself; and when she is married, lest she should be barren.

11 [o]Keep a sure watch over a shameless daughter, lest she make thee a laughingstock to thine enemies, and a byword in the city, and a reproach among the people, and make thee ashamed before the multitude.

12 Behold not every body’s beauty, and [p]sit not in the midst of women.

13 For from garments cometh a moth, and [q]from women wickedness.

14 Better is the [*]churlishness of a man than a [r]courteous woman, a woman, I say, which bringeth shame and reproach.

15 I will now remember the works of the Lord, and declare the things that I have seen: [s]In the words of the Lord are his works.

16 The sun that giveth light looketh upon all things, and the work thereof is full of the glory of the Lord.

17 [t]The Lord hath not given power to the saints to declare all his marvellous works, which the [u]Almighty Lord firmly settled, that whatsoever is might be established for his glory.

18 He seeketh out the deep, and the heart, and considereth their [v]crafty devices: for [*]the Lord knoweth all that may be known, and he beholdeth [w]the signs of the world.

19 [x]He declareth the things that are past, and for to come, and revealeth the steps of hidden things.

20 [y]No thought escapeth him, neither any word is hidden from him.

21 [z]He hath garnished [z]the excellent works of his wisdom, and he is from everlasting to everlasting: [a]unto him may nothing be added, neither can he be diminished, and [b]he hath no need of any counsellor.

22 Oh how desirable are all his works! and that a man may see even to a spark.

23 All these things live and remain for ever for all uses, and [c]they are all obedient.

24 [d]All things are double one against another: and he hath made nothing imperfect.

25 One thing establisheth the good or another: and who shall be filled with beholding his glory?

43

1 The pride of the height, the clear firmament, the beauty of heaven, with his glorious shew;

2 The sun when it appeareth, declaring at his rising a marvellous [*]instrument, the work of the most High:

3 At noon it parcheth the country, and who can abide the burning heat thereof?

4 A man blowing a furnace is in works of heat, but the sun burneth the mountains three times more; breathing out fiery vapours, and sending forth bright beams, it dimmeth the eyes.

5 Great is the Lord that made it; and at his commandment [*][a]runneth hastily.

6 [b]He made the moon also to serve in her season for a declaration of times, and [c]a sign of the world.

7 [d]From the moon is the sign of feasts, a light that decreaseth in her perfection.

8 The month is called [e]after her name, increasing wonderfully in her changing, being an instrument of the [f]armies above, shining in the firmament of heaven;

9 The beauty of heaven, the glory of the stars, an ornament giving light [g]in the highest places of the Lord.

10 At the commandment of the Holy One they will stand in their order, and never faint [h]in their watches.

11 [i]Look upon the [k]rainbow, and praise him that made it; very beautiful it is in the brightness thereof.

12 It compasseth the heaven about with a glorious circle, and [l]the hands of the most High have bended it.

13 [m]By his commandment he [n]maketh the snow to fall aplace, and sendeth swiftly the lightnings of his judgment.

14 Through this [o]the treasures are opened: and clouds fly forth as fowls.

15 By his great power he maketh the clouds firm, and [p]the hailstones are broken small.

16 [q]At his sight the mountains are shaken, and at his will the south wind bloweth.

17 [r]The noise of the thunder maketh the earth [*]to tremble: so doth the northern storm and the whirlwind: [m]as birds flying he scattereth the snow, and the falling down thereof is as the lighting of [s]grasshoppers:

18 The eye marvelleth at the beauty of the whiteness thereof, and the heart is astonished at the raining of it.

19 [m]The hoarfrost also as salt he poureth on the earth, and being congealed, [*]it lieth on the top of sharp stakes.

20 When the cold north wind bloweth, and the water is congealed into ice, it abideth upon every [t]gathering together of water, and clotheth the water as with a breastplate.

21 It devoureth the mountains, and burneth the wilderness, and consumeth the grass as fire.

22 A present remedy of all is a mist coming speedily, a dew coming [*]after heat refresheth.

23 By his counsel he appeaseth the deep, and planteth islands therein.

24 [u]They that [v]sail on the sea tell of the danger thereof; and when we hear it with our ears, we marvel thereat.

25 [w]For therein be [x]strange and wondrous works, variety of all kinds of beasts and whales created.

26 By him the end of them hath [y]prosperous success, and [z]by his word all things consist.

27 We may speak much, and yet [a]come short: wherefore in sum, he is all.

28 [a]How shall we be able to magnify him? for he is great above all his works.

29 [b]The Lord is terrible and very great, and marvellous is his power.

30 When ye glorify the Lord, exalt him as much as ye can; for even yet will he far exceed: and when ye exalt him, put forth all your strength, and be not weary; for ye can never go far enough.

31 [c]Who hath [d]seen him, that he might tell us? and who can magnify him as he is?

32 [e]There are yet hid greater things than these be, for we have seen but a few of his works.

33 For the Lord hath made all things; and to the godly hath he given wisdom.

44

1 [*]Let us now praise famous men, and our fathers that begat us.

2 The Lord hath wrought great glory by them through his great power from the beginning.

3 Such as did bear rule in their kingdoms, men renowned for their power, giving counsel by their understanding, and [a]declaring prophecies:

4 Leaders of the people by their counsels, and by their knowledge of learning meet for the people, wise and eloquent are their instructions:

5 [b]Such as found out musical tunes, and recited [*]verses in writing:

6 Rich men furnished with [c]ability, living peaceably in their habitations:

7 All these were honoured in their generations, and were the glory of their times.

8 There be of them, that have left a name behind them, that their praises might be reported.

9 And some there be, which have no memorial; [d]who are perished, [e]as though they had never been; and are become as though they had never been born; and their children after them.

10 But [f]these were merciful men, whose righteousness hath not been forgotten.

11 [g]With their seed shall continually remain a good inheritance, and their children are [h]within the covenant.

12 [i]Their seed standeth fast, and their children [*]for their sakes.

13 Their seed shall remain for ever, and [j]their glory shall not be blotted out.

14 Their bodies are buried in peace; but their name liveth for evermore.

15 [k]The people will tell of their wisdom, and [k]the congregation will shew forth their praise.

16 [l]Enoch pleased the Lord, and was translated, being an example of repentance to all generations.

17 [m]Noah was found perfect and righteous; in the time of wrath he was taken in exchange for the world; therefore was he left as a remnant unto the earth, when the flood came.

18 [n]An everlasting covenant was made with him, that all flesh should perish no more by the flood.

19 [o]Abraham was a great father of many people: in glory was there none like unto him;

20 Who kept the law of the most High, and was [h]in covenant with him: [p]he established the covenant in his flesh; and [q]when he was proved, he was found faithful.

21 Therefore [r]he assured him by an oath, that he would bless the nations in his seed, and that he would multiply him as the dust of the earth, and exalt his seed as the stars, and [s]cause them to inherit from sea to sea, and [t]from the river unto the utmost part of the land.

22 [u]With Isaac did he establish likewise for Abraham his father’s sake the blessing of all men, and the covenant, 23 And [x]made it rest upon the head of Jacob. He acknowledged him in his blessing, and [y]gave him an heritage, and [z]divided his portions; among the twelve tribes did he part them.

45

1 And he brought [a]out of him a merciful man, which [aa]found favour in the sight of all flesh, even Moses, [b]beloved of God and men, [bb]whose memorial is blessed.

2 He made him like to the glorious saints, and magnified him, so that his enemies stood in fear of him.

3 By his words [c]he caused the wonders to cease, and [d]he made him glorious in the sight of kings, and [e]gave him a commandment for his people, and [f]shewed him part of his glory.

4 He sanctified him in his [ff]faithfulness and [g]meekness, and chose him out of all men.

5 He made him to hear his voice, and [h]brought him into the dark cloud, and [e]gave him commandments before his face, even the law of life and knowledge, that he might teach Jacob his covenants, and Israel his judgments.

6 He exalted [i]Aaron, an holy man like unto him, even his brother, [j]of the tribe of Levi.

7 An everlasting covenant he made with him and [k]gave him the priesthood among the people; [*]he beautified him with comely ornaments, and clothed him with a robe of glory.

8 He put upon him perfect glory; and strengthened him with [l]rich [*]garments, with [m]breeches, with [n]a long robe, and [n]the ephod.

9 And he compassed him with [o]pomegranates, and with many golden bells round about, [p]that as he went there might be a sound, and [pp]a noise made that might be heard in the temple, for a memorial to the children of his people;

10 [q]With an holy garment, with gold, and [r]blue silk, and [r][s]purple, the work of the embroiderer, [s]with a breastplate of judgment, and [t]with Urim and Thummim;

11 With [s]twisted scarlet, the work of the cunning workman, [u]with precious stones graven like seals, and set in gold, the work of the jeweller, with a writing engraved for a memorial, after the number of the tribes of Israel.

12 [q]He set [x]a crown of gold upon the [y]mitre, wherein was engraved Holiness, an ornament of honour, a [l]costly work, the desires of the eyes, goodly and beautiful.

13 Before him there were none such, neither did ever any stranger put them on, [z]but only his children and his children’s children perpetually.

14 [a]Their sacrifices shall be wholly consumed every day twice continually.

15 [b]Moses [c]consecrated him, and anointed him with holy oil: this was appointed unto him by an everlasting covenant, and to his seed, [d]so long as the heavens should remain, that they should minister unto him, and execute the office of the priesthood, and [e]bless the people in his name.

16 [f]He chose him out of all men living to offer [g]sacrifices to the Lord, incense, and a [h]sweet savour, for a memorial, to make reconciliation for his people.

17 [i]He gave unto him his commandments, and authority in the statutes of judgments, that he should teach Jacob the testimonies, and inform Israel in his laws.

18 [k]Strangers conspired together against him, and [l]maligned him in the wilderness, even the men that were of Dathan’s and Abiron’s side, and the congregation of Core, with fury and wrath.

19 [m]This the Lord saw, and it displeased him, and in his wrathful indignation were they consumed: he did wonders upon them, to consume them with the fiery flame.

20 [n]But he made Aaron more honourable, and gave him an heritage, and [o]divided unto him the firstfruits of the increase; especially he prepared bread in abundance:

21 [p]For they eat of the sacrifices of the Lord, which he gave unto him and his seed.

22 [q]Howbeit in the land of the people [qq]he had no inheritance, neither had he any portion among the people: [q]for the Lord himself is his portion and inheritance.

23 [r]The third in glory is Phinees the son of Eleazar, because he had zeal in the fear of the Lord, and stood up with good courage of heart:[s] when the people were turned back, and made reconciliation for Israel.

24 Therefore was there [r]a covenant of peace made with him, that he should be the chief of the sanctuary and of his people, and that he and his posterity [r]should have the dignity of the priesthood for ever:

25 [t]According to the covenant made with David son of Jesse, of the tribe of Juda, that the inheritance of the king should be to his posterity alone: so the inheritance of Aaron should also be unto his seed.

26 God give you wisdom in your heart [i]to judge his people in righteousness, that their good things be not abolished, and that their glory may endure for ever.

46

1 [a]Jesus the son a Nave was valiant in the wars, and was the successor of Moses in [b]prophecies, who [c]according to his name was made great for the saving of the [d]elect of God, and taking vengeance of the enemies that rose up against them, that he might [e]set Israel in their inheritance.

2 How great glory gat he, when he did lift up his hands, and [f]stretched out his sword against the cities!

3 Who before him so stood to it? for the Lord himself [g]brought his enemies unto him.

4 [h]Did not the sun go back by his means? and was not one day as long as two?

5 He called upon the most high [i]Lord, when the enemies pressed upon him on every side; and the great Lord heard him.

6 And [j]with hailstones of mighty power he made the battle to fall violently upon the nations, and in the descent of Beth-horon he destroyed them that resisted, that the nations might know all their strength, because he fought in the sight of the Lord, and he followed the [i]Mighty One.

7 In the time of Moses also he did a work of mercy, [k]he and Caleb the son of Jephunne, in that they withstood the congregation, and withheld the people from sin, and appeased the wicked murmuring.

8 And of [l]six hundred thousand people on foot, [m]they two were preserved to bring them in to the heritage, even unto [n]the land that floweth with milk and honey.

9 [o]The Lord gave strength also unto Caleb, which remained with him unto his old age: so that he entered upon the high places of the land, and his seed obtained it for an heritage:

10 [o]That all the children of Israel might see that it is good [p]to follow the Lord.

11 And concerning the judges, every one by name, [q]whose heart went not a whoring, nor departed from the Lord, [r]let their memory be blessed.

12 [s]Let their bones flourish out of [t]their place, and let the name of them that were honoured be continued upon their children.

13 Samuel, the prophet of the Lord, [u]beloved of his Lord, established a kingdom, and [v]anointed princes over his people.

14 By the law of the Lord he judged the congregation, and the Lord had respect unto Jacob.

15 [w]By his faithfulness he was found a true prophet, and by his word he was known to be faithful in vision.

16 [x]He called upon the [i]mighty Lord, [y]when his enemies pressed upon him on every side, when [z]he offered the sucking lamb.

17 [a]And the Lord thundered from heaven, and with a great noise made his voice to be heard.

18 And he destroyed the rulers of the [b]Tyrians, and all the princes of the [c]Philistines.

19 And before his long [d]sleep [e]he made protestations in the sight of the Lord and his anointed, I have not taken any man’s goods, so much as a shoe: and [f]no man did accuse him.

20 And [g]after his death he prophesied, and shewed the king his end, and lifted up his voice from the earth in prophecy, to blot out the wickedness of the people.

47

1 And after him rose up [a]Nathan to prophesy in the time of David.

2 As is [b]the fat taken away from the peace offering, [c]so was David chosen out of the children of Israel.

3 [*]He played with [d]lions as with kids, and with [d]bears as with lambs.

4 [e]Slew he not a giant, when he was yet but young? and did he not take away reproach from the people, when he lifted up his hand with the stone in the sling, and beat down the boasting of Goliath?

5 For he called upon the most high Lord; and he gave him strength in his right hand to slay that mighty warrior, and [f]set up the horn of his people.

6 [g]So the people honoured him with ten thousands, and praised him in the blessings of the Lord, in that he gave him a crown of glory.

7 For [h]he destroyed the enemies on every side, and [*]brought to nought [i]the Philistines his adversaries, and [k]brake their horn in sunder unto this day.

8 In all his works he praised the Holy One most high with words of glory; [l]with his whole heart he sung songs, and loved him that made him.

9 [m]He set singers also before the altar, that by their voices they might make sweet melody, and daily sing praises in their songs.

10 He beautified their feasts, and set in order the solemn times [*]until the end, that they might praise his holy name, and that the temple might sound from morning.

11 [n]The Lord took away his sins, and [f]exalted his horn for ever: [o]he gave him a covenant [*]of kings, and a throne of glory in Israel.

12 After him rose up a wise son, and for his sake [p]he dwelt at large.

13 [q]Solomon reigned in a peaceable time, and was honoured; for God made all quiet round about him, [q]that he might build an house in his name, and prepare his sanctuary for ever.

14 [r]How wise wast thou in thy youth and, [s]as a flood, filled with understanding!

15 Thy soul covered the whole earth, and thou filledst it with [t]dark parables.

16 [u]Thy name went [u]far unto the islands; and for thy peace thou wast beloved.

17 [v]The countries marvelled at thee for thy songs, and [t]proverbs, and [t]parables, and interpretations.

18 By the name of the Lord God, which is called the Lord God of Israel, [w]thou didst gather gold as [x]tin and didst multiply silver as [x]lead.

19 [y]Thou didst bow thy loins unto women, and [*]by thy body thou wast brought into subjection.

20 [z]Thou didst stain thy honour, and pollute thy seed: so that thou broughtest wrath upon thy children, and wast grieved for thy folly.

21 So [a]the kingdom was divided, and out of Ephraim ruled a rebellious kingdom.

22 [b]But the Lord will never leave off his mercy, neither shall any of his works perish, neither will he abolish the posterity of [c]his elect, and the seed of him that loveth him he will not take away: wherefore he gave a remnant unto Jacob, and [d]out of him a root unto David.

23 [e]Thus rested Solomon with his fathers, and of his seed he left behind him Roboam, even the foolishness of the people, and one that had no understanding, who [f]turned away the people through his counsel. There was also [g]Jeroboam the son of Nebat, [h]who caused Israel to sin, and shewed Ephraim the way of sin:

24 And their sins were multiplied exceedingly, [i]that they were driven out of the land.

25 For they sought out all wickedness, till the vengeance came upon them.

48

1 Then stood up [a]Elias the prophet as fire, and his word [b]burned like a lamp.

2 [c]He [d]brought a sore famine upon them, and by his zeal he diminished their number.

3 [c]By the word of the Lord he [*]shut up the heaven, and also [d]three times brought down fire.

4 O Elias, [dd]how wast thou honoured in thy wondrous deeds! and who may glory like unto thee!

5 [e]Who didst raise up a dead man from death, and his soul from the [*]place of the dead, by the word of the most High:

6 [f]Who broughtest kings to destruction, and [g]honorable men from their [*][g]bed:

7 [h]Who heardest the rebuke of the Lord in Sinai, and in [i]Horeb the judgment of vengeance:

8 [k]Who annointedst kings to take revenge, and [k]prophets to succeed after [*]him:

9 [l]Who was taken up in a whirlwind of fire, and in a chariot of fiery horses:

10 Who wast [*]ordained for reproofs in their times, to pacify the wrath of the Lord’s judgment, before it brake forth into fury, and [m]to turn the heart of the father unto the son, and [n]to [*]restore the tribes of Jacob.

11 Blessed are they that saw thee, and [*]slept in love; for we shall surely live.

12 [l]Elias it was, who was covered with a whirlwind: and [o]Eliseus was filled with his spirit: whilst he lived, [p]he was not moved with the presence of any prince, neither could any bring him into subjection.

13 [*][q]No word could overcome him; and [r]after his [s]death his body prophesied.

14 He did wonders in his life, and at his death were his works marvellous.

15 For all this the people repented not, neither departed they from their sins, [t]till they were spoiled and carried out of their land, and were scattered through all the earth: [u]yet there remained a small people, and a ruler in the house of David:

16 Of whom some did that which was pleasing to God, and some multiplied sins.

17 [v]Ezekias [w]fortified his city, and [x]brought in water into the midst thereof: he digged the hard rock with iron, and made [x]wells for waters.

18 In his time [y]Sennacherib came up, and sent Rabsaces, and lifted up his hand against Sion, and boasted proudly.

19 Then trembled their hearts and hands, and they [z]were in pain, as women in travail.

20 [a]But they called upon the Lord which is merciful, and [b]stretched out their hands toward him: and immediately the Holy One heard them out of heaven, and delivered them by the [*]ministry of Esay.

21 [c]He smote the host of the Assyrians, and [c]his angel destroyed them.

22 [d]For Ezekias had done the thing that pleased the Lord, and was strong in the ways of David his father, [e]as Esay the prophet, who was great and [f]faithful in his vision, had commanded him.

23 [g]In his time the sun went backward, and he lengthened the king’s life.

24 He saw by an excellent spirit what should come to pass at the last, and [h]he comforted them that mourned in Sion.

25 He shewed what should come to pass for ever, and secret things or ever they came.

49

1 The remembrance of [a]Josias is like [b]the composition of the perfume that is made by the art of the apothecary: it is sweet as honey in all mouths, and as [c]musick at a banquet of wine.

2 He [*]behaved himself uprightly in the conversion of the people, and [d]took away the abominations of iniquity.

3 [e]He directed his heart unto the Lord, and in the time of the ungodly he established the worship of God.

4 All, except David and Ezekias and Josias, were defective: for they forsook the law of the most High, even the kings of Juda failed.

5 Therefore [f]he gave their [*]power unto others, and their glory to a strange nation.

6 [g]They burnt the chosen city of the sanctuary, and made the streets desolate, [*][h]according to the prophecy of Jeremias.

7 For [i]they entreated him evil, who nevertheless was a prophet, [k]sanctified in his mother’s womb, [l]that he might root out, and afflict, and destroy; and [l]that he might build up also, and plant.

8 It was [m]Ezekiel who saw the glorious vision, which was shewed him upon [n]the chariot of the cherubims.

9 For he made mention of the [o]enemies under the figure of the rain, and [*]directed them that went right.

10 And of [p]the twelve prophets [q]let the memorial be blessed, and [r]let their bones flourish again out of their place: for they comforted Jacob, and delivered them by assured hope.

11 How shall we magnify [s]Zorobabel? even he was [t]as a signet on the right hand:

12 So was [u]Jesus the son of Josedec: who in their time builded the house, and set up an holy temple to the Lord, which was prepared for everlasting glory.

13 And among the [v]elect was Neemias, whose renown is great, [w]who raised up for us the walls that were fallen, and set up the gates and the bars, and raised up our ruins again.

14 But upon the earth was no man created like [x]Enoch; for he was taken from the earth.

15 Neither was there a young man born like [y]Joseph, [z]a governor of his brethren, [a]a stay of the people, [b]whose bones were regarded of the Lord.

16 [c]Sem and [d]Seth were in great honour among men, and so was [e]Adam above every living thing in creation.

50

1 Simon [*]the high priest, the son of Onias, who in his life repaired the house again, and in his days fortified the temple:

2 And by him was built from the foundation the double height, the high fortress of the wall about the temple:

3 In his days the [a]cistern to receive water, being in compass as the sea, was covered with plates of brass:

4 He took care of the temple that it should not fall, and fortified the city against besieging:

5 [b]How was he honoured in the midst of the people in his coming out of [*]the sanctuary!

6 He was as [c]the morning star in the midst of a cloud, and as the moon at the full:

7 [d]As the sun shining upon the temple of the most High, and as the [e]rainbow giving light in the bright clouds:

8 And as the flower of [f]roses in the spring of the year, as [g]lilies by the rivers of waters, and as the branches of the [h]frankincense tree in the time of summer:

9 As [i]fire and [h]incense in the censer, and as a vessel of beaten gold set with all manner of precious stones:

10 And as a fair [k]olive tree budding forth fruit, and as a [k]cypress tree which groweth up to the clouds.

11 [l]When he put on the robe of honour, and was clothed with the perfection of glory, [m]when he went up to the holy altar, [l]he made the garment of holiness honourable.

12 When he took the portions out of the priests’ hands, he himself stood by the hearth of the altar, compassed about, as a young [n]cedar in Libanus; and as [o]palm trees compassed they him round about.

13 So were all the sons of Aaron in their glory, and the oblations of the Lord in their hands, before all the congregation of Israel.

14 And finishing the service at the altar, that he might adorn the offering of the most high [p]Almighty,

15 He stretched out his hand to the cup, and poured of [q]the blood of the grape, [r]he poured out at the foot of the altar [r][s]a sweetsmelling savour unto the most high King of all.

16 Then shouted the sons of Aaron, and [t]sounded the [*]silver trumpets, and [u]made a great noise to be heard, [t]for a remembrance before the most High.

17 Then all the people together hasted, and fell down to the earth upon their faces to worship their Lord God [p]Almighty, the most High.

18 The singers also sang praises with their voices, with great variety of sounds was there made sweet melody.

19 And the people besought the Lord, the most High, by prayer before him that is merciful, till the solemnity of the Lord was ended, and they had finished his service.

20 Then he went down, and lifted up his hands over the whole congregation of the children of Israel, [v]to give the blessing of the Lord with his lips, and to rejoice in his name.

21 And they bowed themselves down to worship the second time, that they might receive a blessing from the most High.

22 Now therefore [w]bless ye the God of all, which only doeth wondrous things every where, [x]which exalteth our days from the womb, and dealeth with us according to his mercy.

23 He grant us joyfulness of heart, and that peace may be in our days in Israel for ever:

24 That he would confirm his mercy with us, and deliver us at his time!

25 There be [y]two manner of nations which my heart abhorreth, and the third is no nation:

26 [z]They that sit upon the mountain of Samaria, and [a]they that dwell among the Philistines, and [b]that foolish people that dwell in [c]Sichem.

27 Jesus the son of Sirach of Jerusalem hath written in this book the instruction of understanding and knowledge, who out of his heart [d]poured forth wisdom.

28 [e]Blessed is he that shall be exercised in these things; and he that layeth them up in his heart shall become wise.

29 For if he do them, he shall be strong to all things: [f]for the light of the Lord leadeth him, who giveth wisdom to the godly. [w]Blessed be the name of the Lord for ever. Amen, Amen.

51

A Prayer of Jesus the son of Sirach.

1 I will thank thee, O Lord and King, and praise thee, O [a]God my Saviour: I do give praise unto thy name:

2 For thou art my defender and helper, and has preserved my body from destruction, and [b]from the snare of the slanderous tongue, and from the lips that [c]forge lies, and has been mine helper against mine adversaries:

3 And hast delivered me, according to the multitude of thy mercies and greatness of thy name, from [*]the teeth of them that were ready to devour me, and out of the hands of such as sought after my life, and from the manifold afflictions which I had;

4 From the choking of fire on every side, and from the midst of the fire which I kindled not;

5 From the depth of the belly of hell, from an unclean tongue, and from lying words.

6 By an accusation to the king from an unrighteous tongue my soul drew near even unto death, my life was near to the hell beneath.

7 [d]They compassed me on every side, and there was no man to help me: I looked for the succour of men, but there was none.

8 Then thought I upon thy mercy, O Lord, and upon thy acts of old, how thou deliverest [e]such as wait for thee, and savest them out of the hands of the enemies.

9 Then lifted I up my supplications from the earth, and prayed for deliverance from death.

10 I called upon the Lord, [f]the Father of my Lord, that he would not leave me in the days of my trouble, and [g]in the time of the proud, when there was no help.

11 I will praise thy name continually, and will sing praises with thanksgiving; [*]and so my prayer was heard:

12 For thou savedst me from destruction, and deliveredst me from the evil time: therefore will I give thanks, and praise thee, and bless they name, O Lord.

13 When I was yet young, or ever I [*]went abroad, I desired wisdom openly in my prayer.

14 I prayed for her before the temple, and will seek her out even to the end.

15 Even from the flower till the grape was ripe hath my heart delighted in her: my foot went the right way, from my youth up sought I after her.

16 I bowed down mine ear a little, and received her, and gat much learning.

17 I [gg]profited therein, therefore will I ascribe glory unto him that giveth me wisdom.

18 For I purposed to do after her, and earnestly I followed that which is good; so shall I not be confounded.

19 My soul hath wrestled with her, and in my doings I was exact: I stretched forth my hands to the heaven above, and bewailed my ignorances of her.

20 I directed my soul unto her, and I found her in pureness: [*]I have had my heart joined with her from the beginning, therefore shall I not be foresaken.

21 My [*]heart was troubled in seeking her: therefore have I gotten a good possession.

22 The Lord hath given me a tongue for my reward, and I will praise him therewith.

23 Draw near unto me, ye unlearned, and dwell in the house of learning.

24 Wherefore are ye slow, and what say ye to these things, seeing your souls are very thirsty?

25 I opened my mouth, and said, Buy her for yourselves [h]without money.

26 [i]Put your neck [i]under the yoke, and let your soul receive instruction: [k]she is hard at hand to find.

27 Behold with your eyes, [l]how that I have but little labour, and have gotten unto me much rest.

28 [m]Get learning [n]with a great sum of money, and get [n]much gold by her.

29 [o]Let your soul rejoice in his mercy, and be not ashamed of his praise.

30 [p]Work your work betimes, and in his time [q]he will give you your reward.

* Some refer this Prologue to Athanasius, because it is found in his Synopsis.

* Or, collected.

a See Prov. 1. 6.

b ch. 44. 1–50. 24.

c Heb. 11. 5.

d ch. 51. 1–

e ch. 51. 13–30.

* ch. 50. 27.

a Luke 24. 44.

* Or, of another nation.

a Luke 24. 44.

b See Acts 21. 40.

a Luke 24. 44.

* Gr. prophecics. ch. 36. 15 marg. 1 Tim. 1. 18.

* Or, excellency. So 2 Macc. 15. 13. Matt. 6. 26. & 10. 31. & 12. 12 in the Gk.

* About B.C. 133.

* Or, help of learning.

c Acts 13. 17 (Gk.).

* 1.1 Before CHRIST about 200.

a 1.1 1 Kin. 3. 9. & 4. 29. See Jam. 1. 5.

c 1.1 See John 1. 1.

b 1.2 So ch. 18. 10.

c 1.4 See John 1. 1.

d 1.5 Baruch 3. 12. So 2 Esdr. 14. 47.

e 1.6 See Wisd. 9. 13. ver. 20. So Wisd. 3. 15. Comp. Wisd. 15. 3.

f 1.9 Comp. Wisd. 11. 20.

g 1.11 ch. 6. 31. & 15. 6 in the Gk. So 1 Thess. 2. 19.

h 1.13 ch. 2. 3 (Gk.). & 3. 26. & 6. 28. & 12. 12. & 14. 7. & 30. 1, 10 (Gk.). & 31. 22. So Ps. 37. 37.

* 1.13 Or, shall be blessed.

i 1.14 See Prov. 1. 7.

j 1.15 So Prov. 8. 23.

k 1.15 2 Chr. 20. 20 (Gk.).

i 1.16 See Prov. 1. 7.

l 1.17 So Ps. 112. 3.

m 1.19 See ch. 50. 27.

e 1.20 See Wisd. 9. 13. ver. 20. So Wisd. 3. 15. Comp. Wisd. 15. 3.

n 1.20 Prov. 3. 2, 16.

* 1.22 Or, escape punishment. See ch. 23. 11.

o 1.23 Ps. 37. 7–9. So ch. 2. 7.

p 1.24 ch. 39. 9.

q 1.25 See Prov. 1. 6.

r 1.26 So Matt. 19. 17.

s 1.26 See James 1. 5.

* 1.28 Or, Be not disobedient to. ch. 2. 15. Rom. 2. 8 in the Gk.

t 1.28 See James 1. 6, 8.

u 1.29 So ch. 4. 29. & 5. 13. See James 1. 19.

x 1.30 See Matt. 23. 12.

y 1.30 Prov. 5. 14. So Prov. 26. 26.

z 1.30 So Acts 13. 10.

a 2.1 Comp. Matt. 4. 1. 2 Tim. 3. 12. 1 Pet. 4. 12.

b 2.2 ch. 12. 15. Heb. 11. 27 (Gk.).

* 2.2 Or, haste not.

c 2.2 ch. 3. 28. & 5. 8. & 10. 13. & 23. 11. & 25. 14. & 38. 19. & 40. 9 in the Gk. So ver. 4. & 46. 3. & 48. 2. 2 Pet. 2. 5.

d 2.3 ch. 24. 24. See Deut. 10. 20.

e 2.3 See ch. 1. 13.

c 2.4 ch. 3. 28. & 5. 8. & 10. 13. & 23. 11. & 25. 14. & 38. 19. & 40. 9 in the Gk. So ver. 4. & 46. 3. & 48. 2. 2 Pet. 2. 5.

f 2.4 Gk. as ver. 5.

g 2.5 See Prov. 17. 3.

h 2.5 ch. 3. 17 (Gk.).

f 2.5 Gk. as ver. 5.

i 2.6 Ps. 37. 3, 5.

j 2.7 So Ps. 37. 7. ch. 1. 23.

k 2.7 See Deut. 5. 32.

l 2.10 Comp. Ps. 37. 25.

m 2.10 Ps. 30. 2. & 145. 18.

n 2.11 Prayer of Manasses. See Ps. 86. 15.

o 2.11 See Ps. 130. 4.

p 2.12 ch. 22. 18. So Rev. 21. 8. See Wisd. 9. 14.

q 2.12 ch. 25. 23. Heb. 12. 12 in the Gk.

r 2.12 Comp. 1 Kin. 18. 21.

s 2.14 ch. 41. 2. Comp. Heb. 10. 36. James 1. 3, 4.

t 2.14 Ex. 32. 34. So ch. 16. 18.

u 2.15 John 14. 23. So 1 John 2. 5.

x 2.17 Ps. 10. 17.

y 2.18 See Ex. 18. 4.

z 2.18 2 Sam. 24. 14.

a 2.18 ch. 18. 5.

a 3.2 ver. 8. ch. 7. 27. See Exod. 20. 12.

* 3.2 Or, judgment.

b 3.4 1 Tim. 6. 19 (Gk.).

a 3.6 ver. 8. ch. 7. 27. See Exod. 20. 12.

c 3.6 Matt. 11. 28. 1 Cor. 16. 18. 2 Cor. 7. 13. Philem. 7, 20. So Rom. 15. 32 in the Gk.

a 3.8 ver. 8. ch. 7. 27. See Exod. 20. 12.

d 3.9 Gen. 27. 27–29. & 49. 2, &c. Comp. Deut. 33. 1.

e 3.11 Prov. 17. 6.

* 3.13 Or, in all thine f ability.

g 3.14 See Deut. 25. 9.

h 3.15 Matt. 16. 2 (Gk.).

i 3.17 ch. 2. 5 (Gk.).

k 3.18 So Phil. 2. 3.

l 3.18 Prov. 3. 4. So ch. 41. 24. & 45. 1.

m 3.19 Ps. 25. 9, 14. Comp. ch. 4. 18.

n 3.21 So Prov. 25. 27? Rom. 12. 3.

o 3.23 2 Thess. 3. 11 (Gk.).

p 3.26 See ch. 1. 13.

q 3.27 ch. 5. 5 (Gk.).

* 3.28 Or, The proud man is not healed by his punishment.

r 3.28 See ch. 2. 2.

s 3.30 So Ps. 41. 1, 2. Matt. 5. 7. See Dan. 4. 27. & Tobit 4. 7.

t 3.31 Comp. Luke 16. 9.

a 4.1 See Lev. 19. 13.

a 4.1 See Lev. 19. 13.

aa 4.3 So ch. 7. 11.

b 4.3 Prov. 3. 27, 28.

c 4.4 ver. 1. See Tobit 4. 7.

d 4.4 Matt. 5. 42.

d 4.5 Matt. 5. 42.

* 4.5 Or, him that asketh.

e 4.5 So ver. 3.

f 4.5 Comp. Prov. 28. 27.

g 4.6 So Deut. 15. 9.

h 4.6 See Prov. 14. 31.

i 4.9 Jer. 22. 3. See Isai. 1. 17.

j 4.9 Comp. Ex. 18. 21 (Heb. & Gk.).

k 4.10 Job 29. 16. & 31. 17, 18. See James 1. 27.

l 4.10 Luke 6. 35.

m 4.11 Prov. 4. 8.

n 4.11 So Matt. 11. 19. Luke 7. 35.

o 4.12 See Prov. 3. 18.

p 4.12 So Prov. 8. 17. ch. 6. 36. & 32. 14. & 39. 5 in the Gk.

q 4.12 ch. 1. 11 (Gk.), 12. So ver. 18 (Gk.).

r 4.13 Prov. 3. 35. ch. 37. 26 (text).

* 4.14 Or, in the sanctuary.

s 4.15 See Wisd. 3. 8.

t 4.17 Comp. Matt. 7. 13, 14.

q 4.18 ch. 1. 11 (Gk.), 12. So ver. 18 (Gk.).

u 4.18 See ch. 3. 19.

w 4.20 So Eph. 5. 16.

x 4.20 ch. 41. 16.

y 4.21 ch. 20. 22. & 42. 1–8.

z 4.21 ch. 41. 17–24.

a 4.22 ch. 42. 1. See Deut. 10. 17.

* 4.23 Gr. in time of saving.

b 4.26 James 5. 16.

* 4.26 Or, And strive not against the stream.

a 4.27 ch. 42. 1. See Deut. 10. 17.

c 4.29 See ch. 1. 29.

d 4.30 See Eph. 6. 9.

e 4.31 Acts 20. 35.

* 4.31 Or, give. Gk. as Matt. 20. 8.

a 5.1 ver. 8. ch. 13. 11. & 34. 2, 15. & 35. 12. & 37. 11. Acts 3. 5. 1 Tim. 4. 16 in the Gk.

b 5.1 So 1 Tim. 6. 17.

c 5.1 Luke 12. 15, 19.

d 5.2 See Prov. 3. 5.

e 5.4 See Eccles. 8. 11.

f 5.4 So 2 Pet. 3. 9.

g 5.4 See Exod. 34. 7. So ch. 16. 13. 1 Thess. 5. 3.

h 5.5 ch. 3. 27 (Gk.). So ch. 21. 1.

i 5.6 ch. 16. 11.

j 5.7 See Isai. 55. 6.

k 5.7 See 1 Thess. 5. 3.

a 5.8 ver. 8. ch. 13. 11. & 34. 2, 15. & 35. 12. & 37. 11. Acts 3. 5. 1 Tim. 4. 16 in the Gk.

l 5.8 See Prov. 10. 2.

m 5.8 See Ezek. 7. 19.

n 5.8 See ch. 2. 2.

o 5.9 See James 1. 8.

p 5.9 ver. 14. ch. 6. 1. & 28. 13. Comp. ver. 10.

o 5.10 See James 1. 8.

p 5.10 ver. 14. ch. 6. 1. & 28. 13. Comp. ver. 10.

q 5.11 Jam. 1. 19.

r 5.11 So ch. 8. 9. See 1 Pet. 3. 15.

r 5.12 So ch. 8. 9. See 1 Pet. 3. 15.

s 5.12 See Wisd. 8. 12.

t 5.13 So Prov. 18. 21. Matt. 12. 37.

u 5.13 See ch. 1. 29.

x 5.14 ch. 21. 28. & 28. 13. See 2 Cor. 12. 20.

y 5.14 Comp. Prov. 26. 20, 22.

z 5.14 Comp. Prov. 6. 30.

p 5.14 ver. 14. ch. 6. 1. & 28. 13. Comp. ver. 10.

a 6.1 See ch. 5. 9.

b 6.2 See Rom. 12. 16.

c 6.3 See Isai. 56. 3. So Luke 23. 31.

* 6.5 Gr. A sweet throat. Comp. Ps. 119. 103.

d 6.5 So ch. 20. 13.

* 6.7 Or, get him in the time of trouble.

e 6.8 ver. 10 (Gk.).

f 6.10 ch. 37. 4, 5.

e 6.10 ver. 10 (Gk.).

g 6.13 Gk. as Matt. 7. 15. & 10. 17. & 16. 6, 11, &c.

h 6.13 ver. 8–12.

i 6.15 Esther 7. 4 (Engl.). Matt. 16. 26. Mark 8. 37 in the Gk.

k 6.18 Matt. 19. 20. 1 Macc. 2. 66.

l 6.19 So James 5. 7. Comp. 2 Tim. 2. 6.

m 6.19 So ch. 50. 27. Comp. Matt. 11. 30.

n 6.20 So Prov. 17. 16. & 18. 2.

* 6.20 Or, heart. Prov. 6. 32. & 11. 12 in the Heb.

o 6.21 Zech. 12. 3.

p 6.22 ch. 43. 8. & 46. 1.

* 6.24 Or, collar. Prov. 1. 9 (Gk.).

q 6.25 So ch. 51. 26. Matt. 11. 29.

r 6.26 So Deut. 6. 5.

r 6.26 So Deut. 6. 5.

s 6.27 Wisd. 8. 21 (Gk.).

t 6.28 See ch. 1. 13.

u 6.28 ch. 22. 13. Jer. 6. 16 (Heb.). Matt. 11. 29 (Gk.).

w 6.29 ver. 24.

w 6.29 ver. 24.

* 6.30 Or, a ribband of blue silk. Numb. 15. 38.

x 6.31 See ch. 1. 11.

y 6.32 Gk. as Prov. 13. 1. & 14. 8, 15, 18. & 22. 3. & 28. 2. See ch. 21. 12. marg.

z 6.34 So ch. 8. 9.

a 6.35 See Prov. 1. 6.

b 6.36 See ch. 4. 12.

c 6.37 Ps. 1. 2.

d 6.37 1 Thess. 3. 13. So Ps. 31. 24.

a 7.1 So 1 Pet. 3. 13.

b 7.3 See Prov. 22. 8.

c 7.3 ch. 20. 12. & 35. 11. & 40. 8. See Ps. 79. 12.

d 7.5 Job 9. 2, 20. Ps. 143. 2. Eccles. 7. 16. Luke 18. 11.

e 7.6 See Lev. 19. 15.

f 7.6 See Rom. 14. 13.

g 7.7 Comp. 1 Kings 12. 11.

h 7.8 So Isai. 5. 18.

i 7.9 See Prov. 21. 27.

k 7.10 So Luke 18. 1.

l 7.10 See Tobit 4. 7.

m 7.11 So ch. 4. 3. Comp. Prov. 17. 5.

n 7.11 So ch. 11. 14. See 1 Sam. 2. 7.

* 7.12 Gr. Plow not.

o 7.14 ch. 32. 9?

p 7.14 See Eccles. 5. 2.

* 7.14 Or, vain repetition. Matt. 6. 7 (Engl.).

q 7.15 Gen. 3. 19, 23.

* 7.15 Gr. created. ch. 39. 25.

qq 7.17 So ch. 18. 21.

r 7.17 Isai. 66. 24. So ch. 18. 24.

rr 7.18 See ch. 27. 1. marg.

s 7.18 Phil. 4. 3 (Gk.).

t 7.18 See 1 Kings 9. 28.

u 7.19 So ch. 26. 1–3.

v 7.19 Prov. 31. 10.

w 7.20 ch. 33. 30, 31.

x 7.20 Lev. 19. 13. Deut. 24. 14, 15. ch. 34. 22.

w 7.21 ch. 33. 30, 31.

y 7.21 Gk. as ver. 25.

z 7.21 Ex. 21. 2. Deut. 15. 9, 12.

a 7.22 Deut. 25. 4. Prov. 27. 23–27.

b 7.23 See Eph. 6. 4.

c 7.23 ch. 30. 12. Comp. Lam. 3. 27.

d 7.24 ch. 42. 9–11.

y 7.25 Gk. as ver. 25.

* 7.26 Or, hateful.

e 7.27 See ch. 3. 2.

f 7.27 Tobit 4. 3.

g 7.29 Jude 16 (Gk.).

h 7.30 See Deut. 6. 5.

i 7.30 Deut. 12. 19.

i 7.31 Deut. 12. 19.

k 7.31 See Prov. 3. 9.

l 7.31 Lev. 7. 1–7.

m 7.31 Ex 29. 27, 28. Lev. 7. 34.

n 7.31 Lev. 2. 1–10 & 6. 14–16. & 7. 9.

o 7.31 Numb. 5. 9. & 18. 8–19, 28. 2 Chr 31. 6. Neh. 10. 35, 36, 38. So ch. 35. 8, 9.

p 7.32 See Deut. 1##. 8.

* 7.32 Or, thy liberality. See 2 Cor. 9. 5.

q 7.32 So Deut. 15. 10.

r 7.33 See Tobit 4. 17.

s 7.34 ch. 37. 12. Rom. 12. 15.

t 7.35 Matt. 25. 36, 39, 43.

u 7.36 ch. 28. 6. & 38. 20. See Deut. 32. 29. So ch. 18. 24.

a 8.2 Comp. ch. 28. 8. Matt. 5. 25.

b 8.2 ch. 31. 6.

* 8.3 Or, of an evil tongue. ch. 9. 18.

c 8.3 Prov. 26. 20, 21. So ch. 28. 10. Comp. James 3. 6.

d 8.5 2 Cor. 2. 6, 7. Gal. 6. 1, 2.

e 8.5 ch. 9. 5 (Gk.).

f 8.6 Lev. 19. 32.

g 8.9 So ch. 6. 34.

h 8.9 So ch. 5. 11. See 1 Pet. 3. 15.

i 8.10 ch. 28. 11.

j 8.11 So Wisd. 14. 21 (Gk.).

* 8.11 Or, for thy mouth.

k 8.12 Comp. ch. 29. 4.

l 8.13 See Prov. 6. 1.

* 8.14 Or, opinion.

m 8.15 Gen. 4. 8.

n 8.16 Prov. 22. 24 ?

o 8.17 Comp. ch 9. 14.

p 8.17 Comp. Prov. 11. 13. & 20. 19.

a 9.1 See Deut. 13. 6.

b 9.2 Gk. as ch. 3. 13 marg. & 11. 12. & 14. 13. & 44. 6. Comp. ch. 45. 8, 12.

c 9.3 Prov. 7. 5, 10, 23.

* 9.4 Or, playeth upon instruments. Gk. as 1 Sam. 16. 23, &c.

d 9.5 See Job 31. 1.

e 9.5 So Prov. 6. 25.

f 9.5 Gk. as ch. 8. 5.

g 9.8 See Matt. 5. 28.

h 9.8 ch. 51. 13 marg.

i 9.8 See Job 31. 12.

j 9.9 ch. 26. 22. & 41. 21. Rom. 7. 2 in the Gk.

k 9.10 So Luke 5. 39.

l 9.11 See Ps. 37. 1.

m 9.11 ch. 18. 12. See Ps. 37. 38.

n 9.12 Comp. Rom. 1. 32.

o 9.14 Comp. ch. 8. 17.

p 9.15 So Ps. 1. 2.

q 9.18 ch. 8. 3.

a 10.2 Prov. 29. 12.

b 10.4 See Ps. 75. 7. So ver. 8.

c 10.5 1 Esdr. 8. 6 marg.

* 10.5 Or, face. Comp. Ex. 34. 33.

d 10.5 ch. 38. 24 (Gk.). 1 Cor. 1. 20.

e 10.6 Lev. 19. 17. Matt. 18. 21.

b 10.8 See Ps. 75. 7. So ver. 8.

f 10.9 See ch. 17. 32.

g 10.9 Comp. 1 John 3. 17.

h 10.10 So 1 Macc. 2. 62, 63. 2 Macc. 9. 11, 12.

h 10.11 So 1 Macc. 2. 62, 63. 2 Macc. 9. 11, 12.

i 10.11 Isai. 14. 11.

j 10.13 See ch. 50. 27.

k 10.13 See ch. 2. 2.

l 10.14 See 1 Sam. 2. 8.

m 10.17 So Ps. 9. 6.

n 10.18 Comp. ch. 11. 16 (Gk.).

o 10.18 See Job 14. 1.

* 10.19 Or, unstable generation.

* 10.21 Or, principality. Ephes. 1. 21.

p 10.22 Comp. Jer. 9. 23.

q 10.23 Acts 13. 7 (Gk.).

r 10.23 Acts 22. 22 (Gk.).

s 10.25 Prov. 17. 2.

t 10.25 Prov. 15. 5. Comp. 2 Sam. 12. 13.

u 10.27 Prov. 12. 9.

x 10.28 So Matt. 16. 26. Mark 8. 37.

u 10.30 Prov. 12. 9.

* 11.1 Or, of the lowly. ch. 3. 20. & 10. 15. & 12. 5.

a 11.1 Gen. 41. 40. Dan. 6. 3. ch. 39. 4.

b 11.3 ch. 29. 21. & 39. 26 (Gk.).

c 11.4 Acts 12. 21.

d 11.4 Ps. 139. 14.

* 11.5 Gr. tyrants. See Wisd. 14. 16.

e 11.5 See Job 2. 8. Comp. Ezra 9. 3.

f 11.6 1 Sam. 15. 28. Esth. 7. 10.

g 11.7 So Deut. 13. 14. & 17. 6, 7.

h 11.8 See Prov. 18. 13.

* 11.9 Or, in the judgment of sinners. Comp. Ps. 1. 1.

i 11.10 Phil. 3. 12.

i 11.10 Phil. 3. 12.

* 11.10 Or, escape hurt.

k 11.11 Prov. 10. 3. Matt. 19. 22. 1 Tim. 6. 9.

l 11.12 See ch. 9. 2.

m 11.12 Job 42. 10. Prov. 10. 22.

n 11.14 So 1 Sam. 2. 7. Job 1. 21. & 2. 10. ch. 7. 11.

o 11.15 Ezek. 28. 4.

p 11.16 Comp. ch. 10. 18 (Gk.).

q 11.19 See ch. 31. 3. Comp. ver. 24.

q 11.19 See ch. 31. 3. Comp. ver. 24.

* 11.19 Or, pass.

r 11.19 Ps. 49. 10. ch. 14. 4, 15. See Ps. 39. 6.

s 11.20 2 Kin. 23. 3 (Gk.). So Matt. 10. 22.

t 11.21 Eccles. 5. 8.

* 11.22 Or, for a reward.

u 11.23 See Mal. 3. 14. Comp. Job 2. 9. Tobit 2. 14.

q 11.24 See ch. 31. 3. Comp. ver. 24.

v 11.25 Comp. ch. 18. 25.

w 11.26 ch. 18. 24 (Gk.).

x 11.28 See ch. 37. 24.

y 11.32 John 18. 18. & 21. 9 in the Greek.

z 11.34 See John 16. 32 marg.

a 12.1 Comp. Matt. 7. 6.

b 12.2 So Luke 6. 35.

c 12.3 See Tobit 4. 7.

d 12.4 ver. 7. So Gal. 6. 10.

d 12.4 ver. 7. So Gal. 6. 10.

e 12.4 Comp. Matt. 5. 44.

e 12.5 Comp. Matt. 5. 44.

f 12.5 ch. 11. 34.

g 12.6 Comp. Jude 6.

d 12.7 ver. 7. So Gal. 6. 10.

d 12.7 ver. 7. So Gal. 6. 10.

e 12.7 Comp. Matt. 5. 44.

* 12.10 Or, brass.

h 12.11 So Ps. 10. 10.

i 12.11 ch. 19. 26, 27 (Gk.).

j 12.11 Baruch 6. 24.

k 12.11 Wisd. 7. 26. 1 Cor. 13. 12 in the Gk.

j 12.11 Baruch 6. 24.

l 12.11 Comp. James 5. 3 (Gk.).

ll 12.12 See ch. 1. 13.

m 12.12 See ch. 14. 1.

n 12.13 So Ps. 58. 5. See Eccles. 10. 11.

* 12.14 Or, mingled.

o 12.15 See ch. 2. 2.

p 12.16 Prov. 26. 24, 25. See Ps. 28. 3.

q 12.16 Comp. Jer. 41. 6, 7.

q 12.16 Comp. Jer. 41. 6, 7.

* 12.17 Or, supplant. Comp. Ps. 41. 9.

r 12.18 ch. 13. 7. See Job 16. 4.

s 12.18 See Job 27. 23.

t 12.18 ch. 13. 25.

a 13.1 Comp. Deut. 7. 2.

* 13.2 Gr. This shall smite against it, and be broken.

b 13.3 So Prov. 18. 23.

c 13.5 Gk. as ver. 7.

c 13.7 Gk. as ver. 7.

d 13.7 See ch. 12. 18.

* 13.8 Or, by thy simplicity.

e 13.8 See 1 Esdr. 3. 20 (Engl.).

f 13.10 Comp. Prov. 25. 17.

* 13.11 Or, Forbear not.

g 13.11 See ch. 5. 1.

* 13.11 Or, But.

h 13.17 Comp. 2 Cor. 6. 14.

i 13.17 So Prov. 29. 27.

k 13.19 See Job 6. 5.

l 13.19 Amos 8. 4. See Ps. 14. 4.

m 13.22 So Eccles. 9. 15, 16. ch. 26. 28.

n 13.22 ch. 19. 17. & 38. 12 in the Gk.

o 13.23 Job 29. 9.

p 13.25 ch. 12. 18.

q 13.25 See Prov. 15. 13.

r 13.26 Eccles. 12. 12.

a 14.1 ch. 25. 8.

a 14.1 ch. 25. 8.

b 14.1 ch. 19. 16. See Jam. 3. 2.

c 14.1 ch. 12. 12. & 20. 21 marg. Susanna 10 (Gk.). Acts 2. 37.

* 14.1 Or, sorrow.

d 14.2 So Rom. 14. 22. 1 John 3. 21.

e 14.4 ch. 11. 19. ver. 15. See Ps. 39. 6.

f 14.7 See ch. 1. 13.

g 14.9 Prov. 27. 20.

p 14.9 ch. 12. 18.

h 14.10 Prov. 23. 6, 7. ch. 31. 13. See Matt. 6. 23.

i 14.10 See Tobit 4. 7.

k 14.11 Prov. 3. 9.

l 14.13 See Tobit 4. 7. So Luke 14. 13.

m 14.13 See ch. 9. 2.

n 14.13 Supplied from ch. 7. 32. & 15. 16.

o 14.14 See Eccles. 2. 24.

* 14.14 Or, the feast-day. Eccles. 7. 14 (Gk.).

p 14.14 Gk. as ver. 9.

e 14.15 ch. 11. 19. ver. 15. See Ps. 39. 6.

q 14.17 Ps. 102. 26. Heb. 1. 11. See Job 14. 2.

r 14.17 Gen. 2. 17. & 3. 19.

s 14.18 See Matt. 16. 17.

t 14.18 Eccles. 1. 4.

u 14.20 Ps. 1. 2.

x 14.21 See Wisd. 6. 12.

y 14.23 ch. 21. 23. Luke 24. 12. John 20. 5, 11 in the Gk.

z 14.23 So Prov. 8. 34.

* 14.24 Or, stake. ch. 26. 12 marg. & 27. 2. Gk. as Judg. 4. 21, 22. & 5. 26.

a 14.24 Comp. Ezra 9. 8 marg.

b 14.25 So Ps. 25. 13.

c 14.27 Isai. 4. 6. & 25. 4. Wisd. 10. 17. ch. 34. 16.

a 15.2 So 2 Esdr. 13. 55.

b 15.3 So Isai. 55. 1. Comp. ch. 24. 21.

b 15.3 So Isai. 55. 1. Comp. ch. 24. 21.

c 15.3 Comp. John 4. 10.

d 15.6 See ch. 1. 11.

* 15.9 Or, A parable. Comp. ch. 20. 20. Prov. 26. 7. Or, he was not sent of, &c.

* 15.9 Or rather, a parable.

* 15.10 Or rather, a parable.

e 15.10 So Ps. 33. 1.

f 15.11 So Jam. 1. 13. Comp. ver. 20.

f 15.12 So Jam. 1. 13. Comp. ver. 20.

g 15.14 Gen. 1. 26, 27.

h 15.14 Gen. 2. 16, 17.

i 15.15 Matt 19. 17.

k 15.16 Comp. Josh. 24. 15.

l 15.17 Jer. 21. 8. See Deut. 30. 19.

m 15.18 So Ps. 147. 5.

n 15.19 So ch. 17. 15, 19. See Ps. 33. 18.

o 15.19 ch. 23. 19. Heb. 4. 13.

p 15.20 Comp. ver. 12.

a 16.1 So Matt. 25. 30. Luke 17. 10.

* 16.4 Or, tribe.

b 16.6 So ch. 21. 9.

* 16.6 Or, hath been.

c 16.7 Gen. 6. 4. Wisd. 14. 6. Baruch 3. 26.

d 16.8 Gen. 19. 24. Comp. Wisd. 19. 14, 15.

e 16.8 Ezek. 16. 49, 50.

e 16.9 Ezek. 16. 49, 50.

f 16.10 Numb. 14. 15, 35. & 16. 21. & 21. 6. & 26. 64.

g 16.10 Num. 1. 46. Comp. Num. 26. 51.

h 16.11 ch. 5. 6.

i 16.12 So ch. 51. 30. See Ps. 62. 12.

k 16.13 So ch. 5. 4.

i 16.14 So ch. 51. 30. See Ps. 62. 12.

l 16.15 Ex. 7. 3. & 14. 4, 8. Rom. 9. 17, 18.

m 16.16 Gen. 1. 4, 6.

* 16.16 Or, strong partition.

n 16.16 Ezek. 3. 9. Zech. 7. 12 (English).

o 16.17 Comp. Ps. 139. 7.

p 16.18 See 1 Kin. 8. 27. So 2 Chr. 6. 18.

q 16.18 So 2 Pet. 3. 7, 10.

r 16.18 So ch 2. 14.

s 16.19 Ps. 18. 7.

t 16.19 Isai. 24. 18.

u 16.20 See Rom. 11. 33.

x 16.21 ch. 43. 32. See Prov. 25. 2.

y 16.23 Comp. ch. 25. 2 (Gk.).

z 16.24 See Prov. 4. 20.

a 16.25 Comp. Wisd. 11. 20.

b 16.25 Acts 22. 3 (Gk.). So Acts 26. 5 (Gk.).

c 16.26 So Ps. 111. 7, 8.

d 16.27 ch. 42. 21.

* 16.27 Or, beginnings.

e 16.28 So Ps. 148. 8.

f 16.29 Gen. 1. 29–31.

g 16.30 Gen. 1. 25.

h 16.30 See ch. 17. 1.

a 17.1 See Gen. 1. 27. So Wisd. 7. 1, 6.

b 17.1 See Gen. 3. 19. So Eccles. 3. 20. Wisd. 2. 3. ch. 16. 30.

c 17.2 Job 14. 1.

d 17.2 Job 16. 22 and marg. So ch. 41. 13.

e 17.3 See Gen. 1. 26.

f 17.4 Gen. 9. 2.

* 17.4 Or, of him.

g 17.4 Gen. 1. 28.

h 17.5 Same word in Gk.

h 17.5 Same word in Gk.

i 17.8 ver. 13. ch. 18. 4. & 42. 21. 2 Macc. 7. 17. Luke 1. 49 Acts 2. 11 the Gk.

k 17.10 Tobit 8. 15. See Esth. 16. 21.

i 17.13 ver. 13. ch. 18. 4. & 42. 21. 2 Macc. 7. 17. Luke 1. 49 Acts 2. 11 the Gk.

l 17.14 Ex. 16. & ch. 21–23.

m 17.15 See ch. 15. 19.

n 17.16 Gen. 8. 21.

o 17.16 See Ezek. 11. 19.

p 17.17 Deut. 32. 8.

q 17.17 Rom. 13. 1.

r 17.17 Deut. 4. 20. & 10. 15. & 32. 9.

s 17.18 See 2 Esdr. 6. 58.

m 17.19 See ch. 15. 19.

t 17.21 Deut. 31. 6, 8.

u 17.22 So ch. 29. 12, 13. See Tobit 4. 7.

x 17.22 See Jer. 22. 24.

y 17.22 See Deut. 32. 10.

z 17.23 Matt. 25. 34, 35.

a 17.23 So Prov. 11. 31. Comp. Joel 3. 7.

b 17.24 So Acts 3. 19.

c 17.25 Jer. 3. 12.

* 17.25 Or, lessen thy d offence.

e 17.25 Comp. Prayer of Manasses.

* 17.26 Or, illumination. ch. 25. 11.

f 17.27 See Ps. 6. 5. So Baruch 2. 17.

g 17.28 Isai. 38. 19.

h 17.31 Job 25. 4–6.

i 17.32 ch. 10. 9. & 40. 3. See Job 30. 19.

a 18.1 Gen. 1. 1.

b 18.2 Deut. 4. 35.

c 18.3 Comp. Isai. 48. 13 marg.

d 18.3 ch. 42. 23.

e 18.3 See Lev. 10. 10.

f 18.4 ch. 42. 17.

g 18.4 Ps. 106. 2.

h 18.4 See ch. 17. 8.

i 18.5 ch. 2. 18.

i 18.5 ch. 2. 18.

j 18.6 So ch. 42. 21.

k 18.7 1 Macc. 3. 31 (Gk.).

l 18.9 Comp. Ps. 90. 10.

m 18.10 So ch. 1. 2.

n 18.10 Ps. 90. 4. 2 Pet. 3. 8.

o 18.11 ch. 35. 18. Luke 18. 7. James 5. 7 in the Gk.

p 18.12 ch. 9. 11.

q 18.12 Ps. 103. 13, 14.

r 18.13 Ps. 145. 9.

s 18.13 See Jer. 31. 10.

t 18.15 So ch. 20. 15. & 41. 22.

u 18.16 Comp. Deut. 32. 2.

x 18.17 Luke 1. 28 (Gk.) marg.

t 18.18 So ch. 20. 15. & 41. 22.

y 18.20 Comp. 1 Cor. 11. 28, 31.

z 18.20 See Wisd. 2. 20.

a 18.21 So ch. 7. 17.

b 18.22 Deut. 23. 21. Eccles. 5. 4.

c 18.23 Comp. Eccles. 5. 1.

d 18.24 ch. 7. 17, 36.

e 18.24 ch. 11. 26 (Gk.).

f 18.25 Comp. ch. 11. 25.

g 18.27 Prov. 28. 14.

h 18.29 See ch. 50. 27.

i 18.29 See Prov. 1. 6. [Temperance of soul].

j 18.30 ch. 31. 8. So Rom. 6. 6. & 13. 14.

k 18.30 Rom. 1. 27 (Gk.).

a 19.1 Prov. 21. 17.

aa 19.1 So ch. 42. 4.

b 19.2 Hos. 4. 11. Comp. Gen. 9. 21. & 19. 32, &c.

b 19.2 Hos. 4. 11. Comp. Gen. 9. 21. & 19. 32, &c.

c 19.2 1 Kings 11. 1–4.

d 19.2 1 Cor. 6. 16 (Gk.).

e 19.3 Comp. Matt. 6. 19.

f 19.4 Josh. 22. 11.

g 19.4 See Prov. 8. 36.

h 19.5 See Wisd. 12. 14.

i 19.7 ver. 14 (Gk.). So ch. 41. 23 (Gk.).

* 19.8 Or, of friend or foe.

j 19.9 ch. 22. 13, 26. 2 Tim. 4. 15 in the Gk.

* 19.9 Or, shew his hatred.

k 19.10 Comp. Job 32. 19.

* 19.12 Or, heart. ch. 51. 21. Comp. Prov. 20. 27, 30. ch. 21. 14. & 33. 5.

l 19.13 See Lev. 19. 17.

* 19.14 Or, Reprove. ver. 13, 15, 17. Matt. 18. 15 (Gk.).

i 19.14 ver. 14 (Gk.). So ch. 41. 23 (Gk.).

m 19.16 See ch. 14. 1.

* 19.16 Or, willingly.

* 19.17 Or, Reprove. See ver. 14.

n 19.17 See ch. 13. 22.

o 19.18 See Prov. 1. 7. So ch. 40. 26.

* 19.18 Or, of receiving him.

p 19.18 So ch. 23. 28.

q 19.19 So 2 Esdr. 2. 12. See Prov. 3. 18. Comp. 2 Esdr. 7. 53.

r 19.21 Comp. Matt. 21. 29.

* 19.25 Or, judgeth.

s 19.26 ch. 12. 11 (Gk.).

* 19.26 Or, in black.

s 19.27 ch. 12. 11 (Gk.).

t 19.30 So ch. 21. 20.

a 20.1 So ver. 7, 19, 20. Prov. 25. 11.

* 20.1 Or, seasonable. ch. 35. 20.

e 20.1 ver. 1.

b 20.2 Prov. 28. 13.

c 20.3 Heb. 10. 26.

d 20.4 ch. 30. 20.

e 20.5 ver. 1.

f 20.6 See Eccles. 3. 7.

g 20.7 So ch. 32. 4.

f 20.7 See Eccles. 3. 7.

h 20.9 So Prov. 1. 32.

i 20.9 ch. 29. 4, 6 (Gk.).

k 20.11 See Matt. 23. 12.

l 20.12 See ch. 7. 3.

m 20.13 ch. 6. 5.

* 20.13 Or, pleasant conceits.

n 20.13 ch. 21. 16.

* 20.13 [Or,] lost, or, spilt. Ps. 22. 14. Lam. 2. 11 in the Gk.

o 20.14 So 1 Pet. 5. 2.

* 20.14 Gr. For his eyes are many for one to receive.

p 20.15 ch. 18. 18. & 41. 22.

q 20.15 Comp. Matt. 6. 2.

r 20.16 Ps. 41. 9.

rr 20.17 See ch. 27. 1 marg.

s 20.18 ch. 21. 7.

* 20.19 Or, An unpleasant fellow.

t 20.19 So ch. 22. 6.

u 20.20 Gk. as Prov. 1. 6. Comp. ch. 15. 9.

a 20.20 So ver. 7, 19, 20. Prov. 25. 11.

* 20.21 Gr. shall not be pricked. See ch. 14. 1.

v 20.22 ch. 4. 21. & 42. 1 in the Gk.

v 20.22 ch. 4. 21. & 42. 1 in the Gk.

v 20.22 ch. 4. 21. & 42. 1 in the Gk.

w 20.22 See Deut. 10. 17.

v 20.23 ch. 4. 21. & 42. 1 in the Gk.

x 20.24 So ch. 25. 2.

y 20.25 Comp. Prov. 6. 30.

* 20.26 Or, ignominy.

* 20.27 [Proverbs].

z 20.28 See Prov. 12, 11.

a 20.29 See Ex. 23. 8.

* 20.29 Or, as a muzzle in the mouth.

b 20.30 Wisd. 7. 13. ch. 41. 14.

c 20.30 Comp. ch. 29. 10.

d 20.31 ch. 41. 15.

b 20.31 Wisd. 7. 13. ch. 41. 14.

d 20.31 ch. 41. 15.

a 21.1 ch. 5. 5.

b 21.1 Ps. 41. 4. Luke 15. 21.

c 21.2 Comp. Prov. 23. 32.

c 21.2 Comp. Prov. 23. 32.

d 21.2 Wisd. 1. 11. So Ezek. 13. 19.

e 21.3 See Ps. 149. 6.

f 21.5 Ex. 3. 9. & 22. 23. Ps. 34. 6.

g 21.6 See Prov. 12. 1.

* 21.6 Gr. be converted. So ch. 49. 2.

h 21.7 ch. 20. 18.

i 21.8 Jer. 22. 13? Comp. Prov. 24. 27.

k 21.9 So ch. 16. 6.

l 21.9 See Isai. 1. 31.

m 21.10 Comp. Isai. 62. 10.

n 21.10 So Prov. 12. 12.

o 21.11 So John 7. 17. See Wisd. 6. 12.

p 21.12 Prov. 1. 7?

* 21.12 Or, witty. ver. 20. ch. 6. 32. & 22. 27. & 37. 19 in the Gk.

q 21.12 Eccles. 1. 18.

* 21.12 Or, subtilty. ch. 19. 25. & 34. 10 (Gk.). So ch. 42. 18 (Gk.).

r 21.13 Comp. ch. 24. 25.

s 21.14 So ch. 19. 12. & 33. 5. & 51. 21 marg.

t 21.14 Jer. 48. 38.

u 21.15 Prov. 9. 9.

v 21.15 See 1 Kin. 14. 9.

w 21.16 So ch. 22. 15.

x 21.16 ch. 12. 13 & marg.

* 21.18 Or, not to be inquired after.

y 21.20 So ch. 19. 30.

z 21.20 ver. 12.

a 21.21 Judith 10. 4.

b 21.22 So Prov. 25. 17.

c 21.23 See ch. 14. 23.

d 21.25 ch. 28. 25. See Dan. 5. 27

e 21.26 So Prov. 14. 33.

f 21.27 See 1 Chr. 21. 1.

g 21.27 Comp. John 8. 44.

h 21.28 ch. 5. 14. & 28. 13.

a 22.3 See Prov. 10. 1.

b 22.4 Comp. Prov. 13. 22 (Gk.).

* 22.4 Or, shall be the heir of her husband. Comp. Prov. 30. 23.

c 22.6 So ch. 20. 19.

d 22.6 ch. 38. 25 (Gk.).

e 22.6 Prov. 25. 20.

* 22.9 Or, an art.

f 22.11 ch. 38. 16.

g 22.12 See Judith 16. 24.

h 22.13 So ch. 12. 12. See ch. 19. 9.

* 22.13 Or, when he shakes off his filth.

i 22.13 See ch. 6. 28.

* 22.13 Or, wearied.

k 22.15 Prov. 27. 3.

l 22.15 So ch. 21. 16.

m 22.16 So Ps. 112. 6, 7.

n 22.17 See Ezek. 13. 10.

* 22.17 Or, of a polished wall.

nn 22.18 See ch. 2. 12.

o 22.20 Deut. 28. 26. Jer. 7. 33. Zech. 1. 21 (English).

p 22.20 So ch. 41. 22.

q 22.22 ch. 27. 16, 17, 21. & 41. 23 in the Gk. So Prov. 11. 13.

h 22.26 So ch. 12. 12. See ch. 19. 9.

r 22.27 So ch. 28. 25. See Ps. 141. 3.

s 22.27 ch. 19. 12.

a 23.2 See Tobit 3. 3.

a 23.3 See Tobit 3. 3.

b 23.4 ch. 26. 9 (Gk.). So Prov. 6. 17.

* 23.4 Or, giant-like.

* 23.7 [Discipline of the mouth].

c 23.9 Ex. 20. 7. ch. 27. 14. Matt. 5. 33.

d 23.10 ch. 28. 17. 1 Pet. 2. 24 in the Gk.

e 23.11 Comp. 2 Sam. 12. 10.

f 23.11 See Lev. 5. 1.

* 23.11 Gr. justified. ch. 1. 22. & 18. 22. & 31. 5.

g 23.11 See ch. 2. 2.

h 23.12 Lev. 24. 16.

i 23.12 So 2 Pet. 2. 22.

j 23.14 See Job 3. 3.

k 23.15 Comp. 2 Sam. 16. 7.

l 23.16 So ch. 25. 1, 2, 7. & 26. 5, 28. & 37. 18. & 50. 25. See Prov. 6. 16.

m 23.16 ver. 18.

n 23.16 Col. 1. 22.

o 23.17 Comp. Prov. 9. 17.

m 23.18 ver. 18.

p 23.18 So Job 24. 15. Prov. 7. 9. See Job 22. 13.

q 23.19 Prov. 5. 21. See ch. 15. 19.

r 23.20 Gen. 1. 31.

s 23.21 See Lev. 20. 10.

* 23.22 Or, a stranger. So ver. 23.

t 23.23 Ex. 20. 14.

* 23.23 Or, a stranger. So ver. 23.

u 23.24 Comp. Gen. 38. 24, 25. John 8. 4.

* 23.24 Or, visitation. See Wisd. 2. 20.

x 23.24 Comp. Deut. 23. 2.

y 23.25 Wisd. 4. 3. See Job 18. 16.

yy 23.28 So ch. 19. 18.

z 23.28 See Ps. 91. 16.

* 24.1 The praise of Wisdom.

a 24.1 Gk. as ver. 2.

a 24.2 Gk. as ver. 2.

* 24.3 Or, a mist. Wisd. 2. 4. ch. 43. 22.

b 24.4 So Ps. 104. 3.

c 24.5 Job 22. 14.

d 24.8 See John 1. 14. So Baruch 3. 37.

e 24.9 Prov. 8. 22, 23. See John 1. 1.

f 24.10 Ex. 31. 3. & 35. 31.

g 24.10 1 Kin. 7. 14.

h 24.11 Ps. 132. 8, 13, 14.

* 24.11 Or, holy. So ch. 36. 13. Song 5. 1 Macc. 2. 7. See Tobit 13. 9.

i 24.13 See Judg. 9. 15. & Judith 1. 7.

j 24.13 ch. 50. 10. Comp. Isai. 44. 14 (English).

k 24.13 See Deut. 3. 9.

l 24.14 ch. 50. 12. See Ps. 92. 12.

* 24.14 Or, Cades. 1 Macc. 11. 63, 73?

m 24.14 See Josh. 15. 62. & 1 Sam. 23. 29.

n 24.14 Cant. 2. 1. Isai. 35. 1. ch. 39. 13. & 50. 8.

j 24.14 ch. 50. 10. Comp. Isai. 44. 14 (English).

* 24.14 Or, in the water.

o 24.15 Ex. 30. 23. Prov. 7. 17. Cant. 4. 14. Rev. 18. 13.

p 24.15 See John 19. 39.

q 24.15 Ex. 30. 34.

q 24.15 Ex. 30. 34.

r 24.15 ch. 39. 14. & 50. 8, 9(Gk.).

s 24.15 Ex. 30. 36.

t 24.16 Gen. 35. 4 (Gk.).

u 24.17 John 15. 1.

* 24.18 Or, chosen.

x 24.19 See Isai. 55. 1.

y 24.20 Ps. 19. 10, 11.

x 24.21 See Isai. 55. 1.

z 24.21 Comp. ch. 15. 3.

a 24.23 Ex. 20. 1. & 24. 3. Deut. 4. 1. & 29. 1, 2. & 33. 4.

b 24.24 See ch. 2. 3.

c 24.24 Isai. 45. 21.

cc 24.24 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

d 24.25 Comp. ch. 21. 13.

e 24.25 Gen. 2. 11.

f 24.25 See Tobit 6. 1.

g 24.25 Gen. 2. 14.

g 24.26 Gen. 2. 14.

h 24.26 See Josh. 3. 15.

i 24.27 Gen. 2. 13. Jer. 2. 18 (Gk. not Heb.).

* 24.30 Or, drain, or, ditch. ver. 31.

j 24.30 Gk. as 2 Kin. 18. 17. & 20. 20. Comp. Ezek. 31. 4.

k 24.30 Gen. 2. 8. Susanna 4 (Gk.), 7, 15, 17, 18, &c. See Luke 23. 43. Gk. not as ver. 31.

l 24.33 Rom. 12. 6, 7 (Gk.).

l 24.33 Rom. 12. 6, 7 (Gk.).

m 24.34 ch. 33. 17.

a 25.1 ver. 2, 7. See ch. 23. 16.

* 25.1 Or, gloried.

g 25.1 Gk. as ver. 1. ch. 26. 18.

b 25.1 Gen. 13. 2, 5, 8. Ps. 133. 1. See Heb. 13. 1.

c 25.1 See Lev. 19. 18.

d 25.1 Prov. 11. 29 (Gk.).

a 25.2 ver. 2, 7. See ch. 23. 16.

e 25.2 So ch. 20. 24.

f 25.2 Comp. ch. 16. 23 (Gk.).

g 25.4 Gk. as ver. 1. ch. 26. 18.

g 25.5 Gk. as ver. 1. ch. 26. 18.

h 25.6 Prov. 17. 6.

i 25.6 So Prov. 16. 31.

a 25.7 ver. 2, 7. See ch. 23. 16.

m 25.7 ver. 7.

j 25.7 Matt. 5. 43.

k 25.8 See ch. 14. 1.

* 25.9 Or, a friend.

l 25.10 See Prov. 3. 13.

m 25.11 ver. 7.

n 25.11 ch. 17. 26.

* 25.11 Or, to whom.

o 25.12 So 1 John 4. 18.

p 25.13 ver. 23 (Gk.). So Prov. 18. 14.

q 25.13 So ver. 19. Eccles. 7. 28.

r 25.14 See ch. 2. 2.

r 25.14 See ch. 2. 2.

s 25.15 So ch. 26. 7. Comp. Hos. 10. 4 (Heb.).

t 25.16 See Prov. 21. 9.

u 25.17 ch. 42. 14 (Gk.).

* 25.17 Or, like a bear.

q 25.19 So ver. 19. Eccles. 7. 28.

* 25.20 Or, scolding. ch. 26. 27.

v 25.21 So ch. 42. 12. Comp. 2 Sam. 11. 2.

t 25.23 See Prov. 21. 9.

p 25.23 ver. 23 (Gk.). So Prov. 18. 14.

w 25.23 ch. 2. 12. Heb. 12. 12 in the Gk.

x 25.24 So ch. 42. 13? See Gen. 3. 6.

y 25.25 Comp. Prov. 17. 14. ch. 26. 8.

y 25.25 Comp. Prov. 17. 14. ch. 26. 8.

z 25.26 See Deut. 24. 1.

a 26.1 Prov. 31. 10, &c.

c 26.1 Gk. as ver. 1. See Prov. 18. 22.

b 26.2 ch. 28. 15.

c 26.3 Gk. as ver. 1. See Prov. 18. 22.

d 26.5 See ch. 23. 16.

* 26.5 Gr. An evil report. ch. 19. 15. & 28. 9.

dd 26.6 ch. 37. 11.

* 26.7 Or, a yoke of oxen.

e 26.7 So ch. 25. 15.

f 26.8 See Prov. 7. 11. Comp. ch. 25. 25.

g 26.9 ch. 23. 4 (Gk.).

h 26.10 ch. 42. 11 (Gk.).

i 26.10 ver. 25.

* 26.12 Or, stake. See ch. 14. 24.

j 26.13 Prov. 15. 30.

* 26.16 Gr. in the highest places of the Lord. Comp. Gen. 23. 6 marg.

c 26.16 Gk. as ver. 1. See Prov. 18. 22.

* 26.16 Or, ornament. ch. 6. 30, &c.

k 26.17 Ex. 25. 31–37.

* 26.17 Or, in constant l age.

* 26.18 Or, comely. ch. 25. 4.

* 26.18 Or, breast.

m 26.19 Comp. Prov. 5. 15–17.

l 26.19 Wisd. 4. 9. ver. 19.

* 26.22 Or, a swine. Comp. Prov. 11. 22.

n 26.22 See ch. 9. 9.

o 26.22 Prov. 17. 8. & 25. 13 in the Gk.

p 26.24 So Eph. 5. 33.

i 26.25 ver. 25.

q 26.27 ch. 25. 20.

d 26.28 See ch. 23. 16.

r 26.28 So Eccles. 9. 15. ch. 13. 22.

s 26.28 See Phil. 3. 8.

t 26.28 See Ezek. 18. 24.

u 26.28 So Isai. 65. 11, 12.

w 26.29 So ch. 27. 2. & 37. 11. Prov. 20. 14.

x 26.29 Rom. 6. 7.

a 27.1 Prov. 28. 21.

* 27.1 Or, a thing indifferent. ch. 7. 18. & 20. 17. & 42. 5 in the Gk. Comp. 2 Macc. 1. 35 (Gk.).

b 27.1 See Prov. 23. 4.

c 27.2 See ch. 14. 24.

d 27.2 See ch. 26. 29.

e 27.4 See Phil. 3. 8.

* 27.4 Or, thought. Rom. 2. 15. 2 Cor. 10. 5.

i 27.4 Gk. as ver. 4.

f 27.5 See Prov. 17. 3.

k 27.5 Comp. ver. 5.

g 27.5 So Wisd. 7. 20. See Luke 2. 35.

h 27.6 Comp. Matt. 7. 17.

i 27.7 Gk. as ver. 4.

k 27.7 Comp. ver. 5.

l 27.8 So Job 29. 14.

l 27.8 So Job 29. 14.

m 27.8 See Ex. 28. 2.

n 27.9 ch. 36. 26. Luke 9. 12. & 19. 7 in the Gk.

o 27.10 ver. 28.

p 27.12 Comp. Matt. 7. 6.

q 27.13 So 1 Tim. 5. 6. James 5. 5 in the Gk.

r 27.14 See ch. 23. 9.

s 27.16 See ch. 22. 22.

s 27.17 See ch. 22. 22.

t 27.17 See Matt. 26. 73 (Engl.).

u 27.17 So ver. 20.

x 27.19 Comp. Ps. 124. 7.

u 27.20 So ver. 20.

y 27.21 1 Esdr. 9. 20 (Engl.).

s 27.21 See ch. 22. 22.

t 27.21 See Matt. 26. 73 (Engl.).

z 27.22 See Prov. 6. 13.

a 27.23 So Ps. 55. 21.

* 27.23 Or, alter his speech.

b 27.25 Comp. Prov. 10. 8, 10.

c 27.26 See Ps. 7. 15. So ver. 29.

d 27.26 ver. 29 (Gk.). So Ps. 9. 15. & 35. 8.

e 27.28 Comp. ch. 28. 1. See Deut. 32. 35.

f 27.28 ver. 10.

d 27.29 ver. 29 (Gk.). So Ps. 9. 15. & 35. 8.

g 27.30 Gk. as ch. 28. 5, 7.

a 28.1 See Deut. 32. 35. Comp. ch. 27. 28.

b 28.2 Matt. 6. 14. Mark 11. 25. Luke 6. 37?

c 28.3 Comp. Matt. 18. 23–35.

d 28.5 Gk. as ch. 27. 30. So ver. 7.

e 28.6 See ch. 7. 36.

d 28.7 Gk. as ch. 27. 30. So ver. 7.

f 28.7 ch. 30. 11. So Acts 17. 30.

g 28.8 So ch. 8. 1, 2.

h 28.9 ch. 26. 5 marg.

i 28.10 So Prov. 26. 21. ch. 8. 3.

k 28.10 James 3. 5 marg.

l 28.11 So ch. 8. 10.

m 28.12 Comp. Prov. 26. 20.

n 28.13 ch. 5. 14. & 21. 28.

o 28.13 See ch. 5. 9.

* 28.15 Or, third. ver. 14.

p 28.15 ch. 26. 2.

q 28.17 See ch. 23. 10.

r 28.18 See Judith 2. 27.

s 28.20 Comp. Matt. 11. 30.

t 28.21 So ch. 26. 5.

u 28.22 Comp. Ps. 31. 20.

v 28.23 See Cant. 4. 8

w 28.24 So ch. 36. 25. Comp. Prov. 15. 19.

x 28.24 Comp. Gen. 42. 35. Prov. 7. 20.

y 28.25 ch. 21. 25.

z 28.25 So ch. 22. 27. See Ps. 141. 3.

a 29.1 Ps. 37. 26. See Matt. 5. 42.

b 29.1 See Lev. 25. 35.

a 29.2 Ps. 37. 26. See Matt. 5. 42.

c 29.4 Comp. ch. 8. 12.

d 29.4 ver. 6. ch. 20. 9 in the Gk.

e 29.4 Matt. 26. 10 (Gk.).

* 29.6 Or, If he be able.

d 29.6 ver. 6. ch. 20. 9 in the Gk.

f 29.9 Deut. 15. 8, 11.

g 29.10 Comp. ch. 20. 30.

h 29.11 See Matt. 6. 20.

i 29.11 Dan. 4. 27.

j 29.11 Matt. 19. 21. Acts 10. 4.

k 29.12 See Tobit 4. 7.

l 29.12 Luke 12. 24.

m 29.13 So ch. 40. 24.

* 29.14 Or, fail. So ver. 17.

n 29.14 Matt. 19. 5 (Gk.), &c.

o 29.15 Comp. Mark 12. 44.

p 29.18 See Prov. 6. 1. Comp. ch. 8. 13.

q 29.21 ch. 11. 3. & 39. 26 in the Gk.

r 29.21 So 1 Tim. 6. 6, 8.

r 29.23 So 1 Tim. 6. 6, 8.

s 29.26 Luke 12. 37. & 17. 7 in the Gk.

t 29.27 Comp. Luke 14. 9.

u 29.28 ver. 26, 27.

x 29.28 ver. 20?

* 30.1 Of children.

a 30.1 ch. 42. 5. See Prov. 13. 24.

b 30.1 See ch. 1. 13.

* 30.2 Or, good by him. Philem. 20.

* 30.2 Or, kinsfolk.

c 30.3 So Deut. 6. 7.

d 30.5 Ps. 128. 6.

e 30.6 Comp. Ps. 127. 5.

* 30.9 Or, astonished. See Mark 9. 15.

b 30.10 See ch. 1. 13.

f 30.11 See ch. 28. 7.

g 30.12 See ch. 7. 23.

h 30.13 ch. 33. 25.

* 30.14 Of health.

i 30.18 See Tobit 4. 17.

k 30.19 Bel and Dragon 7.

l 30.19 Lev. 4. 10, &c. ch. 45. 16 in the Gk.

m 30.19 Ps. 115. 6.

* 30.19 Or, afflicted.

n 30.20 ch. 20. 4.

o 30.21 See Prov. 12. 25.

p 30.22 So Prov. 17. 22.

* 30.22 Or, exultation. ch. 31. 28 (Gk.).

q 30.23 So ch. 38. 18. 2 Cor. 7. 10.

* 30.25 Or, A noble. ch. 31. 23 (Gk.).

r 30.25 See Judg. 19. 6 (Gk.).

a 31.1 So 1 Tim. 6. 9, 10.

b 31.1 Comp. Matt. 13. 22.

c 31.3 So ch. 11. 19. Luke 12. 19.

d 31.5 So Prov. 28. 20.

e 31.6 ch. 8. 2.

f 31.7 See Eph. 5. 5.

g 31.8 Comp. Luke 6. 24.

h 31.8 ch. 18. 30.

i 31.12 Ps. 141. 4. Prov. 23. 1–3.

n 31.12 ch. 37. 29.

* 31.12 Gr. open not thy throat upon it.

j 31.13 See ch. 14. 10.

* 31.13 Or, before every thing that is presented.

jj 31.14 ver. 18 (Gk.).

k 31.14 Matt. 26. 23. Mark 14. 20.

l 31.15 Comp. Matt. 7. 12.

m 31.16 So Luke 10. 8.

n 31.17 ch. 37. 29.

jj 31.18 ver. 18 (Gk.).

* 31.19 Or, And lieth not puffing and blowing.

o 31.20 ch. 37. 30.

p 31.21 Comp. Isai. 28. 8.

q 31.22 See ch. 1. 13.

qq 31.22 Comp. Prov. 22. 29.

r 31.23 Comp. Prov. 22. 9.

s 31.23 ch. 30. 25 (Gk.).

t 31.23 So Ps. 49. 18.

u 31.25 Isai. 5. 22.

v 31.25 Judith 13. 2, 8.

w 31.27 So ver. 31. ch. 40. 20. Eccles. 10. 19. 1 Esdr. 3. 20. See Ps. 104. 15.

w 31.27 So ver. 31. ch. 40. 20. Eccles. 10. 19. 1 Esdr. 3. 20. See Ps. 104. 15.

y 31.27 ver. 27, 28. Acts 14. 17 in the Gk.

y 31.28 ver. 27, 28. Acts 14. 17 in the Gk.

x 31.29 See Prov. 20. 1.

w 31.31 So ver. 31. ch. 40. 20. Eccles. 10. 19. 1 Esdr. 3. 20. See Ps. 104. 15.

y 31.31 ver. 27, 28. Acts 14. 17 in the Gk.

z 31.31 Comp. Esther 1. 8.

a 32.1 So John 2. 8, 9.

b 32.2 Tobit 2. 1. Luke 11. 37, &c. in the Gk.

c 32.2 So Wisd. 2. 8.

d 32.3 Comp. ver. 7.

e 32.4 So ch. 20. 7. Comp. Eccles. 3. 7.

f 32.5 ch. 49. 1.

g 32.5 Tobit 13. 17.

h 32.6 Rev. 21. 19.

d 32.7 Comp. ver. 7.

i 32.9 Job 32. 6. ch. 7. 14?

j 32.13 Deut. 8. 10. So 1 Tim. 4. 3, 4.

k 32.13 ch. 39. 22 (Gk.). See Isai. 34. 7.

l 32.14 ch. 39. 5. So Wisd. 16. 28. ch. 6. 36. See ch. 4. 12.

m 32.15 ch. 39. 6.

n 32.15 ch. 33. 2. See Luke 20. 20.

o 32.16 So Ps. 37. 6. Prov. 4. 18.

p 32.17 So Ps. 50. 17.

q 32.19 So ch. 33. 29.

u 32.19 So ver. 19. Comp. Rom. 14. 5.

r 32.20 Comp. Ps. 141. 6.

s 32.21 See 1 Cor. 10. 32.

t 32.22 ch. 33. 19.

u 32.23 So ver. 19. Comp. Rom. 14. 5.

x 32.23 1 Cor. 7. 19.

y 32.24 ch. 35. 1.

* 32.24 Or, shall not be hurt.

a 33.1 Prov. 12. 21. See 1 Pet. 3. 13.

b 33.1 See 2 Pet. 2. 9.

c 33.2 ch. 32. 15. See Luke 20. 20.

d 33.2 Comp. ver. 5. Isai 57. 20.

* 33.3 Or, as the asking of Urim. Num. 27. 21. So ch. 45. 10. See Ex. 28. 30.

* 33.5 Gr. bowels. So ch. 19. 12. & 21. 14. & 51. 21.

d 33.5 Comp. ver. 5. Isai 57. 20.

d 33.5 Comp. ver. 5. Isai 57. 20.

e 33.8 Gk. as ver. 11. ch. 36. 6. & 38. 27. & 40. 5.

f 33.9 Gen. 2. 3.

* 33.9 Or, ordained for the number of days.

g 33.10 Gen. 1. 27. & 2. 7.

e 33.11 Gk. as ver. 11. ch. 36. 6. & 38. 27. & 40. 5.

* 33.12 Or, standings.

h 33.13 See Rom. 9. 20, 21.

i 33.15 ch. 42. 24.

k 33.16 Comp. 1 Cor. 15. 8.

l 33.16 2 Esdr. 12. 42.

* 33.16 Or, gleaneth. Isai. 24. 13 (Gk.).

m 33.16 See Isai. 5. 2.

n 33.17 ch. 24. 34.

o 33.19 ch. 32. 22.

* 33.20 Or, Sell not.

* 33.21 Or, look to their hands.

* 33.24 Of servants.

p 33.25 ch. 30. 13.

q 33.26 So ch 42. 5.

r 33.29 So ch. 32. 19.

s 33.30 ch. 7. 20.

* 33.30 Gr. in blood.

r 33.31 So ch. 32. 19.

* 34.1 Of dreams.

* 34.2 Or, hath his mind upon. ver. 15 (Gk.). See ch. 5. 1.

a 34.3 Comp. Prov. 27. 19. Eccles. 5. 3.

b 34.4 So Job 14. 4.

c 34.6 See Num. 12. 6.

d 34.6 See Wisd. 2. 20.

* 34.6 Or, Regard them not.

e 34.8 See Lev. 19. 26.

f 34.9 ch. 36. 20 (Gk.).

g 34.10 ch. 21. 12 marg.

h 34.12 Comp. Prov. 14. 26.

i 34.14 See Ps. 71. 5.

j 34.15 ver. 2 (Gk.).

k 34.16 See Ps. 33. 18.

l 34.16 So Ps. 61. 2–4. & 91. 1–4.

m 34.16 See ch. 14. 27. Comp. Cant. 1. 7.

n 34.18 So Prov. 21. 27. Isai. 61. 8.

* 34.18 Or, the mockeries.

o 34.19 See Prov. 15. 8.

p 34.19 See 1 Sam. 15. 22.

q 34.20 Comp. 2 Sam. 12. 3, 4. ch. 35. 12.

r 34.22 See Lev. 19. 13. & ch. 7. 20.

s 34.24 Baruch 6. 6. Song 14. Susanna 5. Luke 2. 29. Acts 4. 24 in the Gk. So ch. 36. 1.

t 34.25 See Numb. 19. 11, 12.

u 34.26 Isai. 58. 3.

x 34.26 See Matt. 12. 45.

a 35.1 See 1 Sam. 15. 22. Comp. Jer. 7. 3, 5–7.

b 35.1 ch. 32. 24.

c 35.1 Lev. 3. 1. ch. 47. 2. 1 Macc. 4. 56.

d 35.2 Lev. 2. 1. ch. 38. 11.

e 35.2 2 Chr. 29. 31. & 33. 16 in the Gk. 1 Macc. 4. 56.

f 35.4 See Exod. 23. 15.

g 35.6 Ex. 29. 18, &c. ch. 38. 11. & 50. 15. So ch. 39. 14.

h 35.7 So ch. 39. 9.

i 35.8 ver. 10 (Gk.).

j 35.8 So 1 Macc. 3. 49. See Prov. 3. 9.

k 35.9 See 2 Cor. 9. 7.

* 35.9 Or, set apart. Comp. Ex. 19. 23 (Gk.).

l 35.9 1 Macc. 3. 49. See Lev. 27. 30.

m 35.10 So Tobit 4. 7, 8.

m 35.10 So Tobit 4. 7, 8.

i 35.10 ver. 10 (Gk.).

n 35.11 See Prov. 19. 17.

o 35.11 See ch. 7. 3.

* 35.12 Or, Diminish nothing of thy offerings.

p 35.12 See Lev. 22. 20–22.

q 35.12 Comp. ch. 34. 20. See ch. 5. 1.

r 35.12 See Ps. 75. 7.

s 35.12 See 1 Esdr. 4. 39.

s 35.13 See 1 Esdr. 4. 39.

t 35.14 See Exod. 22. 22, 23.

t 35.14 See Exod. 22. 22, 23.

t 35.15 See Exod. 22. 22, 23.

u 35.15 See Ex. 2. 23.

v 35.17 Comp. Gen. 32. 26. Luke 18. 7.

w 35.18 2 Pet. 3. 9.

x 35.18 See ch. 18. 11.

* 35.18 Or. cruel oppressors. See 1 Tim. 1. 13.

y 35.19 Matt. 16. 27 (Gk.). See Rom. 2. 6.

* 35.20 Gr. fair. ch. 20. 1 marg.

z 35.20 See Ps. 72. 6.

a 36.1 Comp. ch. 35. 17, 18.

b 36.3 So Ps. 79. 6. Jer. 10. 25.

* 36.3 Or, upon.

c 36.4 See Ezek. 20. 41. Comp. Matt. 6. 9.

d 36.4 Ezek. 38. 23.

d 36.4 Ezek. 38. 23.

d 36.5 Ezek. 38. 23.

e 36.5 See Josh. 4. 24. So ver. 17.

f 36.6 ch. 33. 8, 11 (Gk.).

e 36.6 See Josh. 4. 24. So ver. 17.

b 36.7 So Ps. 79. 6. Jer. 10. 25.

g 36.8 So Deut. 32. 35.

* 36.8 Gr. oath. Comp. Wisd. 18. 22. ch. 44. 21.

h 36.9 Comp. Isai. 24. 18. Jer. 48. 44.

i 36.10 So Ps. 110. 5, 6.

k 36.11 Ps. 106. 47. Comp. ch. 48. 10.

l 36.11 ch. 4. 13. & 37. 26. & 39. 23. Gk. as ch. 44. 21.

m 36.12 So Dan. 9. 19.

n 36.12 So Baruch 2. 15.

o 36.12 See 2 Esdr. 6. 58.

p 36.13 ch. 24. 11 marg. See Tobit 13. 9.

q 36.13 2 Chr. 6. 41. Ps. 132. 14.

* 36.14 Or, that it may magnify thine oracles. Comp. Rom. 3. 2.

* 36.15 Or, prophecies. Prol. 2 marg. ch. 39. 1. & 44. 3.

r 36.16 ch. 51. 8. So Isai. 40. 31.

* 36.17 Or, suppliants.

s 36.17 Numb. 6. 23–27.

e 36.17 See Josh. 4. 24. So ver. 17.

t 36.17 1 Kings 8. 60.

u 36.17 See 1 Tim. 1. 17.

v 36.18 Comp. ver. 21.

w 36.19 So Job 12. 11. & 34. 3.

x 36.20 ch. 34. 9 (Gk.).

v 36.21 Comp. ver. 21.

y 36.22 Comp. 1 Esdr. 4. 18–25.

z 36.23 Gk. as ver. 24. ch. 37. 12.

* 36.23 Or, common.

* 36.24 Or, to thrive.

a 36.24 Gen. 2. 18 (Gk.).

z 36.24 Gk. as ver. 24. ch. 37. 12.

b 36.25 So ch. 28. 24.

c 36.26 Gk. as Baruch 6. 15, 18, 57. John 18. 40. See Matt. 26. 55.

d 36.26 See ch. 27. 9.

a 37.4 So ch. 6. 10.

* 37.5 Or, in presence of the enemy.

b 37.6 Comp. ch. 3. 13 marg.

* 37.8 Or, what use there is of him.

c 37.8 See Joel 3. 3.

d 37.11 ch. 26. 6.

e 37.11 See ch. 26. 29.

f 37.11 See ch. 5. 1.

g 37.12 ch. 36. 23, 24 (Gk.).

h 37.12 See ch. 7. 34.

i 37.14 See Prov. 6. 16.

k 37.14 Comp. 2 Sam. 18. 24.

l 37.18 See ch. 23. 16.

m 37.18 See James 3. 2.

n 37.19 ch. 21. 12 marg.

o 37.19 Comp. 1 Cor. 9. 27.

p 37.19 Comp. ver. 19.

* 37.20 Or, wisdom. ver. 21.

p 37.22 Comp. ver. 19.

q 37.24 ch. 11. 28. So Luke 1. 48 in the Gk.

r 37.26 Prov. 3. 35. ch. 4. 13. See ch. 36. 11.

* 37.26 Or, credit.

s 37.26 ch. 38. 2 (Gk.).

t 37.28 See 1 Cor. 6. 12.

u 37.29 ch. 31. 17.

* 37.30 Or, variety of meats.

x 37.30 ch. 31. 20.

x 37.30 ch. 31. 20.

a 38.1 See Acts 28. 10.

l 38.1 See ch. 23. 16.

b 38.1 ver. 12.

* 38.2 Or, a gift.

c 38.2 Gk. as ch. 37. 26, not as ver. 1.

d 38.5 Ex. 15. 25. 2 Esdr. 1. 23.

e 38.8 John 19. 39 (Gk.).

f 38.8 Comp. ver. 14.

g 38.9 Isai. 38. 2.

h 38.10 See Isai. 1. 16. Comp. Ps. 103. 3.

i 38.10 Ps. 51. 10.

j 38.11 ch. 35. 2, 6.

j 38.11 ch. 35. 2, 6.

* 38.11 Or, as a dead man. See ch. 44. 9. Comp. Esther 14. 11.

k 38.12 See ch. 13. 22.

b 38.12 ver. 12.

l 38.12 ver. 1 (Gk.).

m 38.13 ch. 43. 26 (Gk).

f 38.14 Comp. ver. 14.

* 38.14 Or, curing. ver. 2 (Gk.).

n 38.15 Comp. John 5. 14. 1 Cor. 11. 30.

o 38.16 ch. 22. 11. Comp. 1 Thess. 4. 13.

p 38.18 So ch. 30. 23. 2 Cor. 7. 10.

q 38.18 See Prov. 12. 25.

r 38.19 See ch. 2. 2.

s 38.20 See ch. 7. 36.

* 38.22 Or, the sentence upon him.

t 38.23 Comp. 2 Sam. 12. 20–23.

u 38.24 ch. 10. 5 (Gk.).

v 38.25 ch. 22. 6 (Gk.).

* 38.25 Gr. of the breed of bullocks?

w 38.27 Wisd. 13. 1 (English).

x 38.27 See ch. 33. 8.

y 38.27 So ver. 28, 30 (Gk.).

y 38.27 So ver. 28, 30 (Gk.).

z 38.28 See Isai. 44. 12.

y 38.28 So ver. 28, 30 (Gk.).

y 38.28 So ver. 28, 30 (Gk.).

a 38.28 So ch. 47. 10.

b 38.29 Comp. Jer. 18. 3.

* 38.30 Or, tempereth it with his feet.

y 38.30 So ver. 28, 30 (Gk.).

y 38.30 So ver. 28, 30 (Gk.).

c 38.33 Comp. ch. 39. 2.

a 39.1 So ch. 44. 3. & 46. 1.

aa 39.2 Comp. ch. 38. 33.

b 39.3 ch. 47. 17 (Gk.). John 16. 25 marg. See Prov. 1. 1.

c 39.3 So ch. 47. 15. See Prov. 1. 6.

d 39.4 See ch. 11. 1.

e 39.5 ch. 32. 14, 15. See ch. 4. 12.

f 39.6 See James 1. 5.

e 39.6 ch. 32. 14, 15. See ch. 4. 12.

g 39.6 See ch. 50. 27.

h 39.9 So ch. 1. 24.

i 39.9 So ch. 35. 7. & 44. 13.

i 39.9 So ch. 35. 7. & 44. 13.

j 39.10 ch. 44. 15.

j 39.10 ch. 44. 15.

* 39.11 Or, gain unto it.

k 39.12 ver. 32.

l 39.13 See ch. 24. 14.

* 39.13 Or, rivers of water.

m 39.14 See ch. 35. 6.

n 39.14 See ch. 24. 15.

o 39.14 ch. 50. 8. See Cant. 2. 2.

p 39.15 1 Macc. 3. 45. & 4. 54. & 13. 51.

q 39.16 Gen. 1. 31. ver. 33. Mark 7. 37. 1 Tim. 4. 4.

r 39.16 So Numb. 23. 19.

s 39.17 See Rom. 9. 20.

t 39.17 See Ps. 33. 7.

u 39.18 See Ps. 115. 3.

x 39.18 See Isai. 59. 1.

y 39.19 See Heb. 4. 13.

z 39.20 Judg. 13. 18 marg. & Gk.

a 39.22 ch. 32. 13 (Gk.). See Isai. 34. 7.

b 39.24 Hos. 14. 9 (Gk.).

c 39.25 So ch. 40. 10.

d 39.26 ch. 29. 21. So ch. 11. 3 (Gk.).

d 39.26 ch. 29. 21. So ch. 11. 3 (Gk.).

d 39.26 ch. 29. 21. So ch. 11. 3 (Gk.).

e 39.26 Gen. 49. 11. Deut. 32. 14. ch. 50. 15. 1 Macc. 6. 34.

d 39.26 ch. 29. 21. So ch. 11. 3 (Gk.).

f 39.27 Rom. 8. 28.

k 39.29 Job 38. 35. Ps. 148. 8.

k 39.29 Job 38. 35. Ps. 148. 8.

g 39.29 ch. 40. 9.

g 39.29 ch. 40. 9.

h 39.30 Deut. 32. 24.

i 39.30 So Wisd. 16. 5.

i 39.30 So Wisd. 16. 5.

i 39.30 So Wisd. 16. 5.

* 39.30 Or, vipers. So Acts 28. 3.

g 39.30 ch. 40. 9.

k 39.31 Job 38. 35. Ps. 148. 8.

l 39.32 ver. 12.

m 39.33 See ver. 16.

a 40.1 See Eccles. 1. 3.

b 40.1 Gen. 3. 19. So ver. 11. ch. 41. 10.

c 40.2 Luke 21. 26 (Gk.).

c 40.2 Luke 21. 26 (Gk.).

d 40.3 Comp. Ex. 11. 5.

e 40.3 See ch. 17. 32.

d 40.4 Comp. Ex. 11. 5.

f 40.4 Ex. 26. 4, &c. ch. 45. 10. 1 Macc. 4. 23. Rev. 9. 17 in the Gk.

* 40.4 Or, To the porter.

g 40.6 Comp. Job 4. 14.

h 40.8 Gen. 6. 7. Ps. 135. 8 in the Gk.

i 40.8 See ch. 7. 3.

k 40.9 ch. 39. 29, 30.

k 40.9 ch. 39. 29, 30.

l 40.9 See ch. 2. 2.

k 40.9 ch. 39. 29, 30.

m 40.9 See Wisd. 3. 3.

n 40.10 So ch. 39. 25.

o 40.10 Gen. 6. 13. & 7. 11.

b 40.11 Gen. 3. 19. So ver. 11. ch. 41. 10.

p 40.11 See Eccles. 1. 7.

* 40.12 Gr. bribes.

q 40.13 See Job 6. 15.

r 40.13 Comp. Prov. 10. 25.

s 40.14 Deut. 15. 8. Comp. Ps. 104. 28. & 145. 16.

t 40.15 See Job 18. 16.

u 40.16 So Job 8. 11. & 18. 16.

v 40.16 See Gen. 41. 2.

w 40.16 Comp. Matt. 6. 30.

* 40.17 Or, a garden that is blessed. So ver. 27.

x 40.18 Phil. 4. 11, 12. 1 Tim. 6. 6.

y 40.18 Wisd. 7. 14? or ver. 17?

z 40.20 See ch. 31. 27.

a 40.21 2 Esdr. 10 22. Wisd. 19. 18. See Ps. 71. 22.

b 40.24 So ch. 29 13.

c 40.26 See Prov. 10. 15.

d 40.26 So ch. 19. 18.

* 40.27 Or, a garden that is blessed. So ver. 17.

e 40.27 Comp. Isai. 4. 5.

f 40.28 Comp. Luke 16. 3.

g 40.29 See Acts 15. 20.

a 41.1 Wisd. 16. 11 (Gk.).

aa 41.2 ch. 42. 8 (Gk.).

* 41.2 Or, to whom every thing is troublesome.

b 41.2 Heb. 3. 18 (Gk.).

c 41.2 See ch. 2. 14.

d 41.6 See Ps. 21. 10.

e 41.7 Comp. Wisd. 4. 6.

f 41.10 So ch. 40. 1, 11.

g 41.11 So Ps. 109. 13.

h 41.12 See Prov. 22. 1.

i 41.13 See ch. 17. 2.

k 41.14 ch. 20. 30.

l 41.15 ch. 20. 31.

l 41.15 ch. 20. 31.

m 41.16 ch. 4. 20.

n 41.16 ch. 4. 21.

o 41.17 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.17 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.18 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.18 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.18 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

p 41.19 Comp. ch. 42. 7.

o 41.19 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.19 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

q 41.19 Comp. ch. 42. 2.

o 41.19 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.19 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.20 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.20 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.21 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.21 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

o 41.21 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

r 41.21 See Matt. 5. 28.

s 41.21 See ch. 9. 9.

t 41.22 So ch. 22. 20.

o 41.22 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

u 41.22 ch. 18. 15, 18. & 20. 15.

o 41.23 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

x 41.23 So ch. 19. 7, 14 (Gk.).

o 41.23 1 John 2. 28 (Gk.).

y 41.23 See ch. 22. 22.

z 41.24 So ch. 3. 18. & 45. 1.

a 42.1 ch. 4. 21. & 20. 22.

b 42.1 See Deut. 10. 17. So ch. 4. 27. & 20. 22.

c 42.2 Comp. ch. 41. 19.

* 42.3 Or, Of thy partners’ speech.

* 42.3 Or, companions.

* 42.3 Or, of the giving. Phil. 4. 15. ver. 7. (Gk.).

d 42.4 See Prov. 11. 1.

e 42.4 So ch. 19. 1.

* 42.5 Or, without profit. See ch. 27. 1 marg.

f 42.5 ver. 8 (Gk.). See ch. 30. 1.

g 42.5 So ch. 33. 26.

h 42.7 Comp. ch. 41. 19.

* 42.7 Or, dealest for. Gk. as ver. 3.

i 42.8 Supplied from ver. 1

* 42.8 Or, rebuke. ver. 5 (Gk.).

k 42.8 ch. 41. 2 (Gk.).

* 42.8 Or, that is accused of fornication. Comp. Susanna 61, 62.

l 42.9 So ch. 7. 24, 25.

m 42.9 So 1 Cor. 7. 36.

n 42.10 So ch. 22. 4.

o 42.11 ch. 26. 10 (Gk.).

p 42.12 So ch. 25. 21.

q 42.13 So ch. 25. 24. See Gen. 3. 6.

* 42.14 Or, wickedness. ch. 25. 17. ver. 13.

r 42.14 Comp. Prov. 7. 21?

s 42.15 2 Esdr. 6. 38.

t 42.17 ch. 18. 4. So ch. 43. 27, 28.

u 42.17 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

v 42.18 See ch. 21. 12 marg.

* 42.18 Or, the Highest. ver. 2.

w 42.18 ch. 43. 6.

x 42.19 So Isai. 46. 10.

y 42.20 Job 42. 2. So Isai. 29. 15.

z 42.21 ch. 16. 27. See ch. 17. 8.

z 42.21 ch. 16. 27. See ch. 17. 8.

a 42.21 So ch. 18. 6.

b 42.21 Isai. 40. 13. See Rom. 11. 34.

c 42.23 ch. 18. 3.

d 42.24 ch. 33. 14, 15.

* 43.2 Or, vessel. ver. 8. See ch. 45. 8.

* 43.5 Or, he stayed his course. Comp. Josh. 10. 13.

a 43.5 ver. 13 (Gk.). So Ps. 19. 5.

b 43.6 Gen. 1. 14, 16. Ps. 104. 19.

c 43.6 ch. 42. 18.

d 43.7 Ex 12. 2. Lev. 23. 4, &c

e 43.8 Comp. ch. 6. 22. & 46. 1.

f 43.8 See Judith 7. 7.

g 43.9 See Matt. 21. 9.

h 43.10 Baruch 3. 34.

i 43.11 Gen. 9. 13.

k 43.11 ch. 50. 7.

l 43.12 Comp. Isai. 40. 12.

m 43.13 So Ps. 147. 16.

n 43.13 ver. 5 (Gk.).

o 43.14 Deut. 28. 12. Job 38. 22. See Ps. 135. 7.

p 43.15 Comp. Wisd. 5. 22.

q 43.16 So Ps. 104. 32.

r 43.17 So Ps. 46. 6.

* 43.17 Or, to groan as a woman in her travail. ch. 48. 19. See Jer. 6. 24. Comp. Mark 13. 8 marg.

m 43.17 So Ps. 147. 16.

s 43.17 See Wisd. 16. 9. Comp. Ps. 105. 34 (Gk.).

m 43.19 So Ps. 147. 16.

* 43.19 Or, it is as the point of sharp stakes.

t 43.20 Gen. 1. 9 (Gk.).

* 43.22 Or, upon the heat.

u 43.24 Ps. 107. 23–27.

v 43.24 1 Macc. 13. 29.

w 43.25 Ps. 104. 25, 26.

x 43.25 Luke 5. 26.

y 43.26 ch. 38. 13 (Gk.).

z 43.26 So Col. 1. 17.

a 43.27 See ch. 42. 17.

a 43.28 See ch. 42. 17.

b 43.29 Ps. 96. 4. & 147. 5.

c 43.31 Ps. 106. 2.

d 43.31 See John 1. 18.

e 43.32 ch. 16. 21.

* 44.1 The praise of the fathers.

a 44.3 See ch. 39. 1.

b 44.5 Comp. ch. 47. 8–10.

* 44.5 Or, ditties.

c 44.6 See ch. 9. 2.

d 44.9 Comp. Gen. 7. 22.

e 44.9 Wisd. 2. 2. ch. 38. 11. (Gk.).

f 44.10 ver. 8.

g 44.11 Prov. 13. 22.

h 44.11 Gk. as ver. 20.

i 44.12 See Ps. 112. 2.

* 44.12 Or, after them.

j 44.13 ch. 39. 9.

k 44.15 ch. 39. 10.

k 44.15 ch. 39. 10.

l 44.16 Gen. 5. 24. ch. 49. 14. Heb. 11. 5. Comp. Wisd. 4. 10.

m 44.17 Gen. 6. 9. & 7. 1. Heb. 11. 7.

n 44.18 Gen. 9. 11.

o 44.19 Gen. 12. 2, 3. & 15. 5. & 17. 4.

h 44.20 Gk. as ver. 20.

p 44.20 Gen. 17. 10, 11. & 21. 4.

q 44.20 Gen. 22. 1.

r 44.21 Gen. 22. 16–18. Gal. 3. 8.

s 44.21 ch. 4. 13. & 36. 11. & 37. 26. & 45. 22. & 46. 1 in the Gk.

t 44.21 Gen. 15. 18.

u 44.22 Gen. 26. 3–5.

x 44.23 Gen. 27. 28, 29. & 28. 14.

y 44.23 Gen. 28. 13.

z 44.23 Gen. 49. 28.

a 45.1 ch. 47. 22.

aa 45.1 See ch. 41. 24. So Ex. 11. 3.

b 45.1 So ch. 46. 13. Baruch 3. 36. Song 12.

bb 45.1 ch. 46. 11. & 49. 10. 1 Macc. 3. 7. See Prov. 10. 7.

c 45.3 Ex. 7. 12. & 8. 18, 19.

d 45.3 Ex. ch. 7–ch. 10.

e 45.3 Ex. 19. 3, 7. Deut. 6. 1, 2.

f 45.3 Ex. 34. 6.

ff 45.4 So Heb. 3. 5.

g 45.4 Num. 12. 3.

h 45.5 Ex. 24. 18.

e 45.5 Ex. 19. 3, 7. Deut. 6. 1, 2.

i 45.6 Ex. 4. 14, 28.

j 45.6 Ex. 6. 16, 20.

k 45.7 Ex. 28. 1, 2.

* 45.7 Gr. he blessed.

l 45.8 ver. 12. See ch. 9. 2.

* 45.8 Gr. vessels, or, instruments. ch. 43. 2, 8. Deut. 22. 5 (Heb. & Gk.). See 2 Cor. 4. 7.

m 45.8 Ex. 28. 42.

n 45.8 Ex. 28. 4 (Gk.).

n 45.8 Ex. 28. 4 (Gk.).

o 45.9 Ex. 28. 33.

p 45.9 Ex. 28. 35.

pp 45.9 So ch. 50. 16.

q 45.10 So 1 Macc. 3. 49. See Wisd. 18. 24.

r 45.10 1 Macc. 4. 23. See ch. 40. 4.

r 45.10 1 Macc. 4. 23. See ch. 40. 4.

s 45.10 Ex. 28. 15, 30.

s 45.10 Ex. 28. 15, 30.

t 45.10 See ch. 33. 3 marg.

s 45.11 Ex. 28. 15, 30.

u 45.11 Ex. 28. 17–21.

q 45.12 So 1 Macc. 3. 49. See Wisd. 18. 24.

x 45.12 Ex. 28. 36.

y 45.12 See Judith 4. 15.

l 45.12 ver. 12. See ch. 9. 2.

z 45.13 Ex. 28. 4.

a 45.14 Num. 28. 3, 4.

b 45.15 Lev. 8. 1–30.

c 45.15 Gk. as Ex. 28. 41 marg.

d 45.15 Gk. as Deut. 11. 21. Ps. 89. 29. Baruch 1. 11.

e 45.15 Num. 6. 23–27.

f 45.16 Num. 17. 5. See 1 Sam. 2. 28.

g 45.16 ch. 30. 19 (Gk.).

h 45.16 See Judith 16. 16.

i 45.17 Deut. 17. 9–11. & 19. 17. & 21. 5. & 33. 10. So ver. 26. See Lev. 10. 11.

k 45.18 Num. 16. 1.

l 45.18 Gal. 4. 17 (Gk.).

m 45.19 Num. 16. 23–35.

n 45.20 Num. 17. 8.

o 45.20 Num. 18. 12, 13.

p 45.21 See 1 Cor. 9. 13.

q 45.22 See Num. 18. 20.

qq 45.22 See ch. 44. 21.

q 45.22 See Num. 18. 20.

r 45.23 Num. 25. 11–13. 1 Macc. 2. 54.

s 45.23 Num. 25. 4–9.

r 45.24 Num. 25. 11–13. 1 Macc. 2. 54.

r 45.24 Num. 25. 11–13. 1 Macc. 2. 54.

t 45.25 2 Sam. 7. 12–16.

i 45.26 Deut. 17. 9–11. & 19. 17. & 21. 5. & 33. 10. So ver. 26. See Lev. 10. 11.

a 46.1 Num. 27. 18. Deut. 34. 9. Josh. 1. 2. & 12. 7.

b 46.1 See ch. 39. 1.

c 46.1 Comp. ch. 6. 22. & 43. 8.

d 46.1 ch. 47. 22. & 49. 13. See Esther 16. 21.

e 46.1 ch. 44. 21 (Gk.). Comp. Josh. 1. 6.

f 46.2 Josh. ch. 6–ch. 12.

g 46.3 See ch. 2. 2.

h 46.4 Josh. 10. 12–14.

i 46.5 Gk. as ver. 6, 16. 1 Tim. 6. 15. Comp. 2 Macc. 3. 24.

j 46.6 See Josh. 10. 11.

i 46.6 Gk. as ver. 6, 16. 1 Tim. 6. 15. Comp. 2 Macc. 3. 24.

k 46.7 Num. 14. 6–9. 1 Macc. 2. 55, 56.

l 46.8 Num. 1. 46.

m 46.8 Num. 14. 38. & 26. 65. Deut. 1. 35, 36.

n 46.8 Baruch 1. 20. See Ex. 3. 8.

o 46.9 Josh. 14. 6–14.

o 46.10 Josh. 14. 6–14.

p 46.10 See Num. 14. 24.

q 46.11 Comp. Judg. 2. 17.

r 46.11 See ch. 45. 1.

s 46.12 ch. 49. 10. See Isai. 66. 14.

t 46.12 Comp. 2 Kin. 21. 18, 26. John 19. 41.

u 46.13 So ch. 45. 1.

v 46.13 1 Sam. 10. 1. & 16. 13.

w 46.15 1 Sam. 3. 19, 20.

x 46.16 See Ps. 99. 6.

i 46.16 Gk. as ver. 6, 16. 1 Tim. 6. 15. Comp. 2 Macc. 3. 24.

y 46.16 1 Sam. 7. 7, 8.

z 46.16 1 Sam. 7. 9.

a 46.17 1 Sam. 7. 10.

b 46.18 Comp. Judg. 10. 12.

c 46.18 1 Sam. 7. 11, 13.

d 46.19 ch. 48. 13. See John 11. 11.

e 46.19 1 Sam. 12. 3.

f 46.19 1 Sam. 12. 5.

g 46.20 1 Sam. 28. 18, 19.

a 47.1 See 2 Sam. 12. 1.

b 47.2 Lev. 3. 3.

c 47.2 1 Sam. 16. 7.

* 47.3 Or, He smote lions.

d 47.3 1 Sam. 17. 34.

d 47.3 1 Sam. 17. 34.

e 47.4 1 Sam. 17. 49–51.

f 47.5 ver. 11 (Gk.). So ch. 49. 5. Comp. 1 Macc. 2. 48 marg. See 1 Sam. 2. 1.

g 47.6 1 Sam. 18. 7.

h 47.7 2 Sam. 5. 7.

* 47.7 Or, contemned. ch. 19. 1.

i 47.7 2 Sam. 8. 1. Comp. ch. 50. 26.

k 47.7 Dan. 8. 8 (Gk.).

l 47.8 So 2 Sam. 23. 1. Comp. ch. 44. 5.

m 47.9 1 Chr. 16. 4.

* 47.10 Or, perfectly. So ch. 38. 28. Comp. ch. 50. 11, 14.

n 47.11 2 Sam. 12. 13.

f 47.11 ver. 11 (Gk.). So ch. 49. 5. Comp. 1 Macc. 2. 48 marg. See 1 Sam. 2. 1.

o 47.11 2 Sam. 7. 12.

* 47.11 Or, of a kingdom.

p 47.12 1 Kin. 4. 21–24.

q 47.13 1 Kin. 4. 25. & 5. 4, 5.

q 47.13 1 Kin. 4. 25. & 5. 4, 5.

r 47.14 1 Kin. 4. 29, 30.

s 47.14 So Prov. 18. 4.

t 47.15 See ch. 39. 3.

u 47.16 1 Kin. 4. 34. & 10. 1.

u 47.16 1 Kin. 4. 34. & 10. 1.

v 47.17 1 Kin. 4. 31, 32.

t 47.17 See ch. 39. 3.

t 47.17 See ch. 39. 3.

w 47.18 Comp. 1 Kin. 10. 22, 27.

x 47.18 Ezek. 22. 18, 20.

x 47.18 Ezek. 22. 18, 20.

y 47.19 1 Kin. 11. 1.

* 47.19 Or, in.

z 47.20 Comp. Eccles. 7. 26.

a 47.21 1 Kin. 12. 15–17.

b 47.22 2 Sam. 7. 15. Ps. 89. 33. Comp. ch. 36. 8. & 44. 21, 22.

c 47.22 See ch. 46. 1.

d 47.22 ch. 45. 1.

e 47.23 1 Kin. 11. 43. Comp. Eccles. 4. 16?

f 47.23 1 Kin. 12. 10–14.

g 47.23 1 Kin. 12. 20.

h 47.23 1 Kin. 12. 28, 30. See 1 Kin. 14. 16.

i 47.24 2 Kin. 17. 6, 18.

a 48.1 1 Kin. 17. 1.

b 48.1 Comp. John 5. 35.

c 48.2 James 5. 17.

d 48.2 See ch. 2. 2.

c 48.3 James 5. 17.

* 48.3 Or, made heaven to hold up.

d 48.3 1 Kin. 18. 38. 2 Kin. 1. 10, 12.

dd 48.4 So ch. 50. 5.

e 48.5 1 Kin. 17. 21, 22.

* 48.5 Or, grave. Ps. 49. 15 marg. ch. 51. 6 in the Gk.

f 48.6 2 Chr. 21. 12, 15.

g 48.6 2 Kin. 1. 16.

* 48.6 Or, seat.

g 48.6 2 Kin. 1. 16.

h 48.7 1 Kin. 19. 4–8.

i 48.7 See 2 Esdr. 2. 33.

k 48.8 1 Kin. 19. 15, 16.

k 48.8 1 Kin. 19. 15, 16.

* 48.8 [Or, thee.].

l 48.9 See 2 Kin. 2. 11.

* 48.10 Or, written of. Comp. Mal. 4. 5, 6.

m 48.10 Cited from Mal. 4. 6. cited also Luke 1. 17.

n 48.10 Comp. ch. 36. 11

* 48.10 Or, establish. So Matt. 17. 11.

* 48.11 Or, were adorned with love.

l 48.12 See 2 Kin. 2. 11.

o 48.12 2 Kin. 2. 15.

p 48.12 2 Kin. 3. 14. & 6. 32–7. 2.

* 48.13 Or, Nothing.

q 48.13 2 Kin. 5. 25, 26.

r 48.13 2 Kin. 13. 21.

s 48.13 See ch. 46. 19.

t 48.15 2 Kin. 18. 11, 12.

u 48.15 Comp. Isai. 1. 9.

v 48.17 2 Kin. 18. 1, 2.

w 48.17 2 Chr. 32. 5.

x 48.17 See 2 Kin. 20. 20.

x 48.17 See 2 Kin. 20. 20.

y 48.18 2 Kin. 18. 13, 17. Isai. 36. 1, 2.

z 48.19 See ch. 43. 17.

a 48.20 2 Kin. 19. 14–20.

b 48.20 See Job 11. 13.

* 48.20 Or, hand. ch. 49. 6. Wisd. 11. 1. Baruch 2. 20, 24, 28 (Gk.). So 2 Kin. 14. 25, &c (Heb. & Gk.).

c 48.21 2 Kin. 19. 35. Isai. 37. 36. See Tobit 1. 18.

c 48.21 2 Kin. 19. 35. Isai. 37. 36. See Tobit 1. 18.

d 48.22 2 Kin. 18. 3.

e 48.22 2 Kin. 19. 2.

f 48.22 Isai. 6. 8.

g 48.23 2 Kin. 20. 10, 11. Isai. 38. 8.

h 48.24 Isai. 40. 1, 2.

a 49.1 2 Kin. 22. 1. & 23. 2. 2 Chr. 34. 1, 2.

b 49.1 Comp. Eccles. 10. 1.

c 49.1 ch. 32. 5.

* 49.2 Or, prospered. So ver. 3 (Gk.).

d 49.2 2 Kin. 23. 4–8. 2 Chr. 34. 3–7, 33.

e 49.3 2 Kin. 23. 3, 25.

f 49.5 2 Chr. 36. 17.

* 49.5 Or, horn. Ps. 132. 17. See ch. 47. 5.

g 49.6 2 Kin. 25. 9. 2 Chr. 36. 19.

* 49.6 Or, by the hand of Jeremie. See ch. 48. 20.

h 49.6 See Jer. 34. 22.

i 49.7 Jer. 37. 21. & 38. 6.

k 49.7 Jer. 1. 5. See John 10. 36.

l 49.7 Jer. 1. 10.

l 49.7 Jer. 1. 10.

m 49.8 Ezek. 1. 3, 4, 15.

n 49.8 1 Chr. 28. 18.

o 49.9 Ezek. 13. 11, 13. & 38. 9, 16, 22.

* 49.9 Or, did good [unto].

p 49.10 2 Esdr. 1. 39, 40.

q 49.10 See ch. 45. 1.

r 49.10 ch. 46. 12.

s 49.11 See 1 Chr. 3. 19.

t 49.11 Hagg. 2. 23. See Jer. 22. 24.

u 49.12 See Ezra 3. 2. & Neh. 12. 7.

v 49.13 See ch. 46. 1.

w 49.13 Neh. 3. 1–32. & 7. 1.

x 49.14 See ch. 44. 16.

y 49.15 Gen. 41. 43, 44.

z 49.15 Gen. 42. 6. & 45. 8.

a 49.15 Gen. 47. 13–26.

b 49.15 See Gen. 50. 25.

c 49.16 Gen. 5. 3.

d 49.16 Gen. 5. 32. & 11. 10.

e 49.16 Gen. 1. 28.

* 50.1 [B.C. 310–290]. Not as 1 Macc. 12. 7. 2 Macc. 3. 1, &c.

a 50.3 Comp. 1 Kin. 7. 23. 2 Kin. 25. 13.

b 50.5 So ch. 48. 4.

* 50.5 Gr. the house of the veil. Comp. Ex. 30. 6, 10. Heb. 9. 7.

c 50.6 See Rev. 2. 28.

d 50.7 See 2 Sam. 23. 4.

e 50.7 ch. 43. 11.

f 50.8 See ch. 24. 14.

g 50.8 ch. 39. 14.

h 50.8 Baruch. 1. 10 (Gk.) See ch. 24. 15.

i 50.9 Lev. 16. 12, 13.

h 50.9 Baruch. 1. 10 (Gk.) See ch. 24. 15.

k 50.10 ch. 24. 13, 14.

k 50.10 ch. 24. 13, 14.

l 50.11 So 1 Macc. 10. 21. See Wisd. 18. 24.

m 50.11 Ex. 30. 7.

l 50.11 So 1 Macc. 10. 21. See Wisd. 18. 24.

n 50.12 See Judg. 9. 15. & Judith 1. 7.

o 50.12 See ch. 24. 14.

p 50.14 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

q 50.15 See ch. 39. 26.

r 50.15 Ex. 29. 40. 41.

r 50.15 Ex. 29. 40. 41.

s 50.15 See ch. 35. 6.

t 50.16 1 Macc. 3. 54. See Numb. 10. 10.

* 50.16 Or, trumpets beaten forth with the hammer. Numb. 10. 2 (Gk.).

u 50.16 So ch. 45. 9.

t 50.16 1 Macc. 3. 54. See Numb. 10. 10.

p 50.17 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

v 50.20 Numb. 6. 22–26.

w 50.22 See Ps. 72. 18.

x 50.22 See Ps. 71. 6.

y 50.25 So ch. 25. 2. See ch. 23. 16.

z 50.26 2 Kin. 16. 24. John 4. 9. See Judg. 9. 7.

a 50.26 Comp. ch. 47. 7.

b 50.26 Ps. 74. 18.

c 50.26 Gen. 12. 6.

d 50.27 ch. 1. 19. & 39. 6. So ch. 10. 13. & 18. 29 in the Gk.

e 50.28 Comp. Rev. 1. 3.

f 50.29 Comp. Ps. 119. 105.

w 50.29 See Ps. 72. 18.

a 51.1 See Luke 1. 47.

b 51.2 Ps. 120. 2.

c 51.2 Matt. 7. 23 (Gk.).

* 51.3 Gr. the gnashing of the teeth. See Matt. 8. 12.

d 51.7 Comp. Ps. 118. 10, 11.

e 51.8 ch. 36. 16.

f 51.10 Comp. Ps. 110. 1. Rom. 15. 6, &c.

g 51.10 Comp. Luke 22. 53.

* 51.11 [Or, because my prayer].

* 51.13 Or, went astray. ch. 9. 8. Baruch 4. 28. Isai. 46. 8 in the Gk.

gg 51.17 See Luke 2. 52.

* 51.20 Or, I got understanding. See Job 12. 3.

* 51.21 Or, bowels. ch. 19. 12. So ch. 21. 14. & 33. 5.

h 51.25 Isai. 55. 1.

i 51.26 Matt. 11. 29. So ch. 6. 25.

i 51.26 Matt. 11. 29. So ch. 6. 25.

k 51.26 Deut. 30. 14. Rom. 10. 8.

l 51.27 See ch. 6. 19.

m 51.28 So Prov. 4. 7.

n 51.28 See Wisd. 7. 11.

n 51.28 See Wisd. 7. 11.

o 51.29 See Ps. 33. 21.

p 51.30 Comp. John 9. 4.

q 51.30 So ch. 16. 12, 14. See Ps. 62. 12.